[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, this
is CS50, and this is already
week nine, which is our second to last.
Indeed, this is really the last week
where you'll learn in this class
how to program.
But indeed, it's this
week that's really meant
to be the pedagogical climax of all
of these various languages we've
been looking at-- all of these various
techniques, all of this syntax.
So that at the end of
CS50 in just a few weeks,
you indeed feel that you
didn't take a class on C,
and you didn't take a class
on Python, but you really more
generally took a class on programming.
Because indeed we know
already about half of you
will go on to study computer science
further, but half of you will not.
And indeed all of your
programming chops here on out,
theoretically, will have
a foundation in what
we've been doing these past many weeks.
But here on out, it's
really going to be up to you
to learn some new fangled
language when it comes out,
or to follow some new trend
when some language eclipses
the ones we've been
using as more popular, as
more appropriate for
problems you want to solve.
And so today really is
about synthesizing so many
of the past few weeks, but doing it in
the context of web programming, which
for better or for worse,
is so very much in vogue
nowadays, both on our
laptops and phones.
And indeed the languages we
looked at in recent weeks are
used not only to make websites, but
also full fledged applications, and app
stores, and the like.
So this really will be the culmination
of those past several weeks.
And indeed we'll even talk about some
familiar concepts like shopping carts
when you're on Amazon, and
these things called cookies
when you're visiting websites.
All of those topics
too will come into play
and you'll have an understanding of
what all that means from the ground up.
So how did we get here?
Well just last week, we
focused on HTML and CSS
primarily, which are not
programming languages.
They're just about aesthetics,
structuring your data,
presenting your data, and so forth.
And we served the web pages we wrote
using this program HTTP server.
This is just one such program-- there's
dozens, hundreds of different web
servers that you can use out there.
This is just a super simple one we
preinstalled in your code space for you
in VS code so that you can
just serve up web pages.
At the end of last week
too, though, we teased
JavaScript, a full fledged
programming language
that you can use to manipulate the
user's experience for the better.
To make things more dynamic and
interactive by actually running code
in the user's browser--
on their Mac, their PC,
their phone-- as opposed
to server side, which up until now is
where all of our code and C and Python
has been written.
So you're writing code on a server,
you're serving code from a server,
but now with HTML, CSS, and JavaScript
it's getting executed in a browser.
But today we're going to be
one final feature of Python--
or really languages like it-- that
you can also use code on the server
to generate automatically dynamically.
The HTML, the JavaScript, the CSS that
you actually want the user to receive.
You don't have to hard code
everything as you have when
making your own home page.
Well, let's consider what some of
the building blocks were last week.
So here's a sample URL,
and over here slash
is the default page on any web server.
It might be index.html, it
might be something else,
that's just a convention.
But it refers to whatever
the default actually is.
You can visit, of course, in
any browser-- like a URL that
ends in file.html, or
something else dot HTML--
and that literally means your browser
wants this file on this server.
Or of course, we saw
that it can be a folder.
And inside of that folder is presumably
some default file name, like again,
index.html, or you can be more
explicit like folder/file.html,
and these more generally
we just called paths.
And indeed a path is just a
location on your Mac, your PC,
or on a server of some
piece of information.
But today we're just
going to rename this only
to use other common terminology,
but they're really just synonyms.
Today we're going to refer to
those same things as routes
because now today we're going to
ultimately replace HTTP server, which
just serves up static content that you
all write with your own web server.
Like now you will be
the ones controlling
what it is the server does in
response to the user's request
so that you can respond
interactively and dynamically.
But we're still going to
see techniques like this.
These were our so-called
HTTP parameters.
They are everything that comes
after a question mark in a URL.
And it can be key = value.
An example was, what?
When we played with
Google, what was the key
and what was the value
that I first tried?
Any recollection?
I was searching for cats
and so the key I figured out
was cue because that's what Larry and
Sergey who created Google years ago
decided the name would be of the HTML
textbox that you type your query into.
And if I type C-A-T for
cat, the value of that
would end up in the URL for Google
as being a question mark cat = value.
And I mentioned that it's
often the case that you
want to send two different
inputs to a server.
And this is why I propose that you
just keep an eye out for ampersands.
And ampersands separate
these key value pairs.
But again, this is the same
darn paradigm as before,
and we've seen this
so many times, right?
Key value pairs in
dictionaries, in Python.
We've seen HTML attributes
and their values.
We've seen CSS properties
It's all the same thing, associating
something with something.
Else even though every
language, every person
seems to have their own vernacular for
it, it really is just the same idea.
This associating of something with
something else we'll continue to see.
And, here to be concrete,
were the HTTP lines of text
that were in those virtual
envelopes, if you will.
If I were indeed selecting-- trying
to search for something like cats
on Google, this, recall, was the
message that got sent to the server
by my browser in order to
tell Google to please search
for not dogs, but in this case cats.
Now what has HTTP server
been doing for us?
Well it's just been serving up
HTML file, CSS files, maybe some JS
or JavaScript files, but it has
been ignoring any HTTP parameters.
Like HTTP server does
not take user input.
Why?
Well what's it going to do with it?
Because you already wrote
the HTML, you already
wrote the CSS, like
there's no decisions to be
made until we introduce a proper
programming language on the server.
And so we're going to move away now
from this simple HTTP server program
and introduce you to your own server
that's going to handle the parsing,
that is the extraction
of these key value pairs,
so that you and I don't have to
write Python code all of a sudden
that analyzes this
stuff, figures out what
pages requested the key value pairs.
All of that we're still going to get for
free by just using the right framework.
And so today we revisit Python,
which we've now used in some form
the past few weeks.
And indeed it's kind of been the glue
that allows us to stitch together
some of our own logic.
We saw it with SQL, we're going
to now see it with HTML, CSS,
and even JavaScript if we want.
And we're also going to see another
language today, not a programming
language, called Jinja.
And this is going to be a common
paradigm in the real world, whereby
different languages, different
libraries, different frameworks
often borrow from each other,
or they use technologies
that someone else wrote just so they
don't have to reinvent that wheel.
So Flask is just a framework.
That is a third party library,
it's pretty popular nowadays,
it's relatively simple, which
is why we use it in CS50.
If you've programmed
before CS50, Django is
another popular framework, or
library, in the Python space,
but it's a little more complicated.
So we focus on Flask.
And Jinja, we'll see, is
not a programming language.
It's just going to be some syntax--
thankfully familiar--
with curly braces that
allow us to use placeholders
in our actual web pages.
So again, you'll wrap
your minds all eventually
around where the lines are among
these various technologies,
but these are not the interesting ideas.
The interesting ideas are the
ones will focus on in code.
But starting today, instead
of running HTTP server
to serve up a static website, we'll have
you start running literally Flask space
run in your terminal window to run
your own web server that's implemented
in Python using this Flask framework.
So bootstrap was a library
for making your CSS
and JavaScript prettier
and more interactive.
Flask is a framework,
or library, for just
making your Python code more pleasant
to use since you're borrowing features
from someone else.
All right, so how can
we go about doing this?
Well, if you were to write your very own
web application, your own amazon.com,
your own google.com
in Python using Flask,
minimally, you need to have a file
called app.py by convention, which
is where all your Python code goes.
And then a folder called templates,
which is where all of your templates
go.
And for now your templates
are just your HTML files.
So if we're going to now start building
more interesting interactive things
like google.com or
amazon.com, we need to be
able to execute code on the server.
And so this is the convention.
It's not indexed at HTML
anymore necessarily,
it's these two things at the top level.
With that said, we'll quickly see
that there are some other conventions.
And in my examples online,
and in the problem set nine,
you'll see another file
called requirements.txt,
which is just a text
file that allows you
to enumerate all of the third party
libraries your application might
want to use.
It's a convention so that the server
can automatically install things for you
without you having to do it manually.
And then static is going to be where
literally your static content goes.
So if you've got images
for your web application,
if you've got JavaScript
files, CSS files,
by convention that goes in static.
These are just conventions,
all of this can be changed.
But this is the way to do things.
So we'll introduce you to the defaults.
All right so what does this mean?
How, for instance, could I go
about implementing my own web
application using Python that somehow
spits out a message like, hello, world?
All right, well turns out, just this.
Now we'll tease this
apart in just a moment,
but this is the contents of a sample
app.py file that apparently uses some
library stuff-- like familiar
syntax from something, import--
something else.
We've seen that before with
CSVs and other libraries--
this is somewhat new syntax, but
it's kind of copy paste for now.
This is definitely new syntax, and
kind of weird with the @ sign here.
But we'll see this
again and again today.
And it's just copy paste initially until
you understand what it's doing for you.
But at least there's
some familiar stuff here,
like index.html is still going to be
with us, but it's going to be up to us
when and how to show it to the user.
So let's make this more real.
Let me go over to VS code here,
and let me go ahead and create a--
how about we'll do
this in Hello-- let me
do mkdir Hello to make a
new folder called Hello.
And I'm going to CD into it just
to isolate all of these files
to the same directory, so that
we have different apps today
and different folders.
And now I'm going to do code of--
let's do this actually.
Let's do our mkdir templates.html--
sorry, not templates.html.
Let me rename that to
templates using the MV command.
This has nothing to do with web
programming, this is me making typos.
So if I type LS now, I've got
a folder called templates.
All right, in there let's
create a file called index.html
that is going to be super simple and
pretty much copy paste from last week.
Let me hide my terminal window, and
let me just very quickly whip up
a simple Hello, world
page using my HTML tag.
Lang will = English, then inside of
this, I'm going to have a head tag.
Inside of this I'm going
to have a title tag,
and I'm just going to
call this thing Hello.
I'm going to then have
a body, and in this I'm
only going to say something
simple like, Hello, world.
And just so this is
mobile friendly, recall
that we touched on these meta tags.
So just in case you after class
play with your mobile device instead
of your laptop, I'll do name
= quote unquote "viewport".
Viewport-- and then content
= and I never remember this,
I'm literally reading
it off of a cheat sheet.
Initial scale = 1.
Width = device width.
And this is just this
magical incantation
that says to the browser,
size things appropriately
for the size of the device.
It blows up the font sizes a bit.
All right, so that's what I
would have done last week.
And I would have served
this web page by running
HTTP server in the same directory,
and boom, I would see that HTML.
But let's now start to take some
control over the user's experience.
And for now it's going
to be underwhelming.
It's just going to
always say Hello, world.
But in a moment, version two
is going to say Hello, David,
or Hello, Carter, a
bit more dynamically.
And we'll quickly escalate from there
to just more interesting applications as
well, culminating with
things like cookies,
and shopping carts, and the like.
So let me go back into
my terminal window,
and as promised, let me create
another file called app.py.
And this is where now I need to
implement the web server I'm going
to run using this Flask framework.
And for now, I'm just
going to kind of do
some copy paste from what we
saw on the slide a moment ago,
from the Flask library--
which we've preinstalled for you--
I'm going to import a function
called Flask capital F. It's subtle,
but it's important there.
And I'm also going to import a few
other things-- a function called
render template, and another
variable called request.
And the only way I know this is
from having taught this before,
read the documentation,
followed a tutorial.
You wouldn't know this unless someone
told you or you read how to do this.
But what this means is
that this library called
Flask has three things in it-- a
function called Flask capital F,
a function called render template, and
a variable built into it called request.
And this is going to be
all the building blocks
I need to implement my own web server.
The convention in Flask, when you want
to create a web app in Python is you
create a variable by
convention called app,
and then you assign it the return value
of that Flask function-- capital F--
and pass into it __name__, which is
weird but we have seen this before.
A few weeks ago anyone recall
when and why we mention __name__?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, if we wanted to check
if the name of the file was itself main
so that we avoided a situation where if
you're writing your own library code,
you don't want your code to
be executed automatically.
You want to potentially
execute the main function.
And that was a solution
to that problem here.
For today's purposes, this
is just the way you do it,
__name__ refers to the current file.
And so this is just a little trick
that says turn this file into a Flask
application.
That's all it is, and for
now that line suffices.
All right, what do I
want to do after that?
Well now I'm in charge
of the web server.
I need to write the
code that decides, based
on the browser's request, what file or
files I'm going to send from the server
to the browser.
Last week HTTP server did all of this
for us just based on the file name.
But today I'm going to take
over control over that process.
And the way I do that is as follows.
I say app.routh with, weirdly,
in @ sign in front of it.
This is known in Python as a decorator.
And it's a feature of
Python not of Flask
that we just didn't introduce in
weeks past, but it's a special--
it's a handy trick to do
what we're about to do.
The root I want to define is
quote unquote "slash", so that is,
here is code I want the server to
execute whenever a user visits,
/slash default page of the website.
Well what code do I
want them to execute?
Well I want them to execute a function.
And I can therefore define
in Python a function.
I can technically call this thing
anything I want-- x, or y, or z.
But because they're accessing
the default page otherwise known
as the index of the site, I'm
going to just more reasonably call
this function index.
But just a convention, you could
call it anything you want, but x,y,
or z is probably a bad stylistic choice.
It doesn't need to take
any arguments in this case.
And the only thing this code--
this function is going to do
is, for now, let's go ahead
and have it return "Hello,
world" quote unquote.
And that's it.
All right now let me go into my
terminal window, let me go ahead
and do Flask run in the same directory
that has app.py and hit Enter.
I'm going to see some cryptic output,
but including a URL of my code space,
and if I open that URL
after hovering over it,
I'll indeed see Hello,
world as you might hope.
But let me do this.
Let me go ahead and
right click on the page
and click View page source,
which, if you haven't done before,
shows you all of the HTML for a
page, however pretty or messy it is.
And that's it, there's no
HTML that I've spit out,
it's just quote unquote "Hello, world".
Well if I actually want to spit
out a full web page, which is not
a big deal here because who cares?
It's just the text anyway.
But if I want to spit out a
whole file, let me do this.
I want to return, essentially,
the contents of index.html,
which have all of the tags I want-- the
mobile friendly stuff and all of that.
Well I can't just return
index.html, but I can return this.
Render template, quote
unquote, "index.html".
And per the documentation for
Flask, this render template function
will go find that file for me in
my templates folder by convention.
It will open it up and then it
will spit the whole thing out
to the browser for me, so I can
keep all my HTML in one place,
and all my Python code
in this one place.
So now if I go back to
my browser and reload,
I don't think I'll
really see a difference,
because it's the same text, ultimately.
But if I view page source now, notice
that, ah, there is all of the HTML
that was just sent to the browser.
So this is only to say, we have
the building blocks-- the puzzle
pieces, if you will--
via which to now store
all of our HTML in one
place-- and presumably CSS,
JavaScript, and so forth-- but
then serve up whatever we want,
even though I'm just blindly
spitting out index.html.
So before we proceed, any questions
on this, which again, I claim
is like my manual version
of what HTTP server was
doing for us automatically last week.
But this is how you do it yourself.
Any questions?
All right, well let's
make it more interesting,
which we could not do with
HTTP server and HTML alone.
Why don't we go ahead and do this.
Let me visit the same URL,
and I'm going to Zoom in.
And your URL will differ
from my code space,
but it's going to end similarly here.
I'm going to do
/?name=David, for instance.
Or q=cats, or name=Carter--
any key value pair I want,
I'm going to append after and
slash and a question mark,
thereby providing user
input to the server.
Albeit in a very user unfriendly way.
No one's going to normally
do this in their browser.
Enter-- nothing changes here,
it just says Hello, world,
but wouldn't it be nice
if it says Hello, David?
Or equivalently, if I Zoom in here
again and change David to Carter
and hit Enter, wouldn't it be nice
if it says Hello, Carter instead?
So we need some dynamism there.
And here's where now Python
is going to be our friend.
If I want to access the HTTP parameters
that the user has provided via
the URL-- be it q=cats or name=David--
I can use this special variable I
already preemptively imported earlier.
And I can do this--
If there is an HTTP
parameter called name
in what I'm going to call request.args.
Then I'm going to go ahead and
create a variable called name,
and I'm going to set it equal
to request.args bracket name.
Else-- if there is no,
quote unquote, "name"
key in this special variable
called request.args,
I'm going to just assume that the
user's name is world by default. Now
what's going on here?
Well, it turns out that Flask provides
us with this special variable called
request.args, and in there is
all of the key value pairs that
might have come in via the URL.
So if you had to guess what type of a--
or what data type is request.args?
That's its name, and here is in context.
Line nine might provide a clue.
In Python what data type
might request.args be?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: It's not going to be
an array or a list because those
are always, in every language
we've seen, numerically indexed.
But you're close.
Someone else?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: It's a dictionary.
So a dictionary is similar
syntactically to a list in Python,
but instead of numeric
indices like 0 1 2,
you can literally use strings
like, quote unquote, "name".
Now that's a bit of a white
lie, it is a dictionary.
But it's Flasks special fancy
version of a dictionary.
But the syntax by which you can
access it is exactly the same.
And I actually-- this is a typo.
I didn't mean to say names there.
I meant to say name singular, but
otherwise I think the code is correct.
This is going to, on line
eight, check if there
is a key called name in
request.args, and if so,
it's going to set it
equal to that value.
Otherwise it's going
to default to world.
I deliberately did not do this.
I added this if else
and did not do this why?
What error might happen if
I just blindly grab name?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If there was nothing at the end of the
URL that was of the form ?name=someone,
then there would be no name key.
And this is a couple of weeks
back, but this would give you
one of those annoying
key errors, when you
get a traceback because
you screwed up because you
used a string that doesn't exist.
That's why I'm just proactively trying
to avoid that situation just like I
might have a couple of weeks ago.
So even though it's more verbose,
this is just much more defensive
so that I don't accidentally index into
a dictionary where there is no key.
But we'll see how we can tighten
this up to be not four lines but one.
But I think now I can do this.
Wouldn't it be nice if now
in my index.html file--
which recall is in my templates folder--
wouldn't it be nice if I
could do the equivalent in C
of like a person S here for instance?
Or in Python, something like this name.
Well it's close, and this is just
because a few different humans
invent different languages,
invent different frameworks.
The syntax for this in
Flask is to actually
do, whoops, two curly braces, and then
name of the variable inside of it.
Why?
It's just probably someone
figured, what are the odds
that a normal person is ever going
to use two curly braces at once
versus just one?
So this is probably
decreasing the probability
that people actually want to output
literal curly braces like this.
So it's similar in spirit to Python's
f strings, it's similar in spirit
to C's person S, It's similar in
spirit to SQL's question marks.
Same idea, slightly different
syntax, and this there is Jinja.
So it's not programming code
per se, it's just a template.
And indeed that's why this
folder is called templates.
It is sort of like a blueprint for
what I want to be spit out to the user,
but I've got these
placeholders like this variable
that I want to plug-in to that value.
Now, this alone is not enough.
Watch what happens if I go
back to my other browser and I
reload the page after changing up here.
Let's do name=David again.
Enter-- nothing outputs
after the Hello comma.
So it seems that the name
variable doesn't exist yet.
And that's why, indeed,
if I do view page source,
you can see what was
sent to the browser,
something's wrong with my placeholder.
But I just need to be
a little more explicit
as to what I want to send where.
So it turns out that the render template
function takes not just one argument--
the name of the template
you want to spit out--
but it takes after that, with
commas, all of the placeholders
you want to plug-in.
So for instance, if you want the
placeholder to be this-- literally
placeholder inside of
those curly braces,
you can then specify as the second
argument to render template,
a placeholder named argument
equals whatever the name is.
So name is the variable in
the lines above, placeholder
is the name of my literal
placeholder in the curly braces,
and so now if I go back to my
browser and reload this with still,
quote unquote--
with still ?name=David in the URL,
now I indeed see Hello, David.
And if I Zoom in here--
and let me move over here.
Let me type in Carter and hit Enter--
now I see Hello, Carter instead.
Now this is a little unnecessary
to explicitly call the placeholder
"placeholder", especially if you
want to have two or three of them.
So you can actually call
this anything you want.
And I'm going to change it back to name,
which is a little more straightforward.
The only weird thing
here is that now you'll
see that you're writing code like this.
And this is correct, and this is
the norm, it just looks weird.
But the thing on the
left of the equal sign
is the placeholder you're using in
the template, the thing on the right
can be any value you want,
including a variable.
So even though I'm naming them
exactly the same-- which looks stupid,
admittedly-- this is
what people tend to do.
Just because it's
simpler than introducing
another word like placeholder.
Any questions now on this?
Any questions on these placeholders?
No?
All right, well let's
tighten this up a little bit
and see if we can't get things
to be more dynamic still.
Let me propose now that
instead of outputting--
instead of using this condition which
made a very simple idea like very
verbose with four different
lines, it turns out
there's an easier way to do this.
You can actually still create
a variable called name,
and you can set it
equal to request.args,
but instead of just blindly
indexing into that dictionary,
it turns out that request.args comes
with a function as well called GET.
You can pass it an argument that
tells you what value you want to get.
And by default, if there is no key
called name in that dictionary,
this function will not throw a key
error, it's just going to return none,
N-O-N-E, the special variable--
the special value in Python.
So it avoids a bug in your code, but
it tightens up four lines into one.
But even nicer, if you
read the documentation,
the GET function can also
take a explicit default value.
So if you don't want none to be on
the screen, like Hello, blank, or--
I mean, that would be weird too.
You can just put in a default
value per the documentation
of this function like world.
So now we've gone from
four lines to just one.
So arguably it's better designed.
And if I go back to
the browser now still
with Carter in the URL and hit
reload, same thing happens,
but we'll notice this.
Suppose I get rid of the name
parameter altogether and hit Enter,
now it goes to the default instead--
world.
So it's just a little better designed
than doing it the other way instead.
All right, how about we take
things up one more notch.
And how about we
introduce multiple routes?
And actually introduce,
perhaps, a form to the mix.
Because again, no normal person
is going to visit a URL and add
and a question mark and their
name, that's not how browsers work.
Well that's how browsers work, that's
not how humans interact with browsers.
You and I use a form,
typically, instead.
So now things can get a
little more interesting
when making our own web
application because maybe we
could do something like this.
Let me go and Zoom out again.
Let me go back to my code here, and
let me move this around and focus now
on the index.html file.
Instead of just this
placeholder, why don't we
go ahead and give ourselves a form
like we've played with a little bit
in the past, be it for
Google or something else.
And let's do this form.
And inside of this form,
let's have an input.
And the name of this input
will be, quote unquote, "name".
So that, too, is confusing.
But inputs have name attributes,
but this is a person's name.
So I'm saying name=name here.
So just a messy world of semantics.
And let me go ahead and make this
a text box by default. And then
let me give myself a button whose
default type will be submit.
And the name of this button
will be greet for instance.
So let's see what happens
here, but let me change
app.py to just be the original simpler.
I'm not passing in any placeholders now,
and I'm going to even get rid of this.
I'm just going to rewind to the
first version of this for simplicity.
Let's now change the URL to
get rid of Carter and myself.
So we just go to and hit Enter, and
now we have a super simple form again.
All right, this is not
super user friendly,
but there's some nice
enhancements we can make.
For instance, we can, for
instance turn off autocomplete,
especially if I want to type
David and Carter manually
and I don't want it finishing
my thought during class.
We can do auto focus which
puts the cursor there blinking
by default, which is nice
because then the human doesn't
have to deal with that.
And then we can even have
a placeholder attribute.
Placeholder=name so that it's like
built in instructions for this thing.
And so now if I go
back to the other tab,
nothing's changed yet because I have
to download the HTML again, reload--
OK, now it's a little
more user friendly.
It says name in light gray.
The cursor is blinking and
I'm sort of ready to go.
But this form hasn't been wired up to
go anywhere yet, and so let's do this.
Let's, for instance, say
that the action of this form
is not going to be
something like google.com,
which we did last time with for cats.
I am now going to be both the front
end and the back end of this website.
The front end is what the human sees--
the web page, the graphics, the forms.
The back end is the
stuff the human typically
doesn't see-- the Python code,
the SQL code, the server itself.
But now I'm in control of both sides
of the experience, the HTML and also
the roots.
So let's just propose that
we invent our own route,
and instead of calling it /search like
Google does, let's call it /greet.
And let me specify that the
method this form will use,
which is technically the
default, will be gets.
And confusingly, it is lowercase
get even though in the envelope
we keep talking about virtually,
it's actually capitals.
Again, left hand wasn't talking to right
hand when these things were decided.
All right, so all I've done is create
a web form that's going to submit
whatever the textbox value
is to a route called /greet.
By default, because there's no
HTTP, or HTTPS, or no domain name,
/greet is going to be assumed
to be not a google.com,
but whatever my own server's URL is.
So whatever my code space's URL is,
that's going to be the implicit prefix.
This /greet is just the route.
So now let's go back to
VS codes app.py file.
How do I now stitch this together?
Well, I think we're good
to go with index.html.
If index.html's purpose in life
is just to spit out this form,
we're done with one of my routes.
But if I want to have a
second route-- greet--
that actually spits out
some greeting to the user,
well let's prepare that template too.
Let me go ahead and
highlight all of this HTML.
Let me go back into my terminal
window and into my Hello directory,
and then into my templates directory.
And let me create another
template called greet.
HTML whose purpose in life will not be
to show a form but to greet the user
with Hello so-and-so.
So in this file I'm going
to paste all that same HTML,
but I'm going to get rid of
the form and essentially revert
to our previous version--
Hello comma-- and then
using the Jinja syntax name.
So one template--
index.html-- is for the form.
The second template, now, is for the
greeting of Hello comma so-and-so.
But otherwise these files,
notice, are almost the same,
except one has the form,
one has just the Hello.
So now let's finish this up in app.py.
Let me go down here after a couple
of blank lines stylistically,
let me do app.route,
quote unquote, "/greet"--
but I could call this
route anything I want.
I'm just using a reasonable verb.
Then let's define another function.
I could call a function
anything I want, X,Y, or Z.
I'm going to call it
more reasonably greet.
No arguments.
And then now is the code where
I want to render the template.
So I do return, render, template, greet.
HTML.
But I need to do one more thing.
What else do I want to do if I
want greet.html to have access
to the human's name?
Just to recap.
I think we solved this
already but I deleted it.
But what do I have to add back?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so I got to
pass in the placeholder somehow.
So I can do this a
couple of different ways.
I'm going to keep it a little
more elegant this time.
I'm just going to put my name--
argument-- there, and I'm going to
set it equal to request.args.GET,
quote unquote, "name", "world".
Before I used a separate variable,
but I only used it in one place,
so that's not strictly necessary.
So this is fine too, but if
this gets a little overwhelming,
notice that I can alternatively do this.
I can create an actual
variable called name
and then I can pass in
an argument called name
with a value that is that variable.
But again, what's really the point here?
It was kind of prettier all on one line.
So these are the exact
same things, I'm just
trying to tighten
things up further here.
All right, so what just happened?
If I go back to my form,
this is still index.html.
If I reload it, nothing has changed.
If I type in my name to this form--
Notice again, the URL I'm currently at--
this is Chrome hiding things,
it's technically / by default,
even though many browsers are
just hiding unnecessary characters
these days.
But watch what happens
now if I scroll over here
and I click greet on this new form.
Notice?
My URL, my route changed
to /greet ?name=David.
And the body of the page at
top left says, Hello, David.
So this is exactly how
google.com works, and it's
how we implemented HTML last time.
But instead of submitting the
form to Google via the form,
I'm submitting it to
myself, my very own route.
So I'm implementing my own back
end for this same front end.
All right, any questions just yet?
Much less interesting
than Google certainly,
but we kind of have
all of the wiring now.
Any questions?
No?
All right, so what can we
do to further tighten this
up and adhere to some conventions?
Well let me propose that in this
version we solve one problem.
And even if you've never
done this sort of thing
before, I daresay we have
enough weeks of CS50 where
if I show you index.html
again and greet.HTML again,
odds are to someone's mind there's
a opportunity for improvement.
Why is this web app-- super simple
though it is-- arguably poorly
designed at the moment?
And the answer lies somewhere
in these two templates--
index.html and greet.HTML.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, they're
almost the exact same except
for the contents of the body.
And it wasn't a big deal,
there's only two pages.
So what I copy pasted this once?
But imagine, now, a normal
website, or even your home
pages which had three,
four, or more pages.
I mean at this point,
you're just copying
and pasting everything,
honestly, as you probably
did necessarily for your home page.
Why?
Because when you have HTML only,
maybe CSS, and even JavaScript,
that's all you can do is
copy paste, copy paste,
and just make sure that you
have the same structure.
Maybe you have the same CSS
file, the same JavaScript file,
the same third party libraries,
but it makes it very,
very annoying as you might have
realized already to just make
a change that affects everything.
So wouldn't it be nice to factor
out all of this and all of this
and just let the body change?
So here too is something that Flask
and really other equivalent frameworks
let us do.
It allows us to create what we're
going to call conventionally
a layout instead.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to copy one last
time all of the same HTML.
I'm going to go into my
terminal window and I'm
going to create by convention
a file called layout.HTML.
This is truly going to
be a blueprint of sorts.
And in layout.HTML, I'm going
to paste all of that same code,
but I'm going to use
now some Jinja syntax
to indicate that I don't want to
plug-in just a variable like name here,
I want to actually plug the
contents of a whole other file.
So instead of just using curly
braces, two of them left and right,
I have to use slightly different syntax
to say I want a whole block of HTML
here from some other file.
And the way to do this, even though the
syntax is a little non obvious, is you
use open curly brace,
percent sign, block,
then you can call the next
word anything you want.
It just has to be a special type
of placeholder for an actual file,
not for just a variable.
I'm going to call it body
only because I'm in the body.
So I want a placeholder
to be the entire body.
And then outside of this, you
then say in one word, no space--
endblock.
So it looks kind of stupid, honestly.
And why do we have yet more ugly syntax?
Again, just different software
developers in the world
are all choosing their own
syntax for their own libraries.
So they all kind of look different
but are all kind of similar in spirit.
And you just get used to
seeing the different syntax.
This now is not nearly as pretty as
the pair of curly braces for variables,
but this is how I can say plug the
contents of an entire file here.
And now what does this let me do?
I can now go back into my
index.html file, which at the moment
still looks like this, but
almost all of this is copy paste.
The only lines that are
interesting and different
are these four lines here in the body.
So what I can actually do now is I'm
going to highlight that and cut it,
and then I'm going to
highlight everything else
and just delete the entire file.
And I'm going to use some
of that same syntax and say
[? %extends"layout.html"% ?] And then
I close my thought with a % and closed
curly brace.
So this syntax as you
might just be inferring
is now saying, please extend
whatever layout.HTML looks like.
That's the original
blueprint, the mold out
of which I want to make this web page.
And now here the syntax is a
little weird too, but similar,
at least from before.
I can now say the block--
the body block that I want
you to plug into that layout
is going to be everything between these
two tags, which we already saw earlier.
But in layout.HTML, They're
sort of giving a placeholder.
In index.html, this is what I'm going
to plug-in to those other placeholders
as well.
So I'm just going to give
myself some extra whitespace.
I'm going to paste the
HTML that was there.
If I want to make clear
what's going on, I
can indent it, although this
has no functional impact.
But it just makes clear that just
like in HTML, you can open a Jinja tag
and close it.
But in Jinja here, we have this here--
hey Python, here comes
the body of this page.
Hey Python, that's it for
And all of this stuff should be
plugged into this main parent layout,
if you will.
So super ugly, admittedly,
but now at least
things get way less
redundant because I'm going
to do the exact same thing over here.
In greet.HTML, it looks like this.
But now I'm going to do this-- extends,
layout.HTML also, just as before.
The body that I want to plug-in is going
to be everything inside of these tags
here.
And this body is just going to be
Hello, name in curly braces like that.
So again, ugly-- syntax
got really ugly fast.
But it's really just
following these patterns now.
And we have two types of placeholders.
Two curly braces for
variables, and now this kind
of syntax with the percent
signs and the single curly
braces for contents of actual files.
And so now in this world-- or
in the world of a home page,
if you were using Flask and
Python to make your personal home
page with all of those various
pages, you would probably
design one main layout with all of
your pretty logos and colors and fonts
and what you want the site to look like.
And then each of your
smaller pages would now
be distilled into just
these smaller fragments.
And whether using Python, or Java, or
JavaScript, or other languages too,
all different programming
languages have popular frameworks
that do things like this.
The idea is the same across all of them.
All right, let's see if it works.
Let's go back into the browser.
Let me go back to my /route.
There's that same form.
Let me type in David and
type-- and click greet.
And indeed I see Hello, David, I
see that greet was automatically
added to the URL by the browser
when I submitted the form, followed
by the key value pairs.
And if I view the page
source as I did earlier,
you'll see that you have
the entirety of that layout
with Hello, David plugged in.
Meanwhile, if I go back to the
form and view this page source,
you'll see the exact same layout,
but with the form tag plugged in.
And here's where you can be a
little less nitpicky with styling.
OK, yes this isn't technically
indented inside of the body.
But it was relative
to the original file.
So at this point in the
game, you don't need
to worry about your outputted
HTML looking super pretty.
You want your source
code that the humans
see to be pretty, not the browser.
This is not a stylistic concern.
OK, questions on these
capabilities then a Flask?
Or problems that we've
just solved and why?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So if the files in question
are in different folders--
For instance, if I go back into
my index page, which has the form,
the roots here are entirely
dependent on what is in app.py.
There's no notion of a folder when
it comes to implementing a web
application anymore.
They are more generically routes.
However, and we've
not done this yet, you
can put your static content--
your images, your video files,
your CSS files-- in a
folder called static,
and there can be subfolders they're in.
And that would affect what you use
as your source attributes for images,
or your source tags for video,
or any of those kinds of assets.
And we'll see that eventually in
the home-- in the problem set next.
Other questions on what
we've just done here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Good
question, how do I-- how
did I ensure that the web
app starts on the form
and then goes to the Hello page?
So whatever you decide
your default index route
is, like the implicit
slash, that is what
is going to be pulled up when a
user visits the domain name where
your website is hosted.
So if I go back over here to app.py,
because my /route is designed to return
index.html, that's exactly
why that response came back.
Good question.
All right, so beyond this, let's
consider, now, issues of privacy.
And we'll touch on this too, as we
get to issues like shopping carts
and cookies, if I Zoom
in on the URL here--
even though the URL itself is a
little long and ugly and cryptic--
but when I type in my
name and hit greet,
of course we keep seeing
name=David in the URL.
In what sense might this be bad design?
Or in what kinds of web apps
might you not want the name
to show up in the URL like that?
Because this is what Google does,
and this is what my app does.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So if I'm logging in with
a username and password,
I could imagine that they show up in
the URL after the question mark where
username= malan and password=12345, but
then all my nosey siblings need to do
is go through my browser
history and boom,
it's right there for them to copy paste.
So that doesn't seem
particularly secure.
Or if someone's walking past you in a
cafe, they can just look at your URL
if it's revealed by the
browser and they see it too.
So GET is not necessarily
the best verb to use
even though it's the default
when submitting forms.
Typically, when you've got anything
remotely sensitive, or anything large--
so be it a password, or credit
card number, or an image or a video
that you're uploading to
Instagram, or to YouTube,
or any such site like that-- you don't
want the data going into the URL.
And thankfully, there's actually
an easy way to fix this.
I can go into my form, which
is currently an index.html,
and I can just change the
method from GET to post.
In lowercase here, but the verb in the
virtual envelope we discussed last week
would itself be capital P-o-s-t.
Now unfortunately,
watch what happens here.
Let me go over to my original
form by going back to the /route--
and I'm reloading the page to make
sure I get the latest, freshest HTML.
And just to confirm here--
yep, if I view source,
method is now POST.
So let me go ahead and type
in David now and click greet.
And before we saw Hello, David.
But now I get method not allowed.
And this is somewhat subtle but
in the title of the tab, notice
that it's a 405 error, which
is not familiar, probably.
Almost all of us have
seen 404 file not found.
Turns out 405, a little
more arcane, is the method.
The HTTP verb is not allowed.
Why?
Because by default, my app.py only
currently supports GET by default.
How do I support POST?
I just need a little bit more syntax.
So let me go back into VS Code here.
Let me go into app.py now.
And after changing the form,
I just need to inform Flask
that what the method I want
this great route to use
should not be the default, which is only
GET, I want it to use these methods.
And it takes a second argument
called methods, the value of which
is a list, the default of
which is, quote unquote, "GET".
So that's the default. This
has not made any changes.
But if I want to support POST
instead, I can explicitly
pass a list with one string in it--
P-O-S-T instead.
And now what does this mean?
We didn't talk about this
in any detail last week,
but inside of this virtual
envelope, typically,
is that line like GET/search,
queue=cats after the question mark.
If you want to hide that kind of
information for privacy's sake,
or because you want to upload an
image, which just doesn't make sense
to put in the URL, essentially
the part of the story would be,
well the computer looks deeper
inside of that virtual envelope.
And anything submitted by a POST
goes below the HTTP headers,
like deeper in that envelope.
So they're still there.
They're just not obviously visible for
prying eyes in the user's own browser.
So just by making that
change in the HTML,
telling the browser to
submit the data via POST,
and changing app.py to tell the
route to expect the data via POST,
I can now go back to my other tab.
Let me go back to the original page.
Let me reload just so
I've got the latest HTML.
And indeed, view page
source, it's still--
yep, it's still POST.
But now when I type in D-A-V-I-D
and click greet now it works.
But, but, but, notice
the privacy implication--
I'm at the greet route
but where's my name?
It's not actually there.
It still went to the
server, but it's not
in your autocomplete or your
history now for privacy's sake.
Questions now on POST?
Yeah.
No?
Just scratching.
All right, can you, the
programmer see this?
Well, let me show you a couple
of other features of Chrome's--
Chrome, and Safari, and
other browsers as well.
I keep going to view page
source, which just shows
you a read only version of your HTML.
But recall that last time, I actually
right clicked and went to inspect,
or viewed developer tools.
And this brings up a much fancier
version of the developer tools.
And under elements here,
you see everything.
And it's nice and pretty
printed, it's hierarchical, ,
it collapses things into these clickable
triangles but it's the exact same
thing.
It's just more interactive.
But notice what I can do today is this--
If I go to the Network tab here,
and let me Zoom out a little bit,
Let me go ahead and re load
the form here and type in David
again and click greet.
Notice now in the Network tab
of Chrome's developer tools,
I see a few things as we saw before.
One, I see that the
request method is POST.
Two, I see that the
server automatically,
without me writing any code for this,
returns 200 when it's successful.
But I can scroll down,
down, down, down, down,
and you'll see that eventually after
all these cookies-- more on those later.
If I click on payload, the
second tab next to headers,
you can see as the developer what
was actually sent to the server.
So indeed, this.
Is going to be super useful
like when doing problem
set nine, maybe your
final projects, if you
want to see what's going
from browser to server,
you have complete control
over all of that information.
Even if you're using HTTPS,
because your browser and you,
the developer can
certainly see all of this.
So again, these developer
tools, even though there's
a lot of tabs and buttons you
probably won't need any time soon,
some of them like elements, and
network, and with JavaScript console
are going to be super useful
to start to get familiar with.
All right, any questions now
on this implication of POST?
Anything at all?
No?
OK, how about one final Hello example
that ties a few of these things
together.
How about now we try to tighten
things up further only in anticipation
of something like problem set
9, or really more complicated
web apps where you might
have not two, but 20
or maybe even more different routes.
It might be ideal to just minimize
how many total routes we have.
So we don't get a
little too overwhelmed.
And I daresay that these
two routes are so short,
maybe I can combine them into one.
And maybe I can keep the user at
what seems to be the same URL,
but just to kind of tidy things up.
So let me propose that
we do this instead.
Let me get rid of my greet route and
let me go into my form in index.html
and let me go ahead and just have the
action of this form still be slash.
I want the form to be visible at
the slash, the index of the site.
But I also want the
form to submit to itself
if only because I don't want to
introduce another route like greet
which eventually, indeed,
will be compelling
so you don't have one root for
everything you want your website to do.
So technically this is the
default too, and if I omit action
the exact same thing
would happen as well.
But let me rewind and
let me now go into app.py
to see how we can make this happen.
Well, if I want my one and now
only route to support both methods,
I can say methods=, and then a list
with both GET and POST in any order
but I'll keep them
alphabetical like this.
Now tells Python hey, this route
should handle both GET and POST
requests at the same place.
Let's now go into this function.
I kind of want to say
the equivalent of this--
if GET, then I want to return the form.
Else if POST, I want to
then return render template
of greet.HTML with the user's name.
But this is not yet complete
code, but I think I can do this.
I'm going to go ahead
and save the following.
I'm going to go ahead and say
if request.method = = GET,
then indeed return index.html.
L if request.method = = POST, then
go ahead and return greet.HTML.
This isn't quite enough though because I
still want to pass in that placeholder.
So let me again add back
name=request.args.GET, quote unquote,
"name", and then a
default value of world.
What does this now do for me?
Well let me go back
to my other tab here.
Let me close the developer
tools, let me go back to the form
here, let me reload to make
sure I have the latest.
Let me view page source just to make
sure I have the latest-- and yep,
I have the latest because
it still says POST.
But it now says slash.
And let's see what happens now.
If I type in my name David,
previously this submitted via POST,
so I didn't see any name or
value thereof in the URL,
but I did end up at /greet.
But if the action is
now slash I click greet,
notice that it still kind of works.
I see Hello, world, although
that didn't quite work.
So we'll come back to
that issue in a moment.
But notice the URL ends in just slash.
And again, Chrome is hiding the slash
because that's all that's there,
but it does not end in name=David
in this case, or name=world.
Now notice this too--
if I reload I'm going
to get this warning.
Do you want to confirm
form resubmission?
The page you're looking for used
information that you entered.
Returning to that page might cause
any action you took to be repeated.
Do you want to continue?
You might have seen this on
websites you've actually visited,
where you hit reload and you're
prompted-- wait a minute,
do you want to do that?
Odds are you've been prompted to
reload explicitly because why?
Whatever you just did
was POST instead of GET.
And by convention, besides
POST being used for privacy
to hide your username, your password,
your credit card number, or the like.
Besides being used to upload
bigger files like images or videos,
POST is also used by convention
to make changes to the server,
to add something to your shopping
cart, to add something to the database.
Whereas GET, as the
name suggests, is all
about getting information, not posting
or sending information instead.
So this is Chrome being a little
careful because if you just checked out
on Amazon and then you
hit reload, you don't
want to accidentally buy the
same book again, so to speak,
even though Amazon and fancy
websites have other defenses
for this too to avoid this issue.
Now there is a bug, though, here.
It says Hello, world instead
of Hello, David, and it
actually would have said
the same a moment ago
and I just didn't retest the
code and reveal as much to you.
Or if I did I didn't even notice it said
Hello, world instead of Hello, David.
It turns out that request.args
is only used for GET.
When using GET, request.args
is a dictionary that
contains all of your key value pairs.
But somewhat confusingly,
when using POST with Flask,
you have to go into request.form.
I have no idea why these are not more
obvious opposites like request.GET,
request.form, and--
sorry, request.GET and request.POST
would be sensible names.
In this case, though, we
have request.args for GET,
and request.form for POST.
All right, that's an easy fix though.
If I go back to VS Code here, let's
change request.args to request.form.
Let's go back to my other tab.
Let me just reload, and you know what?
I'm going to say, OK, continue
to resubmit the same form
because the form was OK, it was
my Python code that was buggy.
Hitting Enter now--
it's accessing David OK.
But watch this-- again if I hit
reload, Command R or Control R,
I get the same Warning.
Are you sure you want
to submit the form?
Yes.
If I do it manually with the reload
icon, I get the same Warning as before.
But if I want to manually induce
a GET request, well that's fine.
Don't hit reload and
send the same request.
Instead go up to your URL and just
put the cursor up there and hit Enter.
And now notice, same
URL is a GET by default.
So any time you and I have
typed URLs into browsers,
GET is always the default. Only
when you click on a button,
typically, that the
programmer has configured
to use POST, are you actually
adding things to your shopping cart,
or the like.
All right, so we are back.
And if I go way back in time
myself, like this is actually
the first web application I
made back in 1997 I believe.
So at the time this would have
been, what, my sophomore or so year.
I had taken CS50, I
took a follow on class
called CS51, which is a
different type of programming.
And then I pretty much taught
myself a language called Perl, which
is somewhat less popular nowadays.
But it's another language like
Python, like Java, like JavaScript,
like others that can be used
to make web based applications.
And the web was very young at the
time and the process via which
students, my classmates, could
register for the first year intramural
sports program-- a.k.a.
frosh IMs was to grab a piece of
paper, and write your name and email
address on it, and walk it across
the yard to Wigglesworth, I believe,
where the Proctor lived.
And you'd slide the piece
of paper under the door,
and that was how we
submitted forms in my day.
So this was an opportunity, even back
in 1997-ish, to move things online.
And the website went on to
live on until I think 2007.
I found this online and then
it's become something else since.
But this was a website via which
people could register for sports,
and people could log in the scores
for various games and whatnot.
And so underneath the
hood, I didn't even
know anything about
databases at the time,
it was just CSV files that
I was storing the data in.
But there were HTML forms.
And there was with Perl, the
language at the time, the way
to do the exact kind of stuff that we've
just been doing already with Flask.
And so what I thought we'd do is
implement a slightly less ugly version
of this.
Repeating graphical backgrounds were
in Vogue in 1997, as you can see here.
But these were the aesthetics of the
day, including the so-called Blink tag.
So let's at least focus on the
functionality of this website
and not so much the
aesthetics, and see if we
can implement some of the plumbing
for actually solving a real world
representative problem.
Be it for freshman intramural
sports, or something else like it
where you're getting data from
users, and processing it somehow.
So let me go over here to VS Code.
Let me create a new directory called
frosh IMs, just so we can keep
all of this code in its own directory.
Let me CD into frosh IMs.
Let me proactively make another
directory called templates,
in which our templates--
our .HTML files--
do need to live.
And eventually I'm going
to go ahead and create two
files minimally, app.py and index.html.
So let's do the first of those, app.py
will live in my frosh IMs directory,
and I'm just going to recreate something
very simple like we have previously.
So from flask in lowercase, import Flask
capitalized, render template, and also
request.
So same first line as before.
Let me then give myself
a variable called app,
set it equal to calling the Flask
function, capital F, with __name__,
and then let me give myself a route for
slash as before with an index function.
Though again, I could
call that anything I want.
And just for now, let's
return render template of,
quote unquote, "index.html"
as though that exists.
So this is not really a web application
as much as it is at the moment
just a recreation of
HTTP server for one file.
Let's now in another tab create a
templates file called index.html.
And I'm going to save
myself a few keystrokes.
Let me copy paste from earlier
almost all of the layout from before.
I've changed the title in advance
to frosh IMs instead of Hello,
but this is essentially
the same template.
And for now, though,
because I'm in index.html,
I'm not going to use extends or
any of that fancy block stuff yet.
I'm just going to go ahead and
create a relatively simple form
via which back in the
day my classmates could
have registered for intramural sports.
So let's go ahead here, and
I'll propose that we do this.
In this page we'll have a form, the
action of which will be a route called
/register, though I could
call that anything I want.
It'll be somewhat private, so I'm
going to use POST instead of GET,
just so that people don't
accidentally maybe register twice
by hitting reload without warning.
Inside of this form, let's
go ahead and give them
an input where autocomplete will be off,
as always, for demonstration's sake.
Auto focus so the cursor
goes there initially.
The name of this field will be literally
name because I want my classmate's name
if they want to register for some sport.
The placeholder will again
be, quote unquote, "name",
just so they see some gray instructions.
And the type of this field
will indeed be text as before.
And then I need to give them the
ability to register for a few sports.
Why don't we keep it simple, like
back in the day basketball, soccer,
and ultimate Frisbee were three
of the sports that we supported.
And so let me do this--
and you might not
have seen this before unless you dabbled
further on with forms on your own.
But I can create a select menu--
otherwise known as a dropdown menu--
in HTML, inside of which are
a whole bunch of options.
And each option typically
follows this paradigm--
the value of the option, and then
the actual text that the human sees.
So the value of these options will
be-- how about we do basketball as one.
And I want the human to see
literally the same thing.
Though just like with a link in
HTML, they could be different,
but I'm going to keep them the same.
Another option will
be, let's say soccer.
And-- oops, let me fix my quotes.
And this human will see
the exact same thing,
though it could say something else.
And then lastly, the value will be,
quote unquote, "ultimate Frisbee",
and the humans will see the same
thing there-- ultimate Frisbee.
All right, so this is going to create,
as we'll soon see, just a dropdown
menu with three separate options.
If I want the students to
be able to submit this now,
let me give them a button,
the type of which is submit.
And this button will be like
the word register on it.
So I think we're pretty much good to go.
This is all just HTML-- no
Python, no Flask per se,
except for the rendering
of this same template.
So let me go into my terminal window.
Let me do Flask run
inside of this directory
because I need to
serve this app instead.
I'm going to see some ugly
output, including my own URL.
And if I hover over that
and then open that URL,
I should now see a
more interesting form.
It's got not only a
field for their name,
but also this dropdown
menu with all three sports.
Now this isn't maybe the
best user experience thus far
because I feel like I'm biasing
people to registering for basketball
maybe because it's checked by
default. I mean a lot of forms
nowadays have a blank
placeholder for the form.
So this is just an aesthetic
thing, but I can do this.
Let me go back to the same
form and let me give myself
just a blank option at the top
that in fact, I'm going to disable.
So you technically can't
select it proactively,
but I am going to select
it by default. And so
we probably haven't seen
those HTML attributes before.
But if I want to create the equivalent
of like a title for this dropdown,
I'm going to literally create a
disabled option that's automatically
selected called Sport so that
you can't select it per se,
but it is there at the top.
So if I go back now to
my other tab, reload--
just marginally prettier than before.
And I'm not biasing people toward
accidentally registering for basketball
alone.
And if I click on this, you'll see that
sport is grayed out and therefore not
manually selectable, but I can select
any of these other three still.
All right, well unfortunately if I
type in David and I try registering,
for instance, for soccer and click
Register, I do end up at /register.
And there's no question
mark, or name, or sport,
so it's probably indeed POST
instead of GET-- those are hints--
but not found.
Notice the tab here very
succinctly says, 404 not found.
Well why is that?
Just to be clear, why did
/register give me a 404?
What's the logic here?
Perhaps just state the obvious, or--
It doesn't exist, right?
We haven't done that
step yet, all right?
So something as simple as that.
And so I actually sort of belabor
that point because as you're
learning a lot of these conventions
and some of this new syntax,
honestly you're just going
to make stupid mistakes.
Something's not going to work.
But again, go back to first principles.
Why is it not found?
All right, register should be a
template maybe called register.HTML.
Oh, I forgot my app.route.
So that should be the kind of
thinking as you try to diagnose
these problems moving forward.
All right, so let me go into app.py, and
let me give myself a second route here.
So app.route, quote unquote, "/route".
Then let me define a function
called anything I want,
but I'm going to call it--
sorry, not /route, /register.
Let me call the function, just
to be consistent, register.
So-- but I could call
that anything I want.
And just for now let's not
do anything too interesting,
let's just return the rendering
of a template called success.HTML.
Let's just pretend for now
that registration is successful
no matter who you are or what you do.
Now I need that template and I
only have index.html at this point.
So let me actually now
do my best practices.
Let me copy all of that.
Let me-- in a separate terminal
window, let me do code--
let me go into my frosh IMs directory.
And let me create a new template
called layout.HTML just like before.
Let me paste all that same code.
Let me delete the form and just
put in that big placeholder,
so block body and then end
block is all I did earlier.
This is just kind of
boilerplate now convention.
Everything else I'm
going to leave the same.
But if I wanted to make it
prettier, I could add my CSS up top.
If I wanted to add this
crazy repeating background,
I could probably do that up top too.
So I can make every page look as
ugly as it did back in my day,
but we'll focus just today on the text.
All right, so add now that I have layout
that HTML, let me clean up index.html.
I don't need all this redundancy.
I don't need all of
these tags at the top.
Instead recall, I think I just
need extends, quote unquote,
"layout.HTML" with the appropriate
signs and curly braces.
I then have the appropriate
block body, though I
could call body anything I want.
But I'm going to stick
with my convention earlier.
And I'm going to delete the tags
down here that I no longer need.
Why?
Because if I go into layout.HTML,
I already have all my open tags,
all my close tags.
The only stuff I want in index.html is
going to be which belongs in the body.
So end block down here.
And just to be pedantic, let me
go ahead and highlight all that.
Hit Shift Tab and that will
unindent it just to line things up.
Just to be tidy.
All right, so better, even though
it looks a little cryptic now.
But now I've laid the
foundation for making
a third page, a fourth page, that
don't have all of that same copy paste.
All right, so now let's
go back into app.py.
Success.HTML is where I left off.
So OK, let me open my terminal window.
Let me code up a template called
success.HTML whose purpose in life
is literally just going to be
to say, you are registered.
Just so that we see some
informative message on the screen.
So this part I do still
need extends layout.HTML.
So there's a little bit of copy
paste still, which is a little ugly
but so be it.
Block body for this template, and I'm
just going to say, you are registered!
All right, and then end block.
So super simple.
It's just an informative
message claiming
that the student is registered.
All right, let's go back to the
original form, which is this.
Let me reload to make
sure my HTML has reloaded.
Type in David, I'm going to register
again for soccer, and click Register.
And, oh, interesting--
method not allowed.
So I'm not getting a 404 anymore,
I'm getting 405 at /register.
What's the deduction here?
How did I screw up this time?
405 is progress.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So it's not--
the placeholder I think is OK.
This is now about the
underlying HTTP stuff.
The method was disallowed--
was not allowed.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Say again?
DAVID MALAN: So GET
versus POST thing too.
So by default, all of these
routes in Flask just by default
assume GET because it's safe.
It doesn't allow you to send information
to the server in quite the same way.
But if I do want to support POST, recall
that we change this to be methods=,
and then a list with, quote
unquote, "POST" in it.
So I just need to enable support for
that method that is that HTTP verb.
All right, let's go back to the form.
Reload just to make sure
I haven't screwed up.
Type in my name David, select soccer
from the dropdown, click Register.
And now I'm not only at
/register in the URL,
it claims that I am indeed registered.
Now of course I'm not--
I've done nothing interesting.
There's no database, there's no CSV
file, we'll get to that in a bit.
But at least I now have
the plumbing in place
to do something dynamic
based on that sport.
All right, well how can
I now improve upon this?
How about we go ahead and implement--
store the actual registrants
in a dictionary in
the computer's memory.
So instead of just claiming
that they're registered,
let's actually make a notation.
And the simplest way as we
did weeks ago in Python,
is just store things in
a variable in memory.
Like a list, or dictionary,
a set, anything like that.
All right, well let me go back
into VS Code and in app.py,
and I think what I'm going to have to
do here is change my register route
to actually do some useful information.
But before I register
the user, let's consider
where I want to actually put them.
And so let me propose
that how about we do this.
At the top of my file, let
me go ahead and declare
a global variable called
registrants, and set
that equal to an empty dictionary.
So we've done this before when
we were playing around previously
with using dictionaries
to store key value pairs.
And I'm going to propose that we store
the registrants as a dictionary why?
Because I'm going to keep it simple.
Like the name is going to be
the student's name-- or sorry,
the key is going to
be the student's name.
And the value is going to be
whatever sport they registered for.
So David and soccer, and Carter
and basketball, and so it's kind
of make sense for a two column
dictionary, so to speak,
as we often depict it on screen.
So how can I use this dictionary?
Well let me go ahead and do this.
Down here under /register, let me
go ahead and initially do this.
How about we get the user's
name from request.form.GET
and set it equal to whatever
the value of name is.
And I'm not going to
give a default value now
because I don't want to call the student
world or something strange like that.
I'm just going to assume
for now that it's there.
Let's then create another
variable called sport, and do
request.form.GET, quote unquote,
"sport" to get these students' sports.
And then let's go ahead and do this--
in the registrant's dictionary, let's
index into it using the
student's name, and let's
set it equal to whatever the sport is.
So I've got these variables
just to keep my code tidy,
and I'm now putting a
key value pair in that--
into that dictionary.
All right, well what
do I want to now do?
And so I'll go ahead and
say success.HTML, sure.
Let's go ahead and do that.
But now I think success.HTML means that.
So let me go back to the form-- reload.
Let me type in David and soccer--
register.
Let me go back and say
Carter and basketball--
register.
OK.
Now let's see what I want to do next.
How about I go into--
let me give myself another route
and let's play around here.
So app.route, let's give
myself another third route
called registrants, whose purpose
in life is just to show me
who all of those registrants are.
Just like you would expect
from a website like this.
And then let me define a function
called registrants or anything else.
And then let me return the rendering
of a template called registrants.HTML.
And let me pass in--
this is kind of neat.
I can do registrants=registrants.
Which again looks weird,
but what am I doing?
I'm presuming to pass
in a placeholder called
registrants, the value of which
is this dictionary that I've been
collecting all of the registrations in.
So similar to the name
placeholder before,
but it's a little more powerful because
now it's a whole dictionary, not just
a single string.
So I think now--
let me be creative here.
Let me go into my templates under my
templates folder and let's do this.
Let's go into my terminal
window, let's create
another template called
registrants.HTML that's
actually going to do this displaying
of all of the registrants for us.
So extends layout.HTML just so I can
borrow all of the same HTML as before.
And let's define block
body just like before.
And inside of this end
block I want to put,
I don't know, a bolded list, or an
ordered list of all of the registrants.
So how can I do this?
Well, let's do an unordered list, UL.
And here's where Jinja and Flask more
generally get kind of interesting.
I want there to be something like this--
an li and then the student's name,
and then an L--
maybe-- li, yeah, like that.
And then maybe sport?
Something like this?
But I didn't pass in a name,
I didn't pass in a sport,
I passed in the entire
dictionary of registrants.
Now in Python, if we
were just doing something
at the black and white terminal window
and doing a command line program,
you know I'd probably have some
kind of for loop in Python.
Jinja does allow you to do this.
So a templating language tends to
come with very lightweight mechanisms
for doing placeholders, doing simple
loops, doing simple conditions.
So Python like syntax,
and it's almost identical.
So watch what I can do.
Inside of this unordered
list, let me not
start to manually output a single
li, let me use this syntax.
The same Jinja syntax that I used for
block, so curly brace percent sign.
And I'm going to say this--
for name in registrants.
So this is just like Python syntax
for iterating over a dictionary.
And now this is going to look stupid,
but the opposite of that is end for.
So in HTML, you use the slash.
In Jinja.
You literally use the
word end, no space,
and then the name of the keyword.
So end for is how you close this.
But this is where
templating gets really cool.
You can now do li, and in here I can
do something like that student's name.
And that's it.
I'm going to leave it like that.
And what I'm doing here is using really
a template as templates are intended.
I've got the basic
building blocks of what
I want this output to look like, but
thanks to this little for loop here,
thanks to Jinja syntax--
the curly brace and
the percent sign, I'm
going to iterate over every dictionary
printing out name, name, name, name.
And so if I've got two kids registered
now, I'm going to see two li's.
David and Carter respectively.
So let's see, let me go back
to my frosh IMs tab here.
And I don't have a link yet,
so I've got to do this manually
like a developer would.
Let me go to /registrants and
I'll Zoom out and hit Enter.
And you'll see what you'll probably
see too when making mistakes
for the first time in this world.
So where is the error message?
Unfortunately internal server
error is not all that useful.
But we do tell you see terminal window.
So if I go to the terminal window,
I haven't been paying attention
to this for quite some time.
And in fact, I have two
terminal Windows open so
that I can still use
commands at the prompt.
But if I go back to my first
terminal window, a.k.a. bash there,
you'll see in your terminal
window when developing
web applications, all of the mistakes
you made in the terminal itself.
This is one of those Python tracebacks
that's related to me screwing up here.
Now let me go ahead here.
And let's see-- type error--
function is not iterable.
End block-- for name
All right, so what mistake did I make?
Well this is what happens
when I don't follow my notes
and make changes on the fly.
So I have this variable on line five
called registrants and all lowercase.
But what did I then do on
the fly here in line 22?
I defined a function called registrants.
So newbie mistake, I
shouldn't have done this.
I can't have a variable and
a function of the same name
because the symbols are
literally identical.
So just to make clear that this
variable up here is actually global,
we'll use our convention like we did in
C often, when we had a global variable.
We'll capitalize it all just to make
it stand out like a constant value
up there.
And so down here, what I'm going to
do is pass in registrants in all caps.
So that was stupid, didn't
mean to confuse there.
But the reason for that
error, to be clear,
is that you can't have a function
that's the same name as a variable.
I could just change the
variable name altogether.
I'm going to go ahead
and just capitalize
it to make it really stand out that this
is, in fact, a global variable up top.
All right, now I'm going
to go back to my browser.
Let's do David and soccer.
All right, but there's going
to be some other mistakes here.
So on line 17, let me go
ahead and change this variable
to be capitalized there because indeed
I want to put the key and the value
in this newly named variable
as all capitals registrants.
Let me now go back to VS Code here.
Let me go back to the form and let
me start adding some data fresh.
Let me register David for soccer.
Clicking register now.
And we should see, you are registered.
But, hopefully, now it's indeed
in the computer's memory.
Let me go back and register
now Carter for basketball.
Clicking register again.
And hopefully it's now registered.
If I now change my route
manually to be /registrants,
which is this newly added route that
I made, and hit Enter, now I see--
thank God.
Now I see the unordered list containing
everything in the computer's memory.
So when I say, you are
registered, I kind of
mean it now because the
server is still running.
And in the computer's memory is,
in this registrant global variable,
a dictionary of key value pairs.
Of course, we're only seeing
the keys at the moment.
So it might be nice to actually
see the values as well.
So let me go back to VS code and
let me go into registrants HTML.
And I'll just do
something a little messy.
I'll just say-- how about--
just to make it a sentence,
is registered for.
And now another placeholder, I'm
going to say registrants bracket name.
So just like in Python,
if registrants is itself
a dictionary, registrants bracket and
then the key you want to index into
is perfectly valid syntax as well.
So now let me go back to /registrants,
let me click reload again.
So why isn't it working everyone?
What's the bug that
I introduced earlier?
If David is registered for none,
and Carter is registered for none,
but David and Carter are in the
dictionary, that's a good thing.
So some of the data is in there.
So why are there no sports associated?
Well the first thing I literally
just did in front of you
all was I went to app.py and
I stared at line 17 thinking,
how did I screw this up?
I'm putting sport as the value of
the key which is the student's name.
All right, line 17 looked
fine to me a few seconds ago.
So I look then with my eyes at
line 16, and this, too, looked OK.
My first thought was, oh did I use
request.args instead of request.form
instead?
Because that would have
assumed GET instead of POST.
But no, that looks OK too.
So then my final instinct was. oh my
God, did I screw up the HTML form?
And so that's why I went
back over to my tab here.
I went to the original form
here, I then view page source.
And this might not be as
obvious to you if you've never
seen the Select menu before--
what is apparently missing here
that might explain my mistake?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: The name is form.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I didn't name this
form field, quote unquote, "sport".
Now to be fair, you haven't seen
me do this as a select menu before
and it's different from this input.
When you have an input tag, you
literally say name= whatever
on the input tag.
It turns out-- I don't know
why I skipped this earlier.
I probably meant to come back
to it-- the select tag also
can take a name parameter.
So if I go back to the name
parameter here and go back
and add the name parameter, let
me go into that template, which
is index.html.
Let me add name= quote unquote,
"sport" in all lowercase,
which is different from the visual
aesthetic of this temporary disabled
option that's just there to make
things prettier for the human.
Now let me go ahead here, and first I'm
going to go into my terminal window,
and I'm actually going to hit Control
C to stop the server altogether
because I want to throw
away the contents of memory
and therefore get rid of that dictionary
that had David and Carter and those non
values.
So this is sort of me clearing
the computer's memory.
I'm going to rerun Flask run.
I get that same URL as before.
So I'm going to hover over
that and open the new tab.
And just to be sure, I'm
going to do view page source.
And here I see now, OK, now the form
has both a name and a sport in it.
All right, now I'm really
going to cross my fingers
because I intend for this now to work.
David will register again for soccer.
Register-- claims we are registered.
I'm going to go back and do it
again for Carter and basketball.
Register-- we still don't have a
link, so I'm going to manually go up
to the URL and change /register
to registrants as before.
Zooming out and hit Enter.
And thank God.
Now I'm actually registered
properly for this.
So-- oh, thank you.
So what is it, like 20
years later, I'm still
struggling to implement this site?
OK, so here now we have for the
first time in Python and web stuff,
now we have a proper web application.
And it's not just echoing back
Hello, David, Hello, Carter--
this could now work for any of you.
And it's currently served privately,
but if I made this URL public,
I could put this on the web now and
let anyone in the world register.
But there's some issues here.
There's some security flaws potentially.
And so for instance, let me
go back to the web form here.
And let me open up the inspect
tab-- the developer tools--
and just remind you that anyone on the
internet, not only you, the developer,
but an adversary can see all of
your HTML, see all of your CSS,
see all of your JavaScript.
But more importantly, because this
is all client side in the browser,
there is literally nothing
technically stopping them
from changing the HTML, or
at least their copy of it.
And I did that last week with Yale.
I changed their website.
But no, I changed my
copy of their website.
But when forms get involved, you
could maybe be actually malicious now.
Because even though
this dropdown menu only
has basketball, soccer, and
ultimate Frisbee, suppose
I really want to register for--
how about let's say--
name your favorite sport.
AUDIENCE: Volleyball.
DAVID MALAN: Volleyball.
We really want to
register for volleyball,
but this website won't let me.
Well there's nothing stopping me
from going under the Elements tab
in my browser, going into
the Select menu here,
and you know what, no one
[INAUDIBLE] ultimate Frisbee.
Let's change this to volleyball.
And let's change this to volleyball--
Enter.
I'm going to close the inspector now.
And as requested, now we
support volleyball in the form.
Now it's not changed on
the server, to be fair,
but think about how HTTP works.
When I fill out this with say,
let's see, Bernie's name--
Bernie really wants to register
for volleyball as well.
At the moment, my code is just going
to trust that what's in request form
is what was in the original
form itself, no matter
whether the human adversarially
actually changed it.
So if I actually submit
this form and click
Register for Bernie and
volleyball, even though that's not
one of the supported available
sports, if I now go to registrants,
my website nonetheless
has trusted that Bernie
and perhaps you are
registered for volleyball.
So what's the implication of this?
Is surely happened in the past
when really poorly implemented
websites allow you to specify the
price of an item, for instance,
in your shopping cart.
And they just trust that when
you click Submit or add to cart
it adds the price to
the back end server.
If you're not validating the price and
making sure, as with a database that,
wait a minute, that price is valid.
Or wait a minute,
those sports are valid.
Who knows what people are
going to do to your site?
And it's that simple to actually
hack a website accordingly.
Now, we can very easily fix this
with some week six style Python.
We really just need to
do a bit of logic here.
And so let me propose this.
Let me go into app.py here.
And at the very top let me also create
how about a global variable called
sports in all caps.
And I'm going to set that
equal to in square brackets
the list of sports I
actually want to support.
So I'm going to put in basketball here,
I'm going to put in soccer here, and--
I'm sorry, no volleyball officially.
I'm going to put in
ultimate Frisbee here.
So I've got this global
list of supported sports.
Now think about how I made
this form a while ago.
I just hardcoded these sports here.
Well I don't have to do that, I can
draw upon my own official list of sports
instead.
So let me scroll down to my
index.HTML rendering template here.
Let me say that the sports
I want to support are these.
So just using the same
placeholder trick as before,
but I'm now telling the template
what sports we currently support.
Now if I go back into index.HTML, I
don't have to manually do any of this.
Let me get rid of all three of
those options, which I manually
inputted earlier, let me use
my new trick with Jinja syntax
and say for sports in sports.
Then let me proactively say end
for, just to finish that thought.
And then in here let me do
option value=value=[? sports ?]..
And then so that the human
also sees the same words,
I'm going to say sport out here.
So I've completely changed
what was hardcoded--
manually typed-- to something
now that's completely dynamic.
So now it's not going to stop
someone adversarially like me
from changing the HTML, but watch this.
The behavior on the form
if we go back is still now
the same dropdown as before.
So aesthetically, it looks the same.
But you know what?
Why don't we be clever now.
And let's go into app.py
and the /register route,
and why don't we say this.
If-- how about sport not in
sports, Then let's return render
template failure.HTML.
Now this template doesn't exist yet.
So let me just quickly
make this real fast.
I'm going to copy that code from before.
Let me create a code
file in failure.HTML.
I'm just going to paste this here.
So we have a super simple error
message, and I'm going to say,
you are not registered.
That's what we mean by failure.
And now in app.py, consider
what logic I've added.
SPORTS in all caps on line
22 is that same global list
as before by asking
[? Pythonically, ?] if sport not
in sports, well then you hacked me.
Like you tried to inject volleyball
or some other sport into request.form.
So I'm just going to say, no
failure, not letting you register.
And I can do this a
little more verbosely too.
Why don't I also say this.
If not name-- so if the name is
blank, let's similarly return
a render template of failure.HTML.
In other words, if you
didn't give me a name,
you left it blank, that's not useful
for me running the sports program.
Let's also consider
that to be a failure.
So if I go back to
this tab now, I'm going
to reload just to make sure I have
the latest client side, let me be lazy
and just click Register.
Enter.
You are not registered because
I didn't give it an actual name.
All right, well let's go back.
How about I now type David but no,
I'm not going to choose a sport.
I just want to register myself.
Nope, that did not work.
Now let me go ahead
here and choose soccer.
This, I think, does work.
Let me go back now and try this hacker
trick whereby I go into the dropdown
menu, I go into the Select menu.
I change, as before, ultimate
Frisbee to volleyball,
and I'll change this
one here to volleyball.
Let me close the tab now.
This looks like it's available now,
but when I click Register this time,
it says you are not registered.
And this is much better than
relying on other techniques you
might see or have seen online with
regard to HTML because there's also
this trick.
Let me go back to the screen here.
Let me go back to index.html,
and you might have seen online,
or you might eventually
see online that there's
other attributes you
can use like required.
You can literally tell the browser,
uh-uh, this field is required.
You cannot leave it blank.
If I go back to the browser now,
reload, and I again presume to be lazy
and I don't type in any
name and click Register--
So that's kind of nice.
Now the browser is being a little more
helpful for me, saying no, no, no.
This is required.
You have to fill this out.
But again, if you know
what you're doing.
OK, well I disagree with
your requiring a name of me.
Let me go in here.
Let me go over to this tag, let
me delete the required attribute,
and now I slip through.
But I didn't slip through on the server.
And so there's a difference here
and an important distinction,
and so many people in the real
world still screw this up.
There's client side validation,
like actually checking
that the data is as you expect
on the client side, the browser.
And there's server side validation.
And even though client side validation,
adding that required attribute
makes things more user friendly, right?
Like that was a pretty little pop up.
It tells me that it's required.
It just looks better than
the previous version.
It is not trustable.
You cannot trust any input that ever
comes from the user because clearly
with an hour or so of CS50, they can
learn how to turn all of these defenses
off.
So even if you like the user
interface better client side,
you have to, have to, have to do
server side validation always.
Users are not to be trusted.
And as soon as any app or
website you make becomes popular,
unfortunately then you have to deal with
all of the adversarial possibilities
as well.
AUDIENCE: Is there any way you
can hack inside the server side
information or potentially hack
[INAUDIBLE] or something like that?
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
Could the adversary potentially
access things sensitive like app.py?
Theoretically no.
If Flask itself is
buggy, then sure, maybe.
If you're running some other software
on your server on your laptop then sure,
it's possible.
However, if your server
is properly configured,
theoretically they should not
be able to get access to that.
With that said, we'll
soon see, or you might
with your final project if
you do something web based,
you're never going to
want to write usernames
and passwords in your actual code.
You can put them in what are
called environment variables.
So sort of in the
computer's memory, but not
in your code just in case
you or someone screws up,
there are still ways to defend
against those kinds of possibilities,
however slim.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] making sure
volleyball didn't get registered.
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
And this comes back to first principles,
just like in C and in Python,
as soon as you return from
a function, that's it.
Nothing below that
line of code executes.
And so to summarize the
question, even though I'm
returning this
failure.HTML template, how
am I making sure we still don't
accidentally put volleyball
in that global dictionary?
It's because, for instance,
if you don't give me a name,
on line 22 at the moment, I'm returning
the failure template and that's it.
Lines 23, 24, 25, 26, 27 never execute.
In particular, 26 never
executes, and that's
where I would have been saving the name.
Similarly, if we do we get an invalid
sport that is either blank or not
in the original authoritative
list, we return failure.HTML
as a template in line 25.
We never get to line 26.
So it just boils down to return
and what that means in Python too.
Good question.
Other questions as well?
No?
All right, how about we make
one more enhancement here or so.
Because the problem with storing
everything in this global dictionary
might be what?
We've got it all
working, finally, but why
is probably a global
dictionary not the place
to store frosh IMs registration data?
What's the implication of this?
AUDIENCE: Might slow the whole process.
DAVID MALAN: OK, it might
slow the whole process down.
But that actually--
RAM is actually good.
Memory is actually
generally a good thing.
So not going to be a dealbreaker here.
Why might I not want to store that
data, though, in that variable?
You can perhaps infer how
I fixed something earlier.
Yeah, in the back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it gets--
it's-- the memory gets deleted.
Garbage collected, if you will,
as soon as Flask stops running.
So if you so much as hit Control C,
you've just lost all of your freshmen
who registered for the sport.
Probably not a good thing.
I did this deliberately a moment ago
and I hit Control C because I did
want to clear the dictionary, but
trusting that your server will never
crash, and your code will always
work, and the power will never go out,
that's not the right way to
build any kind of web application
with persistent data.
So what we probably want
to do is reintroduce CSVs
and we've played with
those in C and in Python.
Could totally use CSVs, but we
also now have SQL at our disposal.
And let me propose that
we do this in SQL instead.
And for this, let me go ahead and
open up a version of the program
that I wrote in advance.
So let me go ahead and
close these templates
which will look very similar
but a little different
from the ones I wrote in advance.
And let me go ahead and
open up in today's--
let me go into source nine, let
me go into frosh IMs how about--
version four, technically,
in the versions online.
And let me go ahead and
open up app.py as follows.
So here is an already made version that
does just a little something different.
At the very top, I'm
importing CS50 SQL library,
which you might recall
we used a couple of weeks
pass just to write Python
that talks to a SQL database.
And this feels like an opportune
moment to bring that idea back.
Down here on line eight,
I'm creating a DB variable
that opens up a file called frosh IMs.db
using syntax that we've seen before.
I did create this frosh IMsdb
file in advance of class
just so that we have a
couple of columns in which
to store names and sports and such.
Here's that same global array
a global list called sports,
and let's just see what's
going on down below.
If I scroll down to
index, this is the same
as before as we wrote
together on the fly.
Let's skip de-register for a
moment and go now into register.
So this one's a little different,
but let's see what I've done.
I've got some comments in here
because I wrote it in advance.
And I think this logic is pretty much
the same, though I tightened it up.
And I'm asking two questions at once
using on line 38, the or keyword here.
Just to say, if there's
not a name, or the sport
is not in sports, that is what
we'll call, now, a failure.
But what's fun now is that on
line 42, I'm using the CS50 SQL
library to execute some actual SQL.
And I'm going to insert into a table
called registrants two columns--
name and sport.
What names and sport?
Well these two values with placeholders,
plugging in name and sport.
Notice I'm using the question marks.
Absolutely necessary so we don't
get one of those SQL injection
attacks because that
too could be possible
if someone typed in some dangerous
words or keywords like delete,
or single quotes, or
semicolons in the form.
Here I'm letting the
library sanitize the data.
And then this is a trick
we haven't yet seen,
and it's really going to
start tying things together.
I can also use a redirect function
in Flask that has the effect of doing
the, if you will,
safetyschool.org trick again,
whereby after the user registers, if
I want to automatically show them now
everyone who is registered
at /registrants,
I don't have to manually expect that
they'll change the URL like I've been
doing for the past few minutes.
I can just redirect them
anywhere I want on my app.
Or heck, I could redirect them to any
URL on the internet using this function
call.
And it's just a nice way to
send them to a different route
if you want them to see, in
this case, those registrants.
So let me do this.
In the same directory, let me
increase my terminal window size.
Let me do SQLite three of frosh
IMs.db, and let me type .schema.
And you can indeed see
it wraps onto two lines
here that each registrant has an ID--
which will be automatically
assigned 1, 2,
3, on up-- a name
which is not null text,
and a sport which is also the same.
And the primary key is just going
to be this unique identifier.
So that I made in advance.
But if I do select star
from registrants semicolon,
there's no one currently
registered for any sports.
But let's try now running this.
Let me go ahead and close my old
version, which we wrote together.
And I'll close that tab.
Let me do Flask run in
this version four here.
All right, I'm going to
see some similar output.
I'm going to open the URL now.
And you'll see that I made
a couple of changes before.
Instead of using a select menu, I used
what are called radio buttons now,
which is a reference to
old school radio buttons
that were mutually exclusive
in cars back in the day.
And we'll see how to do this.
But it's just an alternative
to a select menu.
And I'm going to go ahead and
type in my name again here.
So I'll do David, I'll do soccer
by selecting this radio button,
and I'm going to click Register now.
And notice what happened.
It's a little ugly the formatting,
but so again was this 20 years ago.
Here I have now at the /registrants
route, instead of an unordered list,
I'm just using a simple HTML table.
So I'll show you what this
looks like in just a moment too.
And I'll show you this
deregister button,
which is sort of unnecessarily large.
I also have functionality,
we'll soon see,
for how you can unregister
someone from a sport as well.
So take your name out of contention.
Well, let me go back to
my terminal window here.
And I'm going to click the plus to give
myself a second terminal so I can go
back into source nine frosh IMs four.
I'm going to do SQLite of frosh IMs.db.
I'm going to do select
star from registrants now,
and now you'll see that indeed
there's David registered for soccer.
And in fact, if I quit the Flask program
with Control C and rerun it again,
no big deal because that
next version of Flask
will just use the database as well.
So I'm persisting keeping
the data in SQLite,
whereas I'm actually grabbing it
using my Python code in Flask.
All right let's put one more person in
here so we can delete one of us too.
Carter for basketball, register,
and now we see both of us here.
All right, so let's see how we did this.
Let's go back over to VS Code, let
me shrink down my terminal window.
Let me go into the--
actually let's go into
the templates directory,
and let's look at, for
instance, index.html.
So previously we were
using a select menu.
Turns out radio buttons
use the input tag,
but instead of having an input of
type=text, like for the human's name,
you have type=radio.
And so long as each
of your radio buttons
has the same name, the
same name, the same name,
that's what makes them
mutually exclusive.
So checking one radio
button turns off the others
because they have the same name.
The value I want to assign to
each of these radio buttons
is just the sport placeholder.
This is what the human
sees on the screen.
So it's almost the same
as the Select menu,
it just looks aesthetically different.
But there's my same button.
So that's all the
difference I made there.
And I added a heading tag, H1, just to
say register to make clear what it is.
But let's take a look at another file.
This one now being, how
about the /registrants route.
So if I open up
registrants.HTML here now,
it's way more verbose
than my unordered list.
But this is just kind of boring HTML.
Here's my table tag, table
head, table row, table heading.
This makes things bold as
the first row of the table.
Name, sport, are my two columns.
I've got a third empty column
just so I can fit that button,
as we'll soon see again.
T body for table body.
Here's the same for loop trick
again so that I can output
for every registrant a whole table row.
And there's this weird form in
there, but we'll come back to that.
But there's the registrant's name,
there's the registrant's sports.
But notice the slightly
different syntax here.
Recall that CS50's select--
CS50's execute function, when it
returns to you a list of dictionaries,
you can then get at the individual
columns by way of those keys.
So let's go to the /registrants route.
Let me go back to app.py, scroll down
here, and it's actually super simple.
Here I have a /registrants route
that first executes select star from
registrants.
So just old SQL stuff.
Give me every one from
the registrants table,
let me then render the template
called registrants.HTML
and just pass in this
list of dictionaries.
And we haven't quite done
this yet, but if you go back
to registrants.HTML, how do you iterate
over each dictionary in that list?
Well the syntax is just for
registrant and registrants.
That makes this a dictionary one at a
time in the list, just like in Python.
So registrant.name and
registrant.sport is just another syntax
for using the square bracket notation.
It's just a little
cleaner and slightly more
succinct than having quotes
and square brackets everywhere.
And then the rest of this is just HTML.
So what happens now if I want to--
Carter been cut from the
basketball team, if you will.
So how do we do that?
Well, we want to click this button,
deregister, next to Carter's name.
But how does this work?
And think about now
any website you visited
that has something like a shopping
cart where you can remove things
from your cart, or update quantities,
or add more quantities to your shopping
cart on Amazon or anything else.
Well, let's actually look at the
HTML that my app has spit out.
Let's actually look
at this here and we'll
see the following-- we'll see
that we have here in the HTML
that reached the user, not only is
David in the first column, soccer
and the second, notice that my
registrants.HTML form is also spitting
out a tiny little web form of its own.
It's ugly but I only care about
its functionality for now.
And notice what I'm doing here.
Every registrant in this database
gets their very own deregister button.
And that form has a button
that says deregister.
But notice what else
each of those forms have.
There's no text box, there's no
dropdown menu, there's no radio buttons.
Rather you have a
hidden input field here.
So there is a way with HTML to have
a form that will submit information,
but you don't have to give the user
the ability to change that information.
You can just go ahead and tuck it inside
of the form invisibly, if you will.
Hidden in fashion.
And so what's going to happen is
if I click the deregister button
next to Carter, his primary key is two.
Mine is instead one.
So what's going to happen if
I click his deregister button?
It submits a form with a ID
parameter whose value is two,
and it submits it to
the de-register route.
So what does that mean?
Well, if I go to VS Code
and I go to app.py let's
look at the de-register
root that I skipped over.
So if you access the deregister route
via POST, this code gets called.
I grab from request.form the ID that
was submitted in hidden fashion.
If there's indeed an ID, that is
it's not blank, it's not zero,
it's an actual number
like 1, 2, 3, or more,
I execute delete from
registrants where ID = that value
with a question mark placeholder.
And then I redirect the
user back to registrants.
Now if I go back to this form
here, I click deregister,
we'll see that in action.
Gone is now Carter.
And in fact, if I go back
to my terminal window here,
I open up SQLite three of frosh IMs.db
and rerun select star from registrants,
Carter is now gone.
So again using very
simple HTML forms, you
can get buttons, and links,
and other such UI mechanisms
to do things on the
server that you want.
But there is a danger here.
This now is really meant-- this
example as an administrative website
like it was some 20 years ago just for
us internal staff to be doing things.
Technically this is dangerous,
what I've just done, too.
Even though Carter's ID is two and
hidden, and mine is one and hidden,
what could this allow an
adversary to do if they
had admin access to the same site?
Any thoughts?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Could they change
the value and then deregister?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
They could change the value
of that hidden attribute
by opening up Chrome's, developer
tools, change the number in the HTML.
They could delete anyone, de-register
anyone they want from the database.
Now in this case, I claim this
is fine because this is only
meant for us staff who were
running sports back in the day.
But it's indeed a risk.
So wouldn't it be nice
if we could actually
ensure that only those
users who are authorized
are allowed to execute certain actions?
I think for this
capability we're actually
going to need to introduce
something a bit more.
And so here, of course,
is an opportunity
to talk briefly about, really, what
you and I do all day long every day.
We log in to one or
more websites or apps,
or at least until you're
logged out automatically
and you have to do it again.
So here for instance, is
a screenshot of Gmail.
When you type in your username,
you type in your password, maybe
your two factor code that gets
texted or sent to your phone,
then you're logged in.
And thankfully you're not prompted
to log in again, typically,
for a number of hours, or days, or
weeks, depending on the website.
Like Gmail keeps you logged in for ages.
Your bank probably logs you out within
an hour or so for safety's sake.
So that is completely
configurable on the server.
But how does Gmail know,
how does Google know
that even as you're checking
different mails again, and again,
and again, how do they know that you're
still the same person who logged in?
Well it turns out that using these
same building blocks as today--
HTTP and HTML and more--
you can actually implement
the notion of a login feature
by doing the equivalent of something
with something called cookies.
Essentially what happens
when you first log
into a website for the very
first time successfully
with your username and
password, a cookie, so to speak,
is planted on your computer.
And metaphorically, this is kind
of like taking a hand stamp,
and your hand is now
stamped-- in this case,
a smiley face-- so that
every other time you
click on a link on that
same website-- google.com,
gmail.com, whatever--
unbeknownst to you,
your browser is constantly
presenting that hand stamp.
Just like going into a club, or
an amusement park, or something
like that where they don't
want to check your ID again.
They don't want to
check your ticket again,
they just want to quickly
see the same hand stamp.
And so that is one of the
things that a browser is always
doing for you once you're logged in.
Any cookies that have been planted, so
to speak, in your Mac, or PC, or phone,
are constantly represented to the
site every time you click a link
or make another request to that website.
And mechanically how this works,
not just metaphorically in ink,
essentially this is what happens.
Here is an example of an HTTP
request to something like Gmail.
And suppose, for instance,
that you've logged in.
Typically, as of last week, we said
that coming back from the server
would be another virtual envelope
containing a 200 OK message, and then
the actual web page, or the picture
of a cat, or whatever it may be.
But Google can also, if they
verified that you have some username
and password correctly
inputted, they can do
the equivalent of stamping your hand.
And the way they do this is
they send an additional line
of text in that virtual envelope
from the server to your browser,
literally using another HTTP header.
Not content type-- which just mundane
tells you what kind of content
has come back-- they literally send
an HTTP header called set-cookie.
And then they set a key
value pair on your Mac or PC.
This is the technical equivalent
of this smiley face hand stamp.
And what your computer
is designed to do--
because your computer and internet
browser are supposed to implement
HTTP--
any time you click another link on
Gmail, or click on another mail,
or the like, your browser unbeknownst
to you, presents that hand stamp.
And how it does it technically
is in the envelope it
sends to Google from
your browser, it doesn't
send set-cookie it just sends
cookie: and the exact same thing.
And so long as Google is smart and
they have a database or something
of all of the session values--
session is the technical term for this
maintenance of information across HTTP.
So long as Google has
a big database that
knows that my cookie value is 1, 2,
3, and your cookie value is 4, 5, 6,
they can infer from
this virtual hand stamp
whose emails they should be showing.
Mine or yours or the like.
So this is just scratching the surface.
But if I really want it to enable
only Carter to deregister himself,
I just have to make sure
that I log him in somehow--
username, password, all of that.
I stamp his hand, or really,
put a cookie on his computer.
And only if his cookie
lines up with the user
ID he's trying to deregister should
he be allowed to in fact do so.
So all of this is quite possible.
And indeed the technical
term for this is session.
And what we thought we'd do
in our remaining time today,
show you some examples of exactly
how some of the most familiar web
functionality is implemented
today, some of which
you'll use in your own problem set
nine, which itself will be a web
app or perhaps even your final project.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me close my previous tabs and
all things frosh IMs, and let's move
on to implementing some notion of login.
So in just a moment, I'll
switch over here to VS Code,
and what I'm going to do is indeed
in my source nine directory,
I'm going to go into a login directory.
And if I type ls here,
you'll see app.py,
requirements.txt, which
just refers to libraries I
want to automatically install,
and a templates folder as well.
I'm going to go ahead and
stop the previous server
and close that terminal
window, and I'm going
to open up this version of app.py.
So there's a few new lines here.
And we'll give you these
lines for problem set nine,
but I've got some of the familiar stuff
up here, including this new redirect
function we just used.
And I have a session variable
that comes with Flask too.
So what's nice again about
Flask is that it deals
with all of this cookie stuff for you.
It sets the cookie.
It checks the cookie.
And what Flask does
for you is it gives you
the abstraction of a variable
called session so that anything
you put in the session variable,
which itself is a dictionary,
will be there again,
and again, and again
whenever that same user comes back.
A session is how you
implement, essentially,
the proverbial shopping cart.
If I'm logged into Amazon,
you're logged into Amazon,
Amazon knows which of us is
which by way of that cookie.
And Amazon, if they're using
Flask, provides the programmer
with a dictionary called session.
And flasks make sure that when
Carter is visiting the site,
the code uses his session object.
When I'm visiting the site,
it uses my session object.
But it's all implemented
with those same cookies.
This is the same as before.
These lines are new, and you'll
see these in problem set nine.
This is how we enable
sessions in a web application.
And I'll just wave my
hands at the detail.
There's different ways
to implement sessions,
whether you use cookies on the
server, cookies on the browser,
or other things.
These just ensure that we're
storing the session information
the shopping cart on the server itself.
Now down here, let's
go ahead and do this.
Let's go ahead and run Flask.
Run so I can see what this app does.
If I do this and visit the
URL that gets outputted,
you'll see a very simple web page here.
And if I type in, for
instance, my name--
I'm not going to bother with
a password-- and click Log In,
you'll see that you
are logged in as David.
And now I can log out.
So I'm going to go
ahead and click Log Out.
And now it seems to know
that I'm not logged in again.
I can log in as Carter because I
didn't bother implementing passwords
for simplicity, but now the site
knows I'm logged in as Carter.
Better yet, if I reload, reload,
reload, or click this button again,
and again, notice it still knows
that I'm Carter until such time
as I log out.
All right, well how is this working?
Well let's go back to
VS Code here and let
me scroll down to, first, this route.
This is a very common
paradigm here whereby
I'm checking for the index route.
If there is not a name in the
session, redirect the user to /login.
Now what does that mean?
Well, let me go back to VS Code here.
Let me go to the /route.
So again, your URL will
be different, but I'm just
going to go to slash and hit Enter.
Notice that I got automatically
redirected to log in.
And so many websites do this.
If you go to a website and you're not
logged in, you're very often redirected
to /login, or /account, or something
like that, where you're prompted.
The code for doing that is right here.
If there's no name in the session, if
there's no name in the shopping cart,
if you will, go ahead and return
the user to log in, that route.
Otherwise, , implicitly if they are
logged in, show them index.html.
So let's go down that rabbit hole.
Let me open up in VS Code
a second terminal window.
Let me go into source nine and go
into this same login demonstration,
and let me open up the
template called index.html.
And here's all this is.
There some layout, but
who cares at this point,
it's just the boilerplate generic HTML.
Here is the body block.
I have this.
And this, too, is Jinja because of the
curly brace and the sign. percent sign.
If there's a name in the session--
this is just Python syntax--
then say this sentence.
You are logged in as--
whatever name is in the session,
in the shopping cart, if you will.
And then I just have this HTML
link for logging the user out.
Else if there is no name
in the session, logically,
just say you are not logged in.
And give them a manual link
for logging in instead.
So that's all this particular template
does, but how does the /login work?
Well let's go into this other
template, code of login.HTML,
to which I'm redirected.
Super simple.
This is just copy
paste from HTML before.
I've got a login form that's
going to have an action of /login,
submits for privacy sake just by a
POST, and then the rest of this is just
a simple form.
And I'm using an input type=submit
instead of button=type=submit,
but same idea here too.
And if I go back to app.py,
well let's see how login works.
All right.
It's a lot all at once, but they're
relatively simple reapplications
of the same idea.
So if the user visits /login via GET
or POST, call this function login.
If the user has submitted via POST,
and we saw this technique before,
go ahead and do this on line 23.
Store in this special session variable
that comes with Flask a name key,
and store in it the user's own name.
So, quote unquote, "name" will have a
value of David, or Carter, or the like.
And as soon as you do that,
redirect the user back
to slash just so they
see the home page again.
And this is how Amazon and all
these other websites work too.
Otherwise if they visit this
page implicitly via GET,
and even though I didn't
say = = GET anywhere,
that's the implication because if you
can only get here by a GET or POST,
and we already handled POST,
logically all that remains is GET.
Well then just show them
the login screen instead.
But there's a half a dozen ways
we could express that same logic.
And then for log out, this
is kind of straightforward.
If the user clicks that logout link
and ends up at /logout, this route,
well just change the value of that
key in the session to be none.
Effectively, no, Carter is gone.
David's gone.
There's no one logged in.
So that is all that's
required to actually implement
the notion of logging in and
logging out of a website.
Plus the password thing, which
should probably involve the database,
but one thing at a time.
And really, session is sort of like
the code version of a shopping cart
whereby if I visit the same code,
I get my own session object.
If Carter visits the website,
he gets his own session object.
And the way Flask keeps
us straight is they
put one cookie on my computer, a
different cookie on his computer,
and uses those to line up with
making sure the right session gets
shown to the right actual user.
Questions on this notion of sessions?
No?
All right, how about a couple of final
examples just to tie this all together.
Let me go back into VS Code here.
Let me quit my previous
version of Flask.
Let's go into source
nine and go into store,
which is a separate app altogether.
And let's start by just running
Flask to see what it does.
Let's hover over the URL
and open it in another tab.
And this is pretty ugly too.
Let me Zoom in.
But it's a very simple bookstore.
Like an early amazon.com for
each of these seven books here,
each of which seems to be--
maybe this is H1, this
is H2, H2, H2, H2.
And then there's a
button underneath each.
Well now let's use this as an
opportunity to kind of infer,
like for any website,
how this thing works.
Let me go ahead and
do view page source--
and you can do this for any
website on the internet.
Let's try to figure out how this
bookstore adds things to a cart.
Well here's the H1 tag.
Uninteresting.
H2, H2, H2.
So the juicy part is in these forms.
Each of these forms
has an action of /cart,
so that's the route that's going
to be interesting in a moment.
And it uses POST for privacy's sake.
Each of these forms like the
deregister feature for Carter,
has an ID attribute-- an ID
parameter that's hidden, visually,
that has a value of 1, or 2, or 3.
So like the unique bar codes
for the books, if you will.
But super small numbers, in our case.
And then each of these
other forms just--
each of these other books
has an identical form
except for the value of this here.
Now in this case, this
isn't such a big deal
that a user could technically hack the
HTML of this bookstore, amazon.com,
and change the IDs because, whoa,
what's the worst they're going to do?
Buy more books by adding more
IDs to their shopping cart?
That's not a problem.
There's no prices here, it's
just the unique ideas of books.
So whereas the deregister
was maybe worrisome
because you're changing
the server, I think
it's OK because the user can only
at worst buy more books than they
might via the buttons alone.
So how does this now work?
Well let's go into VS Code again here.
Let me give myself
another terminal window.
And in source nine/store let me open up
app.py which is where all the logic is.
So I'll flip through most of this
quickly because we've seen this before.
These imports are pretty
much the same as before.
This line is the same.
This line is almost the
same but the database now
is called store.db
instead of frosh IMs.db.
This is the boilerplate code
for just enabling sessions,
this notion of a shopping cart.
And so let's see how the index works.
How is it I'm seeing
all seven books at once?
Well in this index function, I'm using
on line 19, select star from books
to get all the books from the database.
And then I'm rendering a template
called bookstore HTML passing in
as a placeholder all of those books.
All right, let's go down that
rabbit hole for a second.
Let me open up books.HTML
in my templates directory.
And here again, even
though it's new today,
it's probably increasingly
familiar syntactically.
Here's the H1.
Here is my loop.
Here's the H2, which is going to output
the current book's title in that loop.
Here's the form.
Here's the ID of that book that's
going to be outputted in the form.
So I didn't manually type out seven long
forms, I just did one in this template
so that it gets generated automatically.
Literally what a website
like Amazon would
do to show you 10 books at a time, or
10 search results or more at a time.
All right, well let's go to
/cart, which was the juicy one.
And this one's longer, but let's
see if we can reason through it.
If the user submits via GET or POST
to /cart, well we first do this.
And this is just necessary
and some boilerplate rewrote.
We're going to use the session object
to store a variable called cart that
in this case, is going to be a list.
So session, again, is just a dictionary.
You can put anything in it you want.
Previously we put
students' names and sports.
Now what I want to do is--
sorry, previously we put the
student's name, the user's name in it.
Now I'm going to actually store
a cart key whose value is a list.
Why?
Because I want to aggregate more
and more books in this list.
All right, so that just makes sure that
I have at least an empty shopping cart
the very first time the user does this.
If they visit this form via POST, let's
go ahead and get the ID of the book
that they posted.
If it is not empty, if there is
a number, like 1, or 2, or 3,
let's go ahead and go
into the shopping cart--
which is a list, per this line--
and just append that ID.
So this list of books
in your shopping cart
is going to contain 1, 2, 4, 6,
whatever books you're actually buying.
And then the user gets
redirected to cart.
What if, though, the user got
here via GET and not POST?
Well this one's relatively
straightforward.
If you just visit /cart, we select
star from books where ID is in--
OK, so this is interesting--
this list.
And this is syntax you
might not have seen before.
But if you read the documentation
for CS50's library, if you
select something and use a
question mark placeholder,
and the placeholder itself is a list, we
output a comma separated list of values
just like you would use
maybe in problem sets seven
for doing SQL queries on your own.
So this just means show me only
those books in my shopping cart.
Not Carter's, not someone else's,
not in the whole database,
only show me the books in my shopping
cart and then render it as such.
So we only saw what the catalog
here looks like at /books.
Let's go ahead and add maybe
the first book to my cart.
And now I see at /cart only
that first book whose ID is one.
Let me now go back to
the bookstore here,
scroll down to maybe the seventh
book and add that to my cart.
And now I see this here too.
Meanwhile all of this information
is stored in my session.
And so when I reload this
cart again and again,
the reason I'm only seeing
my two is because we're
checking only the list in my session.
And flasks make sure, again, that my
session is different from your session,
is different from
Carter session as well.
But you write the code once
and it works for thousands,
millions of people in parallel.
Any questions on this?
Yes, in the back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sorry, say a little louder.
DAVID MALAN: So to recap.
So users will never have
the same session values.
Theoretically, the
cookie that gets planted
does not look like a
smiley face for everyone.
Each of us gets a big random
number that's assigned to us.
So it'd be like each of us
gets a completely unique hand
stamp that no one else can see.
The reason no one else can see it is
because if the website's using HTTPs,
every time this hand stamp is shown,
every time this cookie is sent back
and forth, it's all encrypted as well.
So each of us can-- even if we have
the same contents by coincidence
because we like the same books,
they will be separate cookies,
separate memory, separate sessions.
Behind you.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
When does the session end?
Totally configurable.
Typically it ends when you close the
tab or when you quit the browser.
Or you can also configure cookies to
themselves be persistent for a day,
for a week, for a longer.
So for instance, when
you log into say Gmail,
they plant a cookie on
your computer probably
for a week, a month, a
year, something like that
because it would be annoying and
probably drive you to Outlook
or something else if you kept
having to log into your account.
Whereas your bank account might actually
wait for you to just close the tab.
And then for your own
financial safety they just
automatically delete
the session far sooner.
But totally configurable.
By default as I'm using
it, it will typically
be thrown away when the
browser itself quits.
And here, too, is another reason to
develop websites using incognito mode
because if you want to just
throw away all of your cookies,
you close the incognito window mode.
Open a new one and now
you're starting from scratch.
You don't have to manually
delete all your cookies,
which could log you out of
websites you actually care about.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
When using sessions, if
someone maliciously changes
the value of such forms,
could it affect other people?
Theoretically, no because
the worst you can do
is like add books to your own shopping
cart that you don't want there.
So at that point, even
though it's on the server,
it doesn't affect you, or
Carter, or anyone else,
unless there is something more globally
happening like registering for a sport,
or removing books from
the Amazon database.
That would be problematic.
But in this case, we're removing
things only from my own session
that the website is giving me.
All right, the last topic
for today is this thing here,
which is sort of everywhere
nowadays, these things
called APIs, or application
programming interfaces.
And this is a very
generic term, in fact.
Because any function you've used
in C, in Scratch, in Python,
in SQL, are all APIs.
There is a standard way of
interfacing with those functions.
They all have names.
They sometimes have return values.
They sometimes have arguments.
And an API is just how
you use a function.
Or more generally an API just specifies
how you interact with some service.
And so nowadays there's a
lot of web based services
that you can use to get back data
like the weather, or the current time,
or the database of Amazon
books, for instance,
all might have APIs,
often web based, that
allow you, using URLs or
some other technology,
to just get data from
someone else as though it's
a function you're calling remotely.
But HTTP is very often
the mechanism that's
used to actually get data from servers.
And the way the data can
come back can be as follows.
Let me end with one final example
using some of our familiar shows
from weeks past.
Let me go ahead and close the old
Flask version, go back into source nine
and go into--
how about an example called shows.
And the first version of
this, zero, I'm just going
to go ahead and run with Flask run.
I'll hover over my URL and open it here.
And you'll see now that I have a very
simple form, as we keep doing today.
I'm going to type in
like O-F-F-I-C-E, office,
into this search box and click Search.
And you'll see now that I ended up
at a URL ending in /search?q=office.
So this is like my own baby version of
google.com but I implemented it myself.
And for any title of a TV show from
a couple of weeks past that matches
O-F-F-I-C-E, I spit it out
into an unordered list.
How is this working?
You can maybe imagine,
even if you might not
be able to program this off the top
of your head, certainly, so soon--
let me go into source nine.
Let me go into show zero,
let me open up app.py.
And in this file, you'll
see that I'm grabbing
a file called shows.db, which is
like a simpler version of the one
from a couple of weeks passed.
Here is why I see the web form.
My first route, my
index is super simple.
It just spits out that form.
And my search route, you can
think of this as google.com,
is only like four lines of code.
So if the user sends data to /search,
this function called search is called.
I declare a variable
called shows, I execute
a SQL command that is select star from
shows where title like question mark.
And the syntax here is
a little crazy, but I
want to prefix to the
user's input percent sign,
and suffix it with a
percent sign as well,
putting in between those two
values the actual input, why?
In SQL what does it mean if you
have a percent sign to the left
and to the right?
Nothing to do with Jinja today.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's a wild card.
So it means match zero or
more characters on the left,
or match zero or more
characters on the right,
you have to do the concatenation as
the second argument to this function.
You can't do something clever like
put it here around the question mark,
the question mark is the placeholder
that you plug these values into.
But this just means, hey SQL, show me
all of the titles that have O-F-F-I-C-E
somewhere in them.
That gives me back a
list of dictionaries.
I pass that in as a placeholder
for a variable called shows,
and if we look at search.HTML,
let's look at that.
In my templates directory there's
something called search.HTML.
Super simple, I mean this is like the
essence of google.com search results.
I'm using an unordered
list to keep things simple,
but I integrate over every show
in the show's list that came back,
and I output an li with
each of those shows' titles.
And that's it.
Now Google has blue links, and
little previews, and other text,
the first sentence or so from each page.
But that's the idea.
This is really similar in spirit to
what google.com/search does for you.
Now how is this working there's
no app.py involved here yet.
This is just very basic HTTP.
I submit the form, I go to another
route, and I get back the results.
But check out this version.
Let me close these tabs here and
open my first terminal window.
Let me go into shows one from
today's source nine directory
and do Flask run this time.
Let me go ahead and hover over
that URL and open it here.
And gone now is the Submit button.
Now I'm going to make a user interface
that uses a technique called AJAX--
for Asynchronous, JavaScript, and
XML, which is somewhat of a dated term
because we're not using
something called XML anymore.
But AJAX is a technique whereby you
don't have to submit forms anymore
to get more data from the server.
You can use JavaScript, per last week,
listen for an event like the key press
coming down or up, and as soon
as you hear such an event,
you can secretly in JavaScript code
send a request to the server to get back
more data, and then plug it
into the Dom-- the tree--
in the computer's memory.
And this just makes for
more seamless experiences
like autocomplete on any website.
So now let me try typing O--
we got autocomplete super fast.
F-F-I-C-E. And you'll see every
time I add more keys to my input,
I'm doing another search,
another search, another search,
and the data is changing.
Now how is this working?
Well let me go back to VS Code here.
And in my other terminal
window, let me open up app.py.
And in app.py, you'll
see that there's still
a search route down below that returns
a search template, but watch this.
Let me go into templates/search.HTML and
notice here that we're indeed getting
back an unordered list of shows
again, and again, and again.
And this HTML that's coming back--
let me go here.
Let me open my terminal-- oh, sorry.
This is the wrong version.
Sorry, I was in the wrong folder.
Let's fix this.
In shows one, code of app.py,
it's almost the same thing.
In search here--
OK, well I change this slightly.
Let me show you this version of search.
If I open up app.py,
here's my search route.
I'm getting a variable called q, giving
it the value of whatever request.args
has from the user, like q=office.
And then I'm checking if
the user actually typed
something in execute this SQL query.
Select star from shows where
title is like that using the same.
And this time just to
keep things efficient,
I limited the total results to
50 instead of an infinite number.
Otherwise if the user type nothing,
just to be super safe here,
I'm setting shows
equal to an empty list.
So if you don't type anything
there's nothing to show.
And no matter what, I render
this template called search.HTML.
Well, let's look at that.
If I open up templates/search.HTML,
this time there's no layout.
There's no inheritance
of that layout .HTML,
I am literally generating just
a whole bunch of li fragments.
Why?
Well let's see what's
happening in the browser.
And this is the beginning of an API.
If I wanted to make this API
available-- this application programming
interface--
I could tell the world that if you want
to search for TV shows in my database,
go to URL, that's something, something,
/search?q=office or cat, or dog,
or anything else.
And what I will return to you is this.
Enter-- I will just give you a
whole bunch of li tags, which
almost looks the same.
But let me view the page source.
Only am I going to hand you
back a fragment of HTML.
I'm not giving you an HTML tag, a
body tag, a title tag, a head tag.
I'm not giving you a web page.
I'm giving you a fragment of HTML
that you can now do whatever you want,
including insert this into
your own unordered list.
So notice what happens
in this actual app.
If I go back to VS Code here, let
me open up my index template here,
and you'll see some JavaScript magic.
So in JavaScript here, in my form that
only had the textbox and no button,
what am I doing?
In a script tag here, I am
creating a variable called input.
And I'm using this function
called query selector that
just gets me a reference to
the input text box on the form.
So I can see what the human typed.
This is a little
different today, but I'm
using input.addEventListener, which is
a way in JavaScript to tell it, just
like in Scratch, listen
for something to happen,
like the green flag being clicked.
But in this case listen for
an event that involves input.
That is like typing on
the keyboard, whether it's
by a copy paste, manual
input, or anything else.
Then whenever that happens,
call this function.
And async stands for Asynchronous.
This is a term of art which
means that this function might
take a split second, maybe even
a second or two to execute.
So it's going to do it behind the
scenes, like in the background,
so to speak.
And what is it going to do?
Well, it's going to call a JavaScript
function that all browsers now
support called fetch, which is
a function that uses HTTP to go
fetch more data via from the server.
It's going to fetch data from a
route called /search?q= and whatever
the value is that the user typed in.
So I'm just manually
creating my own mini URL
and telling JavaScript
go fetch me that HTML.
When it comes back via this line
of text here called response.text,
and let me wave my hand at await.
Await just means this might
not come back immediately.
Let's await the response
and when it does come in,
then let's execute this code.
I'm going to do this.
I'm going to search the document,
the whole web page, for this UL tag
which is somewhere in this page
that we'll see in a moment.
Change its inner HTML to
be that fragment of li,
li, li, of all of those matching shows.
And where does this all go?
Well if we scroll up here,
you'll notice that there's
my usual HTML up at the top.
Head tag, body tag, and all of that.
There's the text box that
we've talked about already.
There's no button for submitting
because it all happens automatically.
But there is by default this empty
UL that has nothing by default
until we start using that API.
And the final flourish here this.
This is kind of an ugly, sloppy
way to get data from a server
to just get back a fragment of HTML.
Like what if I'm not using HTML?
I want to store these TV shows in
a PDF, or in some other web tag,
in a table, or something like that.
It doesn't really make
sense for the server
to be presuming that I want like
tags surrounding each of my data.
Better would be to get a
more generic format back.
And that format is almost
always nowadays called
this, our final acronym--
JSON, JavaScript Object Notation.
And let me do this.
Let me close these two tabs here
and open my terminal window,
and cancel the previous version
of Flask that was running.
Let me close this version and
look at our final version called
shows two and do Flask run.
I'm going to hover over that
URL and open it in a browser.
And I'm going to manually visit,
after zooming in, let's do again
/search?q=office Enter.
And this is what JSON looks like.
Now at a glance, this does
not seem like an improvement.
This looks crazy that it's
just this big blob of text.
But it's just enough
text for the computer
to be able to process it reliably.
Notice that there's a
square bracket here.
And if I actually scroll
to the bottom, there
would be a closed square
bracket like way down there.
Inside of that square bracket is
a curly brace, then ID, colon,
and then a number.
Then a title, quote unquote,
colon, and then the title.
And then the closed curly brace.
So what you're seeing in
JavaScript Object Notation
is a very standard super
popular format that's
just text that still uses square
brackets for lists, a.k.a. arrays.
That still uses curly braces for
dictionaries, key value pairs.
So what you see here is a
massive list-- up to 50,
I think-- shows that came back
from this API, each of which
has a dictionary, if you will,
an object of key value pairs.
What keys and values?
An ID key and a title key, each
of which has a value respectively.
And this is the same data
from IMDb, some of which
you might be recalling visually.
This is just a very raw,
computer friendly way
of returning a whole bunch of data
that we humans don't need to see.
But I can use this data by
going back into VS code.
Let me open another terminal window
and go into source nine/shows2.
And in here, let me go ahead and open
up, how about templates index.html,
which previously just use
that inner HTML trick.
And this is not going
to impress-- you're not
going to be pleased with this syntax.
But let me just at least
explain what we're doing.
It turns out that JSON
is just the better
way in general, the more generic,
multipurpose, user agnostic, language
agnostic way of returning data from
a server because it's just text.
So it doesn't matter if you're using
Python, or C, or C++, or JavaScript,
or Ruby, or PHP, or something else.
All of those languages can
process JSON information.
And indeed here is some
JavaScript that does just that.
Same code is before initially.
I declare a variable called input that
gives me access to the user's text box.
I listen for input like
keystrokes going up and down.
And when they happen, I call
this anonymous function.
I fetch data from the server using
the exact same code as before.
Search?q=office, or anything else.
And then this is just
now new code that I
use to convert that JSON
data into my own HTML format,
be it an unordered list, and ordered
list, a table, or anything else.
What am I doing?
I've got a variable called
HTML initialize to nothing.
So I've got no HTML initially.
I then iterate over
every ID in those shows.
So every one of IMDb's
unique identifier,
I integrate over them one at a time.
And then I go into the show at its
ID location and I grab its title.
And this is-- forget
this for just a moment.
I then take this HTML
variable, concatenate,
or join onto it, my own li tag, plus
the title, plus the close li tag.
And I skip this because
it got scary pretty fast,
but it turns out that if some TV shows
have actually angled brackets in them,
that could break my HTML entirely.
So it turns out, you might
recall super briefly last week
we had the copyright symbol,
using an HTML entity,
using the ampersand,
and the hash symbol,
and 169 semicolon--
it turns out there are
other such cryptic sequences of
characters that represent otherwise
dangerous or untypable characters.
Like this, which could confuse
the computer into thinking
it's at the beginning of
a tag, and an ampersand,
which could similarly trick the computer
into thinking that it's an entity which
it isn't.
But long story short, there
are libraries, thankfully,
that handle much of this for you.
For our purposes, the takeaway is that
now that you understand a bit of HTTP,
now that you understand a bit of HTML,
CSS, and JavaScript, all of which
have their roles, you
can use them ultimately
to start assembling your own
web applications as you will
for problem set nine, stitching
together all of those languages
and building full fledged web
applications, mobile applications,
or anything more.
And for that, I think we are all set.
And the first one up here can
have these cookies as well.
We'll see you next time for
our very last CS50 lecture.
[MUSIC PLAYING]