[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
So this is CS50.
My name is David Malan, and this is
Harvard University's introduction
to the intellectual
enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
And this, of course, is
our special family weekend,
wherein not only our CS50's own
students here in the audience, but also
some family members as well.
Now, you're showing up in the
semester a little bit late.
We've just tackled week eight, which
is really our ninth week since computer
scientists start counting from zero.
So we've done a whole lot of
work over the past few weeks,
as you might have heard via
emails or text messages home,
including a language
known here as binary.
So on the screen here, of course,
is a lot of zeros and ones.
And suffice it to say, let me sum
up the past nine weeks with this
is what's going on underneath the hood.
But of course, today, we thought we'd
make things a little more accessible,
a little more broadly applicable.
And indeed, our focus
today will not be on what
these patterns of zeros
and ones represent,
which in astute, I might
notice are replicated visually
with these light bulbs being
in a pattern on and off.
And as your child might have hinted
before class, or perhaps, now,
this might very well spell a
word up to eight characters
long because you can encode, even in
the real world, things digital too.
But today, we'll focus on
things much more high level,
this notion of cybersecurity,
like the security
of our data, our privacy of our
systems, particularly, on the internet
nowadays because presumably, all of
us are carrying technologies around
in our pocket using laptops
and desktops every day.
And so the goal today is
to stipulate that this
is what's going on underneath the hood.
But let's solve some
problems at a higher level,
so that your homework, when you go
back to wherever you're visiting from,
can actually be to apply some
of today's lessons learned.
So with that said, perhaps, the most
common familiar defense of one's
systems, and data, phone, and
laptops, and desktops would just
be these simple passwords.
Unfortunately, you and I
are-- frankly, as humans,
not all that good at choosing passwords.
And this is in itself a relatively weak
form of defense, even though each of us
has dozens, hundreds,
of passwords nowadays
or at least dozens or
hundreds of accounts,
maybe fives or tens of
dozens of passwords.
Indeed, if you're in the
habit of reusing passwords,
we'll see today, probably among
our first lessons learned.
So for instance, if we look back
at the past year, 2021, thanks
to security researchers who take a look
at data that has been hacked or leaked
online by way of public databases, we
have a sense as computer scientists
of what the most
popular, or equivalently,
what some of the worst
passwords are that you and I are
choosing for our system.
So as of this past year,
according to one measure,
the most commonly used password
in systems everywhere was 123456.
All right?
The number two password
in our top 10 here list
was only slightly longer, 123456789.
After that, we took a turn in
the other direction, 12345 alone.
After that, it got a little
more interesting, qwerty,
which might sound
pretty cryptic, but not
if you look down at your US keyboard.
And it's the top left hand row of the
keys on an American keyboard, so also,
not all that hard.
Perhaps, not surprisingly
a little disconcertingly,
number five was password.
Meanwhile, number six returns
us to digits, 12345678.
After that, really, less effort, 111111.
After that, a little more variation,
but not all that much 123123.
After that, it's getting even
less interesting, 1234567890.
And then lastly topping
the list is just 1234567.
So this is not a good
top 10 list to be on.
So among today's first takeaways is if
you see your password on the screen,
you didn't make the list in a good way.
This means hundreds, thousands,
millions of other people
probably have that password of yours.
Now, in and of itself, that's
not necessarily worrisome
because I don't know who has these
passwords in a room as large as this.
But just intuitively,
why is this a bad thing?
Either parent or child is
welcome to raise a hand here.
Why might this be--
intuitively, yeah?
AUDIENCE: Access to it.
DAVID J. MALAN: So access to it.
I mean, we literally, as
computer scientists, now have
a database of really common passwords.
And your thoughts?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
find it out quickly.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, you
can just find it out quickly.
I mean, you could imagine trying to
guess someone's password by just typing
in random letters, random
numbers, random words,
but not if you have a top 10 list.
The adversaries in the world might
as well just start with this list.
Now, you'll notice that even absent
from this are slight variance.
Some of you might be
thinking, I'm not on the list
because I do something clever like I
use an exclamation point for the number
one, or a three for
an E, or a 5 for an S.
And based on the smiles
in the room right now,
you're not all that clever, it turns
out, because other people are smiling
too, which is to say that an adversary
can take those same heuristics that you
might think are making
things more secure by just
tweaking some letters to
numbers or vise versa.
But if you're doing it and
other people are doing it,
the bad guys, so to speak, are
going to be doing it as well.
So unfortunately, when
it comes to passwords,
better is longer, and random,
and really unguessable.
But that's not what most of us have.
In fact, case in point on
our phones, whether you
have an Android device
or an iPhone nowadays,
odds are you have something
relatively simplistic protecting it,
if you have anything at all.
But at least, Apple
and Google are pretty
good at at least nudging us to
choose these kinds of passcodes now.
And a four-digit passcode
is quite common nowadays.
And so here's where we have an
opportunity, thanks to the URL
that you saw on the screen
earlier, to conjecture as a group
just how long might it take an
adversary, someone out there
who's out to get us or get one of us--
how long might it take an
adversary to figure out
your phone's four-digit passcode?
This is CS50's own Carter.
Carter, if you could switch over
and pull the audience here--
if you take out your phone or laptop,
whatever device you might have used
a few minutes ago, to scan that
QR code or to visit that same URL,
you can see these
questions on your browser.
And if you can't, that's fine.
We'll share some aggregate
data, nonetheless.
But you should have an opportunity
to tap one of your answers.
And we'll give folks a few more seconds
if you'd like to play along at home.
And here in just a moment--
probably have many people reporting.
But why don't we go ahead and
take a look at some percentages?
It looks like most of you--
60% to 70%-- are proposing
just a few seconds,
so that's not all that good news
if it's a four-digit passcode.
Some of you are hoping
it's a few minutes.
8% are hoping a few hours.
More than 4% of you are really
hoping, perhaps, it's a few days.
Well, let's actually consider
how we can answer this question
and make today not just conceptual,
but a little quantitative too
and see if we can't slap some
numbers on questions like these,
so ultimately, you can make
more informed decisions
with your system's security.
So for instance, when it comes
to four-digit pass codes,
rather than just consider
how secure it is, well,
let's make it a more precise question
like, what are the forms of attack?
Well, the simplest attack might be just
someone grabbing your phone, be it,
in your family, or maybe at
Starbucks, or the airport,
or the like and just starting all
possible combinations, maybe 0000,
then 0001, and 0002.
We could maybe automate
this a little bit.
So for instance, I might
potentially be able to do something
like robotosize this here.
Let me go ahead and full
screen a quick video here
that's just going to paint a picture
in just a moment on the screen of how,
if we're a really clever adversary
and know how to build things,
well, at least, maybe we could
automate some of that process.
So here's an Android phone
sitting on a counter.
Here's a very simple tripod and a little
touch device robotically doing all
of that hacking for you starting at
0000 probably all the way up to 9999.
Now, that too wasn't necessarily
all that fast, but at least,
the adversary can step
away and doesn't actually
have to be bothered
with the time involved,
the cost involved, in actually
hacking that particular device.
Well, let's go one level deeper,
a little more interestingly,
and consider here how much time
really this so-called brute force
attack would take.
And that's actually a term of art, much
like in yesteryear when maybe there
was a battering ram trying to
brute force their way into a castle
or something like that.
A brute force attack digitally
is just someone trying manually
all possible codes or maybe
robotically trying all possible codes,
but generally automating
the process in some way
to go through all possibilities.
Well, if you've got, for
instance, a four-digit passcode--
let's ask maybe a follow-up question
here, not how long it will take,
but how many possible
four-digit passcodes are there?
Because then maybe, we
can do some quick math.
And if every passcode takes me a second,
or a few milliseconds, or the like,
then I think we can try to extrapolate
from that whether the first answer was
seconds, or minutes, or days,
or hours, or something else.
So how many four-digit
passcodes are possible?
If you take out your same device, it
should have just changed automatically
if it doesn't seem to have maybe reload
your browser with some menu option.
And then tap in here, how many
four-digit passcodes are possible?
Four total, 40, 9,999, 10,000.
Or unsure is OK too.
So let's see.
We'll give you a few more moments.
How many four-digit
passcodes are possible?
And shall we reveal the results?
So now, it looks like a few of you--
2% of you are saying just
for passcodes, 40, 9,999.
There's definitely some contention here.
And 6% are unsure.
Well, how do we wrap
our minds around this?
Well, let's just do
this real simple here.
Let me switch back over
to doing a bit of math.
And if we have here 10 possibilities
for each digit, if there's four digits,
each digit can be zero, one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine.
So that's 10 possibilities.
So if you think about the
number of permutations,
that's 10 possibilities for the first
digit times 10 for the next, times 10
for the next, times 10 for the next.
And so if we do that out, 10
times, 10 times, 10 times, 10 or 10
to the fourth, there are, indeed-- and
66% of you found 10,000 possibilities.
And so now we can kind of
work backwards and decide,
how long is it going to take for an
adversary to hack into this phone?
Because if it's one attack,
one guess per second,
well, that's going to map
out to 10,000 seconds,
but maybe not if the adversary
isn't a roboticist or a human.
What if they're a software
programmer or someone who
has taken even a class
introductory, like CS50 and learned
a little bit of programming?
Well, a little bit
frighteningly, it's not
all that hard to hack
into systems if you just
know how to code, too, and really have
the computer do your work for you.
So in fact, let me go ahead and change
over to another screen on my computer
here.
This is different for students
in the group from VS Code.
This is just a black
and white version of it
that we've used briefly in the past.
And I'm just going to go ahead and
create a program called crack.py.
To crack something
just technically means
to figure out what it is, figure
out a password in this case.
And .py means I'm going to use a
programming language that we here
in CS50 have been dabbling in the past
couple of weeks with more to come next
week as well.
So it turns out, and you need not
understand each of these lines of code,
if I want to try, maybe, generating
all 10,000 possible codes,
I'm not going to bother with a robot.
I've got all these cables
coming out of my computer.
And odds are one of them is a
USB cable or a lightning cable.
Surely, we could figure out how to
connect laptop or desktop to phone
and just automate the process nowadays
by just sending all of the numbers
into the phone until one unlocks the
trick just like in the movies or TV.
Well, in Python, I could write a
program that does this as follows.
I can import, so to speak, all of the
decimal digits, zero through nine.
And this, for students in the room,
is just a slightly better version
of typing out 10 different
numbers manually.
I can also import from
a library, so to speak,
called itertools for
iteration tools, which
means to do something again and again.
I can import a function called
product, which means the cross product.
Combine this with this
some number of times.
And then it's just two
more lines of code.
I can use what's called
a loop in programming.
So for every pass code in
the cross product of all 10
of those digits repeated,
a total of four times--
let me go ahead and-- rather
than bother connecting my phone
and hacking my own phone,
let me just print out
every one of those 10,000
codes on the screen,
and we'll see how fast
the hacker could do this.
Let me go ahead.
And print and with an asterisk, which
is a little trick to format it nicely,
I'm going to print out
each of those pass codes.
And that's it, four lines of
code, maybe 40 seconds of talking,
but maybe really four seconds
of coding if I actually
did this without the audience.
And now let me go ahead
and save the file.
And I'm going to run, as we
do every day in class of late.
Python of crack.py.
And when I hit Enter, I should see on
the screen all 10,000 possibilities
from 0000 9999.
So let's see.
Is it a few seconds,
minutes, hours, or days?
Done.
So barely even seconds plural if that.
So that should be a little
disconcerting because all that adversary
needs to do is grab your phone off the
counter, plug in a cable, and boom.
They're done.
There's no ticking clock or
worries as in the movies or TV
that maybe you're going
to come into the room.
You don't need that much
of a window of time.
So what would be better than this?
Well, let's consider
what our options might
be if we don't want to just
use four-digit pass code.
Some of you, indeed, might have
better passcodes than that.
And maybe, you use four-letter
passcodes instead, so A through Z,
maybe uppercase and lowercase.
That starts to make things
a little more interesting.
So should we poll this question too?
If we upgrade from four
digits to just four letters,
English letters, A through Z, uppercase
and lowercase-- why don't we go ahead
and pol the group here and ask how
many four-letter passcodes are there
instead?
So this time, the range starts at four.
Still not the right
answer, though, this time.
How many four-letter
pass codes are possible?
[INAUDIBLE]
Take a couple more seconds.
All right.
Almost a couple hundred
responses in already.
A few more seconds.
And why don't we go ahead and
reveal now the answers, which are--
OK, so we solved a couple
of problems at least.
OK, someone's just messing with us now.
All right.
So it looks like most of you--
76% of you have claimed it's
seven million plus possibilities.
So that's encouraging because
that's a whole order of magnitude
more than before.
Well, let's figure out how we
might do this mathematically.
So if we've got 26
lowercase, 26 uppercase,
that's 52 possibilities now
for each of those four digits.
So that's 52 times
itself four times, which,
indeed, either off the top
of your head a good guess,
a calculator on the same device
you're using right now, indeed,
gives us seven million instead.
Well, what might be
slightly better than that?
Well, maybe four characters.
And this, indeed, is what
your Macs, PCs, and phones are
urging us to do nowadays, not just
numbers, not just letters, but really
annoying punctuation, so it really
looks cryptic not just to the adversary,
but also to you and me, unfortunately.
And that's the downside.
But here now, we have a mental model,
and really, a computational framework
via which we can evaluate
the security of these.
And I'll go ahead and spoil
some of the math here.
If we've got 52 letters of the alphabet,
uppercase and lowercase, 10 digits,
and if I count them out on my
keyboard, about 32 punctuation symbols
in typical English grammar,
that actually gives us
94 possibilities now, which is
up from 52, which is up from 10.
So now, we're really moving.
And now that would give us
78 million possibilities,
so another order of magnitude.
Now, it's still going to be
relatively fast because you know what?
I can actually do this.
Let me go back into my code here.
Let me reopen this same program.
And I can point out just how
easy it is to make these changes.
Instead of importing digits as before,
I can import, as your child might know,
ascii letters, which are A
through Z, uppercase, lowercase.
And I can just change
this here, ascii letters.
And so this was that first version
where we just changed to letters.
Let me now rerun the code.
And instead of seeing numbers, we'll
see letters flying across the screen.
And if I walk over here to
the screen, we'll see that.
By the time I get here, we're halfway
through the entire alphabet lowercase.
If I now start walking
away, I think, yeah,
we're already done now
with uppercase as well.
If I upgrade this slightly further--
let's go ahead and take it one more
level and, perhaps, do, let's say,
ascii letters, and
digits, and punctuation.
And this would be the
Pythonic way to say that.
And I'm going to add to those
letters those same digits,
those same punctuation symbols.
Let me shrink my font just so the
code still fits on the screen.
And what we now have is with
a two seconds of changes,
a program that if I run this version--
whoops-- without the
typographical error--
this is what we call in CS50 a bug.
So now, we run the same--
this is what we call
in CS50 a second bug--
punctuation.
This is where I cross my fingers.
OK.
So now it's going to be a little hard
to see as flies across the screen.
But you probably are seeing glimpses
of some weird punctuation characters
as well.
And I won't waste our time trying
to talk through this because this
is going to take longer.
We're still in the lowercase.
I'm still over here already.
We've not even gotten
to N, now O, then P.
So this is going to run longer.
But let's end with one final question
on the security of all these systems.
I'm going to cancel that by
hitting Control C on my keyboard.
And let's ask the question instead,
if we use eight-character passwords,
so twice as many characters.
But even that is not terribly long.
This is eight characters alone
on the stage, eight characters.
Using letters, numbers, and
punctuation might be better.
Let's do one final
vote here, if we could.
On your same device, how many
eight-character possibilities
are there now for these passcodes?
And now four didn't even
make the list this time.
All right, a few more seconds,
about 100 responses so far.
How about we go ahead-- and,
Carter, if you wouldn't mind,
let's reveal the results based on the
vote, a pretty decent spread here.
Although the quadrillions
are quickly buzzing in.
And they're contending
with the others here.
Looks like 44% of you said quintillion.
34% said quadrillion.
And this time, for the
first time, you overbid.
So indeed, if we go back to the math
here, at least, the majority over bid.
If we have eight-character
passcodes that
gives us 94 times itself eight
times or 94 to the eighth power.
And in fact, that gives us
roughly 6,095,689,385,410,816
possible passcodes.
Now, what does that mean?
Well, the adversary's
algorithm, the step-by-step code
that they write to try to hack
into your phone, is no different.
And honestly, if your passcode
is eight characters long,
but they're are 00000000, you're
no more secure fundamentally.
You really want to be somewhere in
the sweet spot of that massive range
of values, so that if the adversary
tries this brute force attack just
running through all possibilities,
they will eventually reach
your passcode just mathematically.
It will be there.
Hopefully, though-- well,
maybe not hopefully-- you
and I and they will be
gone from this world
because that much time will have passed.
And if we do out the math here, this
number of seconds, for instance,
is long past when we
will no longer be here.
So that's the sort of measures.
We don't sort of fundamentally change
the equation for the adversary.
It's still the same risk.
It's still the same attack.
But you significantly drive down the
probability of success on their part.
Or conceptually, you drive
up the cost to the adversary.
And indeed, even in the
physical world, this is true.
You just want your passcode
in the digital world
really to be better than
someone else's because you
want someone else's
passcode to be the one
that the adversary does something with.
Just like in the physical world,
even though it's a bit uncomfortable
to consider, your house
doesn't need to be 100% secure.
And indeed, it's
difficult to make it such.
There's always going to
be a point of weakness.
Maybe it's that window, the
door, or something like that.
But if your home is more secure than the
next door home, just probabilistically,
you are more secure.
You're not secure.
And indeed, any website
you see down the road
that says, we are secure because
we do X, Y, or Z, that's nonsense.
Security is really about
comparisons and evaluating things
if quantitatively relative to some other
system, relative to some other code.
So what's the takeaway here?
Well, hopefully, a non-trivial number of
you will go home this weekend on Monday
and change at least one passcode.
But there's going to be a tradeoff here.
We talk about this all the time in CS50.
Any time we improve something, we pay
some price in time, in performance,
in cost, somewhere else.
So what's the downside then of
this advice that you should use
minimally eight-character passcodes?
Why might you want to
say nay and not do this?
AUDIENCE: You have to remember it.
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
DAVID J. MALAN: You have
to remember it, right?
And so here, there is some sociology.
There's some human behavior.
Some of you might have
colleagues, if you're
working in the real
world, at least, back
in healthier times when you had
colleagues with desks in cubicles.
And there's probably one person
in the office with a post-it note
on their monitor with their passcode.
It's a bit of a cybersecurity offense,
but it's also a real world side
effect, maybe of corporate policies,
that aren't really calibrated
for human behavior.
So we'll see if there's
some other defenses.
And indeed, let me propose
that we talk briefly
about one that actually tends
to kick in automatically.
Even if your passcode is
not as strong as we've just
seen, one of these six
quadrillion possibilities, well,
what could we do instead?
Well, has anyone-- and
I'll zoom in on this here--
accidentally locked themselves
out of their own phone before?
When does that happen?
Yeah, when you try the password--
AUDIENCE: Too many times.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so too many times.
Maybe your finger is slightly off.
Maybe you're slightly off, and you just
don't input the same passcode correctly
after five times, 10 times.
There's some reasonable threshold.
And why does that happen?
Well, Apple and Google
equivalently figure just
probabilistically if after
10 guesses, you still
haven't typed in the right
passcode, probably, you're not you.
You're someone else who's
picked up your phone,
so we're just going to go
ahead and lock you out.
Now, what's the effect of this?
Well, this means now that each
of those possible passcodes
no longer takes roughly one second.
Now it takes roughly one minute.
So the attack is still the same.
But if it's now one passcode
or 10 guesses per minute,
we have significantly by a factor of
60 in this story slowed things down.
And unfortunately, does
anyone know what happens
if you screw up again after a minute?
AUDIENCE: It goes longer.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, it goes longer.
It's like five minutes
and then 10 minutes.
And Google is kind of
obnoxious about it.
They don't even give you a time frame.
They just say, try again later.
And so that keeps not only the
adversary out, but also potentially you.
So therein lies that tradeoff.
If you've forgotten your code, if--
nowadays, your finger is slightly wet,
so the screen isn't
responding correctly.
These could be usability downsides too.
So security is really just
about finding the sweet spot
among these various tradeoffs here.
But there's other mechanisms too.
And some of you might recognize this
screen from Gmail via which, of course,
you log in.
But after you log into Gmail or similar
websites, or apps, or systems at work
nowadays, especially, you
might be presented with what's
called two-factor authentication.
And what is this in a
nutshell in layperson's terms?
Many of you, if you do
anything digitally at work,
might have to do this now.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It sends a text to your phone.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
You get texted at your phone,
an additional code that's
not your same password.
It's typically a numeric
code, maybe six digits long.
It expires after a minute or 10 minutes.
But why is this a good thing?
Well, one, it's no longer just a
piece of information that you know
or that you might have written down.
It's information that changes
every time you try to log in.
But more importantly, it's a
fundamentally second factor, which
means it's not just something you know.
Now it's something you have.
So you, for instance, are
the only one theoretically
that should be receiving that code.
And so now the adversary, if they
want to get into your account,
not only have to guess, or brute
force, or maybe read off of a post-it
note your password.
They also have to physically
have access now to that phone.
So there's still a threat,
absolutely, but it's not everyone
on the internet with
an internet connection.
Now it's only the people in Starbucks.
Now it's only the people at work.
Now it's only the people in
your home who might have access
to that second factor.
So there too, it just raises the bar
to the adversary making it harder,
more time consuming, more geographically
impossible for them to attack you.
But what's the downside of
two-factor authentication,
whether it's a device--
or even nowadays,
it's in software, whether
it's on your keychain
or on your phone where you're
prompted for this code.
What's a downside that some of
us have probably experienced too?
AUDIENCE: You forget your phone.
DAVID J. MALAN: You forget
your cell phone, absolutely.
Right, the factor that you
have, you don't have with you.
Or maybe, you're in a basement
somewhere, don't have reception.
You're on a plane.
You can't get the code.
And so there too are these tradeoffs.
And even IT departments
need to keep that in mind
because what does that mean for them?
Well, if you don't have
your phone with you
and you are in the habit of
calling IT to help you fix this,
now there's a cost, a human cost,
maybe even a financial cost.
And so IT policy nowadays is really
just about finding the right balance
and where we want to
spend our resources,
but at least raise the
bar to the adversary.
But of course, there's other ways too.
And this is going to be one
of our homework assignments
if you will after today.
There's this software
called password managers.
And no need to buzz in on your phone,
but maybe with a physical hand.
How many folks here
use a password manager?
OK, let me ballpark this
at 10%, 20%, perhaps.
So we've got 80% upside here and
a lesson learned potentially.
So a password manager is
just a piece of software
on your Mac, your PC, or your phone
nowadays that manages your passwords.
Well, what does that mean?
When you go to a website
for the first time
or you download an app for the first
time and you have to create an account,
you can still use your email
address, or David as your username,
or whatever your name might be.
So you don't have to
change that methodology.
But instead of typing in 123456 as your
same password for that website or app
as well as for every other, now you
use the password manager software
to generate something
difficult to guess for you.
That is you tell the password manager,
give me an eight-character random
passcode, not 0000, but something
with punctuation, with numbers,
with letters.
And better yet, the password
manager, as the name suggests,
remembers that password for you.
And the next time you
go to another website,
you do it again with a
completely different password,
maybe same username, maybe two-factor
authentication, but different password,
different password, different password.
And it doesn't have to be eight.
I mean, I'm in the habit of using a
dozen, two dozen characters in total.
And at that point, I can't even
pronounce the number of possibilities
because it goes well
beyond the quadrillions.
So the probability that someone's
going to get into one of those
accounts for me now is
very, very, very low.
And they're going to take less
interest in me and maybe more interest
in someone else that's not
using as good of a password.
Now, what does this mean in real terms?
Well, when you go to log
into that managed site,
you don't manually type
your password anymore.
In fact, you don't generally
even need to know it.
Nowadays, I probably don't
90-plus, 99% of my passwords.
I entrust them to this password manager.
Now, of course, you'd like to think that
the password manager itself is secure.
So what might that mean?
Well, those of you who do
use a password manager,
how do you access that software itself?
What's protecting your
data in your understanding?
AUDIENCE: Biometrics.
DAVID J. MALAN: So maybe biometrics,
like your face ID, or maybe
your fingerprint, or maybe
more simply, what else?
AUDIENCE: A password.
DAVID J. MALAN: Maybe just a password.
And hopefully, that password that
primary password, that gatekeeper,
is not itself 123456.
Otherwise, it doesn't matter how
secure all of the others are.
But if you're willing to put in
the effort and pick one pretty long
somewhat random very unguessable
password that you just
promise to commit to memory--
and maybe for backup, you
literally print it out
and put it in a safe
deposit box or a safe,
or just hide it somewhere
physically that there's
very low probability
someone's going to find
the backup copy, that might be alone.
But of course, the flip side is now
if you forget that primary password,
you've now lost all of
the eggs in the basket.
If someone gets that primary password,
now they have access to everything.
So that's rather the tradeoff.
But I dare say you're probably less
threatened, depending on your family,
by the people immediately
around you than the billions
of other people on the internet
that have access, potentially,
to those same systems.
So there, too, it's a tradeoff.
But it's up to you to
decide whether or not
to manage your passwords in this way.
But if you were on that top 10
list, or even if you're not,
but you can think of several accounts
that all have the same password,
you're probably going to benefit
from something like this.
And why is it bad, to be clear, to use
the same password on multiple sites
in case that's never sort
of dawned in thought?
Why is that a bad thing,
to reuse a password
on different websites, different apps?
Any intuition?
Yeah, in the back?
AUDIENCE: Once attacked,
it's easy to get to.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Once it's attacked, you can--
the adversary, presumably,
by transitivity,
can see, oh, well, if
this user's username is
malan@harvard.edu on this website,
and their password is foolishly
123456 or even something
way more complicated,
they can probably just
assume with high probability
that if I'm being a
little reckless, let's
try accessing malan@harvard.edu's
use other accounts, other apps using
that exact same password.
And so by transitivity,
essentially, you're
putting your other accounts at risk.
So what's maybe a takeaway?
Minimally here, I would start
to reconsider your passcodes
on your most important data.
Maybe it's medical.
Maybe it's financial.
Maybe it's email.
Anything remotely personal that you
really wouldn't want to have access.
Do you necessarily need
the same level of security
on e-commerce sites or sites
that you don't really care about
or that you signed up for once
and after that, that's it?
Probably not.
So you can decide for
yourself, but again,
software, like a password manager.
And these are just some
of the possibilities out
there are probably to be your friend.
A couple of these are free.
They come with Windows or Mac OS.
A couple are commercial.
Harvard has a site license for
students for one of these as well.
So there are options out there.
But what else do people use?
What else can people use to
keep their systems secure?
So most of us nowadays have probably
heard of encryption, this technique
for just scrambling information.
So when you want to send a message,
an email, or upload a photograph,
or use your credit card, hopefully, it's
not just being sent out for all to see,
but there's some kind
of scrambling going on.
And some fancy mathematics
ensure that encryption
ensures that only you, the sender,
and someone else, the receiver,
can theoretically see what that credit
card number is, what that message is
what that photograph is instead.
So encryption is sort
of commonplace nowadays,
both in websites, and apps, and
ATMs, and other such devices.
But how does it work?
Well, back in week two
of CS50, your child
learned a little something
about encryption, otherwise,
known as cryptography.
And one of the algorithms
we talked about
was quite simply something like this.
This is what we might call, not only
CS50, but plain text, so very plain
text that, in this case, is English
and obviously, everyone in the room
can read it.
But what if I wanted to send this
message out to someone in this room,
or out on the internet, or maybe
equivalently back in the day,
maybe write a message down on a
scrap of paper in grade school
and pass a secret note, a secret love
note to someone in class with hopes
that the teacher or any
other students in the class
can't intercept it and read it?
Well, you probably don't want to
say, this is CS50, or I love you,
or anything remotely sensitive.
But rather, maybe you
want to encrypt it.
And let's change the T to a U.
Maybe change the H to an I, the I
to a J, the S to a T, the I to a J,
the S to a T again, the
C to a D, the S to a T.
And we'll just leave
the numbers, alone even
though I worry someone could probably
guess what this now does say,
nonetheless.
But what was the algorithm as
I rattled those changes off,
whether a student from week
two or parents from week now?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It's a one-letter shift.
DAVID J. MALAN: Just a one-letter shift.
And this is more sophisticated called
a rotational cipher or a Caesar cipher
after Caesar back in the day.
It's relatively simplistic.
But back in the day,
it's not so simplistic
if you're the first person in the
world to ever use it or think of it.
But nowadays, this is
not actually what we use.
But it's similarly
mathematical in nature.
It's not quite as simple as just
adding one or subtracting one
to go from now what we call
ciphertext to plain text.
But it's similarly math that's involved.
And let me just stipulate
that the way the math works
is that the sender and
the receiver just have
to have in mind some kind of secret.
And the secret in this case
would very trivially be one,
but it could be a much bigger,
much more unguessable number,
or maybe some other secret
we share, the presumption
being that my classmates, my teacher
in that grade school classroom, if they
don't know what that secret
is that number is, yeah,
they could try to brute force it and
try all possible mathematics, plus one,
plus two, plus three.
But that's going to take them some time.
And they probably don't care enough.
And so my data might be,
therefore, relatively secure.
But we use encryption
all the time nowadays.
And so for instance, this
is at the start of most URLs
nowadays, even if you
don't type it yourself.
With that said, Safari and even Chrome
now are kind of simplifying, if not,
dumbing down user interfaces
to just hide details
that you and I, as normal
users, don't need to see 24/7.
But it is there.
And if in fact, on your phone
or laptop, you click on the URL,
even if it's super
short initially, you'll
probably see the whole
thing starting with this.
And the S means secure.
The S means that
encryption is being used.
But there's other forms of this,
not just when you visit websites.
There's this, end-to-end
encryption, which
is being talked about more nowadays,
especially during COVID times with so
many more of us on video and
talking about more sensitive things,
telemedicine, talking to
doctors, things that you also
wouldn't want to verbally or visually
get out into the wild just like text.
What's different about end-to-end
encryption versus HTTPS
and the type of encryption that most
of us use every day on websites alone?
End-to-end encryption is
sort of a better feature
that you want to increasingly seek when
using services like Zoom, or Microsoft
Teams, or WhatsApp, or the like.
Any instincts here?
Yeah, over on the right.
AUDIENCE: The encryption happens
in the source and destination.
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
So the encryption, the
scrambling of information,
happens in the source the sender,
and the destination, the receiver,
without a so-called
middleman in between.
And this is actually very
different from most contexts
nowadays that use just HTTPS
because when you're using HTTPS
to buy something on Amazon securely
with your credit card, well, of course,
Amazon needs to be able to decrypt
the message at the end of the day.
And so that's fine.
But even when you're using services
like video conferencing or maybe text
messaging nowadays-- well, if you're
using WhatsApp, that's owned by Meta.
And if you're using Instagram,
that's owned by Meta.
There's a lot of middlemen in
these apps that we're using.
And if they were only
using encryption period
or only using something like
HTTPS, yes, your connection
from you to WhatsApp, and
in turn, to the recipient
might very well be secure
on each end of that channel.
But Meta in between the company
and any other company in between
could theoretically, for better or
for worse, be looking at that data,
whether it's to mine it
for advertising purposes,
whether it's to snoop on
data that you're sending.
That is not end-to-end encryption if
the middleman, a company, typically,
has technically access to that data.
Now, Zoom, and Microsoft Teams,
and WhatsApp, and iMessage,
and other services with which
you're familiar increasingly
are offering stronger
guarantees of encryption,
whereby, it's indeed between parties
A and B and not the one in the middle.
Now, there's downsides here.
And you can actually see this
kind of functionality manifest
in certain settings.
For instance, besides iMessage,
which just does this for you
on iPhones or Macs, besides
Zoom, you can actually
fine tune these settings,
indeed, within Zoom itself.
So here's a screenshot that I took
last night of just what the user
interface looks like today to create
a new Zoom meeting with the latest
version of Zoom software.
And maybe unbeknownst to you, there
is a choice of buttons down here.
And most likely, yours is, by
default, enhanced encryption,
which is brilliant marketing speak
because it's just encryption.
It's not enhanced.
It actually ironically
means worse than this.
But they want you using
it most likely, why?
Well, it's a little easier to implement.
It's a little less expensive
for them computationally.
And to be fair, enhanced encryption
does scramble the data, but not in a way
that Zoom can't see it.
Zoom can, indeed, see it.
But that's actually a
plus in some context
because if you want
to do cloud recordings
and you want a meeting
recorded not on your Mac or PC,
but let Zoom deal with that.
If you want automatic
transcription nowadays,
so the words to appear, whether
it's English or something
else on the screen,
well, you can't really
lock Zoom or any other
middleman out of that
because someone needs
to save it to the cloud.
Someone needs to translate the voice
to those English or some other language
words.
So enhanced encryption
enables those features,
but they also allow a bad
actor, malicious employees,
someone who's just nosey at Zoom
or the equivalent middle man
to just poke around your video
conference and hear what you've said
or see what you've typed as well unless
you instead check this box as well.
So increasingly look for mentions
of end-to-end encryption.
Or give that some thought when
you choose a technology via which
to communicate with someone,
whether it's within your family
or without as well.
Now, last, but not least, there's
other applications of encryption too.
And this, too, might be a lesson
learned as well, full disk encryption.
So a disk is where your data is stored
in your Mac, or PC, or even your phone.
And full disk encryption just
means ideally that all of your data
is encrypted that is somehow scrambled.
Now, hopefully, your password
for your computer or phone
is good enough so that
even though the device is
encrypted with that password,
at least, you'll remember it.
And your phone or your Mac or PC will
automatically decrypt it for you.
Of course, you can't scramble the
information and hide it from ourselves.
One of us, at least, for these
devices needs to have access.
But full disk encryption
typically means that at least when
you close the laptop lid or
power down for the night,
that even if someone
else steals that device,
opens the lid, unless
they have your passcode,
they can't even plug in
fancy cables to the device
and just rip the zeros
and ones off of the device
and see what's actually there.
Full disk encryption
means they could do that,
but they would just see
seemingly random zeros and ones.
Now, there's a downside here too.
This might slow things down potentially.
But it is a feature increasingly that's
offered and is absolutely something you
should consider enabling in
general, especially if your laptop
or phone travels with you.
And certainly, your phone does.
Or if you plan to donate, or
sell, or give away a device,
you don't want to leave
all of the zeros and ones,
the remnants of your own
sensitive data, passed on there.
So Windows has a feature
called BitLocker.
Mac OS has a feature called FileVault.
There's commercial options as well.
But generally, we're at the point
now in 2022 where clicking a button
is sufficient to enable these features.
With that said, don't rush
into all of these decisions.
I would make backups of your data.
And don't maybe email CS50 if
something goes wrong with that process.
But I would do your own due diligence.
But this, too, would be
a menu of possibilities.
And now, the bad side, the
downside, of what seems to be great,
this notion of full disk encryption.
Unfortunately, just as
we can encrypt our data
to protect it from the
adversaries, so can
the adversaries if they get into our
devices, encrypt our data and do what?
Not tell us that secret key.
And so this is generally applied
in the context of ransomware,
which tragically, you
increasingly hear about
in hospital systems, school
systems, municipalities
where systems are getting attacked.
And the data is not just
getting stolen because what
is the adversary typically need with
local municipal or even hospital data?
The value to the adversary
is encrypting all
of the hospital, all of
the municipality's data
preventing them from accessing it
if they have no backups or the like.
And so ransomware is
literally about trying
to convince someone to pay you money or
pay you Bitcoin or something like that
to give you that secret key.
And the key, in this case, is surely
more sophisticated than the number one.
But it's really the same idea.
So here too, yet again, a tradeoff
just as we sort of invent something
for good, it can also be used
for evil in so to speak as well.
But it's really the same
underlying principles,
even though we keep
seeing it and hearing
about it, in these different forms.
And lastly, if only because
folks are generally familiar,
but don't necessarily know what
it is that it's doing for them,
browsers nowadays have what's
often called incognito mode
or private mode, which has nothing
to do with encryption, but does
have to do with cybersecurity,
or really, cyber privacy,
keeping your data from prying eyes.
Incognito mode, if you open
it in Chrome, for instance,
looks a little something like this.
And we use it in CS50 when introducing
students, as we did last week,
to web programming because
it, in effect, lets
you start with a clean slate like
a brand new browser that has never
visited any websites before, which
is good for just diagnosing problems.
But it's often commonly used if you want
to log into maybe your Gmail account
on someone else's computer and you
don't want your password being saved
or you want to visit
some website where you
don't want the URL or the search terms
ending up in your autocomplete history.
So there's multiple
uses for incognito mode.
But what does it really do?
Well, it doesn't stop your company,
it doesn't stop your university,
your internet service provider,
be it, Comcast, Verizon,
or the like from knowing what
websites you go to because--
ask your students.
A couple of weeks ago we talked
about-- actually, a week ago,
we talked about how the internet works.
And unfortunately, every
computer has an IP address,
which is a unique identifier,
which goes out any time you
go anywhere incognito mode or not.
So this isn't really
covering your tracks
outside of your office, or outside of
your home, or outside of your company.
But it is, at least, throwing
away local information.
And so we'll talk, in fact, in
CS50's week nine this coming Monday
about cookies, which you
might generally know about
and what are called sessions.
And so long story short,
what incognito mode does
is it throws away, when you close the
window, any locally stored information,
so these things called cookies,
which are sort of virtual hand stamps
that just remember what
you've logged in as
or what's in your
shopping cart or the like.
But it doesn't hide any information from
anyone outside of your own Mac or PC.
It only prevents those
local prying eyes.
So there, too, even though we
have tools that many of you
are probably in the habit
of using or thinking
you should use to be more private, be
more secure on the internet, what we do
really in CS50, both
weeks past and future,
is talk about how these
technologies work,
so that ultimately, we have all the
more of an educated citizenry here
among undergrads and
here as well as online,
so that you can apply these
same lessons learned to problems
you'll encounter in the future.
So as promised, the homework.
One, you should probably
use a password manager.
It doesn't have to be one
of those ones on the list,
but at least starting that conversation
maybe with someone who does,
maybe the--
it's often the students
in your family, perhaps,
who can advise you on some
of these technologies.
Consider using a password manager
too, using two-factor authentication,
whether it's your phone or
some key fob or the like,
but at least seeking out that feature
at least for accounts that you really
care about, your email, social
media, financial, medical,
anything where you'd be
embarrassed, at best,
or really violated, at worst, if
that kind of information got out
and then increasingly using not just
encryption, which you get automatically
for most technologies today, but
increasingly choosing technologies
that offer stronger guarantees that keep
those middlemen, those companies out
of the way if only so that you
can trust with higher probability
that only party B knows what
party A has said or sent.
Now, this, of course,
was a whirlwind tour.
There's so much more
that you can do online.
Indeed, this course, CS50, can be taken
for free online via platforms like edX
at edx.org/cs50.
I thought it might be
appropriate to end on this note.
If anyone would like
to conjecture before we
start playing music and adjourn for
lunch, what our final message here is.
If we reverse the plus one and maybe
start minus one here, minus one here--
and indeed, thank you
so much for coming.
This was CS50.
[MUSIC PLAYING]