BRIAN YU: In this lab,
your task is going
to be to write a program that
calculates the score for words
in a game of Scrabble and compares the
score for two words against each other.
Scrabble is a game where
your job is to form
words made out of letters
where each letter is
assigned some number of points.
Common letters, like A and E
and I, are only worth 1 point.
Slightly less common letters, like
B or C or M, are worth 3 points.
And rare letters, like Q and
Z, are worth even more points--
10 points, in this case.
And there's an entire
table here that shows you,
for any letter of the alphabet, how
many points that letter is worth.
Using this assignment of
points, we can take a word
and figure out how many
points that word is worth.
For the word "Scrabble," for example,
we know that S is worth 1 point,
C is worth 3 points, so on and so forth,
and we can add up all of those numbers
to figure out that the word
"Scrabble" is worth 14 points.
And once we have that
ability, we can then
compare two words to figure
out, between those two
words, which word is worth more.
If I were to compare the word
"computer" against the word "science,"
for example, I would find that
"computer" is worth 14 points in a game
of Scrabble, and "science" is worth
11 points in a game of Scrabble,
so between those two words,
"computer" would win.
Your task now is to write a program in
C that can do this comparison for you--
taking two words and figuring out which
one would win in a game of Scrabble.
Your program will work like this.
At the command line, you would
run the program ./scrabble.
Your program will then prompt
for a word from player 1,
and player 1 would type in a word--
for example, the word "computer."
And then your program would
prompt player 2 to type in a word,
and player 2 could then type in
a word-- for example, "science."
Your program should then take both of
those words, looking at each letter
and figuring out how much
each letter is worth,
and using that information to
figure out which of the two words
is going to have a higher
score in a game of Scrabble.
In this case, player
1's word, "computer,"
has the higher score, so your
program is going to print something
like "Player 1 wins!"
for example.
Now, how exactly is your
program going to figure out
how many points a
particular word is worth?
Well, in the distribution
code we give you--
which we'll take a look at in a moment--
we give you an array of integers,
called POINTS, in all capital letters,
and this here is an array of 26
integers, each one representing
the Scrabble score for
a particular letter--
in alphabetical order.
And because this is
an array, we can index
into that array using square
brackets to get access
to one particular score
for one particular letter.
For example, if we wanted to figure out
how many points the letter A is worth--
the first letter of the alphabet--
we would use POINTS square
bracket 0 to get access
to the first element
in the array, recalling
that the first element in an
array is the element at index 0.
If I wanted to figure out how
many points the letter B is worth,
I could use POINTS square bracket
1 to get access to the number 3--
the value for the letter B.
Likewise, POINTS square bracket 2
would give me access to the
point value of the letter C,
all the way up to POINTS
square bracket 25,
which would give me access to the
last element in this array, which
in this case is 10,
the value for letter Z.
With that in mind, let's now take a look
at the rest of the distribution code
that we give you for this lab.
Here, in scrabble.c, you'll notice that
after including cs50.h and stdio.h,
we have this array of points that
has all of the point values for each
of the letters of the alphabet
in alphabetical order,
and then inside of the
main function, we've
already written some code for you.
And your task is just going to
be to complete this function.
We start by using get_string to prompt
the user for a word from player 1,
storing that inside of
word 1, and likewise doing
the same thing for player 2--
get_string for player 2, storing
whatever string the user types
in as word 2.
After that, we score both words by
calling this compute_score function,
first on word 1, and then calling
that same function on word 2.
We haven't seen that function
yet, but implementing
that function is going to be up to you.
And we'll save the result of that
function inside of the variables
score 1 and score 2.
Left up to you is to print out the
winner between player 1 and player 2--
to compare those two
values, score 1 and score 2,
and to print either that player
1 wins, or player 2 wins,
or, in the event that both
words have the same score,
to print out that it's a tie.
The other piece of this program
that you'll need to write
is this compute_score function.
This function takes a word as
input, which is of type string,
and returns an int, representing
the score for that particular word.
And you'll likely want to compute
that score by iterating over
all of the characters in the word,
and for each of those characters,
figuring out how many points
that character is worth.
So in summary, here's
what you'll need to do.
First, complete the
compute_score function,
returning the number of points that
would be given to any particular word.
In doing so, you'll want to
ignore any non-letter characters.
In Scrabble, only the letters A
through Z actually count for points,
so if the user includes punctuation or
spaces inside of the text they write,
you should ignore
those other characters,
and only consider the letters
when determining the score.
Your function should
also be case-insensitive.
That is to say, regardless
of whether the character is
an uppercase letter
or a lowercase letter,
you should be able to assign that
letter some number of points.
Both capital A and lowercase a are
each worth 1 point, for example.
After you've completed the
compute_score function,
you should then complete
the main function
by comparing those two
values, score 1 and score 2,
and then printing either player
1 wins, or player 2 wins,
or tie, depending on how those two
scores compare with each other.
After you've implemented
these steps, you
should then be able to run your Scrabble
program, provide a word for player 1,
and provide a word for
player 2, and your program
should be able to tell you
which of those two words
would be worth more
in a game of Scrabble.
My name is Brian, and this was Scrabble.