[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
And this is week five, which is going
to be our last week in C. But what
that means is that we'll have OK--
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
But with this week, with last
week, and really all of the weeks
prior, have you been
hopefully acquiring,
if slowly and with some challenge,
some fundamental building
blocks that are still going
to underlie everything
we continue doing in the
semester, even as we transition
to so-called higher level languages.
Next week, indeed, we'll introduce
Python, a very popular language that
does not have pointers,
does not have memory
management at this very low level.
But that's really just
because someone else wrote
the code that will do that for you.
And it's going to make our lives easier.
Because it means when you want to
solve a problem conceptually up here
to just get real work done
or build something amazing,
you don't have to really
get into the same weeds
as we have been deliberately
this week and now last.
But the goal ultimately is that you
better understand and can better
harness then all that a computer can do
even in those higher level languages.
So today, we're going
to focus particularly
on data structures, how you might
structure your data in memory, which
really amounts to building things
digitally, stitching together
ideas and concepts in memory
using this new building
block from last week, which
of course are these pointers.
Pointers allow you to store addresses
in memory, like in variables.
But with those simple addresses
we can leave these breadcrumbs.
We can point from here to there.
And we can conceptually stitch
pieces of data together.
But there's going to be
different ways of doing that.
And today we'll focus
first on what's generally
known as an abstract data type.
And similar to a type in C more
generally, it does actually
have some properties in it.
But the underlying implementation
details of an abstract data type
are ultimately up to you.
That is to say, an abstract data
type can represent one thing
and can do something.
But how you implement it allows you
some discretion underneath the hood.
So for instance, in the
world of computer science,
a queue is actually a technical term.
This is a type of data structure that
we could theoretically build in code
in C or really any other language.
But a queue has properties just
like queues in the real world.
For instance, if you've
ever lined up for something
to get food in a restaurant,
or go into a store,
or wait for the airport to clear you,
well, you've lined up in a queue.
A queue being some sort of line.
But what's noteworthy about
queues are specific properties.
They are first in, first out
data structures, either virtually
or in the human world.
Which is to say the
first person in the line
should ideally be served
first at the restaurant.
Or the first person in the line should
get through airport security first.
By contrast, if it weren't
first in first out,
you can imagine how
frustrated you would be
if you have this inherent unfairness.
In fact, if you've ever been in line
at a store, a supermarket, or the like,
and all of a sudden they
maybe open a new line.
And now the person behind you
gets to cut ahead and go forward.
That's because they've broken
the concept of the queue.
So it has this inherent potential
for unfairness unless you maintain
this first in first out property.
This would be true too for a to-do
list, just for productivity's sake.
If you're in the habit on paper or
virtually making a to-do list, ideally
you probably want to go
through that list top
to bottom so that you actually
get the first stuff you
thought of done first rather than always
focusing on your most recent thought.
Now, within the world of
queues, there's generally
two operations, two
functions, if you will,
that any queue would have either in
the real world or in the virtual.
Enqueue is usually the technical term
to mean adding something to a queue.
But specifically, it means
adding it to the end of the queue
so that someone isn't cutting in
line, for instance, to go up front.
And then dequeue is just the opposite.
When it's time for the
first person in line
to be served, the time for the first
person in line to go through security,
they are dequeued, so to speak.
So a technical concept, ultimately,
as it's implemented in code.
But it's really just
a real-world concept.
And these are in contrast to
another abstract data type
that we might call a stack.
And a stack, much like a stack
of trays in the cafeteria
has fundamentally different properties.
You can still add and remove things
from them, but consider what happens.
Whenever they clean all of the trays
in the cafeteria or the dining hall,
they put one of the trays down here
and then the next one on top of it.
And then the next one on top
of it, it, it, and so forth.
But of course, which
tray do you presumably
take as a user of that physical stack?
The top one, presumably.
You're not going to futz down
here and try to pull one out.
And so, that would seem to
have an opposite property.
LIFO, last in first out is what
characterizes something like a stack.
And that just makes sense,
certainly, in the physical world
of stacking all of those
cafeteria trays because it just
makes more sense to
grab the most recently
added one, the last added one first.
And at least in that context,
the trays don't necessarily
care what order they're used in.
But even then, you could
imagine that maybe there's
some old dirty nasty tray
at the very bottom that
never gets used because you're
constantly replenishing the stack.
So there might very well be side
effects of these kinds of features.
You might be familiar with using
Gmail for instance, or really
any email program.
What you're looking at in your
inbox is technically a stack,
at least if you've left
the defaults configured.
Why?
You get a new email?
Where does it end up?
Not five pages of emails later,
presumably right at the top.
And the next one's right at the top,
right at the top, right at the top.
And so, if you're like me,
you're guilty of eventually
losing track of some emails.
Why?
Because you've pushed so many
more emails onto the stack
that you lose track of the
things you got earliest.
Last in first out though, is maintained.
The most recent email you get might
very well be the first one you reply to.
But that's not necessarily good
for responsiveness to everyone
else out there.
Similarly, if you store all of
your sweaters in a stack like this,
like a pile of black ones, below
which is a red and then a blue.
Stack might be perfectly fine
for keeping things organized.
It's the sane way to do it if you just
have a shelf in your dorm room or home.
But what's going to be a
side effect of using a stack
to store your sweaters if there
are these in this way as opposed
to a queue?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: It's harder to
get the red and blue ones?
DAVID J. MALAN: It's harder
to get the red and blue ones.
So presumably you're going to much
more often wear, for instance,
if you will, black instead there.
Now, the operations for
adding things to a stack
are similar in spirit, but
just different vocabulary.
You push something on top of a stack.
Even though it's more like in the
tray world you place it or rest it.
But pushing means adding
something to the top of the stack.
And popping means removing something
also from the top of the stack.
So it's not a matter of enqueuing at
the end and dequeuing at the beginning.
With a stack, everything's
happening on top.
You're pushing onto the top and
then popping off of the top.
Now, when it comes to actual code, how
might we implement something like this?
Well, let's just focus
on really how you might
implement the data structure itself.
And we won't implement any functions.
You might implement the
notion of a stack like this.
We've seen typedef before.
It just means define
a new type of my own.
Struct means here comes
a structure, a.k.a.
a data structure of one
or more variables within.
And let's suppose, like last time, we've
had-- we defined already a person data
type using a separate typedef.
And every person has a name
and a number or whatever.
Let me just stipulate that
person exists already.
So here, you might have
to implement a stack,
an array called people of some capacity.
Maybe it's an array of size
10, or 100, or whatever.
This is a constant here
in this context, capacity.
And every element in that
array is a person structure.
And I now have this too, size.
Now, this almost seems like
a synonym for capacity.
But maybe intuitively, anyone
want to propose why I'm apparently
maintaining separately
the capacity of the stack
but also the size of the stack?
Why these two distinctions here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Capacity is how
high the stack could be.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Size is how high
it actually is right now.
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
The capacity is how
high the stack could be,
like how much room is there for those
sweatshirts in my closet, for instance.
Whereas size is just literally
at this moment in time,
how many sweatshirts are in the stack.
It's either capacity or fewer
presumably in total there.
So what is capacity?
Well, we could implement this
in perhaps a familiar way.
I might just define a const
somewhere else in my code of type int
that just defines it to be capacity 50.
But what perhaps is
going to be the downside
of implementing a stack in this way?
Of using an array inside here?
What's a downside now of implementing
a stack using an array and this size
variable within.
What's a caveat here perhaps?
Any hands?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So
it's going to be harder
to reach elements that
aren't the last one.
That is the most recently added one.
So there could be some sweatshirts,
so to speak, way down below.
So we've seen that before too.
But at some point too a
limitation of this design
is what it's going to be finite.
I can maximally fit in this example
50 sweatshirts, or 50 emails,
or 50 cafeteria trays, which is fine.
But at least it's indeed finite.
And at least in the
computer's memory, it
might be nice to use more, and more,
and more, maybe as more things are
getting added to the computer.
So maybe I make this 500.
Or heck, why don't I
make it 5,000 or 50,000?
Well, what's the trade-off there?
If I want to have enough
room to grow, seems
like I should just crank up the
value of capacity endlessly.
But why might I not want to change
the 50 to 500, or 5,000, or 50,000?
What's the trade-off there
perhaps just intuitively?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Because I don't want to
touch memory that I'm not supposed to.
DAVID J. MALAN: You don't want
to touch memory that you're not
supposed to be touching.
And in this case, it wouldn't be--
that wouldn't be a risk per se
unless you indeed overflow the stack.
But there's a related issue in
asking for that much memory.
What would another downside be?
AUDIENCE: You only have one element and
you have [INAUDIBLE] 5,000 [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
[LAUGHS] Exactly.
So if you've got a capacity
of 5,000 but you're only
using one of those elements, it's
awkward to say it non-technically.
Which is just to say
very, very wasteful.
That's just bad design.
It's correct, it will work
for up to 5,000 elements.
But my gosh, you're
wasting 4,999 extra spots.
And that's not going to end
well, especially if you're
using more data structures in memory.
Your Mac, your PC, your phone
is surely going to run out
of memory if you ask for that much.
So it'd be nice if there was
a bit more dynamism there,
whether it's a stack or
a queue, both of which
might be implemented a
little similarly in spirit.
But let's conclude this abstraction by
comparing-- thanks to a friend of ours,
Professor Shannon Duvall of Elon
University, who kindly put together
this graphical animation that's just
under two minutes long that paints
a picture of these two types
of abstract data structures.
And then we'll dive in underneath to how
we might implement problems like these.
If we could dim the lights dramatically.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- Once upon a time, there
was a guy named Jack.
When it came to making friends,
Jack did not have the knack.
So Jack went to talk to the
most popular guy he knew.
He went up to Lou and
asked, what do I do?
Lou saw that his friend
was really distressed.
Well, Lou began, just
look how you're dressed.
Don't you have any clothes
with a different look?
Yes, said Jack.
I sure do.
Come to my house and
I'll show them to you.
So they went off to Jack's.
And Jack showed Lou the box where he
kept all his shirts, and his pants,
at his socks.
Lou said, I see you have
all your clothes in a pile.
Why don't you wear some
others once in a while?
Jack said, well, when I
remove clothes and socks,
I wash them and put
them away in the box.
Then comes the next
morning and up I hop.
I go to the box and get
my clothes off the top.
Lou quickly realized
the problem with Jack.
He kept clothes, CDs,
and books in a stack.
When he'd reach for
something to read or to wear,
he chose a top book or underwear.
Then when he was done he
would put it right back.
Back it would go, on top of the stack.
I know the solution,
said a triumphant Lou.
You need to learn to
start using a queue.
Lou took Jack's clothes
and hung them in a closet.
And when he had emptied
the box, he just tossed it.
Then he said, now, Jack, at the end of
the day, put your clothes on the left
when you put them away.
Then tomorrow morning
when you see the sun
shine, get your clothes from the
right from the end of the line.
Don't you see? said Lou.
It will be so nice.
You'll wear everything once
before you wear something twice.
And with everything in queues
in his closet and shelf,
Jack started to feel
quite sure of himself.
All thanks to Lou and
his wonderful queue.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
[LAUGHS]
AUDIENCE: Great!
[APPLAUSE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Sure.
So that paints a picture of these
two abstract data structures.
But if we really were to
dive underneath the hood
we could implement them in
a number of different ways.
But we really, I think, need
some building blocks via which
we could solve problems like those.
And we'll see today too,
some others as well.
So let's rewind back to week two
when we implement-- we introduced you
to your very first data structure.
That is an array.
And an array, recall, was
just a chunk of memory
whereby elements were stored
by design back to back to back.
It's an array of contiguous
memory specifically.
So with an array, we could certainly
store not just one thing but two,
or three, or even more.
And so, for instance, if we treat my
computer's memory as this abstraction
here, and pictured here are three
bytes or some multiplication thereof,
suppose we're storing in the computer's
memory an array of size three,
storing the digits one, two, and three.
Well, remember, that if
we zoom out per last week,
there's other stuff going on in memory.
So even if we want to add
another number to this array
that we didn't think of when we first
started the program, like the number
four, ideally we would put
it right here next to it.
Otherwise it's no longer an array.
So by definition, if
we're using an array,
it's got to end up right
there after the three.
But what else is going on inside
of your computer's memory?
Well, assuming your
program is of any length,
and you've got other
variables, other functions,
you've been running it for a
while, there's a lot going on.
And your memory's being used and reused.
So for instance,
somewhere in memory might
be immediately adjacent to this,
Hello, comma, world, backslash zero,
the null character,
just because maybe you
have another variable
somewhere in there that
is storing that particular
string alongside your existing
array of size three.
And all of these Oscar the
Grouches here really just
represent what we called
last week garbage values.
There's obviously bits there
because they don't disappear.
They're always going to be inside
of the computer somehow implemented.
But we don't really know
or care what they are.
They're the remnants
of those bytes having
been used for other older variables,
previous function calls, or the like.
But the problem clearly here is
that, OK, one, two, three is there.
But the H is here.
And unless I want to start
taking a bite out of my string
by overriding the H with a four,
we just can't fit it right there.
And yet, even though there's
Oscars all over the place,
those are indeed garbage values.
And therefore, we could use that
space because it's technically unused.
We just don't know or
care what the values are.
So where could I put
one, two, three, four?
Well, my gosh.
I have all this memory
down here that's unused.
I could certainly change those garbage
values to be one, two, three, four.
But to do that, I might need
to do a bit of work here.
It's not just a matter of just
saying boom and it happens.
Now with C and with code, I'd have to
do this a little more methodically.
So let me abstract away everything
else that's a distraction.
Let me assume that there is indeed at
least four bytes available for numbers,
just down here that we could have put
them in a bunch of different spots.
What's involved now in moving the one,
two, three to this new chunk of memory
so we can add the four?
Well, I think conceptually
we're going to have
to copy the one from old to new.
Copy the two from old to new.
Copy the three from old to new.
And then ultimately, we can
get rid of the old memory.
Those three original bytes could
now look like Oscar the Grouch
and just be garbage values
for all intents and purposes.
But now I have room for a fourth byte
wherein I can put the number four.
So this is nice.
But what's a downside of this approach?
What's a downside of solving the problem
in this way, where the problem at hand
is just to grow the array, so
to speak, to increase its size,
to fit one or more numbers?
Seems pretty straight forward.
But yeah.
AUDIENCE: That it's just out of order.
You move the one, two, three,
four to the very bottom.
DAVID J. MALAN: Maybe it's out of order.
But I think that's OK because the order
is just matters that it's relative.
So so long it's still
contiguous back, to back,
to back in a different chunk of
memory, I think we're OK there.
It's not like I changed it
from four, three, two, one.
But a reasonable hunch.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I didn't really plan ahead here.
If I have to add another number,
like five or anything else,
well, I might have to jump
through these hoops again.
Maybe I get lucky and
maybe there's space there.
But not if I have other variables
and other things going on,
that too might be used at some point.
Other thoughts?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Slow efficiency.
DAVID J. MALAN: Slow efficiency, why?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I mean, it's just inefficient.
It's bad design arguably.
Why?
Because I had a copy all of
my original work down here.
And as you note, if I want
to add a fifth number,
I'm going to have to copy it
again, and again, and again.
And do things n times again and again.
Now, maybe that's necessary.
We'll soon see for sure.
But it feels like this is not going to
end well, especially if the array isn't
of size three or four but 300, 400.
Your computer ends up spending so
much time just spinning its wheels.
I mean, honestly, better might be this.
If this is my same array physically
incarnated now, one, two, three,
it's literally on the edge of the shelf.
So there's no room for the number four.
Maybe where we could take this
story is, well, let's just
find room for the four.
Let's just put the four,
for instance, over here,
replacing some available garbage
value, some spare byte over here.
But now, wait a minute.
I've broken the definition of an array.
I can't have one, two, three
and then four over here.
So maybe there maybe could be a
mechanism if I put this thing on again,
where when you get to the
end of the existing elements
maybe I just somehow digitally
point to the fourth array.
And maybe we can stitch together all
of these different values in memory
so that if you follow
the arrows, so to speak,
we can reconstruct exactly
what the order is even
without having to find or make room
here or pick up all of these numbers
and move all of them over there.
So that's perhaps the direction
in which we'll go here.
So let's see how we might
get to that spot as follows.
Let me go ahead and open
up, say, VS Code here.
Let me open up a program
called list.c in my terminal.
And let me go ahead and whip
up a relatively simple program
that just demonstrates what
we did back in week two
when we introduced arrays as follows.
Let me include stdio.h so
we can print stuff out.
Let me do int main void.
No command line arguments for now.
Let me give myself an array
called list of size three.
And I'll just hard-code it to keep
it simple for lecture's sake, each
of which is going to be an integer.
And now, just so we have
some specifics to talk about,
let me put it list bracket
zero the number one,
list bracket one the number two, and
list bracket two the number three.
So I'm just translating into code what
we just had pictorially on the screen
and also physically here with
these numbers on the desk.
Now, let's just do something
mildly useful for this.
How about we do four int i get zero,
i is less than three, i plus, plus.
Let's just print each of
these numbers out just
to make sure they're indeed
in memory as I intended.
So percent i backslash n
comma i and then a semicolon.
And I think that's it for now.
So nothing interesting.
No problem solved just yet.
Just a proof of concept.
So that now when I clear
my terminal and run
make list no apparent
errors at the terminal.
And so, when I now do dot slash list,
I should see, hopefully from left
to right, one, two, three.
But of course, if I want
to add a fourth number now,
there's no mechanism for such.
Certainly in the code that I just
wrote I could go back in here
and change this to a four.
I could go down here and change
lists bracket three equals four.
I could just manually change
the code, recompile the code.
But of course, that doesn't
give me any additional runway
for the fifth or sixth number.
So let me try to take a
different approach drawing
some inspiration from last week.
If I want to allocate
memory dynamically,
maybe because I don't know when I wrote
the program how many bytes I want,
we have another function
as of last week that
does not require that you commit in
advance to a certain number of bytes
via what function can you just ask the
operating system for a chunk of memory.
So malloc, allocate memory.
Now, an array is just a chunk of memory.
And even though since
week two we've been
using this syntactic sugar,
this convenience of just using
square brackets and
indexing into it, it's
just making it easier to manipulate
a chunk of memory that's contiguous
all together back, to back, to back.
So today, just like last week, we
can take those training wheels off
and maybe be a little more
deliberate in how we allocate memory.
Let me go, for instance, and do this.
Let me delete my contents
of my main function here.
Go back into main.
And let me propose now that I declare,
for instance, how about my list no
longer as an array but as a pointer.
So int star list.
And I'm going to go
ahead and initialize this
to be how about a chunk
of three integers for now?
So I'm still going to hard-code it.
But I'm taking a step toward
more dynamism for now.
So let me allocate three times
whatever the size is of an int.
But it's usually going to
be four bytes, as we know.
So this is really going
to be 3 times 4 equals 12.
But it's a little more dynamic.
And now, what can I do down here?
Well, this is just a chunk of memory.
So I can do literally list
bracket zero equals one.
List bracket one equals two.
List bracket two equals three.
And voila, achieve
the exact same effect.
Because, again, an array is just
a chunk of contiguous memory.
But malloc gives you any old
chunk of contiguous memory
so you can rather treat
one like the other here.
Now, if you really want to be cool,
you can do something like this instead.
You could dereference the
address in list and go there.
You could go down here and dereference
list plus one and go there.
But honestly, no one really
writes code like this.
It's just too cryptic.
It's a little too far over the
line at least for most people.
And so, I think the syntactic
sugar as I keep describing it,
just the more user-friendly
square bracket notation
does the exact same thing, figures
out the pointer arithmetic,
and puts each of these integers
in the right chunks therein.
Now, just to be super pedantic, let
me make sure if something went wrong.
So if list equals equals null, that
means that something went wrong.
Like my computer is out of memory,
which we should check for typically.
So let me just immediately return one
signaling anything other than zero,
which means success typically,
just to get out of this program
because something's wrong.
But now let me propose that I've had a--
well, let's do this.
For int i gets zero, i
less than 3, i plus plus.
Though a better design would
always be to use a const.
But I'm just doing this
for demonstration sake.
Let's print out each of these ints too.
And just make sure I
didn't mess anything up.
And let me open my
terminal window again.
Let me do make list again.
Huh.
Implicitly declaring library function
malloc we type void star something,
something implicitly declaring
is the operative words there.
What did I mess up?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] need
the header [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I forgot the header file in
which malloc is declared.
I remember now, OK,
that's in standard lib.h.
And it's fine to look stuff
like that up if you forget.
So let me include standard lib.h.
Now let me clear my terminal.
Run make list again.
Now we're good. dot slash list.
And now, what did I do wrong?
Oh.
[LAUGHS] OK.
Not intended, but teachable moment.
What did I do wrong?
[LAUGHS] Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You are printing [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I'm printing the values of i instead
of what is at location i in the array.
So what I actually meant
to do was print this out.
Thank you.
So now let me recompile
make list dot slash list.
And now, those are the three values I
was expecting, not the indices thereof.
Now, let me just propose that
for the sake of discussion
that I regret having only
allocated space for three integers.
And maybe I really should have
allocated enough space for four.
Now, this is not how you
would do this in practice.
Because presumably if you
have a change of thought
just go back in and correct the code.
But let me propose
that somewhere in here
is a more complicated program
and time passes, dot, dot, dot.
There's a lot of other
interesting code there.
But at some point, I might want
to give myself more memory.
So how can I do this?
Well, let me just ask the operating
system now for four new bytes of memory
so that we can at least in version
one implement the idea on the board
where I just copied the three
bytes into the new four bytes
and then added a fourth value.
So I'm going to use malloc again.
And I'm going to say,
here's a new pointer.
I'll call it temp, tmp for short,
which is quite common when you just
need it briefly.
I'm going to then call malloc again.
I'm going to say, give me
four integers using size of.
Let me again make sure.
So if temp equals equals
null something went wrong.
So let me just immediately return one.
And for good measure,
before I return one,
let me free the original list
so that I don't leak memory.
So I'm not just
immediately returning one.
I'm being a good citizen
and remembering, well,
if this malloc call did succeed
and indeed I got as far as line 18,
but then line 18 failed, I should free
the memory that I previously malloc'd.
So again, that's the rule of thumb.
If you allocate it,
you should be the one
to free it even before
you're about to quit.
Now, once I've done that, I think I
need to do what we did pictorially
on the screen where I need to
copy the one, the two, the three
from the old array into the new.
So how might I do this?
Well, let me give myself a loop.
So for int i get zero, i
less than 3, i plus plus,
because the size of the
original is still the same.
Let me go ahead and treat the new
chunk of memory called temp as an array
itself.
And so, I can absolutely use these
square brackets just like before.
It's just a chunk of memory.
I'm treating it like an array.
And let me add to that value whatever
is at the original list at location i
as well.
So this, again, is just this exercise
of copying from old to new step by step
the one, the two, and the three.
But I still need one additional step.
If my goal at hand now is to have
ultimately a fourth value here,
well, I'm just going to hard-code
this for demonstration sake.
And I'm going to go to the
very last location of temp,
which is of size four.
Which means the last element
in temp is temp bracket three,
because it's zero-indexed.
But there's four total spaces there.
And I'm just going to arbitrarily
for the sake of discussion
put the number four there.
And that is what happened when we
proposed changing the final garbage
value there to that four.
But now I need to do what the slide
did for us magically on the screen.
I should now do a
couple of final things.
I should free the original list, which
I've not done yet, because I only
called free earlier in cases of error.
And that was just to be safe.
I can now free the list.
And now, if I want to inform the
computer that I want list, quote
unquote, my variable called list
to point at not the old chunk
like it originally did
but the new chunk, I think
I can just do this-- list equals tmp.
And again, that's just saying that
if list is a pointer, which it was.
Because look at the very
top line here, on line six
I declared list to be a
pointer to a chunk of memory.
Temp meanwhile is a separate
So down here, this line 33 is
just a matter of my saying,
OK, now henceforth, because I've
already freed the old chunk of memory,
my list variable should point
not at this chunk of three bytes
but this chunk of four bytes
or really 12 in total now.
Or rather 16 now because
we have four such bytes.
Questions now on this
code, the point of which
was quite simply to demonstrate
how we could implement
in code this idea of fairly correctly
but inefficiently allocating
a new array of sufficient size and then
populating it with a new fourth value.
Questions on what we've just done here?
No?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
At this point in the
story, with line 33,
do I not have two different variables
pointing at the same chunk of memory?
Short answer, yes.
But here's where the semantics
are perhaps compelling.
List is the variable that
I intend to use longer term
and keep around in memory.
And again, assume that there's even
more code going on here that we just
didn't write yet.
So it's useful to have that variable.
Temp was just a necessary evil.
Because up here, it would not
have been correct to do this.
It would not have been
correct to say list on line 18
equals the new chunk
of memory because this
would have represented a memory leak.
If I prematurely change temp to point
not at the old chunk but the new chunk,
at that point no one's
pointing at the old chunk.
And so I've lost those three bytes.
Valgrind, for instance,
would yell at you
for having lost as many bytes in memory.
So in this case here, I
do leave this as temp.
Yes, it's duplicative at this point.
But it's not a huge deal if
it was just meant semantically
to be a temporary value.
But down here, at the risk
of one more line of code,
I still want to, to be a good
citizen, free list, and maybe
just for good measure
return zero explicitly.
But notice, it's not doing
it twice per se on line 31.
What am I freeing?
The original address of list.
The three-integer version.
Then I change what list points at.
So it's pointing at a
completely different chunk
of memory, this one of size four.
So eventually, when I'm all done using
this memory for this demonstration,
I still need to free list.
But at this point in
the storyline 40, it's
pointing at the new chunk of memory,
which I similarly need to hand back
to the operating system by free.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: When
would temp equal null?
So let me scroll back up slightly.
This is being a good citizen
and a good programmer.
Whenever it comes to
using malloc, malloc
can return null if the
computer is out of memory.
So this is maybe a much bigger program.
You've got other things going on in it.
And so, you just don't have enough
memory available to be handed.
Malloc needs to signal to
you that there's some error.
And so, it will buy convention
per the documentation,
per the manual pages return null.
So this is just me being a good citizen.
Otherwise, here's another error
that might cause your program
to crash with a segmentation
fault. If you get back
null but you assume that it's good
memory going to address zero, a.k.a.
null, will crash your
program intentionally.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: If you want to write
[INAUDIBLE] at the very bottom
of a program, and you
just put [INAUDIBLE],,
it would [INAUDIBLE] the
same [INAUDIBLE],, right?
DAVID J. MALAN: Correct.
If I were to change my final
line 40 here to be free temp,
this would also work as well.
And here, this is really
a matter of design.
It's a very nitpicky thing.
We could probably debate it.
But because at this point in
the story my main variable
for remembering where the
list is is called list.
This is the more responsible
way to do it, freeing the list,
just so that my
colleagues, my TA doesn't
wonder why are you freeing temporary
memory that you already freed.
It just is a semantic
thing at this point.
But good instinct.
It would also work.
Correct.
Maybe just not good design.
So it turns out that this
gets annoying quickly
as it did in the picture of
doing all of this duplication.
And even though technically it's
necessary to copy those values,
if you need a newer,
bigger chunk of memory,
there is at least a function in C
that simplifies a lot of this for us.
And in fact, let me
go ahead and do this.
Instead of using malloc,
this second time on line 18
in addition to the first
time I used it on line six,
I'm actually going to try and introduce
another function called realloc, which
as the name suggests tries
to reallocate memory for you.
And it works a little
differently from malloc.
realloc expects two arguments.
The first one is what
is the chunk of memory
that you want to try to grow
or shrink, that is, reallocate
to be a different size.
And then you specify
what size you would want.
And indeed, in this case, I
want four times size of int.
And that will now give me hopefully a
new address of a chunk of memory that's
big enough to fit all four numbers.
But what's wonderful
about realloc is that it
will handle all of the copying for me.
So in fact, I'm going to go down here.
I'm going to get rid of all
of this, this extra for loop.
And what I'm simply going
to do instead is this.
Once I can trust after
lines 18 through 23
that realloc worked, and it didn't
return null because I'm out of memory,
I can just say, OK, just immediately
remember that the new list points
at this new chunk of memory instead.
And then, I can still now do this line.
But I can tweak the semantics here
and just say list bracket three
the new final location
in the new list is four.
I don't need to free this here.
I don't need to do this.
All I need now at the
bottom is the final for loop
to just print out these values.
So in short, even though
that was somewhat quick,
using realloc just
moves the entire copying
process that I implemented myself
a moment ago using a for loop.
It just moves it to realloc and lets
it deal with the copying for me.
It's no more efficient.
But at least means I'm writing
less code, which is more pleasant.
And hopefully, the people
who wrote malloc or realloc
are smarter than me and they just will
introduce bugs with lower probability
too.
That was a lot.
Any questions?
AUDIENCE: Why do you
still have to [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
Why do you still need to make list
equal temp as I did on line 24?
So ideally, I would do this.
Ideally I would just change
this line 18 to be list.
That is to say, call--
or actually, even better,
ideally I would just
say reallocate this list
to be of this new size.
But again, things can go
wrong when allocating memory.
You need to check a return value
to see if it was successful or not.
And so, we need to use a return value.
So let's not introduce temp.
Let's just use list.
But here's where a
memory leak might happen.
In the off chance
realloc fails and doesn't
have enough memory for
your four bytes, therefore
it returns by definition null.
You can't overwrite the original value
of list with null to then check it.
Why?
Because now who remembers where
the original three bytes were?
If you prematurely change the
value of list, you've lost.
You've leaked memory in that sense.
And so, that's why-- let
me undo this change--
I declare a temporary pointer
for the sole purpose of making
sure I can check the return value.
And then, once it's good, now
I'll update the value of list.
So it's doing a switcheroo
by making sure first
that you have a new value
to swap with the old.
Other questions on this code?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Does realloc [INAUDIBLE]
memory where [INAUDIBLE] is stored?
DAVID J. MALAN: Indeed.
realloc automatically frees
the previous memory for you.
And better yet, it's
even smarter than that.
If you get lucky and there happens
to be space right after your existing
chunk of memory, so one, two, three,
garbage value, instead of one,
two, three, Hello,
world, realloc won't even
bother copying things from old to new.
It will just say, OK,
I'm going to now reserve
for you more bytes than you
originally asked for so it doesn't
have to waste time doing that copying.
And so, in that sense, this version
is now not only still correct,
it's even better designed because we're
not wasting time with that for loop.
We might have to resort to it if there
is, in fact, Hello, world or something
else in the way.
But hopefully, we'll get
lucky and save those steps.
Other questions on this
manipulation of code here?
Yeah, in the middle.
AUDIENCE: So [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: What if you want
to resize a two-dimensional array?
So very similar in spirit whereby
you can use the same trickery.
Let me wave my hand at
that for now just because I
think that's going to significantly
increase the complexity.
But very same primitives ultimately.
A two-dimensional array is essentially
just a doubly long or quadratically
longer list of memory that
using square bracket notation
is doing some of that
mental math for you.
But it's fundamentally no different of
what's going on underneath the hood.
So with that said and
that code under our belt,
even though that's not going to
be something you'll frequently
need to code yourself,
let's propose now how
we might go about building some
actual data structures ourselves.
The new ingredient
here being this reality
that if you want to resize a chunk of
memory so as to make room for things,
we now have that ability.
Memory addresses.
And pointers just give us the
ability to point around at things
and move things around in memory.
But now that we have
malloc and even realloc,
you can imagine, maybe
rewinding, and you
could implement that stack, that
queue using not an array per
se, because you have to commit
to an array size in advance.
But if you implement your stack or
your queue using a pointer and then
malloc and realloc, and maybe someone
else writes all that code for you,
perhaps now you can imagine
that now the stack can grow
or shrink by using realloc accordingly.
You don't have to preemptively say give
me five bytes, or 50, or 500, or 5,000.
You can say, just give me one initially.
And if I need more, I'll
realloc, realloc, realloc.
And if you keep popping
things off the stack,
you can realloc in the other direction
and ask for fewer and fewer bytes
and the operating system can
take that memory back as well.
So we now have this building block.
Let's see what we can do with it.
So we've had a few pieces of syntax
in recent weeks, all of which
we're going to combine now in
just a slightly more clever way.
So struct is this keyword in C that lets
us build our own structure in memory,
like a collection of two
or three or more variables,
like a person that we've seen before.
The dot operator, recall, we've used
when you do have a struct like a person
and you want to go inside of it.
So person.name or person.number.
We did this a few weeks ago.
Now but the dot operator just allows
you to go inside of a structure
and get the individual variables within.
And then, the star operator,
unfortunately, has a lot of uses now.
One was multiplication.
My God, that was easy back in the day.
Now it's used to declare pointers.
It's also used to dereference pointer.
So to make one exist and
then go to that address.
Unfortunately, it's the same
symbol for all of those.
But it's all related.
But with these three
symbols, it turns out--
you're going to get one
last one today-- and my God,
it finally looks like the concept.
It turns out there's
a clever way any time
you want to use the dot and the
star together, that is, to go
somewhere, and go to an address,
and then look inside of a structure,
you can actually literally use
an arrow symbol on your keyboard.
It's not a single keystroke.
It's a hyphen and then
an open angle bracket.
But at least it looks like an arrow.
And we'll see indeed in code today,
the things I was drawing pictorially
on the screen last time
with yellow arrows,
you can actually now
express as well in code.
And so, here we have our next data
structure called a linked list.
And this is one of the most
useful powerful concepts in C.
It's the kind of thing that you
can take for granted in Java
and Python and higher level languages.
But today, we'll see how we or others
can actually build these things just
using these same primitives.
So a linked list is going
to allow us to actually do
what we used a foam
finger for last week allow
us to link together, for
instance, these three values maybe
with that fourth value over there.
And then if there's a fifth,
maybe this other foam finger
points even farther over
way to that fifth value.
The key being that you can stitch
together fancier data structures
without having to pick all of
these up and find new space.
You just have to at least
connect the dots somehow.
We just need to somehow
point from one to the other.
And that's going to make things
much more efficient, it would seem.
So how do we get there?
So here's my computer's
memory as always.
Suppose that I'm storing the
value one somewhere in there
and it's at 0x123 address, whatever.
And I'm storing the number two
somewhere else in memory, 0x456.
And number three at address 0x789.
This is not in array by definition.
Why?
Even though it's the only
three things on the screen,
what makes this not an array?
AUDIENCE: It's not contiguous.
DAVID J. MALAN: It's not contiguous.
So this violates the
definition of an array.
But you know, especially
since they're sequential,
it kind of looks to a human like a list.
So it would be nice if there
were a data type called list.
And there isn't in C.
There will be in Python.
But you know what?
If I could somehow stitch
together these three values
so I can get from one
to the next to the next,
then I think we could achieve
the idea the concept of a list
without this really annoying
constraint that they all be
contiguous as in an array.
So how do I do that?
Well, at the end of the day I
only have memory at my disposal.
There's no more training
wheels to take off here.
This is what we've got underneath
the hood of a computer.
So if all I have is memory,
I think the solution
to this problem of stitching
together those values in a list
must be to spend a bit more memory.
That's literally the only
resource we have right now.
So let me propose that if we want
to create a list conceptually out
of three values that are in
random although pictorially pretty
positions in memory, let me just add a
little bit more memory to the picture.
So in addition to storing
the one, I'm going
to leave myself some room, a
little scratch pad if you will,
to use some other bits as well.
Same for the two, same for the three.
And you can perhaps see where
this is going based on last week.
If I want to somehow
connect the one to the two,
any instincts as to what I should
write in this box here that
would lead me effectively
from one to the two?
What could go here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: We could
store the address of two.
And so, specifically, what
would you have me write here?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] pointer 0x456.
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
Ideally, I would just put
in this box another integer,
one that happens to be
represented in hexadecimal.
But that's just a base system.
It's just a human thing
for us to look at.
I'm going to put the value 0x456 here.
So let me go ahead and reveal that.
0x456 goes there.
You can perhaps see further
where this is going.
Well, if I want to get
from the two to the three,
I think I need to put below the
two the address of the three, which
gives me 0x789.
Now if three is the end
of the list, I don't
want to let it be some garbage value.
Because that would imply that
who knows where it's pointing.
I need some definitive value.
And just what would your instincts be?
If I want to make clear with
some special sentinel value
that the buck stops here, what do I put?
What might my options be?
AUDIENCE: Null?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So null.
Not N-U-L, per se, but N-U-L-L, which
was the new keyword we introduced last
week, which just represents
an empty pointer, if you will.
Technically the address 0x0.
So literally, the zero address.
And what humans did years ago,
they just decided, you know what?
Nothing should ever live
at address zero in memory.
We're just going to reserve
that one special byte to be
a special signal, a sentinel
value such that if you ever
see a zero address in a pointer,
it just means it's invalid.
It does not exist.
Now, we write that though a little more
pleasantly for the eyes as just N-U-L-L
in all caps.
And that's a keyword in C as well.
But of course, last week, I claimed that
who cares where things are in memory.
And honestly, this quickly gets tedious
even worrying about these values.
So let me abstract this
away and propose that if we
want to remember where all of
these numbers are in memory,
let's give ourselves one
final piece of memory
that just allows us to
start the whole process.
Let me allocate on the left-hand
side here not room for a number,
like one, two, three, just room
for a pointer that henceforth
I think I'll call list by convention.
And then store in that
one additional pointer
a value that just kickstarts
the whole process.
This is the treasure map, if
you will, that you get handed.
And this has the address of the
very first actual node in memory.
Now, technically, we could
just start with this.
But it turns out we'll see
it's just a little cleaner
to use a simple single
pointer that leads
to the things you care about, as opposed
to just starting with the first element
y.
Well, if you ever want to
get rid of this element,
it'd be nice if you could
at least still hang on
to an empty sheet of paper
that indicates that the list is
empty would be one argument for that.
So again, who cares about
these addresses now?
Now with the wave of the hand,
let's just abstract it away.
And there are our pointers.
Each of those addresses in
the squares at the bottom
are simply pointing to the
next element in the list.
The jargon to introduce
here would be that now
that we have these
integers one, two, three,
but they're in these
wrappers, if you will,
these structures that have metadata that
is additional data that is related to
but not the data you
actually care about.
This is data.
This is metadata.
This thing here, rectangularly
we'll call a node--
N-O-D-E. And it's just a term of
art that means it's like a container
in code for storing some values.
This then is a linked list.
And this then is the
graphical incarnation
of one node pointing to the other.
In this case, they happen to
be by chance and by design
of this desk contiguous initially.
But there's no requirement
that they be such.
The one could be over there.
The two over there.
The three over there.
I would just need more foam fingers
to point at one to the next.
Questions on this
concept of a linked list?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, in the back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] array [INAUDIBLE]
by pointer that is outside of the array
itself?
DAVID J. MALAN: Can you say that again?
AUDIENCE: Do traditional arrays
always start [INAUDIBLE] pointer
that is outside of the [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
Do traditional arrays
start with a pointer
that's outside of the structure?
Short answer, no.
Arrays are special in C and
certain other languages.
And the name of an array is
technically a symbol, if you will,
that the computer-- the program knows
maps to a specific location in memory.
It's just a label, a synonym
for an memory address.
It does not take up space.
So to be clear, the name of an
array does not take up space
like that extra square on the left.
But you do need that extra square on
the left when implementing a linked list
so that you can determine
if the list is of size
zero there's nothing being pointed
at, or size three in this case.
We're taking on more
responsibility ourselves.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: How do you
point to the next element?
Can you elaborate?
AUDIENCE: These elements pointing to
the next one, how does [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID J. MALAN: Ah, good question.
If each of these elements
is pointing to the next,
how does three point to the others?
Short answer, it doesn't.
At least in this design
we have more technically
what's called a singly linked list.
And as the arrows imply, it
only goes in one direction.
So if you somehow find in code maybe
a for loop, maybe a while loop,
somehow you're in code over
here, you have no way in code
to go backwards unless we change
this to a doubly linked list
where I add another box that lets
me have arrows in both directions.
Or maybe I just make it circular
and I connect the three back
to the one, which you can totally do.
But that tends to make
life harder because now you
have to figure out when you're stuck
in a loop in your data structure.
But it's doable as well.
But as is, it's a dead end by design.
Other questions on this design here?
Well, how might we implement
this structure in code?
Well, let me just connect the dots
to something we've seen before here.
This is how a couple of weeks ago,
we introduced the notion of a person.
And we claimed a person might
have a name and a number.
Last week, of course, we took off
some of these training wheels.
And a string is really technically
a char star in both cases.
But really, there's no conceptual
difference beyond that.
But let's use this same
paradigm to implement a node
as I described it in that picture.
So let me get rid of
the name and the number
because that's related only to a person.
And let me rename this structure
for discussion's sake to node.
That then invites the question, well,
what needs to go inside of a node?
Well, minimally, an integer.
But this is now where we need to think
a little harder, just conceptually.
Even if you have no idea how
to type it at the keyboard,
what else needs to be part of a node
based on these rectangular pictures
that we've drawn?
What more do we need?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
We need a pointer to another node.
So if I don't know how to implement this
yet, it could be something like pointer
to another node, how do I do that?
Well, you know what?
It turns out you would ideally say this.
If you know that the next node is
itself a node by definition, well,
any time we've needed a pointer we
just use the data type and a star.
And I'm going to arbitrarily,
but I think reasonably,
call this second squared at
the bottom of those rectangles
next as the name of my attribute here.
But node star just connotes
that the next variable
is going to be not a node per
se but the address of a node.
And that's exactly what we did.
You had me put 0x456, 0x789 in that box,
which is the address of another node.
So the way we would express this
in code would be node star next.
But we could call the
variable anything we want.
Now, this is a bit of a white lie.
But we'll fix this right now.
This code won't actually compile.
C takes you pretty literally, recall.
And if you use some term
at the top of your file
that you don't define
until later in your file,
you're going to see some error message.
We've seen this when
I've messed up and I
forgot to include the function
prototypes at the top of my code.
This is related in spirit.
I seem here on my one, two,
three, fourth line of code,
I'm trying to use this new term
of art that I invented here
in my code called node, even
though it's a CS term as well.
But nowhere above this it would seem
did I even define what a node is.
It's not a data type in C.
Every computer scientists
know what a node is.
But it doesn't come for
free with the language.
So I need to do something else.
I need this word here to come
first so that I can use it here.
And so, we have this catch-22.
How can a structure be
self-referential, that is,
point to another version of itself
if the word doesn't yet exist?
So the solution to this in C,
which we didn't need for a person
because there was no notion of listing--
connecting is a list--
we need one more keyword here
that we didn't need for a person.
And we reuse that keyword here.
So kind of an annoying detail.
But if we preemptively call
this whole thing struct node,
you can now refer to the thing on
the inside as a struct node star.
But then you can shorten the name
of the whole thing from struct node
to just node.
Sort of an annoying sequence of steps.
But in short, any time you're building
a node, a linked list in memory,
this is just the paradigm.
You use typedef, struct, the name of
the thing you want to define, like node.
You use that name on the inside if
you want to point from one to another.
And then you can shorten it down
here to just be called node.
Questions then on this code here?
Questions on what we just did?
Well, if I rewind just a moment to that
final picture, what would be the upside
to be clear, of having
jumped through these hoops
and added this complexity if you will?
What problem did we just solve by
linking together these three values
to be clear?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Making lists
that are not [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Making lists that are--
AUDIENCE: Not [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, that are
not contiguous, if you will.
So making lists that are
not contiguous in memory.
The upside of which is that if I want
to add the number four to this list,
it looks like I could choose from
any chunks of available memory
on the screen.
I just need to point from
the end of the current list
to wherever that other one is in memory.
What I don't need to do, to be clear,
is copy the one, the two, or the three.
Everything can just stay put.
Which means time-wise I can
do this much more quickly,
it would seem, without copying
things again and again.
And even without using realloc
to let it do all of the copying
potentially for me.
But as we'll start seeing even more in
the coming weeks, every time we benefit
and solve some problem, we pay a price.
There's a trade-off.
What is a downside as
you might perceive now
of using a linked list
instead of an array?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You use twice as much memory.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I mean, we use twice as much memory.
Because now in addition to storing
the integers one, two, three,
I also need to store a
pointer for each of those.
And honestly, even this picture
is a bit of a simplification.
Technically, in most systems today,
each int would be four bytes.
Technically today, most pointers
though would be eight bytes.
I just didn't want to draw
this weird shape on the board
where the bottom square is even
bigger than the top square.
But technically, we're using even
more than twice as much space
for these pointers.
So there's that trade-off.
Now, thankfully, decades
after C was invented,
memory is generally
much cheaper nowadays.
And so, it's OK to spend
more of it if you need to.
And it depends on what
you want to optimize for.
But that's absolutely here a downside.
What's another downside of having
transitioned to a linked list?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: You can't index into it.
Now, I haven't even tried in code.
But when you have a linked list you can
no longer use square bracket notation.
Because why?
Well, square bracket notation just
assumes the contiguousness of memory.
Location zero is here.
Location one is literally
one to the right.
Location two is literally one
to the right, one to the right.
These things, even though I've
drawn it from right to left
to just keep things pretty,
there are gaps here.
And this is just my
interpretation of this.
These gaps could be big.
They could be narrow.
They could be down here, up here.
They could be anywhere so long as we're
linking things together in this list.
The computer can't just use bracket
zero, bracket one, bracket two anymore
because it can't do simple
arithmetic and jump to the middle.
And now, here's perhaps
the worst price we've paid.
If you don't have square
bracket notation, or really,
you don't have contiguousness,
what algorithm did
we just sacrifice for this dynamism?
If you rewind even back to week zero.
And we gave it a name in week three.
What algorithm can we not use now if
we can't assume that the memory is
back, to back, to back, to back?
AUDIENCE: Binary?
DAVID J. MALAN: Binary search.
Why?
Because binary search, just like the
phone book, back in the first week,
requires being able to arithmetically
jump right to the middle.
Take the total length of
it, divide by two, and boom.
You're right there in the middle
with some simple arithmetic.
Here they might be laid out, again,
with these big or small gaps.
There's no simple math I can
do to just jump immediately
to the one in the middle.
And in fact, again, if
this TV were bigger,
the two could technically be in memory
be way down here or even way over here.
The foam finger could be pointing
in any number of directions
depending on where malloc put the thing.
There's just no way to do binary search.
And so, it would seem that
we've paid another price indeed
in terms of a performance.
We're now talking about
linear time again.
So that's a regression.
Now, that's also a lot.
Feels like a good time for some
muffins and fruit out in the lobby.
And when we come back, we'll try to
solve the problem we just created.
So see you in 10.
So we are back.
And let's see if we can't now
take some of these higher level
concepts of stitching
together these nodes in memory
and translate it to some actual code.
But we'll do it step by
step first before I actually
start writing it in VS Code.
So if, Carter, you wouldn't mind helping
me step through with some visuals,
let me propose that line by line
we solve some of the problems
that we've just created for ourselves
in building this thing in memory.
So let's go ahead and
first consider how we
could build a linked list containing
the numbers indeed one, then two, then
three.
And let's translate each
of those steps to code
and then we'll put it all together
into something that actually runs.
So how about the first step
here will just be this.
To declare a pointer called list
that's initially has no value,
at least at this point in the story.
List is the name of the variable.
Node star just means
that this is essentially
going to be our little
square over here that
points to the beginning of the list.
Of course, it's ideal if
it ultimately has a value.
Because when we initially
call this line of code,
it just gives us indeed that
square over here on the left.
But it's got a garbage value because
there's no equal sign on the other side
there.
So let's propose that
we do one more step here
and actually initialize
it to null so that if only
we know that it's not garbage,
it at least has some known value.
And null is a good way of signifying
that at this point in the story
the list is empty.
Indeed, null indicates
there's no nodes in the list.
So that picture would now look
like this, whereby let's just
draw-- instead of
writing null everywhere,
I'll just leave the squares blank
when it's not a garbage value, per se.
It's literally 0x0 or null.
So that's it for building
a linked list of size zero.
We're done then.
But we want to now add a one,
and then a two, then a three.
So next step here might be this.
If I want to allocate the first of my
rectangles on our previous picture,
I'm going to call malloc.
And I'm going to ask for enough
memory to fit a whole node.
Now, technically, I think that's
going to be four bytes for the int
and eight bytes for the
pointer even though I did not
draw it to scale on the board.
So that's technically
going to be what, 12 bytes?
But again, size of node
just figures out how many
bytes I actually need dynamically.
That's going to return to me the
address of that chunk of memory, which
apparently I'm going to store inside
of a temporary variable called n
for short for node.
But let's see what
this does pictorially.
So when this line of code
is executed, I first get,
on the left, that variable n.
It's got a garbage value by
default because I haven't executed
the whole thing from right to left.
Meanwhile, on the right-hand
side of the expression,
I've got now a node somewhere in memory.
It happened to be free here.
This is where malloc put it for me.
But it does have two
garbage values initially.
But because it's a node per my
typedef earlier, every node I proposed
is going to have a number
and a next pointer.
So we can see those labeled here.
But they've got two
garbage values initially.
But all I care about
initially is that ultimately n
is pointing at that chunk of code.
So initially, if we could back up
two steps, we have-- two steps.
So we have initially--
oh, one step forward.
We have this line of code gives us
this variable here, which has garbage.
When this side of the expression is
executed, that allocates the memory.
And then, when we copy from
right to left the address
of that chunk of memory, that's what
gives us conceptually this arrow.
And the garbage goes away because
that's a valid pointer now.
Of course, there's
still two garbage values
there because we haven't set this node
to store a number like the number one.
So let's go ahead and execute
one other line of code
like this, which, while cryptic-looking,
is just an application of ideas
we've seen in week four and prior.
Star n means to start at
this variable and go there.
Follow the arrow is what the star or
the dereference operator does for us.
And then, the dot operator, recall,
when we first introduced structs,
like for a person
struct, allows us to go
at the number field or the next field.
So if I do star n, and
then in parentheses
to make sure order of
operations is preserved,
dot number, and then assign
it the actual number one,
which puts the one in the
top of that rectangle.
Now, admittedly, this syntax
is not very user-friendly.
It's annoying to remember.
You have to have the parentheses.
So there's another syntax for this.
Whenever you're doing two
things like this in code,
dereferencing a pointer
that is going to an address.
And then further using the dot
notation to go inside of the structure,
you find that wonderfully C
gives us this syntax, whereby
you can just change the
star and the parentheses
and the dot to just be an arrow.
And again, it's not a single
character on your keyboard.
It's a hyphen and then
an open angle bracket.
But I kind of like
the semantics of this.
Because this code now pretty much
matches the picture-- n arrow
leads you to the value that you
want to access or ultimately
change in this way.
There's one step,
though, we've forgotten,
of course, which is that we can't
leave this garbage value here.
Because the garbage value is some
unknown value that effectively
is pointing who knows where.
And we don't want to
accidentally misinterpret
that garbage value as being a
valid address and risk going there.
So of course, what value
should we put here instead?
Our old friend null, just to
signify that this is indeed
the end of the list.
And we could do that with
a line of code like this.
And again, we'll connote as much by
just leaving that empty box blank.
So now, we have a list of size one.
Let's go ahead and add the second
number to it as with these lines here.
List equals n allows us to remember
that indeed, we have this list here.
So if we can step one step forward.
Here's what the picture now looks like.
And technically, let's
go one step further here.
This is now really what's going on in
memory once my list of size one exists.
My main variable called list is
pointing at exactly that first node.
At this point in the story
I don't need to know or care
about the temporary variable
that I called n, even though it
might very well still be there.
But indeed, this now
represents that linked list.
Let's now indeed add the number two.
So with the same line of code as before,
I'm going to allocate another node.
Size of node.
Ideally, I would be
checking for null here.
But we're doing the juicy
parts only on the slides.
Let's now go ahead and depict that.
So what happens with this?
This brings back our n pointer, which
might have been there the whole time.
But we're doing this step by step.
It's a garbage value though because we
haven't yet copied from right to left.
Malloc, of course,
gives us a second chunk
of memory, which maybe ends up
there with two garbage values
by default. I've omitted the labels
now just because they're still going
to be number and next respectively.
Once we copy from right to left, the
garbage value indeed becomes an arrow.
Oscar disappears because it's now
indeed a valid pointer pointing here.
Now, the values themselves
number and next are invalid--
garbage value.
So here is where we can now start using
our new syntax like the arrow notation
or the star and the dot if you prefer.
And we can change the value of n--
follow the arrow to number.
And that becomes two.
Similarly, we can do this
again and set n arrow next.
So start at n, follow the
arrow, access the next field,
and set that equal to null.
Now, we're not quite done yet
because we haven't actually
linked things together.
So here's now where
things get interesting.
How do I combine these two?
Well, let me propose this.
Let me propose on our next line
here we actually update for now
list equal to n.
That is to say, whatever address
this is, whatever it's pointing at,
change list to be the same address
that is point at the same thing.
So if n is pointing here, let's
change list to point here.
And go ahead and do that,
Carter, if you could.
I don't like this.
Can you go one further step?
This is bad.
What is wrong about my sequence of
operations here where I updated list
to point at my new node?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: We [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
We lost the pointer to the other node.
So I don't even care about the
ordering, two one or one two.
The bigger problem now as the
lack of arrows over there suggests
is that I have a memory leak.
I have orphaned my
original node in the sense
that nothing is pointing at it anymore.
Now, absolutely, I could fix this
by adding some temporary variables.
I could add it to the mix.
But at this point in the story I have
not done any such recollection thereof.
So let me back this up.
And let's go forward in the slides.
This is where we left off a moment ago.
I think I need to take into
account order of operations.
And I'm going to keep this simple.
I'm not going to care about the
order of the numbers for now.
I'm fine with a list
that is two and then one.
So with that said, let
me go ahead and update,
I think, this box here to
point at my original node.
So let's see how we
could do this in code.
n arrow next.
So n, arrow, next should
equal the current list.
And this is a little weird again.
But recall what list is.
List is this pointer
here that just contains
the address of the original
address of the list,
or equivalently, it contains this
arrow, whatever it's pointing at.
So what this means in this line of
code, n bracket next means start at n,
follow the arrow,
access the next pointer,
and set it equal to
whatever list equals.
So if list is pointing here, then
next should point there as well.
This, I think, is safe.
Because now we have redundancy.
Now we've got two pointers
pointing at the original list.
And now I think we can do another step
whereby we update list to equal n,
same line of code before
that got us into trouble.
But I'm doing it second
now instead of first.
When I execute list equals n, this
now sets list equal to the same thing
that n equals.
And so, now I have successfully
inserted my new node
containing two into the list.
And in fact, if we advance
one more, we can just
clear up the clutter, assume
that the temporary variable is
gone from the story.
Now we have a linked list where
admittedly ordering is wrong.
It's two one instead of one two.
But at least it's linked correctly.
And I didn't orphan or leak any memory.
Questions on this
sequence of steps here?
Yeah, in back.
AUDIENCE: So [INAUDIBLE] this
is all [INAUDIBLE] type, right?
[INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Spot on.
So this would fall under that
category of a stack, if you will.
Although I've not called it that by name
because I just pushed the number two
onto this data structure, if you will.
And indeed, it ended up at the beginning
of the list instead of the end.
And so, here's where we see a
distinction between an abstract data
structure, which is where we began.
A stack is a thing like the pile of
sweaters that just has push and pop
properties and LIFO access--
last in first out.
How do you implement
something like that in memory?
Well, it would seem that you could
implement the notion of a stack here
not for sweaters but for
numbers using a linked list.
So long as you implement
insertion a.k.a.
pushing by pretending new values to
the list by pretending again and again.
And if, Carter, you don't mind
hitting the keyboard one more time.
If I wanted to add the
number three now, you
could imagine prepending it to the list.
Why?
Well honestly, especially as
this list gets longer and longer,
I kind of like the appeal of
prepending these elements.
Why?
Because even if this list gets
crazy long and way, way out here,
you didn't notice me
following all of the arrows
earlier to do the insertions.
If I want to insert a fourth number,
a fifth number, a sixth number,
all I have to do is
insert it here, if you
will, point it at the original start
of the list, then update this pointer,
and done.
And I would say that's
two steps, give or take.
It's not going to be
n steps as it would be
if I had to append the new
nodes to the end of the list.
Now, of course, we've sacrificed
ordering of these numbers.
They're literally in the
opposite order or whatever order
they were inserted in.
But that might very well be OK
depending on the goal at hand.
Thank you to Carter for
stepping through this.
What if now we wanted
to translate this--
[APPLAUSE]
Oh, sure.
Thank you.
[LAUGHS] It's all for you,
none for me in this example.
So here we have perhaps a
way of translating this now
to some actual code.
And this will be the
last of the intense code
here just to give you a sense of
how we can translate this idea now
to actual steps.
So this is list.c in VS Code here.
Let me go ahead and make a
couple of changes up top.
Let me go ahead.
And how about declaring a
node using typedef struct
node using our new framing as before.
I'm going to give every node
a number, as I proposed.
And every node a pointer to
the next element, which is
going to be implemented just as before.
And I'm going to simplify
the whole name as just node.
So all that is is the exact same
typedef that we proposed earlier.
Now, let me go ahead and get rid of all
of this code which we wrote earlier.
And recall that this was the most recent
version that was not a linked list.
This was just an array that we
allocated and then reallocated.
So this is the old way of doing things.
But it was inefficient because we
might have to lean on a for loop
or lean on realloc to
copy everything around.
We're now going to re-implement the
notion of a list as an actual linked
list, not as an array.
So my main function now
might do something like this.
And I'm going to really
just copy the lines of code
that we just stepped
through on the board.
So let me give myself a
special variable called list.
That's going to be initialized to null.
And this is just my pointer, the square
on the left-hand side of the screen
that represents the start of the list.
And if it's null, it
means the list is empty.
So done.
I'm done implementing a
linked list of size zero.
Well, now, how do I
want to run this code?
Well, let me propose for
the sake of discussion
that this version of the program
will take command line arguments.
So I want to be able to
do something like this.
I want to run this program ultimately
and type in three command line
arguments like this, one, two, three.
And I want my program
in a couple of minutes
to allocate one, two, three nodes
and stitch them together just
like the visualization on the board.
I could use get int.
But it's just going to be faster
if we use command line arguments.
So again, I'm just borrowing
some concepts from week two.
But none of that's possible yet
until I change my code here.
So let's do this.
Int argc string argv.
But you know what?
We know that strings are not
actually a thing anymore.
So I can change my command line argument
definition to be what it really is.
It's really char star.
But it's the exact same
thing as in week two,
just strings are no more, at
least without the training wheels
on anymore like last week.
And now let me do this.
For int i equals one, i is
less than argc i plus, plus.
So what I'm doing with
this loop is I just
want to iterate over the
command line argument.
So I have one number at
a time from the prompt.
What else do I want to do here?
Well, let's go ahead,
and how about do this.
Let's get a number.
So int number equals argv bracket i.
So a couple of notes here.
One, I'm starting for loop
at one instead of zero.
But I'm going up to argc.
argc is argument count, how
many words are at the prompt.
Why am I starting at one instead
of zero though given my goal?
Why am I starting one?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Because [INAUDIBLE]
the first value [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So the first value in argv is
actually the name of the program.
That's obviously not a number.
So I want the second value.
So I'm going to start iterating over
those command line arguments at i
equals one.
So that's all.
I just want to get the
actual numbers at the prompt.
Unfortunately, argv, bracket
i, is a string, a.k.a.
char star.
That is not an int.
So this line of code won't work.
But can anyone think
back to week two where
we had a function for
converting strings to integers?
Anyone?
AUDIENCE: a to i
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So a to i is a function
that converts ASCII
to an integer assuming what you
give it as an argument looks
like a number like
one, or two, or three.
So let me fix this.
Let me actually do the conversion.
If I were really being careful,
I would error-check this,
make sure that there's no digits, just
like you might have in problem set two.
But for today's purposes, I'm
just going to assume the honor
system that the user, me, is going
to run the program correctly.
So now that I have a variable containing
the number from the command line,
let's just allocate a node for it.
So let me do node star n, just
like we did in the visualization.
And let's malloc enough space for
the size of one such node here.
I now need to just be super safe.
So if n equals equals null, like if
I'm out of memory, you know what?
Let me go ahead and just
immediately return one here.
Otherwise, if that's
not the case, let me
go ahead and update the number field
of this new node, which at line 24
does exist because it
did not return null.
So I did not exit early with return.
And let me just store whatever
number this human typed in first.
So the return value of a to i,
which per line 17 is in my variable
called number.
And then, let me go ahead and
just prepend this to the list.
Let me go ahead and say that this next
field first has a known value null,
just so that we get rid of
that second garbage value.
And let me go ahead and
now prepend it to the list.
So if I want to prepend it,
that means this new node
must have a next field that points
to the current beginning of the list.
And again, the goal here is
to prepend, prepend, prepend.
So whatever the current
list is, let's change it
so that this new node points
to that existing list.
And now, step two, as before,
was to update the actual list
to point at this node.
So recall in red on the screen
before, I screwed up originally.
And I only did this line by moving
the pointer too early, if you will.
But I fixed that once
Carter helped me rewind
and we got rid of the red
line, which indicated error.
And I just do n arrow next to change
the next field of this new node
to point to the existing list.
So I'm not orphaning anything.
At this point in the story, I think
my code is correct, not batting
very well though today.
But I think my code is correct.
But the program doesn't
do anything interesting.
So it would be nice to now iterate over
this linked list in memory whatever
its order is and print things out.
Well, how do we do that?
Well, it turns out if you want
to iterate over a linked list,
the general paradigm is
to do something like this.
To define a temporary
variable, I could call it temp.
But another convention
that you might as well see
is called pointer, ptr for short.
But you can call it anything you want.
And you can have a temporary
variable first point
at the first node in the list.
And then in some kind of
loop, like a while loop,
you point it at the
second node in the list.
And then you keep iterating.
You point it at the
last node in the list.
And then, eventually,
you iterate too far,
effectively pointing
at null, at which point
your while loop can
presumably terminate.
So how do I implement that idea of
allocating a temporary pointer that
just points at each node in the list
and lets me print out ultimately
each of those numbers?
Well, let's go back to my code here.
And let me do this.
Let me go ahead and declare
this temporary pointer,
which is going to be a node star also.
Why?
Because it's the address of a node.
The first, the second, the third.
And I'm going to set that equal to
whatever the beginning of the list is.
So that is going to be equivalent
to this version of the picture
here, where pointer is just temporarily
pointing at the first node in the list.
It's not pointing at list
per se, it's pointing
at the first node in the list, which
list is also pointing at itself.
Once I've done this, I
think I can translate
this to code that's a little new--
but it's conceptually familiar perhaps
now-- while that pointer
does not equal null.
So while I have a valid pointer,
like my finger or that arrow
is pointing at an actual node in memory,
well, let me go ahead and print it out.
So let me print out
with percent i backslash
n whatever is in the current
node at the number field within.
And again, this is going to
have the effect, hopefully,
of first printing the three.
And I think I just need to
now update the pointer so
that on the next iteration it's
pointing at the next value.
So if this is where
the story is, how do I
update pointer to point at the
second element of the list?
Well, I want pointer
to point at the two.
And I want pointer to
eventually point at the three.
Well, how do I do that?
Well, the way in code I can
follow these arrows is as follows.
If I currently have pointer
pointing at this node
but I want to point it at the next
node, I can borrow this pointer here.
So whatever this address is
in the first node, a.k.a.
the next field, I can
copy that into pointer.
Because then, pointer
will point at whatever
this is pointing at by just
setting one equal to the other.
So once I've done that, the
picture will become this.
And how do I translate that to code?
Well, new syntax is
surprisingly straightforward.
All I need do is say
pointer after printing
it equals whatever pointer currently
is, but grab its next field instead.
And this is a very common paradigm
when iterating over a linked list
and you're using some temporary
variable like pointer,
you can simply set pointer
equal to pointer next.
And what that means here is as follows.
If this is pointer pointing
from here down to here,
pointer next is follow the
arrow, grab the next field.
So if you set pointer
equal to this thing,
that's the same thing as
pointing this at this same box.
And indeed, if I advance
to the next slide,
even though the arrows
are technically pointing
at different parts of the rectangles,
that's just for graphic's sake,
pointer is now pointing
at the second node.
And when I do this again on my
next iteration, it points at this.
And then, this last step, notice, when I
keep doing pointer equals pointer next,
this will become eventually this value.
But what's this value
in this linked list?
It's null, technically.
So this arrow will
eventually take on this value
when I set pointer
equal to pointer next.
And at that point ptr, my temporary
pointer is going to be null.
So it might as well look
like this pictorially.
And what does that mean for my loop?
Once pointer is null, because you've
walked off the end of the linked list,
what's going to be true of this
loop here started in line 32?
Any observations here?
What's going to be true?
What will happen now as soon
as we hit the end of the list?
Yeah, sorry.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: The loop
is going to break out.
Why?
Because line 32, which
is constantly asking,
well, pointer does not equal null.
Well, if pointer finally
equals null three steps later,
the while loop is now done.
And so, what I can do at
the end of this program
once I printed out those values,
well, first let's go ahead
and open my terminal window.
Let's make list.
Compile dot slash list.
And let me try the same values,
one, and two, and three.
That's going to again allocate one node,
two node, three nodes by prepending,
prepending, prepending
each of those values.
And it's then going to iterate
over them from left to right.
And so, when I hit Enter now,
what should I see on the screen
if my code is correct?
What will I see?
Feel free to just call it out.
AUDIENCE: Three, two, one.
DAVID J. MALAN: Three, two, one,
because I've prepended presumably.
And here we go.
I indeed see three, two, one.
So the list is backwards.
But all of the elements are there.
Now, technically, if I
ran Valgrind on this,
Valgrind would not be happy because
I have never freed any of my memory.
So I should probably now
have a second loop here
that does something like this.
Let me again set pointer equal to list.
I don't need to redeclare
it because I've already
created this thing on line 31.
I just want to reset it to be
the beginning of the list again.
And now, I can do the
same kind of thing.
While prt not equals null,
go ahead and do this.
Well, I don't want to
just do free pointer
and then do pointer gets pointer next.
Why?
My goal is to free all of my memory.
But I think this is going
to get me in trouble.
Pointer equals list just gives
me a temporary pointer that
points at the three, and then
eventually the two, and then the one.
How?
Well, while pointer not equal
null, I'm freeing the pointer.
So this is like saying to malloc,
free that node, free that node, free
that node.
But what's the problem with
what I've just done here?
This code is technically buggy.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: After you free your pointer,
you have no [INAUDIBLE] what's next
[INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
After you call free on pointer,
you are by social contract
with C not allowed to
touch pointer anymore.
It is invalid.
Now it's still going to be a number.
It's still going to
be a pattern of bits.
But it's invalid.
And you'll very often get a segmentation
fault if you tempt fate in that way.
So I can't free the pointer and
then use it literally the next line.
The solution here, like our
swapping of the liquids last time,
was to maybe just have
a temporary variable.
So I can do a switcheroo.
And so, a common way to solve this
problem to get the order of operations
right would be to do
something like this.
Give yourself a temporary
pointer like node star next.
Set it equal to the place you want
to go next, so we're one step ahead.
Now you can free pointer.
And then you can update
pointer to be that next value.
So essentially, you need two hands now.
You create on line 41
another pointer that if this
is pointing at the
first node, the three,
your new pointer is pointing
at the two temporarily.
So now you can tell malloc
via free, release this memory.
But I haven't forgotten
where I want to go next.
And so, I can now continue on.
So a common paradigm for just
iterating over these nodes
and then freeing them, a
couple of observations.
Strictly speaking, I could
have consolidated this.
I don't need two loops to print
the nodes and then free the nodes.
I could do that all at once.
But let's assume that there's other
stuff of interest in my program
and I don't want to just
immediately free it.
There's one other bug that I
should probably address here.
There is still a potential
memory leak up here.
And this one is super subtle, though
Valgrind would help you find it.
Notice that in this loop here when
I'm calling malloc, this line of code
is fine if the first line
of malloc fails and returns
null because I immediately
return and I'm done.
But what if the second call-- but not
the first, or the third call, but not
the first or second fail?
This line of code has me
returning immediately.
You really need to do some
garbage collection, so to speak,
whereby you really need to go
in and free any nodes that you
did allocate successfully earlier.
Honestly, that's going
to be a pain in the neck.
We won't do that here.
But probably what I'd want to do is
write a function called free list
or something like that
and call that function
to free any nodes I
had previously created.
So it's not quite at the finish line.
But the building blocks are indeed here.
Questions on this code?
And I think it's safe for me to
promise that it won't escalate further
from that.
Questions on this?
No?
Well, let me show you one
alternative that you might prefer.
And I'm pretty sure this
isn't an escalation,
it's just an alternative formulation.
Another way you can iterate over
nodes in a list could be this.
Instead of a while
loop, for instance, let
me actually show you one
other piece of syntax here.
You could technically use a for loop.
You could give yourself a node pointer
here that is initialized to the list.
You can then check in your for
loop that it's not equal to null.
And then, you can do your
update as usual like this.
Either of these are equivalent.
Even though this one I
suspect looks scarier,
it's doing the exact same thing
in one line instead of two.
But there's no reason we can't use
for loops instead of while loops
to achieve the same idea.
But I'll leave these
two as demonstrations
of one approach or the other.
But that's just like in week
one, for loops, while loops,
whatever looks simpler to you.
Even though admittedly neither of
these probably looks super clean.
So let's take things back to
things more conceptual here.
Up until now, we've been inserting
elements into this linked list
by prepending them.
Let's consider what the running
time then is of these operations.
So if I've got a linked list of
size three or size n more generally,
time has passed and I've
added a lot of things
to it, what's going to be the running
time, for instance, of searching
a linked list for some value?
And I'll tell you
already, it's not log n.
Because again, binary search is
off the table as per before break.
So what might the running time be of
searching a linked list for some value,
like two, or three, or one, or 50?
What might the running time be?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: O of--
I heard it over here.
O of n.
And why?
Who was that?
Oh, in the middle here?
Who O of n?
AUDIENCE: Because you're [INAUDIBLE]
item in the list [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
You're going to have to go through
every [? item ?] in the list
starting from the left from the
beginning, which is how we've been
drawing things and connecting the dots.
And in the worst case, the element
might very well be at the very end.
So it's going to be big O of n.
What about insertion?
How many steps in
terms of big O notation
has it been taking me to
insert elements into the linked
list using this prepend design?
AUDIENCE: One.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So it's technically
constant time, big O of one.
And again, one is just
representative of any constant.
It could technically be
two steps, or three steps,
or even 10 steps, or 100 steps.
But if it's always
finite and fixed, then
indeed you can say it's in big O of one.
Now, why is that?
Well, again, no matter how
long this list gets, so long
as there's memory available for me
I can just create a little splice
at the beginning of the list to put in
the new node, update the original list,
and I'm on my way.
And it keeps getting longer even though
it might not be spread out in memory.
So big O of one is possible
with these linked lists
if I indeed prepend things.
Of course, if I prepend
things, everything's
going to get out of order potentially.
And we're going to have maybe the stack
property instead of a queue property.
So we might want to do
things slightly differently.
So instead of doing this,
whereby we kept prepending,
prepending, prepending, suppose we
append to the end of the list instead.
So if we now insert the
one, the two, and the three
as we might want to for a queue,
to maintain that fairness property,
we might start with an empty list.
We might add the one.
We might append the
two, append the three.
And so, it just is laid
out differently in memory.
And again, if I can come
to you in the middle,
what's the running
time of search, again,
when the linked list uses
this append implementation?
AUDIENCE: Still big O of n.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
Still big O of n.
Because in the worst case, you're going
to have to go through the whole list
just to find it.
And notice, it doesn't matter if you
have an intuition now that the bigger
numbers might very well be at the end.
You have no way to jump to the end.
You have no way to jump to the middle
or do anything resembling binary search.
Every search has to start from the left
and follow the arrows again and again.
So I don't think we've
done any better there.
And in fact, what is insertions
running time now in big O
when we're appending to
the list in this way,
as we might to implement a
queue instead of a stack?
What's the running time
of inserting a new value?
Big O of?
AUDIENCE: One.
DAVID J. MALAN: So not big O of
one in this case, but big O of n.
Because if I'm appending,
by definition I
have to start here and traverse the
whole thing looking for the end.
Now, this is a bit of an overstatement.
You could obviously
optimize this slightly
by maybe adding another variable that
always points to the last element, sort
of a cheat sheet or a shortcut that
gets you all the way to the end.
That's totally fine.
It's not-- it doesn't really
fit the traditional definition
of a singly linked list.
But there's absolutely smart engineering
solutions to these kinds of problems.
But as designed, it would
indeed be big O event
to insert to if you've got
to go all the way to the end
and you're not using a little extra
memory to get yourself there quickly.
Well, what if we want to take things
one last step and not just append
blindly, because even though
I inserted one, two, three,
if I inserted them in random order,
they would end up in random order.
What if you want to maintain a
sorted list from smallest to largest?
Well, then you might want
to insert numbers like this.
Starting from an empty
list, we might have a two,
then we might try inserting a one.
But we want to keep it sorted.
So now we're going to
prepend in our code.
But then you might
want to insert a four.
So you would append the
four because you're probably
going to look for the
right spot to insert it.
Then we're going to insert a three.
And this one is getting
a little annoying.
Because now you have to iterate over
the list, look for the right spot,
and then do a little
smarter of a splice.
But it's possible.
But you don't want to orphan
the four, for instance.
And then, ultimately, we
get back to this question.
What would the performance
be of your linked list
if you're trying to
maintain sorted order?
Well, search I think is going to be big
O of n for the same reasons as before.
What about insertion?
Big O of what for inserting
into a sorted linked list?
Yeah, in the worst case?
AUDIENCE: Big O of n
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It's still a big O of n.
So it's no worse than, but it's not
really any better than appending.
But we gain the additional property
of maintaining a sorted list, which
might very well be useful if you're
sorting your contacts in your phone
or something like that where it just
makes sense to maintain sorted order.
Now, in the code for online
today, if you take a look
at some of the final versions of
code, like list 6.c and list 5.c
as we'll post on the
website, you can actually
see code that will solve all three of
these problems, the prepend version
that we wrote live, the append
version which we talked through,
as well as this sorted order one.
But I think I'll avoid showing
it live just because I do
think that starts to escalate quickly.
But I think we have
enough of a building block
if we're comfortable with prepending to
at least solve some real-world problems
with these linked lists.
Questions then on linked lists which
we'll now leave behind on their own
but now use this technique to solve
fancier problems but much less code.
Questions on linked lists?
So to recap, we've taken a
sidestep with linked list.
We have this dynamism now where we can
grow and shrink our chunks of memory
without over-allocating or
accidentally under-allocating
as in the world of an array.
We don't have to worry about
copying values endlessly
because once you allocate the node, it
can just stay wherever it is in memory.
And you can just maintain--
you can just stitch it together somehow.
But unfortunately, we've sacrificed
what we started the class
with in week zero, which was binary
search, divide and conquer, which
was like gave us that log
and running time, which
was really compelling if you think back
to the demonstrations and the visuals.
Can we get the best of both worlds?
Can we get the speed of binary
search, something logarithmic,
but the dynamism of
something like a linked list?
Well, we can, actually,
I think, if we start
to think not in a single dimension,
just the x-axis, if you will,
but two dimensions, such
that our data structures
can maybe now have width
and height, if you will.
And so, a tree is perhaps
the right term here.
Much like a family tree, if you
have your elders up here in the tree
and then the branches below them
for their children and grandchildren
and the like.
That's actually what
a computer scientist
means when they talk about trees,
not a tree that grows up like this,
but really one that typically
is depicted growing down.
Although this is just an artist's
depiction no matter what.
But there are certain types of trees
in the world called binary search
trees that are structured on paper
and in visually like a family tree.
But they have a special
property that lends themselves
to exactly that feature binary search.
So for instance, here is an
array back from week two.
And I've sorted a whole bunch of
numbers herein from one to seven.
We know we can do binary
search on this structure
if it's implemented as an array.
But what feature do arrays, to be
clear, not have that linked lists do?
Today's kind of a seesaw.
What did we just gain by adding linked
lists that arrays do not allow Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
You can insert more elements
without having to copy
or moving everything else around.
Right now, in this single dimension, if
these values to the left and/or right
are already used, then you
have to move everything.
And that's where we
started today's story.
So arrays kind of paint
you into a corner.
Because you have to, by definition,
decide in advance how big they are.
Well, couldn't we have
some kind of array
that can still grow but
still is contiguous so we
can do binary search in some way?
Well, yes, if we rethink how
we implement binary search.
Let me propose that this, I've chosen
these seven elements in the array
much like the lockers from week two to
be ordered from smallest to largest.
I've highlighted now in yellow
the middle elements here.
And if we were telling the story of
week two going left or going right,
let me highlight in
red the middle elements
of the left half and the right half.
And then, let me further
highlight in green
the other elements in between those.
And there's actually a pattern
here, as you might notice.
Whereby there's one yellow
in the middle and then
there's the two red and the four green.
There's an implicit
structure there, if you will.
And what if I do start to
think in two dimensions,
and instead of laying out an array of
lockers like this on the x-axis only,
what if I slide the four up, and pull
the one, the three, the five down
and draw this in two dimensions instead?
Well, let me do that, as by
separating these things like this.
Such that, now, let me propose
that each of these squares
maybe it doesn't have to be contiguous.
It can be anywhere in
the computer's memory.
But I can't have these
crazy gaps among them.
How could I perhaps keep these
things connected conceptually?
What should I add to the
picture, if you will?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Branches?
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
AUDIENCE: Branches.
DAVID J. MALAN: So branches
metaphorically here.
And more technically in the
language of C, maybe just
some arrows, some pointers.
So I won't bother drawing
things as rectangles constantly.
Let me propose that we're now just
abstracting away what a node is.
But let me claim that each of
these squares now is a node.
And a node might have a number.
But it might also have a pointer.
Heck, maybe even two or more pointers.
And let me draw those now.
I don't care about addresses
like 0x123, 456, 789 anymore.
Let's just draw our
pointers with arrows.
But now, let me propose that
we could very well think
about this as a tree storing
what was previously array data.
But now, each of these nodes
can be anywhere in memory.
And moreover, even though
I've painted myself
into a corner visually
on the screen, so long
as there's more memory in the computer,
I could put the number zero over here.
I could put the number eight over here.
And if I'm smart, I
could probably, if I want
to insert other numbers, like
2.5 or 1.54 values in between,
I bet we could make room by
swiveling things around and just
hanging things off of these
branches slightly differently.
And so, what does this gain me?
Well, if I instead start to model
my data not single dimensionally
but in two dimensions,
and I connect those nodes
with these pointers, what can I now do?
I think I just gave
myself back binary search.
Why?
Suppose I'm searching
for the number five.
How do I find it?
Well just, like in a family
tree where you might visually
start reading from top
to bottom, I'm always
going to start from the so-called
root of a binary search tree.
This is just like the list pointer
that kicks off the whole linked list
process.
This is the so-called root.
Here I am at the number four.
I want to find the number five.
What decision can I make when I see
that I'm currently at the number four,
just like the phone book from week zero?
Where is five not?
It's not to the left.
And if I had built a little
mobile here or something
we could very dramatically snip
off this branch, this [LAUGHS]
is very low-budget animation.
These nodes could fall to the ground.
And we're left with half
of essentially, a tree.
But what do I now know?
It's obviously the five to the right.
So let me go to the right.
Six is obviously not
the one I'm looking for.
But what do I now know about the five?
Well, five is less than the six.
So I can snip this off here because I
know it's not going to be down there.
And I can follow the
remaining arrow here.
And voila, I just found it.
And now, without getting
into the weeds of the math,
I've got here what, seven elements.
That's roughly eight if I round up.
And if I do some log base two,
I actually-- one, two, three
is the key detail here.
The height of this tree is three.
Because I took a list of
size seven, and I halved it,
and I halved it in order to let
it dangle in these two dimensions,
plus or minus one for rounding sake.
So what do I get back?
I now have binary search.
But it's not like the middle
of the middle of the middle.
I now follow these arrows
in one of two directions.
So each of these nodes
now has an int and maybe
a left pointer and a right pointer.
But you can call them anything you want.
And so, I've gotten back
binary search and dynamism.
Because if you want to add
zero, or eight, or nine, or 10,
we can just dangle them at the
bottom of the binary search tree.
So what would this look like in code?
But we won't actually
implement it line by line.
Well, here was previously our definition
of a node for a linked list, which
was one-dimensional, if you will.
Even though it might bounce
up and down on the screen.
It was still just a line, if you will.
Well, let me get rid of the
single pointer in the linked list.
Let me make a little bit of
room here in this typedef.
And let me propose that we just
add two pointers, each of which
is a struct node star.
One will be called left by convention.
One will be called right by convention.
And so, long as someone, not
me, not today, not in class,
writes the code that stitches
together this data structure too,
handling both the left child
and the right child so to speak,
I think we can indeed stitch together
that two-dimensional structure.
And moreover, once you
have this in memory,
you can translate pretty elegantly
to code binary search itself
using a principle we
talked about recently too.
Here is, for instance,
a function that I'll
write by just clicking through steps
called search whose purpose in life
is to return a Boolean.
True or false, the number I'm
looking for is in the tree?
This search function
therefore takes two arguments,
the number I'm looking for
called number, and then
a pointer to the tree, the
so-called root of the tree.
Now, how can I implement
binary search in code?
Well, recall our brief
discussion of recursion.
It turns out recursion
is a beautiful technique.
And honestly, more
obvious technique when
you have two-dimensional structures,
which finally after five-plus weeks
we now do.
Here is maybe my first
line of code here.
If the tree is null, then
obviously return false.
You've handed me an empty tree.
There's nothing going on.
Obviously, the number you're
looking for is not going to be here.
So that's my safe base
case to make sure I don't
screw up and recursive infinitely.
Well, what else might be the case?
Well, if the number I'm looking for
is less than the tree's own number.
And now, recall that
tree is a node star.
So even though I'm
calling it a tree, it's
really the current node
that's been passed in.
So if the number I'm looking for is
less than the current node's number,
then I must know that the number
I'm looking for is to the left,
so to speak.
So how can I solve that?
Well, this is where
the magic of recursion.
Just return whatever the answer is to
calling search again but on a subtree,
if you will.
This is the equivalent of
snipping off half of the tree.
Pass in the left subtree, if
you will, with the same number.
Else, if the number
you're looking for isn't
less than the current node's
number but greater than,
snip off the other subtree instead.
And just return whatever search says
it finds in the right subtree here.
And then, there's a
fourth and final case.
What else could be true logically?
yeah.
AUDIENCE: Number equals
[INAUDIBLE] number?
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
If the number you're looking for
equals equals the number in this node,
then I'm just going to return true.
And you might recall from our
recurring discussions of design,
I don't strictly need
to ask that explicitly.
Either there's no node, it's
to the left, it's to the right,
or you found it.
So I can just whittle that
down as usual to an else.
And this now returns my true.
So here too, this is where recursion,
once you get comfy with it,
start it gets pretty elegant
and cool in the sense
that, wow, even though
there's a lot of lines here,
I mean, there's only a
few interesting lines.
A lot of it's curly
braces at that, which
strictly speaking I could get rid of.
And so, recursion lends
itself to elegance
when it comes to traversing
these two-dimensional data
structures as well.
So that is in code how you might
implement something like search.
Questions then on these trees?
We have dynamism.
We can insert more nodes to them.
They're faster because we
get better your search back.
But, but, but, there's
got to be a price paid.
Any downsides, or question, or downside?
AUDIENCE: Question.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, let me come
back to that and just one sec.
Downside though, what price
have we paid for this dynamism
and for this binary searchability?
Even though I've abstracted
it away in the picture?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Say again?
DAVID J. MALAN: We're
using a lot of memory.
I'm kind of misleading you now because
I'm just drawing these little squares
with the simple numbers.
But there's actually
three things in there.
A four-byte integer, an eight-byte left
pointer, an eight-byte right pointer.
So we're already up to 16, 20
bytes now to store individual INTs.
That's probably OK though
if memory is relatively
cheap and voluminous as it nowadays is.
But these are the kinds of trade-offs.
And here, too, you see a hint of
why some people still do like,
and you see-- and in
fact, it's so omnipresent.
Because when you have C
you can really fine-tune
how much memory is being used for
better or for worse under the hood.
As we transition soon to Python,
these decisions get made for you.
And you have much, much less
control about how much memory
is being used by your program because
someone else made the design decisions
for you.
Question.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Is it bad
if we don't the parent node?
Not necessarily.
There's no reason why you need to
have pointers in both directions.
However, that can lend
itself to efficiency.
By spending more space
and having arrows go up to
you can actually save more time when
searching the tree and other contexts.
This though would be the canonical
way, the typical way to implement it.
But absolutely, just like
a doubly linked list,
that could help you
solve other problems too.
So turns out I'm overselling
binary search trees.
There are perversions of them, so to
speak, whereby they won't actually
behave as advertised.
For instance, here's a good situation.
Suppose you've got an
empty tree initially.
And you insert the number two.
Well, it's got to go somewhere.
So it might as well become the
root of this binary search tree.
And let's assume that someone
wrote the code to do this.
Now you want to insert
the number one and you
want to maintain the
searchability of this tree.
Well, it's important to note that binary
search tree is different from tree.
If you've just got a
tree in memory, there
is no social contract with
where the numbers need to go.
They can be completely
random all over the place.
Binary search tree means that
you can do binary search,
means that any node here is going
to be greater than every node here
and less than every node here.
And that's a definition.
It's a recursive
structural definition that
must be true to be a
binary search tree or BST.
So if we maintain that property
ourselves, let me insert two,
let me insert one.
One belongs there by that definition.
Let me insert three.
Three belongs there by that definition.
But I kind of got lucky
in that I in the story
inserted two and then
one and then three.
Let me propose a sort of perversion
of the algorithm whereby we just
get unlucky let me propose
that we insert one first.
And then, we insert two.
Well, where does two go?
Well, logically, it goes to
the right because it's larger.
Now, the user inserts three.
Where does it go?
It goes there, logically.
And how does this story unfold?
The user inserts four, five, six.
It's wonderfully sorted
in advance by luck.
But this is a perversion of
the structure in what sense?
It's still technically
a binary search tree.
But what is it look more like?
It really is devolving, if
you will, into a linked list.
And so, if you, the programmer,
don't implement a binary search
tree with some kind of repairs going
on, such that as soon as something
gets, whoa, a little too long and
stringy, I think I can fix this.
It's going to be an annoying line-- a
number of lines of code, which we're
not going to write here or in a P-set.
But we could pivot this thing.
And we could just rejigger things so
that the two becomes the new root.
The one becomes the left child.
The three becomes the right child.
But that's what, two,
three-plus lines of code.
It's possible.
It's doable.
But it's extra work.
It's extra code.
So unless you write that code though
and maintain balance of these trees,
just because it's a binary search
tree does not mean its height is
going to be log base 2 of n.
The height could be n, in which
case you don't get those properties.
So when it comes to looking up in
a balanced binary search tree, yes,
it's log n.
But if it's unbalanced, if you don't add
that additional logic in those repairs
so to speak, it could
devolve into big O of n.
And this is a whole category
of algorithms and fanciness
that you would explore in a higher
level course on algorithms and data
structures.
There's lots of way to do that
sort of fixing that I'm alluding
to in the picture there on the screen.
A few other data
structures, if you will,
toward an end of a sort of
computer science Holy Grail.
So log n is repeatedly a
really good place to end up.
We started in week
zero and we got log n.
We lost it earlier today
by introducing linked list,
but we just got it back, albeit at
the price of spending more space.
But the Holy Grail, so to speak,
when it comes to algorithms
would not be big O of n, certainly.
Definitely not n squared like our
bubble sorts and selection sorts.
And not even big O of log n.
What's better than all of those?
Just big O of one, constant time.
That's the Holy Grail.
Because if we could store
huge amounts of data
but find it instantly in
one step, or two steps,
or heck, even 10 or 20 steps.
But independent of the size of the
data structure that's pretty powerful.
I mean, that's the secret sauce
of the Google's and the Twitters
of the world trying to get back
results really, really fast.
Well, it turns out another abstract
data type or abstract data structure
might be something called a dictionary.
Just like the Merriam-Webster
Oxford English
dictionaries that you might know which
associate, say, words with definitions.
Well, you can think of a dictionary
really abstractly as this.
Two columns maybe on
a spreadsheet of sorts
where the left column represents
something and the right column
represents something else.
The word is on the left and
its definition is on the right.
And that's almost literally
what a dictionary is on paper.
You've got all the words and all
the definitions right next to it.
But more generally, in
computing, a dictionary
really just has not
words and definitions
per se, but key value pairs.
This is a term of art.
And we're going to see this
again and again, especially as we
transition to web
programming, keys and values.
Key is what you use
to look for something.
The value is what you find
ultimately via that key.
So that's the generic term there.
We've seen key value
pairs really in the past.
In week zero we talked
about your contacts
and your iPhone or
Android phone being an app
that has a whole bunch of contacts
presumably alphabetized by first name,
or last name, or the like.
Well, one of those
contact cards ultimately
has someone's number, for instance,
like John Harvard in this case.
So in that type of
application, the keys is
the name, like John Harvard that
you use to find information.
And the value is the
number that you find there.
Or if there's more information
like where he lives
and email address and the
like, the whole contact card
could be the value thereof.
The key is what you use
to look up John Harvard.
Now, back in week zero--
oh, and rather, the corresponding table
then if we draw this in two columns
wouldn't be word and definition
or key value generically,
it would be name and
number, for instance.
So we're just slapping
some new terminology
on this old contacts problem.
Well, this is the picture we
drew way back in week zero,
whereby I claim that log of
n was really, really good.
And indeed it was and has been since.
But the Holy Grail would
indeed be something more
like this in this dashed
green line constant time.
And maybe not literally one step,
but a fixed number of steps that even
as the problem gets huge and you go
way, way out on the right of the x-axis,
the problem does not
depend on the size--
the time to solve the problem
does not depend at all
on the size of the problem itself.
You can have 1,000 contacts
or 100,000 contacts,
constant time means it takes the
same number of steps no matter what.
Well, how can we get to that point?
Well, there's a couple of
final building blocks today.
And there's one called hashing.
And this is something that
will recur a few times.
But for now, hashing is all
about taking as input some value
and outputting a
simpler version thereof.
So for instance, here's
a gratuitously large deck
of cards, which are all the more visible
as a result. And in a deck of cards,
typically you've got what, 52 cards
plus maybe the jokers and whatnot.
And each of those cards has a
number of sorts and a suit on it.
And here are literally
four buckets on the stage.
And how might I go about
sorting these cards?
Not just by number but also by suit.
Well, you could certainly spread them
all out and make a mess of things
and just reason your way through
it and get everything in order
according to suit and
according by number.
But most of us, even if you
don't have four buckets at home,
probably are going to do
something a little more intuitive,
feels like an optimization.
Where if I find the nine
of hearts, I'm going
to put that into the hearts bucket.
The king of spades, I'm going to
put that into the spades bucket.
The jack of diamonds over here.
And I'll do this with the queen of
diamonds, and the ace of clubs here,
and the three here, and the 10 here.
And even though it's still going to be
52 steps, why am I-- and maybe at home,
why would you perhaps
do this step first?
What's the value of bucketizing
the values in this way?
And that actually is a term of art.
What's the value of doing this first
before you sift through and try
to sort the numbers?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: It's easier to make
sure you're not [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
It's easier to make sure
you're not missing anything.
And it's taking a problem
of size 52 and shrinking it
into four problems of
size 13, if you will.
And so, that just helps
simplify things, maybe
reduces the probability
of errors and the like.
And what I'm doing here, to
give it a technical term,
is that I'm hashing the values.
I'm taking as input a card like this.
And I'm reducing it more
simply from a larger domain
to a much smaller range, if you will.
So here is a domain of 52 possibilities.
I want to map that to a range
of four possible outcomes--
the diamonds, the clubs, the
hearts, or the spades here.
And by doing that I'm just
shrinking the size of the problem.
So hashing does that.
It's literally an f
of x type arrangement
whereby you pass something in and
you get back a simpler known value.
Well, a hash function more technically
is the algorithm, or even the math,
or even the code that
implements that idea, converting
something bigger to something smaller
to this indeed finite range of values.
And it turns out that hash tables
are a wonderful application of arrays
and linked lists to try to
leverage the best of both worlds.
The goal being theoretically to achieve
that Holy Grail of constant time.
And that's going to be a
bit of an overstatement
because you're not always
going to achieve it exactly.
But at least we can get a
little closer there too.
So with hash tables, you have
something that looks like this.
This is just an array.
This is an artist's rendition of drawing
it vertically instead of horizontally.
But that's just a detail graphically.
And this array, for instance,
maybe is of size 26.
And where am I going with this?
Well, how does Apple, how does Google
store your context alphabetically
in your phone and search
for things quickly?
Well, they might-- they probably
alphabetize at least in English
according to A through Z. Or
if we convert that to numbers
it's like what, 65 through whatever.
Or really, zero through 25 suffices.
If we're using an array of size
26, we start counting at zero
and we count up to 25.
But let's abstract that away as
just letters of the alphabet.
So maybe what Google and
Apple are doing in your phone
is storing all of the A's up
there, all of the Z's down there,
and everything else in between.
And so, this works
pretty well if you start
adding your friends and your family.
So for instance-- and I'll get rid
of the letter so as to not distract.
Alvis might go in that first spot
because A, you subtract a 65,
maps to zero.
So we put him in the first
bucket, the A bucket.
Maybe Zacharias ends up all
the way at the end there.
And then in the middle
might here be Hermione.
And if we do this dot, dot, dot, you
keep adding all of your classmates,
you might get a contacts database
that has all of this data herein.
Now, each of these nodes,
they're drawn differently
because this is just
another artist rendition.
These rectangles, these long
rectangles represent a contact card,
like John Harvard's that's got the
name, maybe email, definitely phone
number, and things like that.
So this seems great.
Why?
How can I find Alvis?
Well, I go to the A bucket.
How do I find Zacharias?
I go to the Z bucket.
How do I find Hermione?
I go to the H bucket.
But, but, but, I've done
this very deliberately.
What problem will arise eventually
assuming you have enough classmates?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
There'll be too many people,
too many contacts for all
of the available spaces in the array.
There's still some room here.
But I'm pretty sure if I think
back to this particular class,
we've got not Hermione but also
Harry, who's also an H. Hagrid, who's
also an H. So where do put them?
I could just put them arbitrarily
in any of the open spots.
But then you lose the immediacy of
jumping right to the H, right to the A,
right to the Z.
But now that we have linked
lists, we can combine these ideas.
Use an array to get to the first
letter of the name you care about.
And then if you have a collision, so to
speak, whereby someone's already there,
you don't do something
stupid like put Harry
down here just because it's
available, or maybe Hagrid down here
just because it's available
because then you're
losing the immediacy of the lookup.
Why don't you just stitch
them together in a link list?
Now what does this mean.
This means for most of the characters
here, you have constant time lookup.
You look up Alvis, boom, you're done.
Zacharias, boom, you're done.
OK, Harry, Hermione, Hagrid, it
might be one, two, or three steps.
So that's actually devolving
into something linear.
But here we make a distinction today
between theoretical running times,
which we keep talking about, and
honestly, a clock on the wall
running times that
actual humans care about.
This is way faster than
a linked list because you
don't have to search every name.
It's even faster than an array because
you don't need to do binary search.
You can literally, for most of the
names, find them in constant time--
one step.
And again, it's not theoretically
constant because these--
if you only befriend
people who have H names,
it's going to be a crazy
long linked list anyway.
So again, it really depends on what
the nature of the data is here.
But this is pretty
close to constant time.
And in fact, how could
we get even closer?
How could we reduce the
probability of collisions
for the H's or any other letters?
How could we avoid putting
too many H names together?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Say a little louder.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, yeah.
So we could add another
dimension, if you will.
But let's not add a
third dimension, per se.
But let's indeed look at not just
the first letter of everyone's name
but the first and the second.
And in fact, let's see if that
gets us a little further along.
So let me go ahead and propose, if
you go through the whole Harry Potter
universe, there's actually a lot
of collisions if we keep going.
And so, we've got the L's here,
the R's, the S's, and so forth.
Well, let's clean this up here.
Hermione originally
went to the H location.
But let's decrease the probability of
collisions there and everywhere else.
Instead of putting Hermione,
Harry, and Hagrid all together,
let's go ahead and do this instead.
Instead of labeling these
buckets A through Z,
let's give ourselves more buckets.
So in fact, this might be H. Well,
instead of H, maybe this should be HA,
and then this should
be HB, HC, HD, HE, HF.
Now, some of those are
a little nonsensical
because I can't think of names
that match most of those.
But it's deterministic.
At least we know the
bucket will be there,
which is important even if it's empty.
And now, we can put Hermione here.
We can put Harry here.
But oh-oh.
We didn't do this perfectly well.
Hagrid still collide.
So let me come back to you.
How can we reduce the probability
of Harry and Hagrid colliding?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] another letter?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So we can look at the third letter.
So let me try that.
Instead of HA, let's look at HAA, HAB,
HAC, dot, dot, dot, HAQ, dot, dot, dot,
HEQ, HER, HES, and so forth.
And now, I think those names and
probably all of the others we saw
are now much more cleanly distributed.
There is much lower
probability of collisions
unless two people have almost the same
names or one is a prefix of the other.
But, but, but, even though we're now
closer than ever to constant time
because the odds that we hit a collision
and have to devolve to a linked list
are much lower, what's
the downside that's
not completely obvious from how
I've depicted this on screen?
What's the price I'm paying here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So much memory.
DAVID J. MALAN: This is
a huge amount of memory.
The number of cells here in the
array is now what, 26 times 26 times
26 for the first, the second,
and the third possible characters
all combinatorically combined here.
That's a lot.
I didn't even draw them.
I have the dot, dot, dot.
[? Could you ?] evoke that instead?
That's a huge amount of memory.
This is a very sparse data set now.
And odds are, you're going
to waste so much memory,
even for the names like HAE, HA, HEQ.
I can't even think of names.
So many of those buckets
are going to be empty,
not to mention the AAA and the ZZZ
and everything else in between.
So it's a trade-off.
And it might be too
expensive a trade-off.
And so, you might have
to tolerate something
like the collisions we had earlier,
whereby even though they might
very well happen, at least you are
decreasing the probability by perhaps
having more buckets like this.
And in fact, if I rewind now to
where we might have gone with this,
here's how we might represent
these nodes in the tree.
Previously, in the
past, we've had a person
who had a string name and a string
number, a.k.a. now char star.
And so, here now might
be how in this hash table
we represent someone's name
and number as well as a pointer
to the next element in the list.
Let me rewind just to the picture here.
We keep drawing different shapes,
because, again, these are abstractions.
Who really cares if
they're at a scale now.
We've got enough room for the
person's name, not pictured
on the screen it's Hermione's number.
But that's somewhere in this rectangle.
But yes, pictured here
in this little square
is a pointer to the
next node in the list.
So by storing name and number, maybe
her address, maybe her mailing address,
whatever, in addition to a
pointer allows each of these nodes
to be connectable just like
the nodes in the linked list.
But where they're
starting is in an array.
So the array gets us 126--
or gets us-- narrows the
problem from size 26 to one,
gets us to the linked list in question.
Hopefully, it's a single person
or perhaps it has more than that.
Meanwhile, what is the
hash table itself--
the hash table, the whole thing
is literally just an array.
I've hardcoded the
simplest version of size 26
but what do each of those
boxes in the vertical array
represent just a pointer to potentially
a node, a node in a linked list.
And if there's no one there, if
there's no one in location y,
or x, or the like in
that universe, well, it's
just a null pointer signifying
there's no one there.
But if there is, it's going to be a
pointer to a valid node from which we
can get to any of the others as well.
And that so-called hash
function, just like the one
I did with the greeting
cards, well, it's
just a black box, if you will,
but implemented somewhere in code,
like in C. And so, if you pass in
Albus, what is the hash value of Albus?
Well, in the first version of the story
with 26 buckets, it should be a zero.
If you pass in Zacharias,
it should be 25.
And so, just as my cards were being
hashed to one of one, two, three,
four values, now these names are being
hashed to one of 26 possibilities,
or 26 times 26, or 26 to the third power
if you have more and more granularity
than that.
Questions on this implementation
now of this idea of a hash table?
AUDIENCE: Should we [INAUDIBLE] the
value of null and then [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID J. MALAN: If you--
say that again with the null?
AUDIENCE: Could you ever be [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, a good question.
So if there's so much
sparseness, there's
all of these empty cells in the array.
Couldn't you just go in and free
them, or delete them, or just
shrink the array and not have
AAA, and AAB, and AAC only
have the prefixes, two
or three characters
that you need, you
absolutely could do that.
But now, what you lose is the
arithmetic benefit of being
able to map each letter to a number
if you start freeing up unused space,
you don't know that Zacharias
is necessarily at location 25.
Albus is still going
to be at location zero.
But if you've deleted some of
the elements in the middle,
Zacharias could be at 24
if you've deleted one,
23 if you've deleted another.
And so, you don't have
that arithmetic immediacy
that you need in order to index
into the array with constant time.
And the same is going to be true if
it's two letters or three letters.
You need to be able to trust
that you can do some quick math
and jump to the right
index in constant time.
And that's, again, the
appeal of these arrays.
So when it comes to the running time of
a hash table, inserting values into it,
searching for values therein,
at the end of the day,
it technically is big O of n.
Because in the craziest case, you
might have a huge fancy hash table.
But everyone in the universe
has a name starting with H.
And then, it just evolves
into a really long linked list
just like a binary search
tree could do the same.
But if you choose a smarter hash
function, maybe you mitigate that
and you don't rely only
on the first letter
but on the second, or the third as well,
or some other combination of that input
and make your hash
function smarter, odds
are if you get a good hash function you
want to get it to be more of order of n
divided by k, where k means
constant mathematically.
And so, k is the number of buckets.
So ideally you want a
uniform distribution.
You want this many people
here, this many people here.
You don't want there to
be some or no people.
You want a uniform
statistical distribution.
And maybe you get that from
human names, maybe you don't.
But that's the challenge
of a hash function.
Of course, big O of n
over k is not a thing
because we always throw
away constants like k.
So it's still big O of n.
But again, the distinction
today is that, OK, yes,
academically you learned in CS50
that, sure, it's big O of n.
But my God, it's 26 times faster
if you do the hash function well
and you spread everyone
out over the hash table.
And that's the appeal of
these kinds of structures.
And we've got one more
for you, if I may.
And that's something now known as a try.
So it turns out that
a try is even cooler,
if you like this kind of thing, in that
it does not devolve into big O of n.
It is truly constant time.
But there's going to be a price.
There's going to be a gotcha.
A tri is sort of a fancier tree.
And it's short for
retrieval, but pronounced tri
for weird historical reasons.
But a tri is a tree, each
of whose nodes is an array.
So this is all crazy mash-ups now.
People started inventing data structures
just by combining different ones.
So unfortunately, a lot of
the good ideas are taken.
But you just have benefits from certain
aspects of those data structures.
And combining them, ideally, gives you
the best of both worlds, so to speak.
So here might be the root of a tri.
It's literally a big
node, a big rectangle.
But it's actually an array.
So there's 26 locations
in this picture here.
And here's how you use a tri,
for instance, the store names
just like the hash table.
You treat each of the elements
of that array in that node
as a letter of the alphabet.
So A through Z or zero through 25.
And if you want to store someone's
name in here, you do so as follows.
If you want to store an H,
you index into the H location.
And if you want to store the second
letter of someone's name, like an A,
well, you add another node below it.
And such.
One is connected to the other.
And you then identify
the A in that array.
And then you go on and maybe put a G
if the goal is to store-- spoiler now--
Hagrid in this data structure.
And then the R, and
the I, and then the D.
But when you get to the
D, the end of the name,
you have to somehow flag that
this is the end of a name
that we've embedded into
this data structure.
So whereas all of these are
called out in white just
to make it obvious what
we're connecting to what,
green has to be like a
bool that's true that
just indicates the buck stops here.
D is the last letter in
someone's actual name.
And what's kind of
cool now about a tri is
that we can repeat this
for other names as well.
So for instance, here's where
we might put Harry as well.
And notice, they share a common
prefix, HA for Hagrid, HA for Harry.
So we're reusing some of these
nodes, some of these arrays.
We can even slip Hermione in
here too borrowing only the H.
But she gets the H, then the E, then R--
R-M-I-O-N-E, and so forth.
And we mark at the end of her
name too that she's in there.
Now, what's the takeaway here?
Well what is the running time of a tri?
How many steps does it take to find
someone in this data structure?
And let me zoom out so that it
suddenly becomes a massive data
structure with even more in it.
Maybe it looks-- sorry.
No, I'll keep it on this one.
Maybe it looks a little something
like this with just these three names.
But how many steps does it take to
find Hagrid, or Harry, or Hermione,
no matter how many names
are in this data structure?
There's three at the moment.
But it takes what?
H-A-G-R-I-D, so six
steps to find Hagrid.
H-A-R-R-Y, five steps to find Harry.
H-E-R-M-I-O-N-E, eight
steps to find Hermione.
But notice, that those steps
are only dependent on what
the lengths of the humans names.
And let's assume that no one's going
to have a infinitely long name.
It's going to max out at what, eight?
No, maybe 18, maybe 20, 30.
There's actually some pretty
long human names out there.
But it's going to be finite.
You know it's a bounded.
Whereas most contexts
in could grow forever.
So what's compelling here is if you
assume that the longest name is,
I don't know, 50 for the
sake of a theme here,
then you know that finding
anyone in this data structure
will take more than 50 steps.
50 is thus a constant, which means
you have big O of one running time.
It doesn't matter if there's a
million people in this phonebook
or a billion people in this phonebook.
That's going to definitely
add more nodes to it.
But it's still going to take you H-A-R--
I'm sorry-- H-A-G-R-I-D,
six steps to find Hagrid.
H-A-R-R-Y, five steps to find Harry
even if there is a billion other people
in that data structure.
So now, we actually do
seem to have constant time
if you assume that there's going to
be a bound on the length of the name.
Why don't we use tries
for everything then?
What's the price we're paying
for this data structure
even though we've represented
just three characters here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: It's a lot of memory.
Yeah.
And you can see it even
with these three names, most
of the squares on the screen are
empty, bytes and bits that are there
and are allocated.
And they need to be
there because you need
to be able to do that arithmetic thing
of this being zero, this being 25.
So you can jump from boom, boom, boom,
boom, based on each of the letters.
But it's a hugely sparse
data structure, which means
it takes up a crazy amount of memory.
Now, maybe that's tolerable,
especially for short names.
But that's going to be
the trade-off as well.
And this is such a tension in computing.
Almost any time you
want to improve time,
you want to speed up the efficiency,
the speed of your algorithm,
you're going to spend space.
If by contrast you want to
decrease the amount of space,
you might very well have to
increase the running time.
And it is indeed, this
seesaw back and forth.
And you, your colleagues,
your company need
to decide what resource
is the most precious.
Heck, it might be much harder to
code one of these data structures
than another.
You're a human.
Your time is valuable.
Do you really want to spend
hours implementing a tri when,
hey, in 30 minutes I can bang out an
array nowadays or a linked list even.
There too, development time is going
to be yet another resource and why
sometimes there's good code or bad code,
it depends on what you're prioritizing.
So what do each of these
nodes look like in a tri?
Well, we can keep calling it a node.
This is a very generic term for just
a container in these data structures.
In this story though, let me claim that
everyone has a number, like a phone
number, a string, a.k.a char star.
Every node has 26 children, or
technically an array of size 26
that can point to more of these nodes.
Notice that I don't need to store
the name of someone in a try
because it's implicit in the
path that you take to find them.
So that's a minor optimization.
But it saves us some space.
But this would be just a
different data structure
we could use to actually
solve this problem as well,
albeit at a very expensive cost.
And what do we need our variable
to be that stores the try?
Just like before, we just
need a single pointer
that hangs on to the root
of this structure that's
null if it's empty or non-null if
it's actually pointing at something.
Any questions then on tries?
And if it's feeling like a
lot, the fire hydrant, it is.
We started with arrays, then
linked list, then tries.
But questions on how we've just
assembled from these basic building
blocks?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Why isn't the
root of tri [INAUDIBLE]??
Why does that matter?
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
Why is this not size 26?
It's just like with the
linked list before, it just
tends to be in code convenient to have
a separate additional pointer that's
small that just points to the
beginning of the data structure.
Because that way, it can be
null, thereby clearly indicating
there are no nodes.
The whole structure is empty.
If you allocated one of those
nodes, you absolutely could.
But then you'd be just wasting
space, even if it's empty.
And it creates an ambiguity.
So just having a single pointer
linked to the beginnings
of all of these things is a good thing.
Other questions now on tries, or
trees, or hash tables, or arrays?
So what problems might arise?
Well, here's a counterexample.
What names are manifest
in this tri here?
Feel free to just call it out.
What do you see?
AUDIENCE: Danielle.
DAVID J. MALAN: Danielle and Daniel.
So presumably, if these are
two names here, one of which
is a prefix of another, notice that
the data structure still works.
And I chose a friend's name and then
appended a couple of more characters
to it that's also a name because
we have here D-A-N-I-E-L.
And the green technically is implemented
as a bool or something like that
that indicates a word stops here.
But we don't want to preclude
storing Danielle as well, who's
a superstring, if you will, of Daniel.
And so, that's OK too, so long as
the structure allows for the pointers
to keep going.
So even that works out OK whereas
it might not have otherwise.
And in terms of the running time, just
to be clear, at the end of the day,
tries do give you actual constant time
for insertions, lookups, deletions,
and the like because it's dependent only
on the length of the input, the key,
if you will, and not on how many other
people are in your phone or address
book.
And I thought we'd
conclude with a visual.
If you've gotten out into the
square, anyone recognize this?
Sweet Green, a local salad place.
What are we looking at here and
what's its connection to today?
You're about to become all
the geekier in the real world
because you will start to see
data structures everywhere.
What is this?
Or how does this work
maybe in salad form?
Who's been to Sweet Green.
Either of you.
So how does this work?
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] They'll
put your order [INAUDIBLE]
your name [INAUDIBLE] L.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, good.
So if you order a salad for
someone named L, when it's ready,
they put it in the L section here.
And so, this is a set of
key value pairs, right?
If L is the first letter of someone's
name, the value hopefully is the salad.
And so, what you kind of have here
is a dictionary, key value pairs,
where it's not words and definitions.
It's names and salads.
And you can think of this
too as kind of a hash table.
Why?
Even though it actually
doesn't fit on one long shelf
because the store is only so
big, this is really an array.
And apparently, A is missing or
maybe it's around the corner.
But this array just happens
to wrap onto multiple lines.
But it's still conceptually
a single dimension.
But suppose two people have the name L?
What do they do typically?
AUDIENCE: They just put the one
[INAUDIBLE] second letter [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So maybe they-- if they want to
put that much effort into it.
They might look at the second
letter and then the third letter.
Odds are this is not that interesting a
problem to solve optimally in that way.
But they probably do start stacking
the salads on top of each other
or maybe scooching it
over just a little bit.
And so, what do you have there?
Well, now, if you start to view
the lens through CS50 glasses,
OK, you have an array.
And then you have these linked
lists that are sort of growing here.
But even then you run into a problem.
Why?
Because it's not really a linked list.
Because at some point you're
going to hit the boundary here.
So it's kind of like an array of
arrays because you can only fit,
what, three or four salads here.
And so, long story
short, we started today
deliberately talking about real-world
things like stacks and queues.
And even though it did escalate
quickly into binary search trees,
and hash tables, and tries, even
those things are everywhere.
Even though they don't
call them as such,
these are just solutions to problems.
And now, with this final
week of C under your belt,
you have all the more
of a technical toolkit
by which to implement
these things in code.
Next week we'll be able to trust that
someone else solved all these problems.
We'll introduce Python.
And lines of code like this will
finally become lines of code like that.
So that's the promise ahead.
And we'll see you next time.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]