[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
And this is week four.
And if you think back a few
weeks ago already, in week zero,
we started talking
about what images are,
and we talked about representation
of images as this grid of pixels.
And each pixel has some pattern
of bits that defines its color.
Well, it turns out today, we'll take
a deeper look underneath the hood
at how things like
images, and so much more,
is actually implemented using
just these zeros and ones,
and how now as a
programmer, you can actually
harness that, for better or for
worse, to better understand and better
manipulate what's going on
inside of a computer's memory
using a language like C.
In fact, even this bowl of stress
balls that we keep happening
is just a photograph of course.
But if you think back to week zero,
if you sort of enhance, enhance,
enhance this image, like
they do in the movies,
it actually doesn't work out the
way you would think from Hollywood.
As I keep continue to zoom in, and zoom
in, and zoom in on a screen like this,
you'll see that yes, it gets bigger.
But if it gets too big,
what do you start to notice?
The so-called pixelation.
And indeed, you can see
the individual dots.
So next time you watch
some show or movie on TV
that has this sort of
notion of enhancing,
there's actually a finite limit there.
You can only enhance so far as
there's actually information there.
But once you zoom in to a certain level
like this, that's all that's there.
You're not going to see the glint
of the suspect in some crime
drama in their eye just because
you've enhanced the image.
There's only a finite amount
of information actually there.
But we'll see today too
that by understanding
what's going on inside
of a computer's memory
we can start to represent
and even create and code
more interesting things.
So for instance, here is a bitmap,
if you will, which is a term of art.
A bitmap is a type of image.
And it's a map of bits
in the sense that you
have this coordinate system
of a top, down, left,
right at least in this
artist's representation here.
And suppose that maybe we
all decide as the world
that one shall represent
the color white and zero
shall represent the color black.
What might this map of bits,
this bitmap, actually be?
Can you see through it?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: It is
indeed a smiley face.
So an amazing eye.
If I actually turn all of the ones
to white just to visualize this,
you'll see indeed, this is
what was embedded there.
But of course, on our
computer monitors and phones,
we have this grid of
squares, this grid of pixels.
So indeed, if you were to
actually see on your screen
a smiley face, like a black and white
one at that, what's probably going on
underneath the hood is just
some pattern of zeros and ones,
and maybe single bits, one
bit color, if you will,
where one here represents white
and zero represents black.
So if you kind of like
this thing, it turns out
you can do pretty beautiful, pretty
interesting, pretty artistically
inclined things.
If you go to this URL at
your leisure, cs50.ly.art,
it'll actually redirect you to a Google
spreadsheet that we've made in advance.
And we've kind of shrunk
the rows and columns
to resemble a grid of pixels,
tiny little squares, all of which
are white by default, not
unlike this easel here
that we have a couple of
volunteers working away at.
In fact, would you guys like
to come forward for a moment
and say a quick hello
before we come back to you?
DANIEL: Hello.
My name is Daniel.
I'm from Chicago.
DAVID J. MALAN: Welcome to Daniel.
And--
ADAM: Hi, everyone.
I'm Adam.
And I'm from Trinidad and Tobago.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
Well, welcome to you both.
Thank you.
You'll see that in
their hands are actually
a whole bunch of pixels, post-it notes
that we've handed them in advance.
So if you don't mind, we'll come
back to you in a couple of minutes
and see what they've created, if you
will, on this grid of white paper
much like you could create
on this Google spreadsheet.
In fact, feel free to send us your
creations if so inclined via the URL
you'll get at cs50.ly/art.
Now let's come back to week zero
where we define some of the building
blocks for images.
We talked about RGB, which
is just red, green, blue.
And it just one of the
systems, a popular system,
via which you can represent
any color of the rainbow
using some combination of
red, and green, and blue.
And if any of you are
artistically inclined
or have used Photoshop
or similar programs,
you might typically have
some means of selecting
a color via some grid like this.
But down here, notice
there's explicit mentions
of the types of color systems in use.
RGB.
And in fact, here, you
see zero, zero, zero.
And up here under New,
you see the color black.
And that implies that if you have
no red, no green, no blue, well,
that indeed would represent
by convention the color black.
By contrast, if we play around with
Photoshop or any similar program,
if you have a lot of red, a lot
of green, and a lot of blue,
for instance, 255, 255, 255, really
crank it up to the max value,
you can represent with 8 bits per
week zero, well then it turns out
you get the color white here.
And we can play with
these numbers endlessly.
For instance, if we use 255 of
red, but zero green and zero blue,
not surprisingly, the square at the
top of the screen becomes of course red
entirely because it's all
red and no green, no blue.
If we change it instead to 255 for green
but zero for red and blue, of course,
we get green.
And then lastly, if we crank up the
blue but leave red and green as zero,
we of course get blue.
But all this while,
down here highlighted
is something that maybe some
of you have seen before,
like some combination
of numbers and letters.
If any of you have made personal web
pages or used programs like Photoshop,
you might have used these
so-called color codes.
So indeed, the world has this convention
whereby using six digits, or sometimes
three, you can represent a little
more succinctly some amount of red,
green, blue.
And you'll see here, maybe by
inference, that if RGB is zero,
zero, 255 respectively, perhaps
where we're going with this
is that zero, zero, zero, zero, FF is
just an alternative way of expressing
the exact same idea.
No red, no green, and a lot of blue.
But why is that?
And in fact, we'll come full circle
here to introducing something
that we could have done in week
zero, but it doesn't really
solve a problem then.
But today, as we focus more on
images and on memory itself,
turns out understanding these
patterns is pretty useful.
So back in week zero, we
talked, of course, about binary.
And binary by implying two, only
gives you two digits, zero and one.
You and I as humans almost
always use the decimal system
in normal conversation, dec meaning 10.
So we have zero through nine instead.
If a human like us wants to count
up as high as 10, or 11, or 12,
we don't have a digit per
se for 10, 11, and 12.
We start reusing digits.
So it's one zero, one one,
one two, and so forth.
But in other systems,
not binary, not decimal,
but systems called
hexadecimal, hex implying 16,
there are actually more digits than
these which might come as a surprise.
It's not pairs of digits, like
in decimal, single digits.
And frankly, it doesn't really
matter what the digits are.
Because at the end of
the day, these are just
symbols that you and I immediately
associate with some notion of math,
but just strokes on the
screen that represent some--
represent some actual value.
So it turns out that by convention,
when you want more than nine--
10 digits, zero through
nine, you start using
letters of the English
alphabet, A, B, C, D, E, and F.
And you can represent them in lowercase.
It's case insensitive.
So it doesn't really matter.
You might see it in
uppercase or lowercase.
But this is how you can
count beyond nine not
using decimal but using Indeed
something called hexadecimal.
If we get really technical,
this is also known as base-16.
And it's the same idea
as week zero where
instead of using base two for
binary, base-10 for decimal,
you use 16 as the base for hexadecimal.
And so if we run through just
some simple examples here
in the world of hexadecimal, your
columns are just powers of 16.
16 to the 0, 16 to the 1,
16 to the 2, and so forth.
But in the world of hex, we usually,
at least thus far, and today, we'll
see just pairs of digits like this.
So here, for instance, is the
ones column, and the 16's column
if we multiply that out.
So if you wanted to
represent the number you
and I know in the real world
as zero in hexadecimal,
it would just be zero, zero.
If you want to represent the
number one, it would be zero one.
And from there, we get zero two, zero
three, zero four, zero five, zero six,
zero seven, zero eight, zero nine, now
things get potentially interesting.
In decimal, it would
obviously become 10.
But in hexadecimal, it just
becomes zero a then zero
b, which is to say, if
I rewind, after nine
comes in hexadecimal, if
I pronounce it in decimal,
this is how you'd represent 10.
This is how you'd represent 11, 12,
13, 14, and then lastly in hexadecimal,
the 16th value is F, which is
just always going to represent 15.
So where-- how do we connect
this to some of the past math?
Well, once you get to
zero F, in hexadecimal,
if F is the highest you can
count, just like in decimal,
nine is the highest you
can count, what comes next?
If this is 15 I claim, how do
I represent 16 in hexadecimal,
with what pattern of symbols?
What pattern of symbols for hexadecimal?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: One zero.
DAVID J. MALAN: So one zero, not
10, even though you might read it
like that as a typical human.
But one zero.
Because why?
Well, even if this is
completely new to you,
the whole column system, the places,
are exactly the same intuitively.
So you need one in the 16's place
and a zero in the ones place.
And we won't count
all the way up to 255,
but we count if we
count a little higher,
this would be one zero, AKA 16 in
decimal, this would be one one,
AKA 17 in decimal, and then 18, 19,
20, and so forth, dot, dot, dot.
And we can count all the way up to FF.
Because if F is the biggest
digit in hexadecimal,
FF is indeed as high as we can count.
And if each F represents 15, well, let's
just do the math like in week zero.
So 16 times f plus 1 times f is how all
of us learn to do math in grade school,
even though not in hexadecimal.
That's of course 16
times 15 plus 1 times 15.
Multiply that out, you get 240, plus 15.
And ergo, you can count as high as
255 using two hexadecimal digits.
Now this is not the
kind of thing where this
is going to be an interesting exercise
mentally to ever convert in your head.
Generally, you'll get used to
the fact that after nine comes
A and the biggest digit
is F. And you'll just
start to see patterns like
this in the world of Photoshop,
web pages in a few weeks, and beyond.
But why is hexadecimal useful?
Why are we complicating
the world and adding
on top of decimals something else?
Well, it turns out that a
single decimal digit, like F,
the biggest one for instance, is 15.
And here, let me just
propose a bit of mental math.
How many bits do you need to
represent the number 15 in binary?
If you've got the ones place,
twos place, 4s and so forth,
how many bits total?
AUDIENCE: Five.
DAVID J. MALAN: So fewer than five
to count as high as 15 I think.
But close.
Someone else?
I'm seeing a hand.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Four.
DAVID J. MALAN: So four
bits I think suffice.
Because if you want to count as
high as F, that is to say 15,
I think if you have four
bits, you can do that.
Because if over here is the ones
place from week zero for binary,
this is the twos place, this is the
fours placed, this is the eights place.
Do up some quick math.
So 8 plus 4 is 12, plus
2 is 14, plus 1 is 15.
So it turns out that by
convenience, hexadecimal digits
can just be represented consistently
with four bits or fewer.
But four.
And four, of course, is half of eight.
And eight is everywhere, like 8
bits is a byte, which is, again,
just a convention we've seen.
And so the reason that you see
hexadecimal in the world of Photoshop,
and eventually web pages,
is it actually just maps
really nicely to expressing
binary numbers more
succinctly with a
fixed number of digits.
So for instance, any time you see
11111111 in the world as binary,
you know what?
That's a little tedious
to both say and write.
You can represent more succinctly any
group of four 1 bits more succinctly
in hexadecimal as just F. So 11111111
in binary more succinctly and more
commonly now in the world of
Photoshop, memory, images, and the like
is represented more succinctly as FF.
And that's why because it just
maps really nicely to 4 bits.
And so we can be a little more succinct.
So any questions on
hexadecimal, which is just
another way of representing information
but using the same grade school
approach?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So--
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
If you represent 15 with
F, it would use 4 bits.
So base systems are really just a way
for us humans on paper or on screens
to represent information.
If F represents the decimal number
15, the computer underneath the hood
has to use 4 bits to represent it.
So one hexadecimal digit
by convention always
implies 4 bits underneath the hood.
So therefore, if you have
two hexadecimal digits,
like zero, zero, that means eight
zero bits underneath the hood
like for red or for green.
If you see FF, now we know that's
4 one bits and another 4 one bits.
And if we do out the math, that's 255.
That's why in Photoshop, 0000FF means
no red, no green, and 255 of blue.
And it's just way more succinct
than writing out what, 8 plus 8,
plus 8, 24 zeros and ones.
And it's just cleaner
than even using decimal
when you're using units of eight, which
again computers just use everywhere.
So it's just another system.
It's not one you need
to dwell on very much.
But again, it's fundamentally no
different from binary or decimal.
We're just using a
slightly different base.
Now all right.
Well, we had this blank canvas here.
And I think, are you two
perhaps ready to reveal
for the world what you've created?
Do you want to go ahead and--
I'll swivel it around for you.
All right.
Here we go.
Big reveal.
And today's pixel art, a
round of applause if we could.
Very nicely done.
Well, thank you both.
If you want to come up after, and
tear this off, and bring it home,
you're welcome to, and
keep the post-it notes too.
Well, thank you to our volunteers there.
Let's now translate this to
really more technical world
where we're going to see
and consider it more often.
Because in fact, sometimes,
when you've had error messages
over the past few weeks
from clang, the compiler,
you might have even seen
evidence of hexadecimal.
We didn't call it out.
It wasn't useful to know at the time.
But it turns out a lot of
programs use, and a lot of code,
uses hexadecimal for those
reasons of more precise--
more succinct representation.
So for instance, where
else might we see it?
Well, here's that picture we keep
pulling up of our computer's memory.
And each of these squares
in this grid represents
a byte, sort of top left to bottom
right in the computer's memory.
But again, just an
artist's representation.
A few weeks ago, I claimed that each of
these bytes can be numbered of course.
Like this is byte 0 at top
left, then byte one, then
byte two, then byte two billion
if you have 2 gigabytes of memory.
And so we could just number them
like this, zero through 15 on up.
16, 17, 18, and so forth.
But per the reasons earlier, it's
just more common in computer systems
and in software to actually
use hexadecimal just
to describe the locations of, the
addresses, of things in memory.
So instead, a typical programmer,
or a computer scientist,
would call these first 16 bytes
zero through F just because.
But that's because it's a
predictable number of bits.
So if we keep going beyond that, you
would get not 10, not 11, not 12,
but in hexadecimal, one, zero,
one, one, one, two, and so forth,
all the way down on the screen to one
F. And if I shrunk this down or had
a bigger monitor, we would
see eventually 255 bytes later
from the start 255 as well.
But there's a potential problem here
with using hexadecimal in this way.
There's an ambiguity.
Can anyone imagine what can go wrong
if we use hex to just simply describe
locations in memory like this?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: One zero might also be 10.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
One zero might also be 10.
And maybe if you're really
thorough, OK, wait a minute.
It can't be 10 because
here's F over here.
So it's obviously not decimal.
But why create potential confusion,
especially when you're collaborating,
building something with someone?
We want to avoid that ambiguity.
And so the convention
humans decided on years ago
is that if you want to make clear
that a number is in hexadecimal just
by convention, you prefix
all of the digits with 0x.
The X is not another character.
It's not a 17th character.
It's just a human convention of putting
0x to imply, here comes hexadecimal.
And now it's unambiguous.
So now we see 0x10 obviously is
not 10 as we know it in decimal.
But rather it's the number
that comes after a single F.
So it's really the number in decimal 16.
So 0x, any time you see it, that's
just a visual cue that what is ahead
is actually hexadecimal.
So let's now start playing
around with this information.
So here's a super simple
line of code from week one
where I'm just declaring a variable n,
and I'm defining it to be the value 50.
And this is out of context.
We probably need a main
function and all of that.
But let's just rewind to week one
where we actually saw code like this
and do something useful with
a line of code like this.
So let me go over here to VS Code.
And in VS Code, I'll create a
program called, how about addresses?
Since the goal of this--
the goal here is to just play around,
ultimately, with a variable like n.
And let me go ahead and do this.
I'll include, how about standard I/O.h?
I'll do int main void.
So no command line arguments for now.
Int n gets 50.
And now so that we can do
something mildly useful with it,
let's just go use printf and print out
with %i and then a new line whatever
that value of n is.
So this is not going to
be interesting per se.
It's just week one stuff
where I'm defining a variable
and printing it out to the screen.
So let me go down to my terminal
window and do make addresses.
No errors.
So that's good.
I'll do dot slash addresses.
And of course, I should
see the number 50 here.
Now what's going on underneath the hood?
Let's translate now code
to really what's going
on underneath the hood of the computer.
So if this is our grid of
memory, I don't necessarily
know as the programmer,
and I definitely don't
care as the programmer, where
exactly it's ending up in memory.
That's the whole point of using code.
Let the computer figure this out.
But at least conceptually, I know that
by declaring a line of code like that,
the number 50 ends up somewhere
in the computer's memory.
And it's assigned the name n, a
symbol n, by which I, the programmer,
can refer to it.
And I very deliberately used four
of these squares for what reason?
What might be the reason for
using four squares specifically?
Yeah.
Yeah, so an integer is 4 bytes.
At least most of the time on modern
systems, an integer is 4 bytes.
On an older computer,
it might just use one.
Or maybe even 2 bytes.
But here, by convention, we're
almost always going to see 4 bytes.
I don't know if it's
going to end up here.
It might end up over here.
But for now, who cares?
I just know that the computer
can store the information
in this way underneath the hood.
So let's now introduce
another feature of C
that we haven't had occasion
to use just yet that's
going to allow us to start poking
around the computer's memory
for better or for worse.
And this is one of
those situations where
you're about to learn, acquire a skill,
a power, that can actually come back
to bite you.
Because once you know how to start
poking around a computer's memory,
you can do very powerful things.
And next week, we'll see what you
can build in a computer's memory,
but you can also screw up
pretty easily and cause
more of those segmentation faults that
a few of you have already suffered.
So with that said, let's just
stipulate that you know what?
I don't care necessarily
where the 50 is in memory.
But I know it exists at
some address in memory.
And just so I have an
easy address to pronounce,
let's just suppose it lives at 0x123.
So that's the address in memory
in hexadecimal by convention.
And that just happens to be where it
ends up when I write that line of code.
But it turns out, C has some
other operators we can use.
When we've seen the asterisk
before, the star, and we've
used it for multiplication.
But today, we're going to use
it for something more powerful.
And we're also going to
introduce an ampersand, which
allows us to do something as well.
The ampersand operator
is going to allow us
to get the address of a piece of data
in memory, like by literally putting
ampersand before the
name of a variable, C
will tell us, tell you, what
address that variable lives at.
Maybe it's 0x123, maybe it's 0x456.
Who knows?
But that will give you back the answer.
The star does the opposite.
It sort of means, go there.
So using the star, otherwise known
as the de-reference operator,
I can actually go to a
specific address if I want.
And we'll see what this means in code.
So how can I leverage this in
some mildly interesting way
to start poking around?
But eventually, we'll use this primitive
to build more interesting things.
So let me go back to say, VS Code here.
And let me go ahead and do this.
I'll clear my terminal to start fresh.
And I'll introduce another
format code for printf, %p.
And for now, just take it on
faith that this it is %p because.
But %p is going to allow me to print the
address of a variable if I additionally
tell C, get the address of n.
So I'm changing %i to %p.
And that's just something you have to
do when printing addresses for now.
But I need to change an in
front of the variable name.
So I don't print n, the number 50.
I print out something like 0x123.
And it's not going to
be as simple as that.
We'll see on the screen
though where it actually
ended up in my code space's memory.
So here we go.
Dot-- down in my terminal, make
addresses again to recompile.
And now, dot slash addresses
should reveal not the value of 50,
but the address of 50.
And there it is.
It's pretty long.
It's not quite as simple
and pretty as 0x123.
But there's the 0x, meaning
here's a hexadecimal address.
And it's 7ffcc784a04c.
Suffice it to say your code space,
and even your Macs and PCs nowadays,
have a lot of memory.
That's why, in part, this
address is so big, not as small
as the thing on my slide.
So this at the moment
isn't that useful yet.
But it introduces us to a concept
that we'll now call pointers.
And pointers are admittedly one of
the more challenging aspects of C.
And if in future life, you tell friends
that, oh, I took a class called CS50,
and we learned C, you'll
probably get kind of a look
at people like, why did you learn C?
Or like, oh, C was hard.
And it's largely because
of this topic, which
isn't to say that it's that
hard to wrap your mind around.
But it's definitely very different.
And it's not a feature that you can
harness in higher level languages
that we'll see in class two, like
Python, and Java, and the like.
C is about as close to
the computer's hardware,
so to speak, that you can get
before things get actually scary,
the so-called assembly language we
saw in week two when I had a link,
and compile, and
assemble, and all of that.
That gets really low level.
And you really have to be an expert
with the computer's CPU, or brain,
to understand that.
But with C, you can actually
poke around the computer's memory
and do powerful things with that.
But again, with great
power comes responsibility.
It's very easy to break programs by
misusing memory or just having a bug
that touches memory in some
way that you don't intend.
So pointers, at the end of the day,
are pretty much what we just saw.
A pointer is really just a variable
that contains the address of some value.
A pointer is a variable that
contains the address of some value,
or more simply, it's fine to
think of it as an address.
A pointer is an address of
something in the computer's memory.
Now, what might we do to actualize this?
Well, here's two lines of code.
It turns out by using our two new
operators today, I can declare an int,
call it n, and assign it a
value like 50, just like before.
If I want to store the
address of n in a variable,
and not just print it
immediately via printf,
I can declare a variable,
for instance, called p.
But I could call it anything
I want, like any variable.
But because it's an
address, it's not int p.
It has to be int star p, so to speak.
And the star here on the left
hand side of the equal sign
is just a clue to see that means
p is going to be a pointer.
That is, p is going to
be the address of what?
The address of an integer.
Now technically, it's
still an integer itself
because an address is just a number
whether it's 1, 2, 3, or 0x123.
So this is really just
a semantic difference.
So int star p just means
that this variable doesn't
contain any old number, like 50.
It specifically contains a number
that is the address of something else.
So how can I now use this?
Well, let me go back to VS Code.
And let me propose that we
add a line of code like that.
So instead of just directly
printing out that value,
let's go ahead and define a second
variable called p that's of type int
star p, set it equal to
ampersand n, and then this time,
let's not just print out ampersand n.
Let's actually print out the value of p.
So the only two new
things here if I zoom in
are I've used not only the ampersand
on the right to get the address of n.
I'm now using the star
on the left to tell C
that p is still a variable as always.
But it's a pointer.
It is the address of some
other value like this.
And I'm still going to print it
with the same format code, %p.
So that doesn't change.
So let me go ahead and zoom out and
do make addresses, and ./addresses.
And there it is, exactly the same thing.
Now in and of itself,
not that useful yet.
But the fact that you can now access
the addresses of things in memory
means that we'll be able to build
things, and construct things, and link
things together by knowing
where they live, so to speak.
So any questions on
this technique thus far?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: I guess I'm a little
confused about the [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: A good question.
On line six, must it be
star p and ampersand?
And in this case, yes.
Because what am I doing?
On the left, and I'll get rid
of the equal sign for now,
this would give me a variable called
p that's not an integer per se,
but that's the address of an integer.
But without the equal sign, I'm not
storing anything in that variable.
So by adding the equal
sign and then ampersand n,
I am explicitly figuring out with
ampersand what the address of n
is, which already exists per
line five and tucking it away
in this new variable called p.
Other questions?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
Every time I run the program, it
uses up a different piece of memory?
Short answer, yes.
Computers, though,
long story short, also
have something called virtual memory.
So if you run it again and
again, you might actually
see the same addresses on the same
Mac, or PC, or cloud-based server.
But we'll see in a bit where
at a high level it's laid out.
But it will always
exist at some address.
Good question.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Correct.
Ampersand n is the address of n.
And int star p is a pointer called p.
And honestly, in an ideal world, if
C were made today and not decades ago
when humans were first
creating languages,
ideally, we would just have
a data type called pointer.
And then this would be a little less
complicated because it would literally
be what it says.
The humans who invented
C didn't do this.
But this is the idea.
So pointer is not a
legitimate word in the code.
It is a term of R in English.
But this is really just the idea.
But the way you express
pointer as a data type
is a little more cryptic
as int star p here.
But notice in line seven, when I
print out p, I don't use a star.
I don't use an ampersand.
Why?
I literally just want
to print the value of p.
And we've been doing
that since week one.
If you want to print a variable, just
describe the variable by its name.
No special syntax.
Any other questions on this thus far?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: What's the
advantage of using pointers?
With pointers, we'll see today
some applications of them,
really the idea is going
to come to fruition
next week when we're
going to create what
are called data structures in
memory, where we can build not just,
for instance, one dimensional
data structures like an array.
We'll see next week,
we can actually create
the equivalent of two
dimensional data structures,
or even three dimensional
data structures,
by using these addresses and
sort of linking things together.
And we'll see the beginnings
of that this week.
But for now, focus at least for
now on just really the syntax
and what these building
blocks can do for us.
AUDIENCE: Does the p pointer
have to be an integer?
DAVID J. MALAN: Does the p integer--
does the p pointer have to
be an-- point to an integer?
Short answer, no.
And we'll come back to this.
For now, for the sake
of discussion, we're
only dealing with integers
like the number 50.
You mentioned strings, or characters.
Absolutely.
We're about to go there soon.
So you can use the address of anything
you want in the computer's memory.
So in fact, let's translate this
now to just the same picture just
to help you wrap your minds around
what these two lines of code really
fundamentally are doing.
So if I come back to
my grid of memory here,
let's plop the number 50 in the
variable n at the bottom right,
like it was before.
So this is that first
line of code as before.
But with the new second line of code,
as soon as I create p, what do I do?
Well, first, remember that n lives
somewhere in the computer's memory.
Usually, I don't care
precisely where it is.
But for the sake of
discussion, let's suppose
it's at 0x123, which is easier to
say than where it actually ended up.
And now what is p?
Well, p is just another variable.
And variables live in memory too.
So let me just hypothesize
that p lives up here.
And it turns out that p once you
assign it, the value of ampersand n
means that C will take a
look at the variable n,
realize, oh it lives at 0x123,
and what goes in the value of p
is literally 0x123.
So again, it's still an
integer, which is confusing.
But it's technically an integer
being used as an address.
And now just a prompt here, notice
that this pointer is pretty darn big.
It's like eight squares.
What's the implication of that?
Because I did that deliberately.
How big must a pointer apparently be
in most modern systems, would you say?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, good.
Computers today are very big.
You have gigabytes of
RAM in your computer.
You therefore need big
pointers to be able to point,
and memory that's
conceptually pretty far away.
So to be clear, how many bytes
does a pointer apparently take up?
Well, it seems to take up 8 in total.
Integers by convention
nowadays are usually 4.
Pointers though nowadays are
typically 8 in this case.
So I'm drawing it in a manner
consistent with the reality,
even though at the end of the day,
it's not really that interesting
what values are in here.
In fact, let's emerge from these weeds.
I don't really care
what else is going on
in my computer's memory at
the moment because I've only
got those two lines of juicy
code defining n and defining p.
So let's hide all of the other squares.
And honestly, I mean it
when I say that programmers
need to know that a variable
exists somewhere in memory,
and needs to be able to get that
address using the ampersand,
but you're never going to printf
like I did, the actual address.
It's not generally interesting,
unless you're debugging your code.
But you're not going to start typing
out crazy 0x numbers in your code
to move things around.
You just need to know that the computer
can figure out where things are.
So frankly, by that logic,
who cares that it's 0x123?
Tomorrow, it could be
0x456 or something else.
So one of the ways to think
of a pointer is literally as
a variable that points
at something else.
And indeed, in this case, p, yeah,
technically it has an address.
And yeah, technically
it's 0x123 in this story.
But honestly, who cares?
I just need to know that using
p, I can get to the value n.
And so what are these addresses?
And in fact, if Carter wouldn't mind
joining me up here for a moment,
what are these addresses?
Well, just like in our human
world we have mailboxes,
even though you might not check
it very frequently nowadays,
but to get physical mail, every home,
every business has a unique address.
The Science and Engineering Complex
is 150 Western Avenue Allston,
Massachusetts, 02134 USA.
And theoretically, that uniquely
identifies that building in the world.
Well, here we have two mailboxes.
Over here, we have a value n
that happens to live, I'll claim,
at address 0x123.
And then over here, I claim there's
another address called by name p.
I don't actually care where it is, even
though it definitely exists somewhere
in the computer's memory.
But if this is p, which is a variable,
and that's n, another variable,
ideally, this mailbox
would be twice as big
because of the number of bytes using.
But Home Depot only had
identical sized mailboxes.
But here is p, one variable.
There is n, another variable.
If I open up this mailbox,
what should I find inside of it
based on our story thus far?
What value will I pull out
dramatically in just a moment?
Yeah, I think.
0x123.
Now using this, you can kind
of think of this as like X
marks the spot, no pun
intended, where I can now
walk around the computer's memory
and find my way to that location
by sort of following the treasure map.
Or if I want it more dramatically,
thanks to our little Yale foam
finger here, you can think of it more
abstractly as p is just pointing at n.
That's not going over well.
So let's switch over to the Harvard one.
So p is pointing--
AUDIENCE: Whoo.
DAVID J. MALAN: So p is pointing at n.
And so it turns out we will
be able to write code now
that will do the equivalent
of me walking over to n.
But for now, Carter, if you want
to reveal what's in the mailbox,
we should see indeed the number 50.
So that's really all that--
Carter is waiting for applause.
So really, nicely done.
Thank you.
So that's just a physical
metaphor of what's going on here.
In one variable, we have an address.
And that variable by
convention is called a pointer.
In the other variable per week
one, we just have a value like n.
And you can, yes, follow
the map and walk yourself
to that particular address.
And we'll see how to do that in code.
But what's really interesting is this
abstraction, that pointers literally,
or really I guess, figuratively,
point at some other value in memory.
All right, questions, then,
on pointers in this form.
AUDIENCE: Can pointers
point to each other?
DAVID J. MALAN: Can pointers
So yes.
There are things called double pointers.
We're not going to
see them anytime soon.
But using star, star, you can
express an address of an address.
But we won't see that just yet.
Other questions on pointers?
Yeah, in front.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Are array-- so to
summarize, are arrays then pointers?
So short answer, there's a relationship.
And we'll come back to
that in a little bit.
But arrays are technically
different from pointers.
But we're going to be able to blur
the lines a little bit by using one
like the other.
But let me come back to
that in just a bit of time.
All right.
So if we have now this
mental model, if you will,
of what a pointer is
in memory, I think we
can start to peel back a
layer of simplification
that we've been assuming for the
past few weeks since week one.
So a string, recall, is
a sequence of characters.
And so if you want to
create a string that says,
hi, in all caps and
an exclamation point,
we do string s equals
quote unquote "hi".
And we can hard code it like
this, or we could use get string.
But for now, just assume
that I hardcoded it
into my code to always say, hi, in
all caps with an exclamation point.
Well, what does that look
like in the computer's memory?
Well, let's stop looking
at the entire memory
and let's just focus on
really what's going on.
Once you create a string
called S and store in it hi,
you know that a couple
of things are happening.
H, and I, and the exclamation point
are ending up in the computer's memory.
We know from week two that this thing,
the so-called NUL character, NUL, AKA
backslash zero, is also
being added for you.
And it's somewhere in memory.
At the moment, I don't really care
where I drew it at the bottom right.
Yes, it has an address.
But for now, it just ends up somewhere.
And in fact, here's a little
visual cue as to how this happens.
In C, any time you use double
quotes to give you a string,
you can imagine that the
double quotes are like a clue
to not only store HI exclamation point,
but also put the NUL character there
for you.
And this is in contrast to what chars,
if you want individual characters, what
syntax did we use instead?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So single quotes.
Single quotes do not add
magically a backslash zero.
They literally just store one character.
So again, strings have
always been a little special.
You get some extra--
an extra byte for free
so that you know where
the string ends, and functions like STR
compare can then find their way there.
So in memory, it might indeed
look a little like this.
And if we assume that there's
going to be somewhere in memory,
these things are going to
be somewhere in memory,
we can address them per week two
by way of the name of the variable.
So if S is the name of
the variable, S bracket 0
is how you would refer
to the first letter.
S bracket 1, S bracket 2.
And if you really want, S bracket 3
would get you at the NUL character
at the very end.
But what is S?
So technically in this
line of code here, not only
is the computer giving you memory for HI
exclamation point backslash zero, we--
it turns out that S itself must
take up some amount of space
because S is the variable.
And every time we've talked
about variables thus far,
I've given you a rectangle on the
screen in which to store its value.
So let's assume for the sake of
discussion that the H is at 0x123
and I is at 0x124 exclamation
point is at 0x125,
and the NUL character is at 0x126.
Well, what then is S?
Well, s is just going to
be some other variable.
And I'll draw it somewhat abstractly
without all of the other boxes,
up here.
And I'll claim that the
name of this variable is s.
But it turns out, what is s really?
How do strings really work?
Well, s is a variable, and
has been since week one.
But when you define it, what the
computer is doing for you automatically
is when it knows you want to
store HI exclamation point,
it puts that somewhere in memory.
The computer then figures
out for you, what's
the address of the very first character?
And it stores that address,
and only that address,
in the variable you created on the
left hand side of the equal sign.
And that's enough.
To represent a string with three
letters of the alphabet or punctuation,
you don't need three variables.
You just need one.
You just need to know the
beginning of the string.
Why?
Why is it sufficient for a variable to
only store the first byte's address,
and not all of the bytes' addresses?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Because of the design of strings per
week two, we always NUL terminate them.
So it's suffices to only remember
the first byte's address.
Because from there, you can
sort of follow the breadcrumbs
byte, after byte, after byte.
And until you see the new
line, sorry, the NUL character,
you know that all of those characters
are apparently part of the same string.
So this is what's been going on in the
computer's memory all since week one.
And in fact, if we
abstract this away, you
can really think of S as being
just this, really a pointer
to that chunk of memory.
So in fact, what do we have here?
Well, in the left to recap on the code
here, on the left hand side string,
that's what ensures that we'll
actually be able to store
a string in a variable called s.
We're going to have on the right
hand side, though, the actual value.
So let me switch back to VS Code here.
And let me change my code to no
longer involve integers alone.
So I'm going to add the
CS50 library just so
that I can use some shortcuts in there.
CS50.h.
And then in my main function, I'm
going to go ahead and do this.
String s equals quote unquote "HI"
in all caps, exclamation point.
And then I'm going go ahead and print
out using %S as always backslash n
the value of s.
So this program at the moment,
not interesting at all.
It's just week one stuff again.
./addresses indeed prints out hi.
But it turns out that
now that I know this,
what's really been going on
underneath the hood all this time?
Well, here's that same line of code
that defines the variable called S.
And it turns out anyone, want to guess
what string is actually a synonym for?
String, it turns out, is kind of a white
lie we've been telling since week one.
There is no such thing as
string as a keyword in C.
It's technically a CS50 thing.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: It's a
pointer to a character.
So really, all this time, we've
kind of been lying to you.
There is no "string" quote unquote.
It's actually char star.
And if I may dramatically
here, go, the training wheels.
That didn't land very well.
So what have we been doing?
Well, it turns out that string
is a much easier way conceptually
to think about what a
string of characters is.
My God, if we had a start in week
one by having you type char star,
yeah, you might get past it.
But this is just way too much ugly
syntax, not intellectually interesting
at all.
So we abstract it away.
What a char star was in the
first week of C, by telling you
it's actually called string.
Now string is a term
of R. C programmers,
programmers in any language
will use the word string
to mean a sequence of characters.
But in C, it's not technically
a word unto itself.
It's rather a synonym that we
ourselves created in some form.
So in fact, how did we do this?
Well, think back to just last week.
Last week, I proposed
that it'd be really nice
if we had a person data
type, which the creators of C
did not think of decades ago.
But that's OK.
We can define it ourselves.
What did we do here?
Well, we're using syntax like this.
Recall that we defined
a person to be what?
To be this structure.
This structure, using the
new keyword last week,
struct, means that a person
is just a name and a number.
And it could have been other things.
We just kept it simple.
But how did I associate
person with that structure?
Well, we claimed that
it was this value here,
typedef, which as you might
expect, defines a data type.
So what did we do as CS50 back
in week one without telling you?
Well, we could have done
something like this.
Int itself is a little cryptic.
And maybe we should have to keep things
even simpler said, hey, everyone.
Turns out you can define integers in
C. And if you wanted to do this, well,
if you want to create the
keyword integer as a data type,
you can just typedef it to int.
So typedef creates the word
on the far right, integer,
and creates a synonym for
it in this case called int.
So what did we do in week
one without telling you?
We have a line of code like
this in the CS50 library
that associates quote unquote "string"
with more cryptically char star.
And this is why in week one onward,
any time you use the CS50 library,
you can write the word string as
though it's a real C data type.
And that's just because we wanted to
have this abstraction, these training
wheels on for the first
weeks, so we don't
have to get in the weeds of
all this crazy memory stuff.
We can sort of talk about
strings at a higher level.
But that's all they are.
Strings are the address
of the first character
in that sequence of characters.
Questions now on any of these details?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: What about the strings
libraries that [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
What about the strings
library, which we have used?
Unrelated.
So it does not define the word string.
Everything in there actually
relates to char stars.
And so in fact, if you've used
the CS50 manual, which is just
our user-friendly version of the actual
manual pages for the official language,
C, you'll see throughout that now if
you start poking around or turning off
less comfortable mode,
you'll actually see
that we changed any
mentions of char star
in the official documentation
for these first weeks
to just string to simplify it.
But underneath the hood, C does not know
the word string per se as a keyword.
But it's absolutely a concept that
every program in the world knows about.
And in fact, in other languages,
in Python for instance,
there will actually be a proper
string, although it's not
going to be called string.
It's going to be called
STR, STR for short.
Questions on these strings here.
Well, let me propose there's
one other feature of this syntax
that we can now leverage as follows.
Let me propose that if we go back
to the previous version of my code
here, wherein, let me switch
back to VS Code in just a moment,
I'm going to rewind in VS Code to the
integer version of my code from before.
And most recently, it looked like this,
before when we were using integers
only and not, in fact, strings at all.
Let me propose that there's
this other feature of C
that we can use that actually
allows us to go to an address.
So at the moment, let me just
rewind and do, make addresses,
to remind you what this program did
when it was using integers alone.
And there's that address.
Why?
Because on line seven,
notice, I'm printing out
the value of p, which is a pointer.
So of course, it's going
to look like an address.
But let me zoom out now
and make one change.
Instead of printing out p, how can
I use today's second new operator,
not the ampersand, but the star,
to actually go to that address?
Well, what I can actually do
on this line of code, is this.
If I want to print out the actual
integer 50 that's in that variable,
or equivalently at that address, I can
go to p here and not print p literally,
because that's just an address.
I can now say, star p.
And star p means go there.
More technically, de-reference p.
That is, follow the treasure map to the
actual address and do what Carter did.
Open the mailbox and print whatever
was in the mailbox, which recall,
was the actual number 50.
So let me try this.
Let me recompile the code.
So make addresses.
OK, let me clear my terminal window.
Dot slash addresses.
This time, I shouldn't
see the 0x anything.
I should see just the
number 50 in this case.
And here too is kind of a unfortunate
design decision, certainly
pedagogically I would say in
C. If I zoom in on this code,
star is unfortunately being
used in two different ways.
In an ideal world, they would
have used three different symbols
to make this more semantically clear.
But this is what we're stuck with.
So in line six, when
you declare a pointer,
that is a variable
that stores an address,
you put the type of
variable that you want
to point at, then a star just because,
and then the name of the variable.
And then on the right
hand side, you actually
get the address of
whatever using ampersand.
But when you want to go to an address,
you want to de-reference a pointer,
you don't use int again.
And we've never done that.
Once you declare a variable, you
never again mention the data type.
But in the world of
pointers now, if you want
to not print out p but go to
whatever address p is storing,
you use star p here.
So a good visual indicator
would be when you
declare a pointer, that is
make it exist in your program,
you have to declare the
data type with the star.
But when you use a pointer,
you just use the star.
In an ideal world, this would be
a completely different symbol.
But again, this is what we have.
Questions now on that syntax.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Why can't we just do
the ampersand here, are you saying?
It was still a little quiet.
So strictly speaking,
we do not need line six.
So this is really for
pedagogical sake that I
am defining a separate variable
p and then printing it out.
At this point though, I'm just kind
of going in circles, if you will.
Because more simple
would have been what I
would have done in week one,
which would be get rid of p
altogether, get rid of p
here, and just print out n.
But today, we're just giving you this
new building block, this new syntax,
via which you can figure out
the address of something,
and then reverse the process later
and actually go to it as well.
Other questions on what we've
done here with these pointers.
All right.
Well, let's context
switch back to the string
now and see what more we can do with
this here in the case of our strings
here.
Let me refine this to zoom out, let me
delete the integer-related code here,
let me do string s equals quote unquote
"HI" in all caps, let me go ahead
and for the moment
include CS50.h at the top
so that indeed I can use the key word s,
string rather, and let me go ahead now
and do something more
than I did last time.
Last time, I did printf of %s
backslash n, and then I printed out s.
And again, I'll recompile this
just for clarity, make addresses,
dot slash addresses.
That just prints out hi.
So that's, again, week one stuff.
But now that we have
this other bit of syntax,
we can do some interesting things too.
So for instance, suppose I
want to print out not s itself,
but what if I want to
print out the address of s?
At what memory location is s?
Well, I can change my %s to %p,
which now we know p is for pointer.
So %p means print out
the value of a pointer.
That is an address.
And here, I can actually
print out s itself.
But why that is, we'll see in a moment.
Let me do this.
Here go the training wheels.
String does not technically exist, but
it does if I'm using the CS50 library.
But if I get rid of the CS50
library, as I'm metaphorically
doing by taking off the training wheels,
I can't use the word string anymore.
And in fact, let me make
this mistake deliberately
as you might have
accidentally in past weeks.
Here is the error message I get
if I forget the CS50 library, use
of undeclared identifier string.
Did you mean standard in?
It's trying to be helpful, but it's
not because I didn't mean standard n.
So indeed, this is
confirmation that C does not
know the word string exists,
at least as a keyword.
Exists as a concept, but not a keyword.
So I could fix this by
adding back the CS50 library.
But that's kind of a step backwards,
educationally, instead of a step
forward.
What could I do instead to fix this
now if the training wheels are now off?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Replace "string" quote unquote
with char star instead.
So I'm going to go ahead
and change this to char.
Technically, you can put
the literal star here,
the asterisk, or you can put it
there, or you can put it here.
By convention is to do what
I've done from the beginning,
put the star next to the name of the
variable as opposed to anywhere else.
Let me go ahead now and--
or sorry.
I meant to add the spaces there.
You could do this too.
But this would be the
most normal convention.
So now let's do this.
Make addresses, compiles OK
now, dot slash addresses.
What should I see?
Hi or something else?
Feel free to just call it out.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So still hi, you say?
Someone else?
AUDIENCE: Memory location?
DAVID J. MALAN: A memory location.
All right, so it could be
one of the two options.
Either I'm going to see the string,
or I'm going to see a memory address.
Though I do, in fact,
see a memory address.
And this one is quite
different from the integer one.
But does anyone now want to
explain why you were correct?
Why am I seeing the address
down here and not hi?
It's subtle.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
Because I left my %p there, which
means, hey, printf, show me a pointer.
But this is where printf is smart
and has been smart since week zero.
Humans who invented printf decades
ago wrote code that notices that OK,
%s means to treat the following value,
not as just an address per se that gets
printed literally, but print
it as with the mailbox demo,
as sort of a treasure map that leads
you to the address of a character.
So simply by changing
one character, %p to %s,
and if I now do make addresses
again and dot slash addresses,
this now is identical to week
one, but hopefully makes sense.
Because %s is just a clue to printf
that means, go to this address in s.
Print out every character there
and thereafter until you see, what?
The NUL character.
And then stop printing anything more.
And this is why hi has
printed since week one.
Today, we can see the address %p.
But this combination of having access
to addresses and the NUL terminator
is all the information printf
needs to actually do something more
useful by printing the actual strings.
Any questions now on
this approach to %s?
Yeah, in back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, so why is it
traditionally being used in this way?
Honestly, the word string
has been around for decades.
It's not a key word you should be
able to type in C unless you're using
a library like CS50's.
And so s just means string.
So even though it doesn't exist
as a key word, %s connotes string.
And humans decades ago, like today,
just kind of know what that means.
So they could have chosen
any letter of the alphabet.
But s sort of makes the most sense.
All right.
Well, let's-- in back.
Other question?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
Before-- let me zoom in.
I did not use a star before the s.
Why?
Well, it's subtle here.
But printf was invented
years ago to know,
given an address like in the
variable s, printf knows to go there.
So if we looked at the source code
that some human wrote years ago for C,
we would likely see the actual
asterisk that you're referring to.
Printf is taking on the
responsibility for going to s.
If you were to do star s here
instead, an asterisk, and an s,
that would now be literally a character.
Because if I say star s, that
means go to the address in s.
And all you're going to find
there is a single character.
What printf wants to know is
not, what is the character there?
What is the address of that character?
Why?
Because printf needs to walk
through the rest of those characters
looking for the final NUL character.
And in fact, let me see,
with a bit more syntax,
if we can highlight this a bit more.
Let me do this.
In addition to printing s, let's
try out our syntax in another way.
Let me print out with
%s how about not s here,
but let's print out some addresses.
%s backslash n, close quote,
and then let's print
out, how about this?
The first character in the string
s would be called s bracket 0.
But how do I get the address
of the first character in s?
Well, I could technically just
use today's new primitive.
I can just add an ampersand.
That always gives me the
address of some value.
So when I end this thought
and clear my terminal window
and run make addresses,
still compiles, when
I run addresses in just
a moment, any guesses
as to what I will see line by line?
This will print out two things.
And you don't have to remember
what the actual number was.
But at a high level,
what will be printed now?
The same thing twice.
Why?
Well, when I run this, what I'm printing
here, and let me zoom in at the bottom,
I indeed see two really long addresses.
But they're, in fact, the same.
Why?
Well, that's because, again, if s is the
address of a character, as implied now
by either the CS50 word string, or
the actual phrase char star, well,
then s is just an address.
By contrast per week two,
s bracket 0 is a char.
Always has been a char, specific char.
But if you want the address of that
char, you just add the ampersand.
Well, it turns out that strings, per
the definition we keep emphasizing,
is just the address of the
first character in a string.
So of course, if you do this, you're
going to see the exact same thing.
And if I do this a bit more, generally,
you don't want to copy paste.
But this is just for visualization sake.
Let me print out all the characters.
So another, another, another.
And let me change this to print out
the address of bracket one, bracket
two, and bracket three.
So all four characters,
H, I, exclamation point,
and the NUL character.
Notice I'm using %p for all of them.
So if I now do make addresses
and dot slash addresses,
now notice, and this is kind of cool.
The first two are indeed still the same.
But what's noteworthy about
the other values on the screen?
Yeah, they're consecutive.
Each of these is just 1 byte away.
Even if you're not good at hex yet and
there's a crazy number of digits here,
who cares?
They're all the same except for the
last ones, four, four, and then five,
six, seven.
And this confirms what I've been
claiming for weeks is that in an array,
all of the characters are back to
back to back contiguous 1 byte away.
So with just this ampersand,
with just this star,
it's actually a pretty
cool tool in the toolkit
to have Because you can start to
poke around what's actually going
on inside of the computer's memory.
And in fact, if we do this, I can
introduce one other cool trick here,
if you will.
Let me propose that we can actually
now do arithmetic on pointers.
And you don't have to.
You'll see a simpler way to do this.
But now that you have perhaps this
underlying understanding of where
things are in memory
and it's just addresses,
we can actually do
something kind of neat.
We can do something like this.
Let me go back to how about the
string version of this with hi.
And let me do this instead.
Let me clean this up a bit, get
rid of some of these lines of code.
And let me do this.
Let me print out %c, %c, %c.
Let me get rid of all these ampersands.
We're going to roll
back to week two stuff.
Just to be clear, when I compile
and run this version of the program,
and I'll zoom in, what should
get printed on the screen?
This is just week two stuff now.
No pointers per se.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Just HI
exclamation point, one per line,
because I have all of
these backslash n's.
So let me do that.
Let me go down here,
make addresses, Enter.
OK, pretty good.
Dot slash addresses.
And indeed HI exclamation point.
But now if you're getting
a little more comfortable,
and it's fine if you're not yet today,
but over the coming week or weeks,
as you get a little more comfortable
with the equivalence of addresses
with our definition in the past of
arrays, and strings, and all of this,
you can start to play around.
And I can do this instead.
If I want to print out the
first character in the string,
I could do, like week two, s bracket 0.
That will always work.
And you can keep using that.
That's not a CS50 thing.
It's just a convenience in C. But I
could technically print out not s,
because s is an address.
But what would be the syntax I could use
to say, print out the character at s?
Any instincts?
How can I say, go to the address in s?
It's one of two possible answers today.
So of our two new--
of our two new operators today, we
have the ampersand and the star.
Which one will lead us
to what is at an address?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So the star.
So in fact, if I want to print out, what
is at address zero, at the address s,
I can just do star s.
And if you really want to get
fancy, how do you print out
the second character that's immediately
to the right of it, so to speak?
Well, you can go to, with
the de-reference operator--
and do you want to answer this one?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: S plus 1.
Ergo, pointer arithmetic.
You can do math, simple
addition, subtraction,
whatever, on pointers if you want.
And you can do this here too.
So star, if you want to
pluck this one off too,
how do I print out the
last character, the third?
AUDIENCE: s plus 2?
DAVID J. MALAN: s plus 2.
Because if you know and
understand that a string is just
a sequence of characters,
every character is just a byte,
and these bytes are
back to back to back,
you can just go wherever you
want in the computer's memory.
And here, I can do make addresses
again, dot slash addresses.
And voila, we now have
hi exclamation point.
So we haven't printed out anything new.
But again, just by using these two new
operators, the ampersand and the star,
you can figure out the
address of something,
and you can go to the
address of something.
OK, question in back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Indeed.
It ends up being the exact same.
And so I might have
used this term before.
The ampersand technique-- sorry.
The square bracket technique where
you do s bracket zero, s bracket one,
s bracket two, that's actually what
we would really call syntactic sugar.
It works.
And you can use it.
You should use it.
It's nice and simple.
But the square bracket
notation underneath the hood
is essentially being converted
to this, which this is not fun.
This is when you want to
show off to your friends,
you know how to do cool stuff in code.
But this is not as readable as just
s bracket zero, and one, and two.
But that's all that's
happening underneath the hood.
And so again, this is
why in CS50 we spend time
on some of these lower
level building blocks.
Because if you assume that indeed
your computer's memory is just
this grid of bytes and you have now the
code ability in code to get an address
and go to an address, you can
start doing anything you want.
And you can poke around a
computer's memory at any location.
And herein lies the danger.
I'm kind of on the
honor system right now
that if my string is hi exclamation
point, it's kind up to me
to go to the first byte,
the second, and the third.
But I could get kind of crazy now.
And if I want to see what's going
on in the computer's memory, I mean,
there's nothing stopping me
from doing like s plus 50.
And let's see what's there.
So make addresses, dot slash addresses,
hi, and then, OK, nothing it seems.
Well, how about 5,000 bytes away?
Let's just poke around.
What's inside of the computer's memory?
So make addresses again, make
addresses, dot slash addresses, Enter.
OK, still nothing there.
Let's try 50,000.
All right.
Make addresses, dot slash addresses.
OK, there we see it.
So you've probably
done this, some of you,
by accident because you probably went
too far to the left or to the right
in an array touching
memory that you shouldn't.
Suffice it to say I should not go
blindly touching 50,000 bytes away.
Because who knows what's there?
And indeed, in your computer,
when a program is running,
the computer segments it into
different segments of memory.
And if you get a little too greedy and
you touch another segment of memory
that technically was not allocated to
you by Mac OS, or Windows, or Linux,
or the operating system,
bad things happen.
And you get a segmentation fault.
And that means it's a bug in your code.
So you can now do this.
And this means hackers too
can do things like this.
If they can somehow inject
code into your C program,
maybe they can poke around
the computer's memory.
And indeed, this is kind
of the technique whereby
maybe a really sophisticated hacker
can jump to this memory, this memory,
this memory looking for
something like your password,
or your financial information,
or anything that's in the program
but at some other address.
There's nothing stopping an
adversary, at least right now,
from poking around if they can
execute code on your computer
from doing this kind of thing.
So there and again is the power
of C, but also the danger.
And you'll absolutely suffer more
seg faults in the coming days.
But ultimately, the goal
is going to be to help you
solve them ultimately and fix things.
But for now, I think
that was quite a bit.
So let me propose that we go ahead
and take our longer break here,
maybe 10 minutes, and have ourselves
some whoopie pies in the transept.
We'll be back in 10.
All right.
So we're back.
And to recap where we left off, you
now have this new capability in code
to do pointer arithmetic
like treat addresses
as numbers, which they
really are in hexadecimal
or otherwise, and add
them together and kind
of poke around a computer's memory.
And it was asked during break
actually how we might further
harness this in the context of string.
So I didn't change the code
we wrote just before break.
Recall that we last broke the program
by checking out bytes 50,000 bytes away.
But let's not do that.
And let's actually try printing out
not individual characters, like I did,
per the %c, but why don't we try
printing out strings and substrings
if you will?
So let me clear my terminal window.
Let me change all of
these %c's to %s, %s, %s.
And then let me rewind to what
we've been doing since week one
with strings, which is
just print them out,
for instance, with that first line.
And the only difference at
the moment is that now, I
took off the training wheels.
I got rid of CS50.h wherein string
is typedef to char star for you.
Got rid of that.
So now on line five, I'm declaring
s as being a char star, which
just means the address of a character.
And printf is smart enough to
know that the end of a string
is wherever that NUL character is.
But now that I can do
pointer arithmetic,
notice that I could do
something like this.
If I want to print out
s, I just print out s.
Suppose I do s plus 1 here and s plus
2 here, again, after changing %c to %s.
Any intuition around what this code will
now print on the screen line by line.
Yeah, thoughts?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK,
reasonable conjecture.
Maybe the memory address of h, that
of i, that of exclamation point.
But other thoughts?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
I think it's actually
going to do the latter.
It's going to print,
hi, in the usual way.
Because honestly, line five is this--
rather line six is the same as week one
stuff, except we took off
the training wheel of string
and we're calling it char star.
But I think line seven is
indeed going to print out i.
And line eight is just
going to print out
because it will be just
the exclamation point.
Printf will still be smart enough to
know where each of those substrings,
portions of the strings, end
by the same logic as always.
But let me go ahead and zoom
out, run make addresses, Enter,
compiles OK, dot slash addresses.
And now indeed, this is all a string is.
It's a sequence of characters
identified by its first byte.
If you then start poking
around and tell printf
to print at what's at the next
byte, or the next, next byte,
it's going to do its
same thing, printing out
that character and everything after
it up until that NUL character.
So again, even though
there's a lot going on,
we've introduced these
two new operators,
there's nothing that's happening today
that hasn't been happening for weeks.
But hopefully, through this week, this
week's lecture, this week's problem
set, and beyond, you'll
start to realize that now,
you just have more tools by
which to harness those lower
level implementation details.
So last week two, recall one
other implementation detail.
I claimed that you could not compare
two strings quite as easily as you could
compare two integers for instance.
And I told you to use a
different function instead
that you probably used one or more
times with the past problem set.
How are you supposed to
compare strings apparently?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so string compare.
STR Comp.
That additional function that we said,
eh, you just have to use it for now.
But you might have a
little intuition already
as to why we have to use STR
compare and we can't just
use equals equals to compare strings.
Any intuition for this already?
Why was STR compare necessary last week?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
Equals, equals would compare
literally the two memory
addresses instead of the actual
strings character by character.
And unless the memory addresses
are literally the same,
so you compare that exact
same memory address,
two different strings
probably are not going
to be considered equal even if us
humans, they indeed look equal.
So let's see this.
Let me go ahead and close addresses.c.
And actually, before
I do one last mention,
one of the powerful things about
pointer arithmetic, as an aside,
is that C, and really the
compiler, is smart enough
to know how many bytes to
keep adding and adding.
And by that, I mean this.
Right now, we got lucky because a
string is a sequence of characters.
And by definition, every
character is a single byte.
You can poke around and do s plus
1 to get the next byte, s plus 2
to get the third byte.
However, if we weren't
dealing with strings,
suppose we were dealing with
integers that were in an array
back to back to back, if you
wanted to get at the next integer,
you could still do plus
1, or plus 2 to get
at the next or the next, next integer.
You would not start to get into the
weeds of doing plus 4, and then plus 8.
You don't have to know or care how big
the data types are in the computer.
C and the compiler will
figure that out for you
based on the data type in question.
So keep that in mind if ever doing this
on a different data type than chars.
All right, so let me go
ahead and open up a file
that I wrote in advance most of.
And let me hide my terminal
window and show you this.
So here is a program called
compare.c, whose purpose in life
is to compare two strings.
I'm back to using the CS50 library.
Because at least for now, and
probably a couple more weeks,
it is so much easier to get input
from the user using CS50's function,
get int.
But we'll conclude today by taking
off those training wheels as well.
So you can see how you can actually get
user input with nothing CS50 specific.
So line six and seven, pretty boring.
Week one stuff.
Get an int called i,
get an int called j,
and store them in two
variables, i and j respectively.
If i equals equals j, print
out the same, else print
out that they're different.
Let me just stipulate for time's sake,
I'm pretty sure this code is correct.
This will get two
integers from the human.
It will compare them
and tell me correctly
if they're the same or different.
And I'll prove as much by running
make compare dot slash compare.
And I'll type in 50 for i, 50 for j.
And they're the same.
And now I'll do, how
about 50, and say 13.
And those are different.
So let me just stipulate
this code is indeed correct.
Would have worked in week one,
also works now in week four.
But let me now change it to
compare not two integers,
but as I hinted, maybe
two strings instead.
So let me go ahead and
change this line of code
to maybe be string s equals get
string, asking the user for s.
Then let's change this second
line here to be string t,
just to keep the variable
names short for now.
And t is a good choice after
s for something like this.
Get string, prompt the human for t.
And then let's change our i and
j here to do the wrong thing,
per the intuition earlier.
If s equals equals t,
then print out the same,
else, print out that they're different.
Now if I want, I could take off at
least some of the training wheels.
I could change this to char star.
Either is fine.
I still need the CS50 library
though because I'm using get string,
because it's actually hard, as we'll
see today, to get strings manually
without using a library.
But I'll keep it using string
just for now with the library.
All right, make compare
again, dot slash compare.
And now let me go ahead and type in, for
instance, hi, exclamation point, Enter,
and hi, exclamation point, Enter.
And oh, they're different.
All right, they're
obviously not visually.
But they are underneath the hood.
And you probably do have
the intuition for this
already, whereby what's
going on underneath the hood
is that we're comparing accidentally
the two memory addresses.
So in fact, let's go there.
Let's consider the memory.
And let me zoom out now so I can
just have more bytes to play with.
So the squares are a little smaller than
before just so we can fit more in them.
And let me propose that when I declare
s on what was line six a moment ago,
it ends up somewhere in memory
like the top left hand corner
of my picture for discussion's sake?
And when I execute that same line
of code, and get string is called,
and I type in hi
exclamation point, we know
from week one that get string puts it
somewhere in the computer's memory.
And I'll propose that it's in the bottom
left hand corner of the screen here.
What happens after that?
Well, I know, even though
I don't generally care,
that H, I, exclamation
point, and the NUL character
exist at some address, like 0x123,
124, 125, 126 for discussion's sake.
And what's in s?
Same as before break, 0x123.
So that's all that's happening
again on line six, which
is pretty much the same as when
we were getting an s earlier.
But notice now with line seven, when
I get a second variable called t
and I call get string again.
And by coincidence, as the
human, I type the same thing.
Well, what happens here? t
gets its own chunk of memory,
maybe at the top right.
That second version of hi
gets somewhere else in memory.
The computer could be smart
and notice that it's the same.
But C doesn't generally do that for you.
It just plops it
somewhere else in memory.
And maybe it's at address 0x456,
457, 458, 459, or wherever.
But you can perhaps see
where this is going already.
t now, of course, contains the
address of that first byte.
And so in my code, on line nine,
when I compare s and t for equality,
suffice it to say they are
not equal because of the way
the strings are laid out
in the computer's memory,
it's indeed looks the same,
the same values are there.
But if we abstract away further, you
can really see that s and t not the same
themselves.
And so how did we fix this?
Or really, how did we avoid this
last week without spilling the beans
and going down this
rabbit hole of explaining
why you have to use STR compare?
Well, if I go back to my code here,
let's do it now the right way.
Let me go ahead and
include a line of code
that says string compare of
s comma t, both as inputs.
And then if you recall,
what does STR compare return
when two strings are equal?
There's three possible return values.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So zero.
So one is for if it comes alphabetically
or ASCIIabetically first or second.
But for now, I just want zero.
If I want to use STR
compare, I do need string.h.
So string.h does exist.
That's not a CS50 thing.
There's no keyword
string as a data type.
That's a CS50 thing.
But string.h does exist.
So I think now with that
change on line 10, if I do make
compare, and dot slash
compare, and then run again,
type again, hi exclamation
point, hi exclamation point,
I think now they're the same.
And just as a second check, HI in
all caps, maybe hi in lowercase,
those are, in fact, different.
Why?
Well, STR compare, which was
written by some other human decades
ago is just smart enough to know
that it should go to s and go to t,
start comparing them left to right,
stopping once it hits one or both NUL
characters, and return zero
only if everything in s
and in t are exactly the same.
Are any questions then on this here?
Any questions on why
we're using STR compare?
All right.
If no-- yeah, oh.
In the middle.
AUDIENCE: Why do [INAUDIBLE] integers?
Why [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yes.
So why-- why is it not
the case with integers?
So it turns out it's not
the case with integers,
with floats, with bools,
with doubles, with longs.
Literally every other
data type works correctly.
Strings though are special.
They're useful enough in programming
and have been for decades
that the authors of printf,
and the authors of STR
compare, and bunches of other
functions, strlen for that matter,
just kind of treat strings special
because they're just useful.
We humans interact using language,
be it English or anything else.
And so it's just useful to
have into the language C
just sort of first class support for
this notion of strings of human text.
So the short answer is just because.
It just is necessary--
strings are different.
They're implemented with this
address and the NUL character.
Everything else,
though, is just a value.
But a string again is a white lie.
It's an address.
It's not a thing unto itself.
Good question.
Yeah, in front.
AUDIENCE: How come [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh really good question.
So in my code here in VS
Code, what if I do this?
Instead of STR compare,
and instead of if s equals
equals t, what if I start playing
around using star s and star t?
Really interesting case to consider.
Let's go back to our sort
of deductive logic here.
So star, the asterisk operator
today, means go there.
So when I've typed in HI
once and then HI again,
both uppercase for instance, what
is at the address s literally?
Someone else.
What is at the address s?
Yeah.
So not quite.
At the address.
So not, what is the address?
What is at the address 0x123?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: h.
And what is at the address 0x456?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: h also.
And so here, you're kind of cheating.
You're comparing the first character of
both strings, but not every other one.
Now you could be really pedantic.
And here, again, this is
not a good use of code.
But you could do this.
If that, and how about this craziness?
So star s plus 1 equals
equals star t plus 1.
And you could do this for
every character manually.
But that's why STR compare exists.
It does all of this for you.
But that's why.
And that's the intuition.
So I would encourage you too, anytime
there's something kind of weird going
on, there's--
I realize we might be
straining credibility now,
we haven't told you
that many white lies.
And so most everything
that we've seen thus far
can explain pretty much all
of the behavior up until now
from week one onward in C. So let me
revert this back to the right way.
If s STR compare of s
and t equals equals zero,
this now is the right
version of the code.
And now here is, again,
where you can play.
So let me do this.
Let me clear my terminal
window just to tidy things up.
Let me get rid of all of
this comparison stuff.
And let's just see what's going on, as
you are welcome to in your own code.
Let's print out, for
instance, as we might
have in week one, the value of
s itself on a new line, comma s.
And then let's just print out
t just to make sure it compiles
and I'm not doing anything wrong.
But this is not going
to be that interesting.
And frankly, I don't
need string.h anymore
because I'm not using STR compare.
So make addresses dot slash
addresses, there's my--
oh, sorry.
That's fun.
Not %t, %s here too.
Ignore that.
Let's do this again.
Make a-- oh, and that's
the wrong program.
Dot slash-- let's do make
compare dot slash compare.
And let's type in hi again and hi again.
And now we just see the two strings.
I'm not comparing.
But now we can kind of play around.
Instead of printing out %s,
which prints the string,
how do I print the address in s?
I just need to make a slight change.
If I want to see not what's at s,
but I want to see s, the address--
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Change %s to %p?
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
So change %s in both places here to %p.
So now, printf will treat
it literally as an address.
It's not going to do any
fancy this with a loop
from left to right looking
for the NUL character.
It's just going to print out s and t.
So let me clear my terminal,
run make compare, whoops.
Let's do make compare dot slash compare.
Enter.
Type in hi, type in hi again.
And now you see, oh,
so this is interesting.
It's not quite as straightforward as
the other values which were slight--
1 byte away.
They're almost the same.
But this one ends in b0.
This one ends in f0.
So they're indeed
separated by some number
of bytes, not just one, but a few.
Because these strings are indeed longer.
All right.
So once you've seen this here,
how can we now maybe leverage
this to solve other problems?
Well, let me propose that we do this.
Let me zoom out here,
let me close compare.
And let me open up another program I
wrote part of in advance called copy.c.
So copy.c in theory
makes a copy of a string.
How?
On line eight, I'm doing
the same thing as before.
Get string, storing it in a string, or
char star, and asking the user for it.
Then I'm not asking get string again.
I'm just making a copy super simply
with line 10 here, string t equals s.
Now intuitively, I think that's
how I would copy a variable.
That's how we've copied variables
every week thus far in C.
But something is going to go wrong.
In line 12, in English,
does someone want
to explain what you think line 12 does?
Don't worry about finding
any bugs or mistakes.
But what does line 12 seem to
be doing using two upper, which
is thanks to the C type library, which
I've included the header file for?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, right?
It's kind of like ugly syntax.
But this would seem to be
capitalizing the first letter of t
specifically and just changing it.
So we have t bracket 0 here,
because we want to save the change.
And we're passing to two upper,
the first character here.
So this is how we did
uppercase in the past.
And now I print out s and
t respectively using %s.
So this feels like it should work.
I copied s and stored
it in t on line 10.
And then I change t
and only t on line 12.
But you can perhaps, if
you're comfy thus far,
see where this is going if I
do make copy, dot slash copy.
And let me type in lowercase hi
exclamation point this time, just once.
So I'm going to hit Enter.
And watch what we see
for the value of s and t.
The new value of s and t at the
end of my program seems to be what?
It seems to be the same.
Hi is capitalized both times.
So what's the intuition then for this?
Why did this just happen?
Yeah, in back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, I assigned
s and t the same memory address.
So it did copy s into t.
But C takes this very literally.
What is s?
It's an address.
What is t?
It's a copy of that address.
If you want to copy the whole string
like a normal human would expect,
hey, you or someone has
to do a lot more work.
You have to go to that address, copy
this character, this one, this one,
this one, and copy it to
a new location and memory.
That does not happen
automatically here for you in C.
It does in some other
languages, those of you
who've programmed in certain
higher level languages.
This just works as you would hope.
And that's one of the benefits
of Python and other languages
that we'll soon see.
But for now, it literally takes
at face value what this is.
Copy the address into this address.
And I'll make that more clear by getting
rid of the string keyword, which,
again, is just a typedef.
This is technically an address here.
So what's being copied is the value of
that address, not all of the characters
that might very well follow it.
So I should make one note too here.
I'm going to start getting
more in the habit of trying
to avoid segmentation faults
because things could go wrong here.
For instance, on line 12 previously,
I was kind of blindly, naively,
dangerously assuming that there will
be at least one character in s or t.
That might not be the case.
If the user just hits Enter,
there's no characters to uppercase.
And so this is reckless of me and
could theoretically create a seg fault.
So I should probably start to be
smarter and say something like this.
If the length of t is
greater than zero, OK,
now it's safe to actually
capitalize the first letter.
And that will decrease the probability
now of those segmentation faults
by just not making any assumptions
about what the human does.
Almost always, your programs will
crash when you've made a mistake,
yes, but the user gives you an input
that you yourself did not expect.
So what does this all
look like in memory?
Well, let's go back to
the big grid, this time
focusing on the copying of values.
And let's do this.
Here's s as in this new program
just declared to be a char star.
Here is where my lower case high maybe
ended up in the computer's memory.
That's probably at 0x123, 124,
125, whatever, something like that.
And that's, of course, what
ends up in s as a value.
When I declare t, I do get a second
variable called t just like before.
But when I copy s into t, what happens?
It's really just literally 0x123.
Whatever the value of s is
is now also the value of t.
And so if we abstract
this away at a high level,
get rid of all of those extra
squares, this is what s and t now are.
They're indeed copies, but
copies of each other, not
copies of the underlying characters.
And so if you follow
those arrows and try
to print them both out after
capitalizing one or the other,
you're going to unfortunately end up
capitalizing not just one of them, s,
but both of them, s and t.
Because literally,
it's the same address.
Any questions, then,
on this visualization?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
Is this pass by reference?
We haven't-- we have not seen
in detail an example like that.
Right now, you're copying by value.
But references will come into play.
And remind me in a bit if I
haven't used that term yet.
But this is just copying things by--
that could have ended poorly, value.
Other questions.
No?
All right, so with this in mind, how
do we actually copy things properly?
For this, we actually need
another building block.
So today, we give you two functions.
One of which is called malloc,
one of which is called free.
And these are used all of
the time by like every piece
of software you and I use on
our Macs, PCs, and phones,
whether it's written in C or
some equivalent other language.
Malloc is for memory allocation.
It's a function that you can use to
ask the operating system, MacOS, Linux,
Windows, anything, for some
number of bytes, 1 byte, 100
bytes, a gigabyte of memory.
You can ask malloc for however
much memory you want in advance.
It will return to you the address
of the first byte of memory
that it found free for you.
Unlike a string, it
is not NUL terminated.
And so the danger with malloc is
that it's on the honor system.
If you ask it for 1 byte or 10 bytes,
you, the programmer, in a variable,
have to remember how many bytes you
requested, 1, or 10, or the like.
Strings do that for you, not when
we're getting now to this low level.
Malloc is just going to give you some
memory and it's up to you to manage it.
Free does the opposite.
When you're done with
some chunk of memory,
you can free it by passing in that same
address and just hand it back to Mac
OS, Windows, or Linux, and
say I'm done with this,
you can let me use this
for something else later.
As an aside, if your computer
has ever frozen, or hung,
the whole thing maybe just
spontaneously reboots,
yet another reason for
a bug like that might
be if you write a program with a
bug that keeps mallocing, mallocing,
mallocing that is asking for
more and more and more memory,
but you make a mistake
and you never free it,
well eventually, the computer is
going to literally run out of memory
and something is going to go wrong.
And that's often when computers freeze.
They're just out of memory.
It has the memory there, but the
program was trying to use too much of it
endlessly.
So this too will be a
mistake that some of us
will surely make in the coming weeks.
But hopefully, you'll
now see the solution.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
And let me propose that
we do the following.
I'll hide my terminal
window for a moment.
And I'm going to introduce
another header file up here.
And I promise there's not going
to be too many more of these.
But this one is called standard
lib.h for standard library.
And in this file are the declarations,
the prototypes for malloc, and free,
and a bunch of other stuff as well.
It lets me now manage my own memory.
So let's focus now on line 11.
Line 11 is where I went wrong before.
Because conceptually, I want
to copy the whole string.
But of course, I'm only copying
modestly the individual address.
So how do I copy the whole darned thing?
Well, what I need to do is this.
When I declare t to be the
address of something in memory,
why don't I set t to be the
address of a free chunk of memory?
So let me ask the operating
system, give me this many bytes.
Tell me what the address is.
And I'm going to store that
in t initially just so I
know where there's free space for me.
So how do I do that?
Well, quite simply, I call malloc,
and then I pass in the number of bytes
that I need.
Now for HI exclamation
point, I think I need three.
Although wait, no.
I really need four because
of the NUL character.
But I don't think I should be
hard coding numbers like this.
Because who knows what the
human is going to type in?
So I can actually use strlen
of s, and then plus 1.
This will ask malloc then
for however many bytes
corresponds to the number of
characters the human typed in plus 1,
for again, the NUL character.
So it's just being smart and defensive
rather than choosing a number myself.
But now all t is is a
pointer, if you will,
to some random chunk of free space.
So there's nothing there yet.
Or there's bits there.
But who knows what value they are?
They're certainly not identical
to what the human typed in.
I now have to do this.
So how can I copy one
string into the other?
Well, let me do this.
Instead of capitalizing something
just yet, let me do this.
How about four int i get 0, i
is less than the length of s.
And then i plus plus.
So I'm going to iterate for
the whole length of the string.
And in here, I'm just going to do this.
The ith character in t should be
identical to the ith character in s.
So I'm just literally copying from right
to left each and every character in s.
And I can trust that
there's enough memory in t.
Why?
Because I asked for
that many bytes plus 1.
Now there's technically a bug here.
I actually should probably do this.
I should do plus 1 here.
Or if you prefer, I should do
less than or equal to the strlen.
But I think it's a little
clear to do the plus 1.
Why do I for the first time want
to go just beyond the boundary of s
and copy 1 more byte?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, I
need the NUL character.
I could technically manually add it
with some additional line of code.
But I might as well just copy it.
Because backslash zero
is backslash zero.
So this time, and
probably only this time,
it's reasonable and correct to go just
beyond the boundary of your string
so you copy the NUL terminating
character so that the computer also
knows where t ends.
And now I think what I can do
a little more safely is this.
Let me go down here and say,
t bracket 0 equals 2 upper
of t, of 2 upper of t bracket 0.
So same line of code as before.
If I actually want to be really
safe, I should probably do this.
So if the strlen of t
is greater than zero.
So there's at least 1 byte there.
OK, now it's safe to blindly
capitalize the first character.
And I think that now
puts me in better shape.
So let me try this now.
Let me open up my terminal,
make copy, dot slash copy.
I'm going to type in hi
exclamation point in all lowercase
crossing my fingers this time.
And now if I zoom in, it
indeed capitalized only t
and not s in this case.
So pictorially, let me switch over here.
Here is, as before, the variable
s pointing at hi in all lowercase.
When I call malloc though,
that gives me a chunk of memory
that I'm going to store
the address in t of.
So if t is some other
variable, as it is in my code,
and there's some other available chunk
of memory, I don't know where it is.
But let's assume as always
it's at 0x456, 457, 458, 459.
So 4 bytes total.
What is now happening?
Well, t is defined as pointing to that.
Because that's what malloc
gives us, the address
of the first byte of the free memory.
And now with for loop, I'm just
iterating over it, copying the h,
then the i, then the exclamation
point, and then for good measure,
the backslash 0 instead.
Questions then on this process here?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: A really good question.
If I omitted in my code the
plus 1 and I didn't do less than
or equal to so that I'm copying the
fourth byte, odds are in this program,
because it's so short, you wouldn't
notice that there's an actual error.
But what could happen is
when I call printf on t,
if there's no NUL byte there, it
might print h, i, exclamation point,
some random values, some random values,
some random values, some random value
until it gets lucky and there
happens to be a 0 byte, a NUL
byte by chance for instance.
So if you don't include the backslash
zero some way, that's going to happen.
And I say some way.
I could even do this.
I could technically just copy the length
of the string s, and at the very bottom
here, I could do something
like t bracket i--
sorry, t bracket strlen of t.
I could do this.
But this is just not necessary.
I could manually add it
at the end of the string.
But again, I'd claim that
it's just simpler to borrow,
that is copy, the one that's
already in s because it's
the same thing at the end of the day.
Good question.
Other questions on this
copying correctly now?
All right.
Is there any room for improvements here?
Well, let me propose
a slight optimization.
This is kind of a
throwback now to week one.
Turns out that arguably, my line 13
here, wherein I have this for loop,
now that I'm doing things
in loops again and again
and using a function like
strlen, this is correct.
It will iterate from zero on up to
the length of i, length of s plus 1.
But it's kind of stupid of me to
write this for loop in this way.
Why?
Well, here's my
initialization on the left.
Here's my condition in the middle.
And in general, calling a
function inside of your condition
is probably not very good design.
Why?
Why is it bad for me to be calling a
function like strlen in this condition
in the middle of my for loop?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, you're
just calling it again and again
for no reason.
The length of s never changes.
So why are you wasting everyone's
time by calling strlen of s
again, again, again, again just to
check this inequality, whether i
is less than that value?
So it turns out if you haven't
discovered this already,
there's a slight
optimization we can do here
that has nothing to do fundamentally
with strings, or pointers, just
with better design.
I can actually define
two variables at once.
I could do this.
Let me remove this whole condition.
And let me add a comma after i
equals 0, set n, or any variable,
equal to the strlen of s plus 1.
And then after the semicolon, just ask
the question while i is less than n.
So it's almost the same.
But notice now my condition in
the very middle of this loop
is at least comparing two static values.
n never changes.
Sorry.
One static value. n never changes.
All that changes is i.
But I'm not foolishly calling strlen,
strlen, strlen again and again.
Why?
Well, how does strlen work?
Similar in spirit to printf,
strlen, given the name of a string,
looks at the first
character and then starts
looking through the entire string
looking for the NUL character.
And we saw this in week two counting
up how many characters are there.
So it's just a waste of
time again and again.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] all the way
at the top so that way, [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID J. MALAN: Totally.
If you wanted to use
n multiple times, you
could absolutely take it out of for
loop, put it right after s is defined,
and reuse n and again and again.
Absolutely.
But in general, consider this.
When designing for loops, even
though modern compilers like Clang,
can actually fix this problem,
this inefficiency for you,
good practice would be don't
call functions unnecessarily,
especially if the answer is
always going to be the same.
All right.
So what else should I
perhaps refine here?
Well, how about I do one last thing
and just comment on what exactly
could go wrong here.
Well, a couple of things.
Well, actually, this is just silly too.
Surely, someone before me in the
world has had to copy a string before.
Surely, there's a function
like called strcpy maybe,
like strcompare, like strlen.
And indeed there is.
So let me propose that we actually
get rid of this whole for loop
and we actually just call a function
called strcpy, no O, just strcpy.
And pass in the destination, which
is t first, and then the source
that you want to copy
into the destination.
And that takes the place
entirely of that whole loop.
So again, I demonstrated the loop first
just to be very pedantic about it.
But that's wasting time.
You're wasting time writing
lines of code you don't need to.
strcpy is what you can use here instead.
And so this has now always existed.
And what more can I do?
Well as one final point, it
turns out that there's actually
things that can go wrong in this
code even besides the string
being too short.
If the human just hits Enter
and there are no characters,
I don't want to blindly capitalize the
first character that doesn't exist.
That's why I added that if condition.
But there's other things
that can go wrong.
And we introduce those to you today.
It turns out that functions like get
string and functions like malloc return
potentially a special value.
And wonderfully confusingly, it's
also called NULL, but with two L's.
All right?
So left hand and right hand weren't
talking so well decades ago.
NUL is a backslash zero.
It's a single character as it always
has been for a couple of weeks now.
NULL is technically a pointer.
It's an address, but it's address zero.
It's like the top left hand corner,
if you will, of your computer's memory
that just nothing is ever
supposed to go in by convention.
So NULL is a synonym for zero.
But it's specifically an address.
Now why is this useful?
Well, suppose that in my code here,
something goes wrong with get string.
Suppose you're being a little crazy and
you type in way too long of a string.
It's not just hi, but it's
like an entire essay of text.
And there's not enough
memory in the computer.
How does get string signal
to the programmer, whoa,
that's way too big of a string,
I can't fit it in memory?
Well, we never told you this.
But all of this time,
it turns out that get
string will return this special value
called NULL if something goes wrong.
So to be really careful now, you
should do something like this.
If s equals equals literally NULL, then
you better exit the program entirely
and return like one, or two, or three
to signify that something went wrong.
Don't go any further.
Similarly with malloc, it's possible if
you ask for way too much memory, that
could fail, especially if you're
asking now for double the memory
after the human typed something in.
So if t equals equals
NULL, then you know what?
Let's also return one,
or some other value,
to just get out before something
crashes or freezes on the human as well.
So honestly, I tend not to do this
always in class because the code just
gets so bloated and complicated.
But you absolutely in practice
need to start doing this.
Otherwise, you will be responsible
for the freezes, and the crashes,
and the reboots that
users in the real world
might actually encounter otherwise.
Of course, if we get to the
bottom of this program now,
I should probably return zero
explicitly, or implicitly, to just
signify that everything is successful.
But there's one other
thing I haven't done.
We introduced malloc.
But what did I claim also existed?
AUDIENCE: Free.
DAVID J. MALAN: So free.
I'm also being a little reckless now.
Here I am not practicing
what I'm preaching.
I'm asking the computer
for memory via get string,
for more memory via malloc,
and I'm never technically
handing it back.
So really what I should be doing
at the very bottom of my program
too is freeing the
memory I've asked for.
So henceforth, it is a rule,
a law, if you will in C,
whenever you allocate memory with
malloc, or certain other functions
as well, you, the programmer, must
free it when you're all done with it.
Now this is a bit of an
overstatement because technically,
when programs quit, they'll
free the memory automatically.
So you're not going to break someone's
Mac or PC because you necessarily
have this bug.
But for programs that are running
all the time, like someone
keeps a Chrome, their browser open,
Microsoft Word, or the like, bad things
will happen if over time you
never, never, never call free
and the program keeps running.
So always get into this habit here.
You do not need the free memory that
comes from get string because the CS50
library automatically frees it for you.
But you, any time you use malloc
henceforth, as you did or I did here,
you must free that by just passing
in the same address you got back.
Questions now on malloc and free?
Questions?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
So free just-- so what does free do?
So free just lets the
computer know that you
are done with that
chunk of memory, which
means that if you have
another line of code
elsewhere, that same
memory might be reused,
and can be used again and again.
And that's going to be necessary
certainly for any long running program.
You can't ask for memory constantly.
You'll eventually run out.
So you need to free it in this way.
Other languages as an aside.
Python, yet another motivation
in a couple of weeks
for it is going to be Python
and certain other languages
manage all this headache for you.
But in C, the goal here is to really
harness these capabilities ourselves.
All right.
So it turns out almost everyone
in the room, everyone in the room,
myself included, you're
going to screw up
when it comes to anything memory
related if you haven't already.
Seg faults are in your future.
But hopefully, there's tools via
which you can detect these things
and fix them proactively, and not just
use printf, or debug50, or rubber duck.
We actually have another tool
we can equip you with now
that will help you find some mistakes.
So let me do this.
Let me close copy.c.
Let me open a program I wrote
in advance called memory.c
that doesn't do anything
really interesting.
But it's going to have two bugs in it.
Notice that I've included
standardio.h as always.
I've also included standardlib.h,
which is necessary now
for anything related to malloc
and or free and the like.
Line six.
It's a little weird what I've done here.
But this is the manual way of asking
for enough memory for an array.
In week two, how do we ask
for memory for an array?
You very simply say, int x3.
And that gives you an array
called x of size three.
But if you do it manually now
using malloc, what you have to do
is use syntax like this.
You call malloc, you ask for three
things times however big an int is.
Now we know it's four.
So you could literally write 12 here.
But this is more generic.
So three times the size of an
integer will give you 12 dynamically.
And what does malloc return?
The address of the
first byte you get back.
Where do I want to put that?
Well, I want to put it in a variable.
Now the variable can't just be
int x because that's a number.
It's not an address per se.
If I want to store this address
in a variable, I could call it x,
I could call it p.
But int star x just means that x is
now the address of a chunk of memory,
specifically a chunk of
memory that's big enough not
for one, but for three ints in total.
All right, now, I'm just
sort of naively putting
our old friend 72, 73, and
33 at the first, second,
and third locations in memory.
But perhaps based on
week two or week four,
I'm clearly screwing up
here in a couple of ways.
Someone want to identify
at least one bug?
What did I do wrong?
AUDIENCE: You start at
zero instead of at one.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
this is now amateur stuff.
I should be zero indexing
not one indexing.
So this has got to be
zero, one, two ultimately.
And other bugs that are maybe
more week four specific?
Other bugs.
It's more subtle.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: I'm not
freeing the memory, right?
So I'm not practicing what I'm
preaching by freeing this memory.
Now suppose these are non-obvious.
And honestly, after an hour or two of
this, this shouldn't be obvious yet.
It will be over time.
How could I find these bugs
with software as opposed
to just staring at the thing,
or asking someone for help?
Well, let me propose this.
Let me first go ahead and run make
memory to compile the program.
And it seems to work-- look fine.
There's no syntax errors at least.
Dot slash memory, notice,
seems to work fine too.
Now this program doesn't
do anything interesting.
There's no printf or anything like that.
But it didn't crash.
There's no segmentation
fault. But that doesn't
mean there aren't bugs
latent in the software.
And this is true, sadly,
of all of today's software.
Chrome, and Microsoft
Word, and other programs
surely have memory-related bugs
that people at Google and Microsoft
haven't yet found.
But there are tools at least to
find the most obvious of those bugs.
And we're going to introduce you
now to a program called valgrind.
So valgrind, it's a
fairly fancy program.
But we'll use it for very simple ways.
We'll look at your code and find
memory errors as it's executing
and try to help you
understand where they are.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
Memory seems to be fine.
I feel like, OK, I'm going
to submit this homework.
All is good.
No error messages.
That's no longer the case.
Now you need to poke a
little more at your code
to see if maybe there's
still some bug there.
So let me do this. valgrind and
then space, dot slash memory.
So just like debug50, you run it
on a program you already compiled.
valgrind, I'm going to run it
on a program I already compiled.
Let me zoom in on my terminal
window so we can see more at once.
And Enter.
All right, the output is crazy
cryptic for no good reason.
There's lots of numbers and equal signs.
It's a lot of clutter.
But there is some
juicy information here.
And let me start from the top down.
Invalid write of size four.
So write means to change a value,
read means to access a value.
And this is, again, esoteric, like
a lot of our error messages are.
But it looks like after a block of
size 12 alloc'd, and then there's
these weird hex notation.
There's some mention of malloc.
But honestly, the juicy part
here is memory.c, line six.
That's probably my fault. So let's
look at line six per that output.
Let me shrink the terminal
window, look at line six.
OK, 12 is now germane.
If you did the mental math
of the size of an n times 3,
12 is somehow involved here.
But line six is now happening next here.
That's where the memory came from.
What is this?
Let me zoom back in.
Where is there invalid
write of size four?
What's perhaps going wrong here?
Invalid write of size four.
What does that mean?
It's like a very technical
way of explaining.
The bug is actually one line later, on
line seven, as we already identified.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Indeed.
And I misspoke a moment ago.
The bug actually arises
here with line nine.
So after the allocation of memory, I'm
somehow writing 4 bytes incorrectly.
And unfortunately, the
onus is kind of on you
to sort of think through
deductively what could that mean.
But I'm clearly touching 4 bytes of
memory in these few lines of code
that I shouldn't be.
And hopefully here as the light
bulb already went off earlier,
oh, I'm not zero indexing.
OK, that must mean that x
bracket three, as you know,
is just too far past
the chunk of memory.
So I'm invalidly writing to
4 bytes that I shouldn't be.
So again, it's not super obvious.
This is not super user friendly.
But at least it does give you
a clue as to where that bug is.
So the fix there is going to be
quite simply to change the one
to a zero, the two to a
one, and the three to a two.
That'll fix that.
But there's still a second error.
And let me look at the
cryptic output again.
Heap summary, some stuff there, OK,
this does not sound good down here.
12 bytes in one blocks are definitely
lost in loss record one of one.
Very arcane output two.
But clearly related to line six
again, our allocation of memory.
Now here too, it's not
obvious what the solution is.
But memory is lost.
AKA, this is a memory leak.
And now the deduction
is kind of up to you.
What is leaking?
Oh, wait.
I didn't call free.
And so the second
solution here is probably
to free x at the very
end of the program.
And if you really want to be
pedantic, you should probably check,
like I proposed earlier,
if x is NULL, just
get out now while you
still can and don't even
touch those other lines of code.
But if you get to the
bottom, return zero.
But really, the takeaways
are, I fixed my zero indexing
of the array to avoid the
invalid write of size four.
And now, I'm freeing the
memory that I asked for.
So there should be no leak lost.
All right, let's try this again.
Make memory, dot slash memory.
No visible errors yet.
But let me now increase my
terminal window again, do
valgrind of dot slash
memory, crossing my fingers,
and now all heap blocks were
freed, no leaks are possible.
I don't see any invalid writes.
There's still a crazy amount of output.
But none of it is erroneous.
It's not bad.
Now I fixed my memory bugs.
And so now my ta, my
tf, they're not going
to find them either
because at least valgrind
has proactively done that for me.
Questions then on valgrind?
Generally, it's those two types
of errors you might trip over.
There's not too much else
in the way of arcane output.
Questions then on this?
No?
All right, well, what
else might be going on?
So someone alluded to this earlier.
What happens when you, for
instance, forget the NULL terminator
or you generally start poking around
memory that you yourself didn't ask for
or looking at values
you didn't put there?
Well, let me go ahead and open this.
Code of garbage.c, in honor of
Oscar the Grouch here of sorts.
And here is a simple program if
I hide my terminal window that
just does something kind of arbitrary.
I first declare an array called scores.
But I made it crazy big, like 1024.
That's a lot of integers.
But so be it.
And then I integrate
over those integers.
And I print each of those scores out.
So I'm using week two syntax here.
But based on this program, what
have I clearly not done that I did
do back in week two?
I've allocated the array, I'm
printing the array, but, but, but--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, I didn't
initialize any values for that array.
Back in week two, we didn't do 1024.
We did like three.
And I typed in three test
scores or something like that.
Here, I'm allocating memory even
more than that just because I really
want to be dramatic with
what I'm demonstrating.
But I'm not initializing
those values to anything.
And so here, it turns
out in C, generally,
if you do not initialize
a variable, or you do not
initialize an array
with explicit values,
there are going to be garbage
values there, so to speak,
remnants of that memory having
been used before probably
by some other function of yours, some
library function, or something else
while your program is running.
Not a huge deal with a super
small program like this.
But for anything sizable,
memory is going to be used,
and unused, and used, and unused that
is malloced and freed again and again.
There's going to be lots of garbage
values in the computer's memory
by default. So if I open my
terminal window here, let
me do make garbage, let me zoom in on
my terminal so we can see the output.
When I run dot slash
garbage, theoretically, I
should see 1,024 integers, but none
of which have been initialized.
Now I'm going to get
lucky with some of them.
And it looks like, wow, OK, a lot
of them are initialized to zero.
And C does in some contexts
initialize memory for you
to zero, at least at the beginning,
but not again and again typically.
But if I start scrolling backwards
in time at this array of size 1024,
where did these values come from?
So just random positive and negative
numbers interspersed among the zeros?
Well, that's because I'm literally
poking around on the random 1,024
bytes of the computer's memory.
Who knows what's there?
So the lesson here is that
garbage values are indeed
this term of R. It means that
a variable that you might have
defined that you might have declared.
If you don't give it an explicit value,
who knows what's going to be there?
And the lesson here
is just don't do that.
Always initialize
variables to something,
either yourself, or
prompting the human for it.
Questions about garbage values.
You'll see them sometimes if you print
things you shouldn't or touch arrays
beyond their boundaries.
All right.
So maybe to make this a little visual
too, it turns out that a lot of things
can go wrong unfortunately
with pointers.
And we've seen some of them.
And here's another program
that's a little contrived.
It's very simple.
And it just is about
manipulating values.
It doesn't do anything
useful per se except
demonstrate some of today's concepts.
So in main here, let me
propose that we declare
a pointer called x that's going to store
eventually the address of an integer
apparently.
Here's another one called y that's
going to store the address of an integer
as well.
Here now, I'm allocating enough
memory to fit one integer.
Now technically, it's four.
We know that.
But size of int just gives
me that answer dynamically.
So it will work on all systems.
And I'm going to store the address
that malloc finds for me in x.
Then I go to x and put
the number 42 there.
All right, why?
The sort of meaning of life, the
universe, and everything here,
but star x, again, just means go to
that address and put a value there.
So why?
I don't know.
But it's just correct at this point.
But what about this line here?
Star y equals 13.
Unlucky in this case.
What's bad about this line here, star y?
It's a combination now of today's
primitives and that point here.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, we didn't ask
the computer to allocate any space.
So y was not initialized with an
equal sign at any point to anything.
And so what is inside y so to speak?
A garbage value.
Maybe it's zero, which isn't bad,
because at least it's nice and simple.
But maybe it's some crazy
large positive number,
or some crazy large negative number.
Either way, odds are
if I go to this address
or that address randomly with star
y, bad things are going to happen.
And so let me go ahead and propose.
Well, let's not do that.
Let's actually do this
instead, assign y equal to x.
And we've done that before.
And then I can go to y now and
change what was a 42 to a 13.
Again, why?
This is just for educational sake.
But for now, this does not crash because
I only de-reference y with star y
after actually giving it a value.
Albeit, a duplicate value similar
to our copy example earlier.
So our friends at Stanford have
put together a wonderful visual.
It's about two minutes long.
Allow me to dramatically
dim the lights, if we could,
and play with what happens with memory
when you do bad things like this.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 1: Hey, Binky.
Wake up.
It's time for pointer fun.
BINKY: What's that?
Learn about pointers?
Oh, goody.
SPEAKER 1: Well, to get
started, I guess we're
going to need a couple of pointers.
BINKY: OK, this code allocates two
pointers which can point to integers.
SPEAKER 1: OK, well I
see the two pointers.
But they don't seem to
be pointing to anything.
BINKY: That's right.
Initially, pointers
don't point to anything.
The things they point
to are called pointees.
And setting them up is a separate step.
SPEAKER 1: Oh, right, right.
I knew that.
The pointees are separate.
So how do you allocate a pointee?
BINKY: OK, well, this code
allocates a new integer pointee
and this part sets x to point to it.
SPEAKER 1: Hey, that looks better.
So make it do something.
BINKY: OK, I'll de-reference the
pointer x to store the number
42 into its pointee.
For this trick, I'll need my
magic wand of de-referencing.
SPEAKER 1: Your magic
wand of de-referencing?
That's great.
BINKY: This is what the code looks like.
I'll just set up the number and--
SPEAKER 1: Hey, look.
There it goes.
So doing a de-reference
on x follows the arrow
to access its pointee, in this
case, the store 42 in there.
Hey, try using it to store the number
13 through the other pointer, y.
BINKY: OK.
Just go over here to y and
get the number 13 set up,
and then take the wand of
de-referencing and just--
[BUZZER SOUND] whoa!
SPEAKER 1: Oh, hey.
That didn't work.
Say, Binky, I don't think de-referencing
y is a good idea because setting up
the pointee is a separate step.
And I don't think we ever did it.
BINKY: Good point.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah, we
allocated the pointer y,
but we never set it
to point to a pointee.
BINKY: Very observant.
SPEAKER 1: Hey, you're
looking good there, Binky.
Can you fix it so that y
points to the same point as x?
BINKY: Sure.
I'll use my magic wand
of pointer assignment.
SPEAKER 1: Is that going to
be a problem like before?
BINKY: No, this doesn't
touch the pointees.
It just changes one pointer to
point to the same thing as another.
SPEAKER 1: Oh, I see.
Now y points to the same place as x.
So wait, now y is fixed.
It has a pointee.
So you can try the wand
of de-referencing again
to send the 13 over.
BINKY: OK, here it goes.
SPEAKER 1: Hey, look at that.
Now de-referencing works on y.
And because the pointers are sharing
that one pointee, they both see the 13.
BINKY: Yeah, sharing.
Whatever.
So are we going to switch places now?
SPEAKER 1: Oh, look.
We're out of time.
BINKY: But--
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: Our thanks
to Professor Nick Parlante
of Stanford for spending
a huge amount of time
doing stop motion animation for that.
But hopefully now, you have a
sense of what too can go wrong
when you misuse a memory in this way.
But at the end of the
day, we really only
have these four new
building blocks today,
like the star operator, the
ampersand operator, malloc, and free.
And really with that, and
the underlying understanding
of what your computer is
doing underneath the hood,
we have this way now to
really manipulate things
in memory, for better or for worse.
And eventually, we'll see
how we can build things.
But we can also now
use today's primitives
to better explain some
things that we've been
asking you to take for granted
over the past several weeks.
So for instance, let
me propose that we do--
one volunteer up here if we could.
Could we get one volunteer who--
you want to come straight up?
Yep, right in the middle.
Come on.
You'll have to take a
left or a right there.
All right.
So we have two empty glasses
here and two colors of liquid.
And we have, let me give you the mic,
if you'd like to say hello to the group.
MOINE: Hello.
I'm Moine.
I'm in [INAUDIBLE] and first year.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
Welcome.
Well, welcome here.
I'm going to go ahead and fill these
two glasses with this colored liquid,
purple here on my right.
Let's fill up a glass here.
MOINE: It's ominous.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yes, don't drink.
And now we'll put some orange in here.
And what we'd like you to do for
the audience, if you don't mind,
is swap the two values.
You've got a purple value
and an orange value.
And I'd like the purple liquid in
this glass and the orange liquid
in that glass please.
MOINE: Can I have another glass?
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, OK.
Good intuition.
But for the microphone--
MOINE: Can I have another glass?
DAVID J. MALAN: So you can.
And just in fact, I
brought one here for you.
Why are you asking for this though?
MOINE: Because if I just pour this
into this, then it'll get mixed up.
DAVID J. MALAN: Right.
So obviously we need like a
temporary variable, if you will.
So here is your temporary variable.
MOINE: And you want--
OK.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
There's-- yeah.
All right so pouring the
value of the orange glass
into this temporary
variable, if you will.
All right.
And now pouring the value of the purple
glass into the former orange glass.
And now--
MOINE: And now this goes back.
DAVID J. MALAN: The temporary value goes
back into the original purple glass.
And now I think we give
you round of applause
for having done that very well.
[INAUDIBLE]
MOINE: Thank you.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
So it should go without saying that in
the real world, that's how you do this.
And in fact, in code, that's pretty
much how you have to do this,
although ask us sometime for
a super fancy way of doing it
without a temporary variable.
It turns out that is
possible using bits.
But for now, let's suppose
that, indeed, this demonstrates
what is the reality in code.
If you want to swap two
values, you need to have
something like a temporary variable.
So for instance, on the screen here
is a-- the beginning of a function
called swap, whose purpose in life is
to, as you just did, swap two values,
call it A and B. So orange
and purple respectively
are now just A and B and
integers to keep things simple.
Well, here is the
corresponding code, if I may,
to what you just enacted as a human.
You declared a temporary variable,
a call temp in this case,
which was like me handing
you the empty glass.
And you stored the orange
liquid in it, AKA A, you then
change the value of the formerly
orange glass to be equal to the purple
by pouring one into the other.
And then you did the opposite there.
Now at the end of this, you still have
a temporary variable that's now empty.
So it's temporary in
literally that sense.
You just don't need it anymore.
But it was necessary along the way.
So I dare say this code
is correct logically.
This will swap two values A and B thanks
to the use of that temporary variable.
Unfortunately though, if I
actually do this in practice,
let me go over to VS Code
here and open a program
I wrote in advance called swap.c,
which does this as follows.
In here, notice I have my prototype
for a swap function at the very top.
And let me scroll down
to the very bottom.
There is that exact same code.
So I'm-- the same code for
swapping two values A and B,
which I'm claiming for now is correct.
Now if I go back up here, what
is main going to do for us?
Main is really just meant
to be a demonstration
of the correctness of your algorithm.
So here I declare on line seven
and eight, two variables, x and y,
being one and two
arbitrarily respectively.
I then on line 10 just print
out what the value of x is and y
is just so I can see it on the screen.
I then call the swap
function on line 11,
and then I literally print the exact
same thing again, I print x and y.
Hopefully, it'll
obviously be the opposite.
So I think logically,
swap is indeed correct.
Let me do make swap and
then dot slash swap.
And I should see x is 1, y is 2,
and then hopefully x is 2, y is 1.
Enter.
But I don't.
And it did work in the sense that
the code compiled, the code ran.
So it's not like some bug in that sense.
But because I don't quite understand
what's going on underneath the hood,
at least as of right
now, or prior weeks,
this code here is indeed
buggy in some way.
But does anyone have an intuition,
perhaps based on today's discussion,
as to why this code, while logically
correct, clearly works in reality,
apparently does not work in C?
Any intuition?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
And to summarize, here's
that term of art I promise.
When you call a function and pass
in two arguments, like a and b,
you're passing those arguments by value.
So copies of those values effectively.
And so when swap is
actually called here--
sorry.
When you pass an x and
y, we call them a and b.
But that's just a convention.
We could call the
parameters anything we want.
What a and b are are indeed the
values of x and y respectively,
but copies of the values.
So this code here is very
successfully, in VS Code too,
swapping the values of a and b.
But as you note, because I'm passing
them in by value, literally one,
literally two, and not by another
term of art, by reference, AKA
by their addresses, swap
has no capability in C
to go to those locations,
swap the actual locations,
just like we did
successfully in reality.
But I think we really
have the syntax already
for solving this if we consider that
really, this is just an issue of scope.
And we've talked a bit
about scope in the past,
whereby scope refers to the
context in which a variable lives.
And generally, I've claimed
that a variable exists
between the most recent curly braces.
And that's pretty much true for
the swap function because a and b,
I now claim again, exist only in
the context of these curly braces.
They have no effect on main up top,
which has different variables x and y.
But we can consider now what's
really going on underneath the hood.
And here's that same picture of
memory, as we've seen in the past.
If we zoom in and see on
these little black chips,
this is a bunch of bytes of memory.
If I create a grid out of
it just to kind of highlight
that we can address each of these bytes,
throw away the plastic circuit board,
and focus only on those bytes,
what's going on underneath the hood
when functions are called in C, which
you've been doing for weeks now?
Well, this rectangle of memory, if
we kind of abstracted away further,
is generally broken up into
different regions or segments,
like I called them earlier.
And different things get
put in different parts
of the computer's memory.
And without getting too
into the weeds, when
you double click a
program on your Mac or PC,
or when you do dot slash
something on a Linux,
you are loading your machine
code into the computer's memory
from the computer's hard drive.
So all the zeros and ones that
compose Microsoft Word, or Chrome,
or whatever are loaded into
the computer's memory or RAM.
And by convention, it's put up top
in the so-called machine code area.
And that's how the CPU has
access to them quickly at that.
Below that are what are
going to be our globals.
So global variables, which we
haven't used very much in C.
But you can declare them outside of
main at the very top of your files.
If you have globals, they end
up up there as well, just FYI.
And then there's this
big chunk of memory
that we saw valgrind mention
indirectly earlier called the heap.
And it's kind of like heap, literally.
It's a heap of memory that
you can use as you see fit.
And the heap is where
malloc grabs memory from.
So initially, there's
nothing in the heap.
It's just a big chunk of free space.
Any time you call malloc, malloc
kind of carves out from the heap area
more and more bytes.
And malloc keeps track
of, essentially, which
bytes have already been allocated.
So initially, it looks empty.
But different bytes,
squares if you will,
keep getting requested again and again
as a program runs thanks to functions
like malloc.
And it grows, if you
will, conceptually down.
So the more and more memory you
request from malloc, it starts up here.
But then the next chunk you
get is down here conceptually.
The next chunk is down here, down here.
So it kind of fills the available
space in the computer's overall memory.
But there's this other chunk
of memory called the stack.
And just like a stack of trays
in Annenberg or a cafeteria,
kind of grow upward, so
does a stack of memory.
And it turns out the stack is
where functions have variables,
and have arguments stored temporarily.
So whenever you call a function
and it has variables inside of it,
or has arguments there too,
this is the chunk of memory,
and the computer's overall block of
memory, that are used for functions.
But any time you call
malloc, it's memory up here.
At the end of the day, they
just had to pick a direction.
Top, bottom, and technically
it's an artist's rendition.
You could circle this thing
around any orientation you want.
But you're just using a finite amount
of memory in this conventional way.
Malloc starts here,
functions start here.
Now you can kind of see
where bad things can happen.
And indeed, one of the other
reasons programs, computers,
can crash is if you ask for way
too much memory from the heap
by calling malloc
many, many, many times,
or if you call way too many functions,
or accidentally per last week,
you recurse infinitely many times,
you might have a segmentation fault.
And that's because you're
using too much stack memory.
So this is bound to be
a problem eventually.
And the onus is on the
programmer to just minimize
the probability of doing that and really
avoid the possibility of doing that
by just checking return values, checking
if malloc or get string return NULL.
Because you can proactively
with conditionals
make sure that these two things
do not collide by just making sure
that you get back non-NULL values.
So let's consider the stack
in the context of swap
and what's really happening here.
And Carter, if you wouldn't mind
helping me animate the screen here,
when I call the main
function of any program,
it is allocated a slice of memory called
a frame at the bottom of this stack.
So if Carter, you want to
go ahead and advance here,
here's the first slice of
memory that will always
be used by main whether it has command
line arguments, or local variables.
It just ends up here in memory.
Suppose now per our swap.c
program that main calls swap.
Well, where does the
memory for swap end up?
Right up here.
So swap had two variables--
two arguments a and b.
And it also had a temporary variable.
So all of those end
up in here in memory.
And if you want to go
ahead and advance again,
Carter, once swap is done
executing, whether it just
returns because there's no more lines
of code, or you explicitly return,
this memory is just
freed up automatically.
You don't call free.
You don't undo malloc.
This just all happens automatically.
It has been since week one.
Now technically, it's still
there even though we've
removed it from the picture.
And there's your first
hint of garbage values.
There's still zeros and ones there.
And they're left in the original--
the previous configuration.
And so the reason you get
random values in the memory
is because even though we
haven't drawn swap here,
there was stuff there a moment ago.
It's going to be there the next
time you use that same memory.
Now let's go ahead and step through
this a little more methodically.
Main has two variables
called x and y one and two.
So let's advance and
represent x as one, y as two
taking up these two chunks of memory.
When we call swap now, swap
gets a new slice of memory
that then gives us three variables,
a and b, technically the arguments,
and temp.
So what happens?
Well, because functions automatically
pass in values by value,
or rather pass in
arguments by value, x gets
copied into a, y gets copied
into b, and then once we
start executing the algorithm,
a la the watered glasses, well,
what happens here?
So if I execute the first line of code,
temp equals a, temp gets a copy of a.
What happens next? a equals b.
So a takes on a copy of b.
And now we do the final swap
in the glass, is b equals temp.
b gets a copy of temp.
Now we don't have to change temp
because it's essentially empty,
although there's the garbage value.
One is always now going to be
there until we reuse that memory.
The important thing, though, is
that a and b have been swapped.
But what obviously has not been swapped,
as is manifest as when swap returns, x
and y are untouched.
Because copies thereof were passed in.
So we need a solution to this problem.
And if we advance one more time, if
you don't mind, let me step over here
but then call you back in a second.
This code here is logically correct.
This is what you did.
But this is now a detail of c.
You can't just swap the things by
value, because you're only changing it
in the scope of the swap function.
But I think if we change it to
this and add some annoying syntax,
we can solve the problem.
Just like you can declare
variables as storing addresses,
you can declare arguments to functions,
AKA parameters, as taking addresses.
This new version of swap means that
a shall be the address of an integer.
b shall be the address of an integer.
And now it gets a little cryptic here.
Temp is the same because it's just
an integer like it was in week one.
Nothing special about temp.
But if you want to get the
value at a, you do star a.
And that goes to the address,
grabs the number one presumably.
If you want to change the value
of a, you go to that address,
you follow the treasure
map to the other mailbox,
and you set it equal to
whatever is at the value of b.
You go to b as well.
Last line, you go to b
now and change it to be
whatever the temporary variable was,
which happened to be the same as a.
So that's where the
final value gets swapped.
But here, there's a lot more
crisscrossing metaphorically
across the stage where
you're going to all
of these different addresses in the
swap function to make these changes.
So if we advance now to the
pictorial version of this,
here's the same story
as before with main.
And x and y are one
and two respectively.
When swap gets called now, notice,
and I'll do it with arrows here,
a is effectively pointing to x,
b is effectively pointing to y.
If we really get into the weeds,
these are actually addresses.
But who cares about the specifics?
It's really just the concept here.
So now what happens?
Int temp gets star a.
Star a means start at a and go there.
Follow the arrow, if you will.
Sort of chutes and ladders style.
And then that's one.
So we put one in temp.
All right.
Star a equals star b.
So let's do it from right to left.
Star b means follow the arrow.
It's two.
And then what do you do?
Follow the arrow.
It's now two because you copy one
to the other from right to left.
And then lastly, star b gets temp.
So start at b, go to b.
And now store whatever
the value is in temp.
So just by having this basic new
syntax of like ampersands, and stars,
and so forth, we can
actually now go to places
and circumvent what is
otherwise a feature of C,
that these variables are locally scoped.
But you can still access things
in other functions as well.
So thank you so much for
helping step through this.
So we now have a
application of this that
explains why now in this version of the
C code this would actually now work.
So in fact, let me go
back to my swap code here.
And let me change the function
ever so slightly in VS Code.
So let me scroll down,
leaving main the same.
And let me change swaps
prototype to taking in addresses.
Let me go to a here.
Let me go to b here.
And let me go to b here as well.
But nothing else changes.
This change here in
particular is enough of a clue
to see that means when you call
swap and pass in two values,
I'm expecting addresses
now, not integers.
But now that I've made this
change, I do need to go up to main
and make one change.
Does anyone have the intuition
for what now needs change
in main so that I pass in x and y by
reference, that is by address rather
than by value or copy?
Yeah, in back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So close.
So on the swap line, it's not star that
I want in front of the x and the y.
It's instead--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: What's the other one?
AUDIENCE: Ampersand.
DAVID J. MALAN: It's the ampersand.
Why?
Because if I want to enable swap
to go somewhere, just like Carter
and I played this game
with the mailboxes,
I need to inform swap of the
address of x and the address of y.
And again, per the
beginning of today's class,
ampersand is the syntax
via which we do that.
So I add an ampersand here to get
the address of x, ampersand here
to get the address of y.
And now this code lines
up with the picture
that Carter just helped us walk through.
And so when I run make swap
here, I have a mistake.
Oh, what did I do wrong?
Not intentional.
But I guess worth pointing out.
I screwed up here.
It doesn't like ampersand
x because of something
on line three, which is
way early into the code.
What did I screw up?
Yeah, in the middle.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so this
is why we-- you should not
copy paste, even though it's necessary
for things like function prototypes.
If I changed swap at the bottom,
I need to change its prototype.
So let me add the star there, add
the star there, or just re-copy paste
it at the top of the file.
Now let me do make swap again.
Let me now do dot slash swap.
And I should now see x is 1, y is 2.
And hopefully, x is 2,
y is 1, which I now do.
So the logic is the same.
The algorithm is the same.
All the week zero stuff is the same.
Except now in week four, you just
have a bit more expressiveness
via which you can tell the computer
exactly what you want to manipulate
and how.
Any questions then on
this technique here?
No?
All right.
Well, when we fix this, there's
still going to be problems.
And just so you've seen
some terms of art here,
this is bad whenever you have two
arrows pointing at one another certainly
if you might use and reuse
more and more memory.
And it turns out there are some terms of
art that might suddenly now make sense,
especially if you've programmed before.
Bad things can happen by this design.
But there's really only
this kind of design
because it's a finite amount of memory.
So at some point, bad things
are going to happen no matter
what if a computer runs out of memory.
So it's not that this
was a poor decision.
It's just sort of a necessary one given
finite amounts of memory in a computer.
But a heap overflow,
so to speak, is when
you actually overflow the heap and touch
memory that you shouldn't up there.
Stack overflow is when you somehow
overflow the stack and touch
memory that you shouldn't down there.
So with that said, these are really
just problems that can happen.
And they're specific
incarnations of what
are generally called buffer overflows.
A buffer, like in the YouTube
sense, is just a chunk of memory,
that in the case of YouTube, stores the
next few seconds or minutes of video.
But generally speaking, a
buffer is just a chunk of memory
that the computer is
using for some purpose,
be it the stack, be it the heap,
be it an array in the computer.
And so buffer overflows are
what happens when you just
have logical bugs in your code.
But with these primitives
now in mind, we
wanted to conclude with
a final revelation.
And that's how some functions
like these here work.
The other thing in the CS50 library,
besides the typedef for quote unquote
"string" is, of course,
all of these functions.
And we give you these functions.
Because honestly in C, it is
hard, it's annoying, it's painful,
it's difficult to get
user input correctly.
It's very easy when you don't
know how much the human is
going to type to write buggy
code when it comes to it.
And indeed, it's really
hard to store it correctly
without accidentally having
some kind of buffer overflow.
So for instance, let me
show you a program here.
I'm going to go ahead and
write this one from scratch.
So let me go ahead and
open a file called get.c,
wherein I'm going to go ahead and mimic
the idea of getting integers manually
without the CS50 library.
So I'm going to include
standardio.h only,
I'm going to define main as not
taking any command line arguments,
and then I'm going to
do something like this.
Give me a variable x with no value yet.
And normally, I would do
something like get int.
But let me take that away.
No more training wheels
for get int either.
So let me just define the int x.
Let me then just print out
something like a prompt.
And I'll just do x colon just to
make it obvious to the human what
we're waiting for.
And now I'm going to use a built-in
C function to get user input.
I'm going to call a function
called scanf, which sort of scans
the user's keyboard for input.
I'm going to scan it for an integer.
So just like printf, I'm going
to use i because I expect an int.
And then I want to
tell scanf where to put
the human's integer from the keyboard.
It is not correct though to say x.
Because if I say x, I run
into the same swap problem.
Scanf.
No function can change the
value of x unless I pass it
not by value, but by reference.
So we're back to our ampersand friend.
And now, it has a treasure map
to the actual location of x,
and can therefore change it.
And so now at the very
end of this program,
let me do something simple like, let's
just go ahead and print out with printf
the value of x, using %i as always
plugging in x, not ampersand x.
This is now week one stuff.
I want to print the
actual integer value of x.
So the only change here is
that instead of using get int,
I'm now using this new function that
as of today exists called scanf.
So let me go ahead and run get.
Make get to create this program.
Dot slash get.
Let's go ahead and
type in a value for x.
50.
Enter.
And it just works.
So it turns out get int is
pretty simple to implement.
However, notice what does not work.
If I type in cat, for instance,
cat gets converted to zero.
And meanwhile, get int, recall,
will re-prompt the user.
If a human does not
type an actual integer,
you get automatically re-prompted.
So that's one of the
features we for CS50
added to get int just to make
your programs more user friendly.
But otherwise, get int
is pretty straightforward
to re-implement using scanf.
Unfortunately, that's
not true for strings.
Because how do you know when you
write your code what word the human is
going to eventually type in?
How long they're greeting, like hi is?
If their name is David, or
Carter, or anything else,
you just don't in advance
how much memory you need.
So how might we do this with strings?
Well, let me go ahead
and declare a string s.
Although, you know what?
There's no CS50 library.
So we do char star s today instead.
And that gives me not a
string per se, but a pointer
that will point presumably to a string.
Ideally, I would use this.
Get string.
But again, we've taken
that training wheel away.
So now that I have a pointer s, suppose
I prompt the human for a value for s,
just like before.
Let me use scanf now and tell the
user that I expect to read a string,
%s from the keyboard, and store it in s.
Now this is subtle.
I don't technically need an ampersand
here, even though I did for an int.
And I would for a float, and a double,
and a long, and a bool, and a char.
Why do I not need an ampersand in
this story to pass by reference?
Because s is--
AUDIENCE: Already [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: It's already an address.
Again, strings are just special.
Strings now are always addresses.
So you don't need to additionally
add an ampersand here.
That's the only subtle difference here.
But now, if I go ahead and print out
at the very end what the value of s is
using %s as before, this program looks
like it's almost the same as the int
version.
But let's do make get.
And OK, so this is not good.
All right, so it doesn't
like an uninitialized value.
So let me make it happy.
I said earlier to always
initialize my variable.
So let's initialize it to NULL so
that at least something is there.
That's your good default value nowadays.
Now if I do dot slash
get, now we're good.
And let me type in something like cat.
OK, cat is not x.
Well, let me try another word.
Maybe it's just cat is wrong.
Dog.
OK, let me try David.
It just doesn't seem to be working.
Moreover, it's printing it as a zero.
What logically, though, is the bug here?
Scanf worked a moment ago for integers.
But it's not working for strings.
And it seems to be forgetting
C-A-T. It's forgetting D-O-G.
It's forgetting D-A-V-I-D. Why?
What's happening here?
Think back to our yellow
pictures of memory.
When I-- yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: It might be
reading just the NULL itself
because s is being initialized to NULL.
And what step have I forgotten
from just a few minutes ago?
What did I not actually
request of the computer?
Actual memory to store the
C-A-T, the D-O-G, the D-A-V-I-D.
There's nowhere have I asked the
computer for some amount of memory.
And so technically, it might be
reading it into some garbage location.
And that's really the problem
here. s is initialized to NULL now.
And so in fact, it is
printing zero as NULL.
But I'm not seeing any
of the other letters
because there was nowhere to put them.
C-A-T, D-O-G, D-A-V-I-D because I didn't
ask for 3 bytes, 4 bytes, 5 bytes,
100 bytes.
There's no use of malloc.
There's no use of an array.
There's no memory allocated for
anything other than the pointer itself.
And this is where, honestly,
life gets hard with scanf.
I could solve this problem
in a couple of ways.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Instead of declaring
s to be a pointer, let
me declare s to actually
be an array of four chars.
And now let me go ahead
and recompile the code.
So make get dot slash get,
and I'll type in cat now.
That now works.
Why?
Well, I'm allocating an
explicit array of size four,
enough for a one, two, three
letters, plus a NULL character.
Here's where to someone's
question earlier, it
turns out that in some
contexts, you can treat arrays
as though they are pointers themselves.
So you will sort of do
the conversion for you.
But for now, just assume that s
is just an array of size four.
And if you pass it into
scanf, that's like a treasure
map that leads to those 4 bytes so
scanf can now successfully fill it
with C-A-T, D-O-G. But
let's try this again.
Let's type in David.
And here, OK, we got lucky.
But I technically touched
memory that I should not.
And in fact, if I typed in a long
enough string, and I don't think
I could do it very easily
by-- without typing
this thousands or hundreds of times.
Still OK.
But you'll notice that it's
forgotten the rest of it now.
So somewhere, we went beyond
the boundary of the array.
And we just don't have enough
storage space for that entire thing.
So what do you do in your program?
If you don't know how long the person's
name or the animal name is going to be,
what do you do?
40?
400?
4,000?
40,000?
At some point, you have to
draw a line in the sand.
And that's why getting user input
is so annoying in a language like C.
And that's why get string exists.
What we do, if you're curious,
is we look at the user's input
and we take baby steps.
We look at it one character at a time.
And every time we see another
character, we actually
call malloc again and say, no.
I need more than 1 byte.
I need 2.
Oh wait, they typed in three letters.
I need 3 instead of 2.
Oh, I need 4 instead of 2.
And we have this crazy
loop essentially that
keeps asking for more and more
memory but by taking baby steps.
And honestly, if you all had
to do that in week one, my God.
We couldn't even write,
hello, world anymore.
And so that's why these training
wheels exist, at least early on.
And that's why in higher level
languages like in Python,
you don't have to do this at all.
It just works as you'd expect.
So what more can we do?
Well, you'll see in problem set
four this coming week, if I open up
an example like this,
phonebook.c, you'll
see that you can manipulate
files now, that you
have a vocabulary for pointers.
It's going to be new quickly.
But here we have an example of how.
I have a program using some
familiar libraries here.
But as I claim in my comment, this
saves names and numbers to a CSV file.
All of my examples thus
far, I type in some words,
I type in some names,
and some phone numbers,
and they disappear because
we only store them in memory.
But if you want to store data in like a
CSV file, Comma Separated Values, which
is like a simple spreadsheet
like Excel, and Apple Numbers,
and Google Sheets can open, you
can actually do this yourself.
So just as a teaser for this
week, here on line nine,
I'm using a new data type.
Not a CS50 thing.
This is a C thing called file.
But if you want to
manipulate files, you need
to use addresses, that is pointers.
So here is me creating
a variable called file
that's going to point to an
actual file on the hard drive,
on the server, or your Mac, or PC.
fopen is going to be a new function
you'll use that will open a file.
And it will return effectively
a pointer there to in memory.
The file name I want to
open is phonebook.csv.
And in this example, it's
going to be a pen mode.
It will keep allowing me to add more
and more names and numbers to this file.
Here are some old get string
stuff because I'm not going
to reinvent get string with scanf.
But down here is a
slightly new function.
It's not printf, but fprintf.
And it turns out it's very easy
to print things not to the screen,
but to a file with fprintf.
And it takes an additional
argument, instead
of starting with the
quoted string, you'll
have to say what file
you want to write to.
And fprintf we'll figure out
how to get the bits into that
file passing in something
like name, comma number.
So if I run this somewhat
quickly here, let me do this.
Let me pre-create a file
called phonebook.csv.
And in phonebook.csv, I'm going to
create a temporary row here, name
comma number just so that
there's something in this file.
And now let me go ahead and do
this and split my screen here.
If I have phonebook.csv on the
right and phonebook.c on the left,
let me compile, make phone book, which
is the C version, dot slash phonebook.
And now I'm prompted
for a name and a number.
So I'll type in David, and
then for instance plus 1-949--
what is it?
4682750.
Enter.
Oh, damn it.
Bug.
Pretend that didn't happen.
I forgot to Enter in the file.
So let's do this again.
If I run the program again,
David, and plus 1-949-4682750,
Enter, it's been saved now to the file.
And if I close this file and I
reopen code of phonebook.csv,
you'll see that the file is persisting.
And if I downloaded this
to my Mac, or my PC,
I could double click the CSV file.
And voila, Excel would open up,
or Apple Numbers, or the like.
And I've actually created
an actual CSV file.
If you're smiling because I keep
repeating my phone number out loud,
I would encourage you to call
or text that number sometime.
It might very well be
an Easter egg of sorts.
But via these functions here
do we have now the ability
to write files input and output.
And among the goals then
for this week, as we'll see,
are to actually play with images
in the spirit of something
like Instagram filters or the like.
And we'll introduce you, for
instance, to a file format called
BNPs, which to come full circle to the
start of class, are just maps of bits,
but more than just single bits for white
and black, but rather colorful patterns
as well.
And will give you images
like this of the Weeks Bridge
here across the river at Harvard.
And you run, after writing
your own code in C,
and understanding how the data is
stored in the computer's memory,
you'll be able to apply your own
Instagram-like filters to make
things grayscale instead,
or sepia in this case.
You can even flip the bits around
so that the thing is a mirror image.
You can blur things further.
Or if you really are
feeling more comfortable,
you can even write code that
finds the edges of the image
and creates works of art like these.
So all that and more
in problem set four.
We will see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]