[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this is week
six, wherein we finally transition
from Scratch to C to, now, Python.
And, indeed, this is
going to be somewhat
of a unique experience in that,
just like a few weeks past--
perhaps, for the first
time-- and now, today, you're
going to learn a new language.
But the goal isn't just to throw
another fire hose of content and syntax
and whatnot at you, but rather, to
really equip you all to actually teach
yourself new languages in the future.
And so, indeed, what we'll do today,
what we'll do this coming week
is prepare you to stand on your own.
And once Python is
passe and the world has
moved on to some other language
in some number of years,
you'll be well equipped
to figure out how
to wrap your mind around some
new syntax, some new language
and solve problems, as well.
Now, you recall, in week zero,
this is where we started--
just saying hello to the world.
And that quickly escalated
just a week later in C
to be something much, much more cryptic.
And if you've still struggled
with some of the syntax,
find yourself checking your
notes or your previous code,
that's totally normal.
And that's one of the reasons
why there are languages besides C
out there-- among them,
this language called Python.
Humans over the decades
have realized, gee,
that wasn't necessarily the best design
decision, or humans have realized, wow,
you know what?
Now that computers have gotten faster
with more memory and faster CPUs,
we can actually do more with
our programming languages.
So just as human languages evolve,
so do actual programming languages.
And even within a programming language,
there's typically different versions.
We, for instance, have
been using version C11
of C, which was updated in 2011.
But Python itself continues to evolve,
and it's now up to version 3-plus.
And so there, too, these things
will evolve in the coming days.
Thankfully, what you're about
to see is "Hello, World!"
for the third time, but it's
going to be literally this.
None of the crazy syntax above or
below, fewer semicolons, if any, fewer
currently braces.
And, really, a lot of the
distractions get out of the way.
So to get there, let's
consider exactly how
we've been programming up until now.
So you write a program in C
and you've got, hopefully,
no syntax error, so you're ready
to build it-- that is, compile it.
And so, you've run make, and then,
you've run the program, like ./hello.
Or if you think back
to week two, where we
took a peek underneath the
hood of what make is doing,
it's really running
the actual compiler--
something called clang-- maybe with
some command-line arguments creating
a program called hello.
And then, you could do ./hello.
So, today, you're going to start
doing something similar in spirit,
but fewer steps.
No longer will you have
to compile your code
and then run it, and then, maybe, fix
or change it, and then compile your code
and run it, and then repeat, repeat.
The process of running
your code is going
to be distilled into just a single step.
And the way to think
of this, for now, is
that, whereas C is frequently used as,
indeed, a compiled language whereby
you convert it first
to 0s and 1s, Python's
going to let you speed things up
whereby you, the human programmer,
don't have to compile it.
You're just going to run what's called
an interpreter-- which, by design,
is named the exact same thing
as the language itself--
and by running this program
installed in VS Code
or, eventually, on your own Macs or PCs.
This is just going to tell your
computer to interpret this code
and figure out how to get down
to that lower level of 0s and 1s.
But you don't have to compile
the code yourself anymore.
So with that said, let's consider
what the code is going to look like,
side by side.
In fact, let's look back
at some Scratch blocks,
just like we did with C in week
one, and do some side by sides.
Because even though some of
the syntax this week and beyond
is going to be different, the ideas
are truly going to be the same.
There's not all that much
intellectually new just yet.
So whereas, in week zero, we
might have said hello to the world
with this purple puzzle
piece, today, of course--
or, rather, in week one, it looked like
this in C. But today, moving forward,
it's going to, quite simply,
look like this instead.
And if we go back and
forth for just a moment,
here, again, is the
version in C, noticing
the very C-like characteristics.
And just at a glance here, in
Python, I claim it's now this.
What do you apparently need
not worry about anymore?
What's gone?
So semi-colon is gone.
And, indeed, you don't need those to
finish most of your thoughts anymore.
Anything else?
AUDIENCE: Backslash n.
DAVID MALAN: So the
backslash n is absent.
And that's curious because we're
still going to get a new line,
but we'll see that it's
become the default.
And this one's a little more
subtle, but now, the function
is called print instead of printf.
So it's a little more
familiar in that sense.
All right.
So when it comes to
using libraries-- that
is, code that other people
have written-- in the past,
we've done things like #include
cs50.h to use CS50's own header
file or standard I/O or standard lib
or string or any number of other header
files you have all used.
Moving forward, we're going to give
you, for this first week, a similar CS50
library--
just very short-term training
wheels that we'll quickly
take off because, in reality, it's
a lot easier to do things in Python,
as we'll see.
But the syntax for this,
now, is going to be
to import the CS50 library in this way.
And when we have, now, this
ability, we can actually
start writing some code right away.
In fact, let me switch
over to VS Code here.
And just as in the past,
I'll create a new file.
But instead of creating
something called .c,
I'm going to go ahead and create
my first program called hello.py,
using code space hello dot py.
That, of course, gives me this new tab.
And let me actually, quite simply, do
what I proposed-- print, quote unquote,
"Hello, world" without the /n, without
the semicolon, without the f in print.
And now, let me go down
to my terminal window.
And I don't have to compile it.
I don't have to do dot slash.
I, instead, run a program called
python, whose purpose in life
is, now, to interpret my code
top to bottom, left to right.
And if I run python of hello.py,
crossing my fingers, as always--
voila.
Now I have printed out "hello, world."
So we seem to have gotten the new
line for free, in the sense where
it's automatically happening.
The dollar sign isn't
weirdly on the same line,
like it once was in week one.
But that's just a minor detail here.
If we switch back to, now,
some other capabilities--
well, indeed, with the CS50
library, you can also not
just import the library
itself, but specific functions.
And you'll see that,
temporarily, we're going
to give you a helper function called
get_string, just like in C, that just
makes it work exactly
the same way as in C.
And we'll see a couple
of other functions
that will just make
life easier, initially.
But, quickly, will we take
those training wheels off
so that nothing is,
indeed, CS50-specific.
All right.
Well, how about functions,
more generally, in Python?
Let's do a whirlwind
tour, if you will, much
like we did in that first week
of C, comparing one to the other.
So back in our world of Scratch,
one of the first programs we wrote
was this one here, whereby
we ask the human their name.
We then used the return value
that was automatically stored
in this answer variable
as an second argument
to join so that we could say
"Hello, David" or "Hello, Carter."
So this was back in week zero.
In week one, we converted it to this.
And here is a perfect example of
things like escalating quickly.
And, again, this is why
we start in Scratch.
There's just so much distraction
here to achieve the same idea.
But even today, we're going to
chip away at some of that syntax.
So, in C, we had to declare
the variable as a string, here.
We of course, had the
semicolon and more.
Well, in Python, the
comparable code, now,
is going to look, more
simply, like this.
So semicolon is, again, gone
on both lines, for that matter.
So that's good.
What else appears to have
changed or disappeared?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [? Do you have ?]
the same type of variable?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So I didn't have to specifically
say that answer is now a string.
And, indeed, Python
is dynamically typed.
And, in fact, it will infer
from context exactly what
it is you are storing in that variable.
Other details that seem
a little bit different?
A little bit different.
What else jumps out at you here?
I'll go back.
This was the C version.
And maybe focus, now, on the
second line because we've rather
exhausted the first.
Here's, now, the Python version.
What's different here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You don't need to worry
about %s or percent anything.
You just have the
variable after [? them. ?]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
There's no %s anymore.
There's no second argument, at
the moment, per se, to print.
Now, it is still a little weird.
It's as though I've deployed some
addition here, arithmetically.
But that's not the case.
Some of you have program before.
And plus, some of you might
know, means what in this context?
So to combine or, more technically--
anyone know the buzzword?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Concatenate.
DAVID MALAN: To concatenate.
So to concatenate is the fancy
way of what Scratch calls joining,
which is to take one string on
the left, one string on the right
and to join them together.
To glue them together, if you will.
So this is not addition.
It would be if it were
numbers involved instead.
But because we've got a string--
Hello comma-- and another string
implicitly in this variable
based on what the human typed in in
response to this get_string function.
That's going to concatenate Hello
comma space, and then, David or Carter
or whatever the human has typed in.
But it turns out, there's going to be
different ways to do this in Python.
And we'll show you a few different ones.
And here, too, try
not to get too hung up
on or frustrated by all of the
different ways you can solve problems.
Odds are, you're going to be picking
up tips and techniques for years
to come if you continue programming.
So let's just give you a
few of the possible ways.
So here's a second way you could print
out hello comma David or hello comma
Carter.
But what has changed?
In the previous version, I
used concatenation explicitly.
And the space here is
important, grammatically,
just so we get that in the final phrase.
Now, I'm proposing to
get rid of that space
to add a comma outside of
the double quotes, as well.
But if you think back
to C, this probably
just means that print,
similar in spirit to printf,
can take not just one
argument, but even two.
And in fact, because of this
comma in the middle that's
outside of the double
quotes, it's hello comma,
and then, it will be
automatically concatenated
with-- even without using the plus,
to whatever the value of answer is.
And by default, just for
grammatical prettiness,
the print function
always gives you a space
for free in between each of the
multiple arguments you pass in.
We'll see how you can
override that down the line.
But, for now, that's just
another way to do it.
Now, perhaps the better, if
slightly cryptic way to do this--
or just the increasingly common way--
is, probably, the third version,
which looks a little weird, too.
And, probably, the weirdness jumps out.
We've suddenly introduced
these curly braces,
which I promised were mostly gone.
And they are.
But inside of this
string here, I've done
a curly brace, which might mean what?
Just intuitively.
And here is an example of
how you learn a new language.
Just infer, from context,
how Python probably works.
What might this mean?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So this is an indication,
because the curly braces--
because this was the way
Python was designed--
that we want to plug in the value of
answer, not literally A-N-S-W-E-R.
And the fancy word here is that the
answer variable will be interpolated--
that is, substituted
with its actual value.
But, but, but-- and this
is actually weird-looking;
this was introduced a
few years ago to Python.
What else did I have to change to make
these curly braces work, apparently?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Drop the f before the--
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
There's this weird f.
And so, it's like part of printf.
But now, it's inside
the parentheses there.
This is just the way
Python designed this.
So a few years ago, when
they introduced what
are called format strings or fstrings,
you literally prefix your quoted string
with the letter f.
And then, you can use
trickery like this,
like putting curly braces
so that the value will
be substituted automatically.
If you forget the f, you're going
to literally see hello comma curly
brace answer closed curly brace.
If you add the f, it's,
indeed, interpolated.
The value is plugged in.
All right.
Questions on how we can just say hello
to the world via Python, in this case.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: If you do this without
the f, what would happen?
DAVID MALAN: If you
do this without the--
AUDIENCE: [? The f. ?]
DAVID MALAN: Without the f?
If you omit the f, you will literally
see H-E-L-L-O comma curly brace
A-N-S-W-E-R closed curly brace.
So, in fact, let's do this.
Let me go back to VS Code here, quickly.
I've still got my file
called hello.py open.
And let me go ahead and
change this ever so slightly.
So I'm going to go ahead and--
let's say from cs50 import get_string.
And that's just the new syntax
I propose using to import
a function from someone else's library.
I'm going to now go ahead
and ask the question--
let's go ahead and use get_string,
storing the result in answer.
So get_string, quote
unquote, "What's your name?"
And then, on this line, I'm going
to deliberately make a mistake here,
exactly to your question.
Let me just say hello comma
answer, and just this.
Now, even though answer
is a variable, Python's
not going to be so presumptuous as to
just plug in the value of a variable
called answer.
What it's going to do, of course, is--
if I type in my name--
whoops.
I typed too fast.
Let me go ahead and rerun that again.
If I run python with hello.py,
type in my name and hit Enter,
I get hello comma answer.
Well, let me do one better.
Let me apply these
curly braces as before.
Let me rerun python of hello.py.
What's your name?
D-A-V-I-D.
And here's, again, the
answer to your question.
Now, we get, literally,
the curly braces.
So the fix here,
ultimately, is just going
to be to add the f there, rerun
my program again with David.
And now, hello comma David.
So this is, admittedly, a little
more cryptic than the ones
with the plus or the comma, but
this is just increasingly common.
Why? because you can
read it left to right.
It's nice and convenient.
It's less cryptic than the %s's.
So it's a new and improved version,
if you will, of printf in C,
based on decades of experience of
programmers doing things like this.
Questions on printing in this way?
We're now on our way to
programming in Python.
Anything?
All right.
Well, what more can we do
with this language, here?
Well, let me propose
that we consider that we
have, for instance, a few other features
that we can add to the mix, as well--
namely, let's say some
data types, as well.
So let me flip over here,
to back to the slides.
And there's different data types
in Python, as we'll soon see.
But they're not as explicit.
As we already saw, by using
a string from get_string,
you don't have to
explicitly state what it is.
But you saw-- recall, in C--
all of these various data types.
And then, in Python, nicely enough,
this list is about to get shorter.
And so, here is our list in C. Here
is an abbreviated list in Python.
So we're still going to have strings,
but they're going to be more succinctly
called strs now, S-T-R. We're still
going to have ints for integers.
We're still going to have floats
for floating point values.
We're even going to have
bools for true and false.
But what's missing, now, from
the list is long and floats.
And why is that?
Or rather, long and double.
We'll recall that, in
C, those used more bits.
Well, in Python, the smaller data
types, previously-- int and float,
themselves-- just used
more bits for you.
And so, you don't need to
distinguish between small and large.
You just use one data
type, and the language
gives you a bigger range than before.
It turns out, though, there's going
to be some other features, as well,
of Python, and these
data types-- one of which
will be called range, another
of which will be list.
So gone will be arrays.
We'll actually use something
literally called a list.
Tuples-- sort of x, y pairs for
coordinates and things like that.
Dicts for dictionaries-- so
we'll have built-in capabilities
for storing keys and values
we'll see, and even a set.
Mathematically, a set is
a collection of values,
but it automatically gets
rid of duplicates for you.
So all of these things, we could
absolutely implement in C if we wanted.
And, indeed, in problem set five, you've
been implementing your very own spell
checker using some form of hash table.
Well, it turns out that, in Python,
you can solve those same problems,
but perhaps a little more readily.
In fact, let me go back
over here to VS Code,
and let me propose that
I do the following.
Let me go ahead and create
a file called dictionary.py.
Let me propose that I try to
implement, say-- problem set five--
our spell checker in Python instead
of C and achieve, ultimately,
the same kind of
behavior whereby I'll be
able to spell check a
whole bunch of words.
So this is jumping the gun
a little bit because you're
about to see syntax will revisit
over the course of today.
But, for now, I've got a new
file called dictionary.py.
And let me begin to create some
placeholders for functions.
We'll see in just a bit that, in Python,
you can define a function called check,
and that check function can
take a word as its input.
And I'll come back to
this in just a moment.
In Python, I can define
a second function
like load, which itself will
take a whole dictionary,
just like in problem set five.
And I'll go ahead and come back
to the implementation of this.
Meanwhile, we might similarly
implement a function
called size, which takes no arguments
but, ultimately, is going to return
the size of my dictionary of words.
And then, lastly, for consistency
with problem set five,
we might define an unload
function, whose purpose in life
is to free any memory that
you've been using, just
to give it back to the computer.
Now, odds are, whether you're
still working on speller
or have finished speller, you wrote
a decent amount of lines of code.
And indeed, it's been,
by design, a challenge.
But one of the reasons for these
higher-level languages like Python
is that you can stand on the
shoulders of programmers before you
and solve very common
problems much more quickly.
So that you can focus on building
your new app or your web application
or your own project to solve
problems of interest to you.
So at the risk of
crushing some spirits, let
me propose that, in Python if you want
a dictionary for something like a spell
checker, well, that's fine.
Go ahead and give yourself a variable,
like words, to store all of those words
and just assign it equal to a
dictionary-- or dict, for short,
in Python.
That will give you a hash table.
Now, it turns out, in
speller recall, you
don't need to worry about
words and definitions.
It's just about
spell-checking the words.
So strictly speaking, we
don't need keys and values.
We just need keys.
So I'm going to save myself
a few more keystrokes
by just saying that, technically,
in Python, using a set suffices.
Again, a set is just a collection
of values with no duplicates.
But they don't necessarily
have keys and values.
It's just one or the other.
But now that I have-- on line one,
I claim the equivalent, in Python,
of a hash table, I can actually
do something like this.
Here's how I might implement
the check function in Python.
If the word passed into this function
is in my variable called words,
well, return True.
Else, go ahead and return False.
Done.
No, wait.
You're thinking, if
anything at all, maybe
we want to handle lowercase instead
of just uppercase and lowercase.
Well, you know what?
In Python, if you want to force
a whole word to lowercase,
you don't have to iterate
over it with a loop.
You don't have to use any of that
C-type functions or anything.
Just say word.lower, and that
will convert the whole thing
to lowercase for parity
with the dictionary.
All right.
How about something like
the load function in Python?
Well, in Python, you can open files just
like in C. For instance, in Python, I
might do open, the dictionary
argument in read mode,
just like fopen in Python.
I might do something like this.
For each line in that file, let me go
ahead and add, to my words variable,
that line.
And then, let me go ahead
and close that file.
And I think I'm done.
I'm just going to go
ahead and return True,
just because I think I'm already done.
Now, here, too, I could
nitpick a little bit.
Technically, if I'm reading
in every line from the file,
every line in the dictionary ends
with, technically, a backslash n.
But there's an easy
way to get rid of that,
just like you might see
with an alternative syntax.
What I'm actually going to do is this.
Let me grab from the current
line, the current word,
by stripping off with reverse strip--
rstrip; a function we'll, again, see--
that just gets rid of
the trailing new line--
the backslash n at the end of that line.
And what I really want to do, then,
is add this word to that dictionary.
Meanwhile, if I want to figure out what
the size is of my dictionary, well--
and, see, you're probably writing code
to iterate over all of those lines,
and you're just going to count
them up using a variable.
Not so in Python.
You can just return the
length of those words.
And better still, in Python, you
don't have to manage your own memory.
No more malloc.
No more free.
No more manual thinking about memory.
The language just deals
with all of that for you.
So you know what?
It suffices for me to
just return True and claim
that unloading is done for me.
And that's it.
Again, whether, you're in the
middle of or already finished,
this might, perhaps,
adjust some frustration,
but also, enlightenment in that this
is why higher-level languages exist.
You can build on top
of the same principles,
the same ideas, with
which you've been dealing,
struggling even this past week.
But you can now express yourself
all the more succinctly.
This one line implements a hash
table for you, and all of this, now,
just uses that hash
table in a simpler way.
Any questions, now, on
this, keeping in mind
that the point, nonetheless,
of speller in p-set 5
is to understand what's really
going on underneath the hood
and, better still, to notice this.
This might seem all rather amazing,
but let me go ahead and do this.
I've actually got a couple of
versions of speller written here,
and I've got a version written in C
that I won't show the source code for.
But I'm going to go ahead and
make that version of speller in C.
And I'm going to go ahead
here and, let's say, split
my window here for just a moment.
And I'm going to go into a
Python version of speller,
really, that I just wrote.
And on the left-hand side here,
let me go ahead and run speller--
the version I compiled in C--
using a big text like
the Sherlock Holmes text,
which has a whole lot of words in it.
And on the right-hand
side, let me run python
of speller.py, which is a
separate file I wrote in advance,
just like we give you speller.c.
And I'll, similarly, run this
on the Sherlock Holmes text.
And I'm going to do my best to hit Enter
on the left and the right of my screen
at the same time.
But we should see, hopefully,
the same list of misspelled words
and the timings thereof.
So here we go on the right.
Here we go on the left.
All right.
A race to see which one wins here.
C is on the left.
Python is on the right.
OK.
Interesting.
Hopefully, Python's close behind.
Note that some of this
is internet delay.
And so, it might not necessarily
be a crazy number of seconds.
But the system is, indeed, using,
if we measure it, a low level.
How much time the CPU
spent executing my code?
C took a total of 1.64 seconds.
That was pretty fast, even though it
took a moment more for all of the bytes
to come over the internet.
The Python version, though, took what?
2.44 seconds.
So what might the inference be?
One, maybe I'm just
better at programming in C
than I am in Python, which
is probably not true.
But what else might you
infer from this example?
Should we, maybe, give up
on Python, stick with C?
No?
So what might be going on here?
Why is the Python version,
that I claim is correct--
and I think the numbers all
line up, just not the times.
Where is the trade-off here?
Well, here, again, is
this design trade-off.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: In order to save the
programmer time, [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
In order to save the
human programmer time,
there's a lot more features built
into Python-- more functions,
more automatic management
of memory and so forth--
and you have to pay a price.
Someone else's code is doing
all of that work for you.
But if they've written some
number of lines of code,
those are just more
lines of code that need
to be executed for you,
whereas here, the computer is
at the risk of oversimplifying
only running my lines of code.
So there's just less overhead.
And so, this is a perpetual trade-off.
Typically, when using a more
user-friendly and more modern language,
one of the prices you
might pay is performance.
Now, there's a lot of smart computer
scientists in the world, though, trying
to push back on those same trade-offs.
And so, these interpreters,
like the command I wrote,
Python technically can-- especially
if you run a program again and again--
actually, secretly, behind the
scenes, compile your code for you,
down to 0s and 1s.
And then, the second, the third, the
fourth time you run that program,
it might very well be faster.
So this is a bit of a
head fake here, in that
I'm running them once and only once.
But we could get benefit
over time if we kept
running the Python
version again and again
and, perhaps, fine-tune the performance.
But, in general, there's
going to be this trade-off.
Now, would you rather
spend the 60 seconds
I wrote implementing a spell
checker or this 6 hours,
16 hours you might be or have
spent implementing the same in C?
Probably not.
For productivity's sake, this is why
we have these additional languages.
Just for fun, let me flip over to
another screen here and open up
a version of Python that's
actually-- in just a second--
on my own Mac instead
of the cloud so that
I can actually do
something with graphics.
So, here, I just have a black and white
terminal window on my very own Mac.
And I've pre-installed Python,
just like we've done so
for VS Code in the cloud for you.
Notice that I've got this photo of,
perhaps, one of your favorite TV
shows here, with the cast of The Office.
Notice all of the faces
in this image here.
And let me propose that we try to
find one face in the crowd, CSI-style,
whereby we want to find, perhaps,
the Scranton Strangler, so to speak.
And so, here is an example
of this guy's face.
Now, how do we go about finding
this specific face in the crowd?
Well, our human eyes,
obviously, can pluck him out,
especially if you're
familiar with the show.
But let me go ahead and do this instead.
Let me go ahead and
propose that we run code
that I already wrote in advance here.
This is a Python program
with more lines of code
that we won't dwell on for today.
But it's meant to
motivate what we can do.
From a pillow library, implying
a Python image library,
I want to import some
type of information,
some feature called image so
that I can manipulate images,
not unlike our own problem set four.
And this is powerful.
in?
Python.
You can just [MIMICS EXPLOSION]
import face recognition as a library
that someone else wrote.
From there, I'm going to
create a variable called image.
I'm going to use this face
recognition libraries.
load_image_file function.
It's a little verbose, but it's
similar in spirit to fopen.
And I'm going to open office.jpeg.
I'm going to, then, declare a second
variable called face_locations, plural,
because what I'm expecting to get back,
per the documentation for this library,
is a list of all of the faces'
locations that are detected.
All right.
Then, I'm going to iterate over each
of those faces using a for loop,
that we'll see in more detail.
I'm going to, then, infer what the
top, right, bottom, and left corners
are of that face.
And then, what I'm going to do
here is show that face alone,
if I've detected the face in question.
So let me go ahead,
here, and run detect.py.
And we'll see not just the
one face we're looking for.
But if I run Python of detect.py,
it's going to do all of the analysis.
I'll see a big opening here,
now, of all of the faces that
were detected in this here program.
[CHUCKLES] OK, some better
than others, I guess,
if you zoom in on catching someone.
Typical Angela.
If you want to, now,
find that one face, I
think we need to train
the software a bit more.
So let me actually open
up a second program called
recognize that's got more going on.
But let me, with a wave
of a hand, point out
that I'm now loading not only the
office.jpeg, but also toby.jpeg
to train the algorithm to
find that specific face.
And so, now, if I run this
second version-- recognize.py--
with Python of recognize.py--
hold my breath for just a moment;
it's analyzing, presumably,
all of the faces--
you see the same, original photo.
But do you see one such
face highlighted here?
This version of the code
found Toby, highlighted him
with the screen and, voila,
we have face recognition.
So for better or for worse,
this is what's happening,
increasingly societally, nowadays.
And honestly, even though I
didn't write the code live--
because it's a good dozen or more
lines of code-- it's not terribly many.
And literally, all the
authorities-- all we have to do
is import face recognition
and, voila, you have access.
These technologies are here already.
But let's consider, for just a moment--
how did we find Toby?
How might that library--
even though we're not going to
look at its implementation details,
how does it find Toby
and distinguish him
from all of these other
faces in the crowd?
What might it be doing, intuitively.
Think back even to p-set four, what you,
yourselves, have access to, data-wise.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [? Since ?] we gave it
an image of Toby's face before,
it probably looks at are the pixels in
one area the same as in another area
and allots it to the same--
from that reference image to this image.
And then, it's going to say, hey,
a lot of the similar consult ranges
are here and here, so
we can safely guess
that this is the same [? person. ?]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
And to summarize for the camera here, we
have trained the software, if you will,
by giving it a photo of Toby's face.
So, by looking for the same
or, really, similar pixels--
especially if it's a slightly
different image of Toby--
we can, perhaps, identify
him in the crowd.
And what really is a human face?
Well, at the end of
the day, the computer
only knows it as a pattern
of bits or, really,
at a higher level, a pattern of pixels.
So maybe a human face is,
perhaps, best defined, in general,
as two eyes and a nose and a mouth that,
even though all of us look similar,
structurally, odds are, the measurement
between the eyes and the nose
and the width of the mouth,
the skin tone and all
of these other physical
characteristics are patterns
that software could, perhaps,
detect and then look, statistically,
through the image, looking
for the closest possible match
to these various measurement shapes,
colors and sizes and the like.
And, indeed, that
might be the intuition.
But what's powerful here, again, is
just how easy and readily available
this technology now is.
All right.
So with that said, let's
propose to consider what more we
can do with Python itself, get back
to the fundamentals, so that you,
yourselves can start to implement
something along those same lines.
So besides having access to
things like a get_string function,
the CS50 library provides a few
other things, as well-- namely, in C,
we had these.
But in Python, we're
going to have fewer.
In Python, our library, short-term, is
going to give you not only get_string,
but also get_int and get_float.
Why?
It's actually just
annoying, as we'll soon
see, to get back an integer
or a float from a user
and just make sure that it's an int and
a float and not a word like cat or dog,
or some string that's
not actually a number.
Well, we can import not just the
specific function, get_string,
but we can actually import all
of these functions one at a time,
like this, as we'll soon see.
Or you can even, in Python, import
specific functions from a file.
One of you asked a while back, when
you include something like CS50.h
or standard I/O .h, you're actually
getting all of the code in that file,
which, potentially, can add bulk
to your own program or time.
In this case, when you import
specific functions from Python,
you can be a little
more narrowly precise
as to what it is you
want to have access to.
All right.
So, with that said,
let's go ahead and see
what conditionals look like in Python.
So in the left-hand side
again, here, we'll see Scratch.
So it's just a contrived example
asking if x is less than y, then,
say, x is less than y.
In C, it looked like this.
In Python, now, it's going
to look like this instead.
And here's before in
C, and here's after.
And just to call out a few of
the obvious differences, what
has changed, in Python, for
conditionals, it would seem?
What's the difference?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: There's a
lack of curly braces.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So there's no more curly braces.
And, indeed, you don't use those.
What appears to be taking their
place, if you might infer?
What seems to have taken their place?
What do you think?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So the colon at
the start of this line, here.
But also even more important,
now, is this indentation below it.
So some of you, and we know
this from office hours,
have a habit of indenting
everything on the left, right?
And it's just this
crazy mess to look at.
Frustrating for you, surely.
But C and Clang is
pretty tolerant when it
comes to things like
white space in a program.
Python, uh-uh.
They realized, years ago, that-- let's
help humans help themselves and just
require standard indentation.
So four spaces would be the norm here.
But because it's indented
below that colon, that,
indeed, indicates that this,
now, is part of that condition.
Something else has gone missing,
versus C, in this conditional.
What else is a little simplified?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So no more parentheses.
You can still use them,
especially when you need to,
logically, to do order of
operations, like in math.
But in this case, if
you just want to ask
a simple question, like if x less
than y, you can just do it like that.
How about when you have an if else?
Well, this is almost the same,
here, with these same changes.
In C, this looked like this.
And it's starting to get
a bit bulky-- at least,
if we use our curly braces in this way.
In Python, we can tighten
things up further, even though,
strictly speaking, in C, you don't
always need the curly braces.
But here, gone are the
parentheses, again.
Gone are the curly braces.
Indentation is consistent, and
we've just added another keyword,
else, with the colon.
But no more semicolons, as well.
How about something larger,
like this, in if, else, if else?
This one's a little curious.
But in C, it looked like
this-- if, else, if else.
In Python, it now looks like this.
And there's, perhaps,
one curiosity here that,
honestly, all these years
later, I still can't
remember how to spell it half the time.
What's weird about this?
What do you spot as different?
Yeah, over here.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Instead of else if, it's elif.
Why?
[SIGHS] Apparently, else
space if was just too many
keystrokes for humans to type, so
they condensed it into this way.
Probably means it's a little
more distinguishable, too,
for the computer between
the if and the else, too.
But just something to remember, now.
It's, indeed, elif and not else if.
All right.
So what about variables in Python?
I've used a couple of
them already, but let's
distill exactly how you define
and declare these things, as well.
So, in Scratch, if we wanted to
create a variable called counter
and set it equal, initially,
to 0, we would do something
like this-- specify that it's an
int, use the assignment operator,
end the thought with a semicolon.
In Python, it's just simpler.
You name the variable, use
the assignment operator,
as before, you set it equal
to some value, and that's it.
You don't mention the type.
You don't mention the
semicolon or anything more.
What if you want to change
a variable, like counter,
by 1-- that is, incremented by 1?
You have a few different ways here.
In C, we saw syntax like this, where you
can say counter equals counter plus 1,
which, again, feels illogical.
How can counter equal counter plus 1?
But, again, we read this code, really,
right to left, updating its value by 1.
In Python, it's almost the same.
You just get rid of the semicolon.
So that logic is there.
But recall, in C, we could do
something slightly different
that we can also do in Python.
In Python, you can
also, more succinctly,
do this-- plus equals, and then,
whatever number you want to add.
Or you can even change it
to subtract, if you prefer.
Sadly, gone is something you've
probably typed a whole lot.
What was the other way you can add 1?
AUDIENCE: Plus plus?
DAVID MALAN: Plus plus is
no more, sadly, in Python.
Just too many ways to do the
same thing, so they got rid of it
in favor of just this syntax, here.
So keep that in mind, as well.
What about loops, when you want to do
something in Python again and again.
Well, in Scratch, in week zero,
here's how we meowed three times,
specifically.
In C, we had a couple
of ways of doing this.
This was the more mechanical approach,
where you create a variable called i.
You set it equal to 0.
You then do while i is
less than 3, the following.
And then, you, yourself
increment i again and again.
Mechanical in the sense that you
have to implement all of these gears
and make them turn yourself, but
this was a correct way to do that.
In Python, we can still
achieve the same idea,
but we don't need the int keyword.
We don't need any of the semicolons.
We don't need the parentheses.
We don't need the curly braces.
We can't use the plus
plus, so maybe that's
a minor step backwards if you're a fan.
But otherwise, the code, the
logic is exactly the same.
But there's other ways to
achieve this same idea.
Recall that, in C, we
could also do this.
You could use a for loop, which
does exactly the same thing.
Both are correct.
Both are, arguably, well-designed.
It's to each their own when it
comes to choosing between these.
In Python, though, we're going to
have to think through how to do this.
So you don't do the same for loop as
in C. The closest I could come up with
is this, where you say for i--
or whatever variable you want to
do the counting-- in-- literally
the preposition-- and then,
you use square brackets here.
And we've used square brackets
before, in the context
of arrays and things like that.
And the 0, 1, 2 looks like an array, in
some sense, even though we've also seen
arrays with curly braces.
But these square brackets,
for now, denote a list.
Python does not have arrays.
An array is that contiguous chunk
of memory, back to back to back,
that you have to resize somehow
by moving things around in memory,
as per two weeks ago.
In Python, though, you can just create
a list like this using square brackets.
And better still, as we'll see,
you can add or even remove things
from that list down the road.
This, though, is not going
to be very well-designed.
This will work.
This will iterate in Python three times.
But what might rub you the
wrong way about this design,
even if you've never seen Python before?
How does this example not end well?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Making a
large list [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
If you're making a large list, you have
to type out each one of these numbers,
like comma 3, comma 4, comma 5, comma,
dot, dot, dot, 50 comma, dot, dot, dot,
500.
Like, surely, that's
not the best solution,
to have all of these
numbers on the screen,
wrapping endlessly on the screen.
So, in Python, another way to do
this would be to use a function
called range, which, technically,
is a data type onto itself.
And this returns to you as
many values as you ask for it.
range takes some other
arguments, as well.
But the simplest use case here is, if
you want back the numbers 0, 1, and 2--
a total of three values--
you say, hey, Python, please
give me a range of three values.
And by default, they start at 0 on up.
But this is more
efficient than it would be
to hard code the entire list at once.
And the best metaphor I could come
up with is something like this.
Here, for instance, is a deck of cards.
This is normal, human size, and
there's presumably 52 cards here.
So writing out 0 through 51 on
code would be a little ridiculous
for the reasons you know.
And it would just be very unwieldy
and ugly and wrapping in all of that.
It would be the virtual equivalent of me
handing you all of these cards at once
to just deal with.
And, right, they're not that big, but
it's a lot of cards to hold on to.
It requires a lot of memory or
physical storage, if you will.
What range does, metaphorically,
is, if you ask me for three cards,
I hand you them one at a time, like
this, so that, at any point in time,
you only have one number
in the computer's memory
until you're handed the next.
The alternative-- the
previous version would
be to hand me all three cards at
once, or all 52 cards at once.
But in this case, range is
just way more efficient.
You can do range of 1,000.
That's not going to give you a
list of 1,000 values all at once.
It's going to give you
1,000 values one at a time,
reducing memory significantly
in the computer itself.
All right.
So, besides this, what about doing
something forever in Scratch?
Well, we could do this, literally, with
a forever block, which didn't quite
exist in C. In C, we had to hack
it together by saying while True--
because True is, by definition,
T-R-U-E, always true.
So this just deliberately
induces an infinite loop for us.
In Python, the logic's
going to be almost the same.
And infinite loops in
Python tend to actually
be even more common because you can
always break out of them, as you could
in C. In Python, it looks like this.
And this is slightly more subtle,
but gone are the curly braces.
Gone are the parentheses.
But ever so slight difference, too?
A capital T for True and it's
going to be a capital F for False.
Stupid little differences.
Eventually, you're going to
mistype one or the other.
But these are the kinds of
things to keep an eye out
and to start recognizing in your
mind's eye when you read code.
Questions, now, on any
of these building blocks?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: In the for loop, was i
set to 0 once for [? every loop? ?]
DAVID MALAN: In the for loop, was i--
it was set to 0 on the first
iteration, then 1 on the next,
then 2 on the third.
And the same thing for range.
It just doesn't use up as
much memory all at once.
Other questions, now, on any of
these building blocks of Python?
All right.
Well, let's go ahead and build
something a little more than hello.
Let me propose that, over
here, we implement, maybe,
the simplest of calculators here.
So let me go back to VS Code
here, open my terminal window
and open up, say, a file
called calculator.py.
And in calculator.py,
we'll have an opportunity
to explore some of
these building blocks,
but we'll allow things to
escalate pretty quickly
to more interesting examples so that
we can do the same thing, ultimately,
as well.
And, in fact, let me
go ahead and do this.
Moreover, I've brought some
code with me in advance.
For instance, something
called calculator0.c,
from the first week of
C. And let me go ahead
and split my window here, in fact, so
that I can now do something like this.
Let me move this over here, here.
Calculator.py.
So now, I have, on the left
of my screen, calculator.c--
or calculator0.c because
that's the first version I
made-- and calculator.py on the right.
Let me go ahead and implement,
really, the same idea here.
So on the right-hand side,
the analog of including cs50.h
would be from cs50 import get_int if
I want to, indeed, use this function.
Now, I'm going to go
ahead and give myself
a variable x without defining its type.
I'm going to use this
get_int function and I'm
going to prompt the user
for x, just like in C.
I'm, then, going to go ahead and
prompt the user for another int,
like y, here, just like in C. And at
the very end, I'm going to go ahead
and do print x plus y.
And that's it.
Now, granted, I have some comments
in my C version of the code,
just to remind you of
what each line is doing.
But I've still distilled this
into six lines-- or, really, four
if I get rid of the blank line.
So it's already, perhaps,
a bit tighter here.
It's tighter because something really
important, historically, is missing.
What did I seem to omit altogether
that we haven't really highlighted yet?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
The main function is gone.
And in fact, maybe you took
for granted that it just
worked a moment ago when I
wrote hello, but I didn't
have a main function in hello, either.
And this, too, is a feature of Python
and a lot of other languages, as well.
Instead of having to adhere to
these long-standing traditions,
if you just want to write code
and get something done, fine.
Just write code and get something
done without, necessarily,
all of this same boilerplate.
So whatever is in your Python file--
left indented, if you will, by default--
is just going to be the code that
the interpreter runs, top to bottom,
left to right.
Well, let me go ahead, now,
and run code like this.
Let me go ahead and open
back up my terminal window,
run python of calculator.py.
And I'll do x is 1, y is 2.
And as you might expect, it gives me 3.
Slight aesthetic bug.
I put my space in the wrong place here.
So that's a newbie mistake.
Let me fix that, aesthetically.
Let me rerun python of calculator.py.
Type in 1.
Type in 2.
And, voila, there is now
my same version again.
But let me propose, now, that we
get rid of this training wheel.
We don't want to keep
taking one step forward
and then two steps back by
adding these training wheels,
so let me instead do this.
In my version of calculator.py,
suppose that we take away, already,
the training wheel that is the
CS50 library here and let me,
instead, then, use just Python's
built-in function called
input, which literally does just that.
It gets input from the user and it
stores it, as before, in x and y.
So this is not CS50-specific.
This is real-world Python programming.
Well, let me go ahead and run,
again, python of calculator.py.
And, of course, if x is 1 and y is 2,
x plus y should, of course, still be 3.
It's apparently 12, according to Python,
until CS50's library gets involved.
But does anyone want to
infer what just went wrong?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: We're always [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
The input function, by design,
always returns a string of text.
After all, that's what
the human typed in.
And even though, yes, I typed
the number keys on the keyboard,
it's still coming back as all text.
Now, maybe we should use
like a get_int function.
Well, that doesn't exist in Python.
All you can do is get textual
input-- a string from the user.
But we can convert one to the other.
And so, a fix for this so that we
don't accidentally concatenate--
that is, join x plus y together--
would be to do something like this.
Let me go back to my Python code, here.
And whereas, in C, we could
previously do typecasting--
we can convert one type to another--
that generally wasn't the case when
you were doing something complex,
like a string to an int.
You could do a char to
an int and vise versa.
But for a string, recall, there was a
special function in the C-type library
called a to I, like Ascii to integer.
That's the closest analog, here.
And, in fact, the way
to do this in Python
would be to use a function
called int, which,
indeed, is the name
of the data type, too,
even though I have not
yet had to type it.
And I can convert the
output of the input function
automatically from a string
immediately to an int.
And now, if I go back to my terminal
window, rerun python of calculator.py
with 1 and 2 for x and y,
now, I'm back in business.
So that, then, is, for
instance, what the CS50 library
does, if temporarily this week, is it
just deals with the conversion for you.
And, in fact, bad things could
happen if I type the wrong thing,
like dog or cat instead of a number.
But we'll cross that bridge
in just a moment, as well.
All right.
What if we do something slightly
different, now, with our calculator.
Instead of addition,
let's do division instead.
So z equals x divided by y, thereby
giving me a third variable z.
Let me go ahead and run
python of calculator.py again.
I'll type in 1.
I'll type in 3 this time.
And what problem do you
think we're about to see?
Or is it gone?
What happened when I did this in
C, albeit with some slightly more
cryptic syntax, when I divided
one number, like 1 divided by 3?
Anyone recall?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You would round
to the nearest integer.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So it would round down
to the nearest integer,
whereby you experience truncation.
So if you take an integer
like 1, you divide it
by another integer like
3, that technically
should be 0.33333, infinitely long.
But in C, recall, you
truncate the value.
If you divide an int
by an int, you get back
an int, which means you get only
the integer part, which was the 0.
Now, Python actually handles this
for us and avoids the truncation.
But it leaves us, still, with one other
problem here, which is going to be,
for instance, not necessarily
visible at a glance.
This looks correct.
This has solved the problem in
C. So truncation does not happen.
The integers are automatically converted
to a float-- a floating point value.
But what other problem did we
trip over, back in week one?
What else got a little dicey when
dealing with simple arithmetic?
Anyone recall?
Well, the syntax in Python
is a little different,
but let me go ahead and do this.
It turns out, in Python, if you want to
see more significant digits than what
I'm seeing here by default, which
is a dozen or so, let me go ahead
and print out z as follows.
Let me first print out a format
string because I want to format z
in an interesting way.
And notice, this would have
no effect on the difference.
This is just a format string that, for
no compelling reason at the moment,
is interpolating z in those curly braces
using an fstring or format string.
If I run this again with 1 and 3, we'll
see, indeed, the exact same thing.
But when you use an
fstring, you, indeed,
have the ability to format
that string more precisely.
Just like with %f in Python, you could
start to fine-tune how many significant
digits you see--
in C, rather.
In Python, you can do the same, but
the syntax is a little different.
If you want the computer to
interpolate z and show you
50 significant digits--
that is, 50 numbers
after the decimal point--
syntax is similar to C,
but it's a little different.
You literally put a colon
after the variable's name.
dot 50 means show me the decimal point
and, then, 50 digits to the right,
and the f just indicates please
treat this as a floating point value.
So now, if I rerun
python of calculator.py,
divide 1 by 3, unfortunately, Python has
not solved all of the world's problems
for us.
This, again, was an example
of floating point imprecision.
So that problem is still latent.
So just because the world has
advanced, doesn't necessarily
mean that all of our problems
from C have gone away.
There are solutions using third-party
libraries for scientific calculations
and the like.
But out of the box, floating point
imprecision is still an issue.
Meanwhile, there was
one other problem in C
that we ran into involving numbers,
and that was this-- integer overflow.
Recall that an integer
in C only took up,
what, 32 bits typically, which meant
you could count as high as 4 billion
or, maybe, if you're doing positive
and negatives, as high as 2 billion,
after which, weird things would happen.
The number would go to 0 or negative or
it would overflow or wrap back around.
Well, wonderfully, in
Python, they did, at least,
address this, whereby you can
count as high as you want.
And Python will just use more
and more and more and more
bits and bytes to store really big
numbers so integer overflow is not
a thing.
With that said, Python is limited
to how many digits it will show you
on the screen at once as a string.
But, mathematically, your
math will be correct now.
So we've taken a couple of steps
forward, one step sideways.
But, indeed, we have solved
some of our problems here.
All right.
Questions, now, on any of
these examples thus far?
Question?
All right.
Well, how about another problem
that we encountered in C. Let's
revisit it here in Python, as well.
So let me go ahead and,
on the left-hand side
here, let me open up a file called,
say, compare3.c on the left,
and let me go ahead and create a new
file on the right called compare.py.
Because recall that bad
things happened when
we needed to compare two
values in C. So on the left,
here, is a reminder of
what we once did in C,
whereby, if we want to compare values,
we can get an int in C, store it in x.
A get_int in C, store it in y.
We then have our familiar,
conditional logic here,
just printing out if x
x less than y or not.
Well, we can certainly do the
same thing, ultimately, in Python
by using some fairly familiar syntax.
And let's just demonstrate
this one quickly.
Let me go over here, too.
I'll do from cs50 import get_int,
even though I could do this, instead,
with the input function itself.
x equals get_int, and I'll
prompt the user for that.
y equals get_int, and I'll
After that, recall that I
can say, without parentheses,
if x is less than y, then print out,
without the f, "x is less than y."
Then, I can go ahead and say else if
x is greater than y, I can print out,
quote unquote, "x is greater than y."
If you'd like to interject
now, what did I screw up?
Anyone?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Elif.
DAVID MALAN: Elif, right?
So elif x is greater than y,
else-- this part's the same-- print
"x is equal to y."
There's no new logic going on here.
But, at least syntactically,
it's a little cleaner.
Indeed, this program is only 11 lines
long, albeit without any comments.
Let me go ahead and run
python of compare.py.
Let's see.
Is 1 less than 2?
Indeed.
Let's run it again.
Is 2 less than 1?
No, it's greater than.
And let's, lastly,
type in 1 and 1 twice.
x is equal to y.
So we've got a pretty side-by-side,
one-to-one conversion here.
Let's do something a little
more interesting, then.
In C, how about I open, instead,
something where we actually
compared for a purpose?
So if I open up, from
earlier in the course--
how about agree.c, which prompt the
user to agree to something or not?
And let me code up a new
version here, called agree.py.
And I'll do this on the
right-hand side, with agree.py.
But on agree.c on the left--
notice that this is how we
did this yes-no thing in C--
we compared c, a character,
equal to single quotes 'Y'
or equal to single quotes little 'y.'
And then, the same thing for n.
Now, in Python, this
one is actually going
to be a little bit different, here.
Let me go ahead and, in
the Python version of this,
let me do something like this.
We'll use get_string.
Actually, no.
We'll just use input in this case.
So let's do s equals input.
And we'll ask the user the same thing--
Do you agree, question mark.
Then, let's go ahead and
say, if s equals equals--
how about Y?
Huh.
How do I do this?
Well, a few things.
Turns out, I'm going to do
this-- s equals equals little y.
Then, I'm going to go ahead
and print out "Agreed."
And elif s equals equals capital
N or s equals equals lowercase n,
I'm going to go ahead and
print out "Not agreed."
And I claim, for the moment,
that this is identical, now,
to the program on the left
in C. But what's different?
So we're still doing the same
kind of logic, these equal equals
for comparing for equality.
But notice that, nicely enough, Python
got rid of the two vertical bars,
and it's just literally the word "or."
If you recall seeing ampersand ampersand
to express a logical and in C, [GRUNTS]
you can just write,
literally, the word "and."
And so, here's a hint of why
Python tends to be pretty popular.
People just like that it's
a little closer to English.
There's a little less of
the cryptic syntax here.
Now, this is correct, as
this code will now work.
But I've also used double
quotes instead of single quotes,
and I also omitted, a few
minutes ago, from my list of data
types in Python the word "char."
In Python, there are no chars.
There are no individual characters.
If you want to manipulate an individual
character, you use a string--
that is to say, a str--
of size 1.
Now, in Python, you can use
single quotes or double quotes.
I'm deliberately using
double quotes everywhere,
just for consistency with
how we treat strings in C.
It's pretty common, though,
to use single quotes instead,
if only because, on most
keyboards, you don't
have to hold the Shift key anymore.
Humans have really started
to optimize just how
quickly they want to be able to code.
So using a single quote
tends to be pretty popular
in Python and other languages, as well.
They are fundamentally the same,
single or double, unlike in C,
where they have meaning.
So this is correct, I claim.
And, in fact, let me
run this real quick.
I'll open up my terminal window here.
Let me get rid of the version
in C and run python of agree.py.
And I'll type in Y. OK.
I'll run it again and type in little y.
And I'll stipulate it's going
to work for no, as well.
But this isn't necessarily
the only way we can do this.
There are other ways to
implement the same idea.
And in fact, I can go
about doing this instead.
Let me go back up to my code here.
And we saw a hint of this earlier.
We know that lists exist in
Python, and you can create them
just by using square brackets.
So what if I simplify the
code a little bit and just
say if s is in the
following list of values--
capital Y or lowercase y.
It's not all that different,
logically, but it's a little tighter.
It's a little more compact.
So elif s is in capital N or lowercase
n, I can express that same idea, too.
So here, again, it's just getting a
little more pleasant to write code.
There's less hitting of the keyboard.
You can express yourself
a little more succinctly.
And using the keyword in,
Python will figure out
how to search the entire list
for whatever the value of s is.
And if it finds it, it will
return True automatically.
Else, it will return False.
So if I run agree.py again and type in
capital Y or lowercase y, that still,
now, works.
Well, I can tighten this up further
if I want to add more features.
Well, what if I want to support
not just big Y and little y,
but how about "Yes" or
"yes" or, in case the user
is yelling or someone who isn't
good with CapsLock types in "YES?"
Wait a minute.
But it could be weird.
Do we want to support this or this?
This just gets really tedious,
quickly, combinatorially,
if you consider all of
these possible permutations.
What would be smarter
than doing something
like this, if you want to
just be able to tolerate
"yes" in any form of capitalization?
Logically, what would be nice?
AUDIENCE: Maybe, whatever the
input is, you just transfer it over
to all lowercase while
uppercase, and then redo it?
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Super common paradigm.
Why don't we just force the user's input
to all lowercase or all uppercase--
doesn't matter, so long as we're
self-consistent-- and just compare
against all uppercase or all lowercase.
And that will get rid of all of the
possible permutations, otherwise.
Now, in C, we might have
done something like this.
We might have simplified this
whole list and just said--
let's say we'll do--
how about lowercase?
So y or yes, and we'll
just leave it at that.
But we need to force,
now, s to lowercase.
Well, in C, we would have
used the C-type library.
We would have done to.lower and
call that function, passing it in.
Although, not really
because, in C-type, those
operate on individual characters
or chars, not whole strings.
We actually didn't see a function
that could convert a whole string in C
to lowercase.
But in Python, we're going to benefit
from some other feature, as well.
It turns out that Python supports what's
called object-oriented programming.
And we're only going to scratch
the surface of this in CS50.
But if you take a higher-level
C course in programming or CS,
you explore this as
a different paradigm.
Up until now, in C, we've been
focusing on what's called, really,
procedural programming.
You write procedures.
You write functions, top
to bottom, left to right.
And when you want to
change some value, we
were in the habit of using a
procedure-- that is, a function.
You would pass something, like
a variable, into a function,
like toupper or tolower, and it would
do its thing and hand you back a value.
Well, it turns out that it would be
nicer, programming-wise, if some data
types just had built-in functionality.
Why do we have our variables over
here and all of our helper functions,
like toupper and tolower over
here, such that we constantly
have to pass one into the other.
It would be nice to bake into our
data type some built-in functionality
so that you can change variables
using their own, default built-in
functionality.
And so, Object-Oriented
Programming, otherwise known as OOP,
is a technique whereby certain
types of values, like a string--
AKA str-- not only have
properties inside of them--
attributes, just like a struct in C--
your data can also have functions
built into them, as well.
So, whereas in C, which is not
object-oriented, you have structs.
And structs can only store
data, like a name and a number
when implementing a person.
In Python, you can, for instance,
have not just a structure--
otherwise known as a class--
storing a name and a number.
You can have a function call
that person or email that person
or actual verbs or actions
associated with that piece of data.
Now, in the context of
strings, it turns out
that strings come with a
lot of useful functionality.
And in fact, at this URL here,
which is in docs.python.org,
which is the official
documentation for Python,
you'll see a whole list of methods--
that is, functions-- that come
with strings that you can actually
use to modify their values.
And what I mean by
this is the following.
If we go through the
documentation, poke around,
it turns out that strings come
with a function called lower.
And if you want to use
that function, you just
have to use slightly different syntax
than in C. You do not do tolower,
and you do not say, as I just did,
lower because this function is
built into s itself.
And just like in C, when you want to go
inside of a variable, like a structure,
and access a piece of data inside
of it, like name or number,
when you also have functions
built into data types--
AKA methods; a method is just a function
that is built into a piece of data--
you can do s dot lower open
paren, closed paren in this case.
And I can do this down here, as well.
If s.lower in, quote unquote,
"n" or "no", the whole thing,
I can force this whole
thing to lowercase.
So the only difference here, now,
as an object-oriented programming,
instead of constantly passing
a value into a function,
you just access a function
that's inside of the value.
It just works because of how
the language itself is defined.
And the only way you know
whether these functions exist
is the documentation-- a class,
a book, a website or the like.
Questions, now, on this technique?
All right.
I claim this is correct.
Now, even though you've never
programmed, most of you, in Python
before, not super well-designed.
There's an subtle inefficiency,
now, on lines 3 and 5 together.
What's dumb about how I've
used lower, might you think?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I feel like, using it twice,
you'd just want another [? variable. ?]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
If you're going to use the same function
twice and ask the same question,
expecting the same answer, why are
you calling the function itself twice?
Maybe we should just store
the result in a variable.
So we could do this in a
couple of different ways.
We, for instance, could go up here
and create another variable called t
and set that equal to s.lower.
And then, we could just
change this to be t, here.
But honestly, I don't
think we technically
need another variable altogether, here.
I could just do something like this.
Let's change the value of s to
be the lowercase version thereof.
And so, now, I can quite simply
refer to s again and again like this,
reusing that same value.
Now, to be sure, I have now just
lost the user's original input.
And if I care about that-- if they typed
in all caps, I have no idea anymore.
So maybe I do want to use a
separate variable, altogether.
But a takeaway here, too,
is that strings in Python
are technically what
we'll call immutable--
that is, they cannot be changed.
This was not true in C. Once
we gave you arrays in week two
or memory in week four, you
could go to town on a string
and change any of the characters
you want-- uppercasing, lowercasing,
changing it, shortening it and so forth.
But in this case, this returns a
copy of s, forced to lowercase.
It doesn't change the original string--
that is, the bytes in
the computer's memory.
When you assign it back
to s, you're essentially
forgetting about the old version of s.
But because Python does memory
management for you-- there's no malloc,
there's no free--
Python automatically frees up
the original bytes, like Y-E-S,
and hands them back to the
operating system for you.
All right.
Questions, now, on this technique?
Questions on this?
In general, I'll call out--
the Python documentation
will start to be your friend
because, in class, we'll only scratch
the surface with some of these things.
But in docs.python.org,
for instance, there's
a whole reference of all of the built-in
functions that come with the language,
as well as, for instance,
those with a string.
All right.
Before we take a break, let's go ahead
and create something a little familiar
too based on our weeks
here, in C. Let me
propose that we revisit those
examples involving some meows.
So, for instance, when we had our
cat meow back in the first week
and, then, second in C, we did something
that was a little stupid at first
whereby we created a file, as I'll
do here-- this time, called meow.py.
And if I want a cat
to meow three times, I
could run it once, like
this, a little copy-paste.
And now, python of
meow.py, and I'm done.
Now, we've visited this
example two times, at least,
now in Scratch and in C.
It's correct, I'll stipulate, but
what's, obviously, poorly designed?
What's the fault here?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: It should just be a loop.
DAVID MALAN: It should
just be a loop, right?
Why type it three times?
Literally, copying and pasting
is almost always a bad thing--
except in C, when you have the function
prototypes that you need to borrow.
But in this case, this
is just inefficient.
So what could we do
better here, in Python?
Well, in Python, we could probably
change this in a few different ways.
We could borrow some of the
syntax we proposed in slide form
earlier, like give me
a variable called i.
Set it to 0, no semicolon.
While i is less than 3-- if I
want to do this three times--
I can go ahead and print out "meow."
And then, I can do i plus equals 1.
And I think this would do the trick.
Python of meow.py, and we're
back in business already.
Well, if I wanted to change this
to a for loop, well, in Python,
it would be a little tighter, but
this would not be the best approach.
So for i in 0, 1, 2, I could
just do print "meow", like this.
And that, too, would get the job done.
But, to our discussion earlier,
this would get stupid pretty quickly
if you had to keep enumerating
all of these values.
What did we introduce instead?
The range function.
Exactly.
So that hands me back, way more
efficiently, just the values I want,
indeed, one at a time.
So even this, if I run it a third or
fourth time, we've got the same result.
But now, let's transition to where
we went with this back in the day.
How can we start to modularize this?
It would be nice, I claimed, if
MIT had given us a meow function.
Wouldn't it be nice if Python
had given us a meow function?
Maybe less compelling in Python,
but how can I build my own function?
Well, I did this briefly with
the spell checker earlier,
but let me go ahead and propose
that we could implement, now,
our own version of this
in Python as follows.
Let me go ahead and start fresh
here and use the keyword def.
So this did not exist in C. You
had the return value, the function
name, the arguments.
In Python, you literally say
def to define a function.
You give it a name, like meow.
And now, I'm going to go ahead and,
in this function, just print out meow.
And this lets me change it to
anything else I want in the future.
But for now, it's an abstraction.
And in fact, I can move it
out of sight, out of mind--
just going to hit Enter a
bunch of times to pretend,
now, it exists, but I don't
care how it is implemented.
And up here, now, I can
do something like this.
For i in range of 3, let me go
ahead and not print "meow" anymore.
Let me just call meow and
tightening up my code further.
Let's see.
Python of meow.py.
This is, I think, going to be the
first time it does not work correctly.
OK.
So here, we have, sadly,
our first Python error.
And let's see.
The syntax is going to be
different from C or Clangs output.
Traceback is the term of art here.
This is like a trace back
of all of the lines of code
that were just executed or,
really, functions you've called.
The file name is uninteresting.
This is my codespace,
specifically, but the file name
is important here-- meow.py.
Our line 2 is the issue--
OK, I didn't get very
far before I screwed up--
and then, there's a name error.
And you'll see, in Python, there's
typically these capitalized keywords
that hint at what the issue is.
It's something related to names of
variables. "meow" is not defined.
All right.
You're programming Python
for the first time.
You've screwed up.
You're following some online tutorial.
You're seeing this.
Reason through it.
Why might "meow" not be defined?
What can we infer about Python?
How to troubleshoot, logically?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Maybe.
Is it because "meow" is defined after?
As smart as Python seems
to be, vis-a-vis C,
they have some similar
design characteristics.
So let's try that.
So let me scroll all the way back
down to where I moved this earlier.
Let me get rid of it--
way down there.
I'll copy it to my clipboard.
And let me just hack something together.
Let me just put it up here.
And let's see if this works.
So now, let me clear my
terminal, run python of meow.py.
OK.
We're back in business.
So that was actually
really good intuition.
Good debugging technique,
just reason through it.
Now, this is contradicting
what I claimed back
in week one, which was that
the main part of your program,
ideally, should just be
at the top of the file.
Don't make me look for it.
It's not a huge deal
with a four-line program,
but if you've got 40
lines or 400 lines, you
don't want the juicy
part of your program
to be way down here, and all
of these functions way up here.
So it would be nice, maybe, if
we actually have a main function.
And so, it actually turns out
to be a convention in Python
to define a main function.
It's not a special function that's
automatically called, like in C.
But humans realized, you know what?
That was a pretty useful feature.
Let me define a function called main.
Let me indent these lines underneath it.
Let me practice what I'm
preaching, which is put
the main code at the top of the file.
And, wonderfully, in Python,
now, you do not need prototypes.
There's none of that
hackish copying and pasting
of the return type, the name
and the arguments to a function,
like we needed in C. This is now OK
instead, except for one, minor detail.
Let me go ahead and
run python of meow.py.
Hopefully, now, I've solved this problem
by having [GROANS] a main function.
But now, nothing has happened.
All right.
Even if you've never
programmed in Python before,
what might explain this
behavior, and how do I fix?
Again, when you're off in the real
world, learning some new language,
all you have is
deductive logic to debug.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I remember in C,
even though we [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Right.
So the solution, to be
clear, in C was that we
had to put the prototype up here.
Otherwise, we'd get an error message.
In this case, I'm actually
not getting an error message.
And, indeed, I'll claim that you
don't need the prototypes in Python.
Just not necessary because that
was annoying, if nothing else.
But what else might explain?
Yeah, in the back?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Maybe you have to call main itself.
If main is not some special status in
Python, maybe just because it exists
isn't enough.
And, indeed, if you want to
call main, the new convention
is actually going to be-- as the
very last line of your program,
typically-- to literally call main.
It's a little stupid-looking,
but they made a design decision.
And this is how, now, we work around it.
Python of meow.py.
Now we're back in business.
But now, logically, why does
this work the way it does?
Well, in this case-- top to bottom--
line 1 is telling Python to
define a function called main
and, then, define it as
follows, lines 2 and 3.
But it's not calling main yet.
Line 6 is telling Python how to
define a function called meow,
but it's not calling these lines yet.
Now, on line 10, you're
telling Python, call main.
And at that point, Python has
been trained, if you will,
to know what main is on line 1,
to know what meow is on line 6.
And so, it's now perfectly
OK for main to be above meow
because you never called them yet.
You defined, defined,
and then, you called.
And that's the logic behind this.
Any questions, now, on the
structure of this technique, here?
Now, let's do one more, then.
Recall that the last thing we
did in Scratch and in C was to,
actually, parameterize
these same functions.
So suppose that you don't want main
to be responsible for the loop here.
You instead want to, very simply,
do something like "meow" three times
and be done with it.
Well, in Python, it's going
to be similar in spirit to C.
But, again, we don't need to
keep mentioning data types.
If you want "meow" to
take some argument--
like a number n--
you can just specify n as
the name of that argument.
Or you can call it anything
else, of course, that you want.
You don't have to specify
int or anything else.
In your code, now, inside of meow,
you can do something like for i in,
let's say--
I definitely, now, can't do this because
that would be weird, to start the list
and end it with n.
So, if I can come back over
here, what's the solution?
How can I do something n times?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Using range.
So range is nice because I can
pass in, now, this variable n.
And now, I can meow-- whoops.
Now i can print out,
quote unquote, "meow."
So it's almost the same as in
Scratch, almost the same as in C.
But it's a little simpler.
And if, now, I run meow.py, I'll have
the ability, now, to do this here,
as well.
All right.
Questions on any of this?
Right now, we're taking this
stroll through week one.
We're going to,
momentarily, escalate things
to look not only at
some of these basics,
but also, other features, like
we saw with face recognition
with the speller or the like.
Because of how many of us are here,
we have a huge amount of candy
out in the lobby.
So why don't we go ahead
and take a 10-minute break?
And when we come back, we'll do
even fancier, more powerful things
with Python in 10.
All right.
So we are back.
Among our goals, now, are to
introduce a few more building
blocks so that we can solve more
interesting problems at the end,
much like those that we began with.
You'll recall, from a few weeks ago, we
played with this two-dimensional Super
Mario world.
And we tried to print a vertical
column of three or more bricks.
Well, let me propose that we use
this as an opportunity to, now,
tinker with some of
Python's more useful, more
user-friendly functionality, as well.
So let me code a file called
mario.py, and let's just print out
the equivalent of that vertical column.
So it's of height 3.
Each one is a hash, so let's do
for i in range of 3 initially,
and let's just print out a single hash.
And I think, now, python of mario.py--
voila.
We're in business, printing out
just that same column there.
What if, though, we want to print
a column of some variable height
where the user tells us how
tall they want it to be?
Well, let me go up here, for
instance and, instead, how about--
let's do this.
How about from cs50 import?
How about the get_int
function, as before?
So it will deal with making sure
the user gives us an integer.
And now, in the past, whenever we
wanted to get a number from a user,
we've actually followed
a certain paradigm.
In fact, if I open up
here, for instance,
how about mario1.c
from a while back, you
might recall that we had code like this.
And we specifically use
the do while loop in C
whenever we want to get
something from the user,
maybe, again and again and
again, until they cooperate.
At which point, we finally
break out of the loop.
So it turns out, Python
does have while loops,
does have for loops, does
not have do while loops.
And yet, pretty much any time
you've gotten user input,
you've probably used this paradigm.
So it turns out that the Python
equivalent of this is to do,
similar in spirit, but
using only a while loop.
And a common paradigm in
Python, as I alluded earlier,
is to actually deliberately induce
an infinite loop while True--
capital T-- and then, do what you want
to do, like get an int from the user
and prompt them for the height,
for instance, in question.
And then, if you're sure that the
user has given you what you want--
like n is greater than 0, which
is what I want, in this case,
because I want a positive integer;
otherwise, there's nothing to print--
you literally just
break out of the loop.
And so, we could actually use
this technique in C. It's just not
really done in C. You
could absolutely, in C,
have done a while True loop with
the parentheses, lowercase true.
You could break out of it, and so forth.
But in Python, this is the Python way.
And this is actually a term of art.
This way in Python is pythonic
This is "the way everyone does it,"
quote unquote.
Doesn't mean you have to, but that's the
way the cool Python programmers would
implement an idea like this-- trying
to do something again and again
and again until the user
actually cooperates.
But all we've done is take
away the do while loop.
But still, logically, we
can implement the same idea.
Now, below this, let me go ahead and
just print out, for i in range of n
this time-- because I want
it to be variable and not 3.
I can go ahead and print out the hash--
let me go ahead and get
rid of the C version here--
open my terminal window and I'll
run, again, Python of mario.py.
I'll type in 3 and I get
back those three hashes.
But if I, instead, type in 4,
I now get four hashes instead.
So the takeaway here is,
quite simply, that this
would be the way, for
instance, to actually get back
a value in Python that is
consistent with some parameter,
like greater than 0.
How about this?
Let's actually practice what we preached
a moment ago with our meowing examples
and factoring all this out.
Let me go ahead and define
a main function, as before.
Let me go ahead and
assume, for the moment,
that a get_height function exists,
which is not a thing in Python.
I'm going to invent it in just a moment.
And now, I'm going to go ahead
and do something like this. for i
in the range of that height, well, let's
go ahead and print out those hashes.
So I'm assuming that get_height exists.
Let me go ahead and implement that
abstraction, so define a function,
now, called get_height.
It's not going to take any
arguments in this design.
While True, I can go ahead and
do the same thing as before--
assign a variable n, the
return value of get_int
prompting the user for that height.
And then, if n is greater than
0, I can go ahead and break.
But if I break here, I,
logically-- just like in C--
end up executing below
the loop in question.
But there's nothing there.
But if I want get_height to
return the height, what should
I type here on line 14, logically?
What do I want to return, to be clear?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So I actually want to return n.
And here's another curiosity
of Python, vis-a-vis C.
There doesn't seem to be an
issue of scope anymore, right?
In C, it was super important to not only
declare your variables with the data
types, you also had to be
mindful of where they exist--
inside of those curly braces.
In Python, it turns out you can be a
little looser with things, for better
or for worse.
And so, on line 11, if I
create a variable called n,
it exists on line 11, 12 and even
13, outside of the while loop.
So to be clear, in C,
with a while loop, we
would have ordinarily had not a colon.
We would have had the curly
brace, like here and over here.
And a week ago, I would
have claimed that, in C, n
does not exist outside of the while
loop, by nature of those curly braces.
Even though the curly braces
are gone, Python actually
allows you to use a variable any time
after you have assigned it a value.
So slightly more powerful, as such.
However, I can tighten this
up a little bit, logically.
And this is true in C. I don't
really need to break out of the loop
by using break.
Recall that or know that I can
actually-- once I'm ready to go,
I can just return the value I care
about, even inside of the loop.
And that will have the side effect
of breaking me out of the loop
and, also, breaking me out of and
returning from the entire function.
So nothing too new here, in terms of
C versus Python, except for this issue
with scope.
And I, indeed, returned
n at the bottom there,
just to make clear that
n would still exist.
So either of those are correct.
Now, I just have a Python
program that I think
is going to allow me to
implement this same Mario idea.
So let's run python of mario.py.
And-- OK, so nothing happened.
Python of mario.py.
What did I do wrong?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I have to call main.
So, at the bottom of my code,
I have to call main here.
And this is a stylistic
detail that's been subtle.
Generally speaking, when
you are writing in Python,
there's not a CS50 style guide, per se.
There's actually a Python style
guide that most people adhere to.
And in this case, double blank
lines between functions is the norm.
I'm doing that deliberately, although
it might, otherwise, not be obvious.
But now that I've called main on line
16, let's run mario.py once more.
Aha.
Now we see it.
Type in 3, and I'm back in business,
printing out the values there.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Why do you [INAUDIBLE]?
Why can't [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
Why do I need the if condition at all?
Why can't I just return n
here as by doing return n.
Or if I really want to be succinct,
I could technically just do this.
The only reason I added
the if condition is
because, if the user types
in negative 1, negative 2,
I wanted to prompt them again and again.
That's all.
But that would be totally acceptable,
too, if you were OK with that result
instead.
Well, let me do one other
thing here to point out
why we are using get_int so frequently.
This new training wheel,
albeit temporarily.
So let me go back to the
way it was a moment ago
and let me propose, now,
to take away get_int.
I claimed earlier that, if
you're not using get_int,
you can just use the input
function itself from Python.
But that always returns
a string, or a str.
And so, recall that you have to pass the
output of the input function to an int,
either on the same line or, if you
prefer, on another line, instead.
But it turns out what
I didn't do was show
you what happens if you don't
cooperate with the program.
So if I run python of mario.py
now, works great, even
without the get_int function.
And I can do it with 4.
Still works great.
But let me clear my terminal
and be difficult, now,
as the user and type in
"cat" for the height instead.
Enter.
Now, we see one of
those trace backs again.
This one is different.
This isn't a name error, but,
apparently, a value error.
And if I ignore the
stuff I don't understand,
I can see "invalid literal
for int with base 10-- "cat.""
That's a super cryptic way
of saying that C-A-T is not
a number in decimal notation.
And so, I would seem to have
to, somehow, handle this case.
And if you want to be
more curious, you'll
see that this is, indeed, a traceback.
And C tends to do this, too, or the
debugger would do this for you, too.
You can see all of the
functions that have
been called to get you to this point.
So apparently, my problem
is, initially, in line 14.
But line 14, if I keep
scrolling, is uninteresting.
It's main.
But line 14 leads me to execute
line 2, which is, indeed, in main.
That leads me to execute line
9, which is in get_height.
And so, OK, here is the issue.
So the closest line number
to the error message
is the one that probably
reveals the most.
Line 9 is where my issue is.
So I can't just blindly ask the user for
input and, then, convert it to an int
if they're not going to give me an int.
Now, how do we deal with this?
Well, back in problem
set two, you might recall
validating that the
user typed in a number
and using a for loop and the like.
Well, it turns out, there's a
better way to do this in Python,
and the semantics are there.
If you want to try to convert something
to a number that might not actually
be a number, turns out, Python
and certain other languages
literally have a keyword called try.
And if only this existed for
the past few weeks, I know.
But you can try to do the
following with your code.
What do I want to try to do?
Well, I want to try to execute those
few lines, except if there's an error.
So I can say except if there's
a value error-- specifically,
the one I screwed up and
created a moment ago.
And if there is a value error, I
can print out an informative message
to the user, like "not an
integer" or anything else.
And what's happening here, now, is
literally this operative word, try.
Python is going to try to get input
and try to convert it to an int,
and it's going to try to
check if it's greater than 0
and then try to return it.
Why?
Three of those lines
are inside of, indented
underneath the try block,
except if something goes wrong--
specifically, a value error happens.
Then, it prints this.
But it doesn't return anything.
And because I'm in a loop, that means
it's going to do it again and again
and again until the human
actually cooperates and gives me
an actual number.
And so, this, too, is what
the world would call pythonic.
In Python, you don't, necessarily,
rigorously try to validate
the user's input, make sure
they haven't screwed up.
You honestly take a more
lackadaisical approach
and just try to do something,
but catch an error if it happens.
So catch is also a term of art,
even though it's not a keyword here.
Except if something
happens, you handle it.
So you try and you handle it.
You best-effort
programming, if you will.
But this is baked into the mindset
of the Python programming community.
So now, if I do python of mario.py and
I cooperate, works great as before.
Try and succeed.
3 works.
4 works.
If, though, I try and fail by typing
in "cat," it doesn't crash, per se.
It doesn't show me an error.
It shows me something more
user-friendly, like "not an integer."
And then, I can try again with "dog."
"Not an integer."
I can try again with 5.
And now, it works.
So we won't, generally,
have you write much
in the way of these try-except
blocks, only because they
get a little sophisticated quickly.
But that is to reveal what
the get_int function is doing.
This is why we give you
the training wheels,
so that, when you want
to get an int, you
don't have to jump through all
these annoying hoops to do so.
But that's all the library's really
doing for you, is just try and except.
You won't be left with any
training wheels, ultimately.
Questions, now, on getting
input and trying in this way?
Anything at all?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: I'm still
[INAUDIBLE] try block.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, could you put the
condition outside of the try block?
Short answer, yes.
And, in fact, I struggled
with this last night
when tweaking this example
to show the simplest version.
I will disclaim that, really, I
should only be trying, literally,
to do the fragile part.
And then, down here, I
should be really doing
what you're proposing, which
is do the condition out here.
The problem is, though, that, logically,
this gets messy quickly, right?
Because except if there's a value error,
I want to print out "not an integer."
I can't compare n against
0, then, because n doesn't
exist because there was an error.
So it turns out-- and
I'll show you this;
this is now the advanced
version of Python--
there's actually an else
keyword you can use in Python
that does not accompany if or elif.
It accompanies try and except,
which I think is weirdly confusing.
A different word would have been better.
But if you'd really prefer, I
could have done this, instead.
And this is one of these design things
where reasonable people will disagree.
Generally speaking, you
should only try to do
the one line that might very well fail.
But honestly, this looks stupid.
No, it's just unnecessarily complicated.
And so, my own preference was actually
the original, which was-- yeah,
I'm trying a few extra
lines that, really,
aren't going to fail, mathematically.
But it's just tighter.
It's cleaner this way.
And here's, again, the
sort of arguments you'll
start to make yourself as you get
more comfortable with programming.
You'll have an opinion.
You'll disagree with someone.
And so long as you can back you argument
up, it's pretty reasonable, probably.
All right.
So how about we, now, take
away some piece of magic
that's been here for a while.
Let me go ahead and
delete all of this here.
And let me propose that we revisit not
that vertical column and the exceptions
that might result from getting input,
but these horizontal question marks
that we saw a while ago.
So I want all of those question
marks on the same line.
And yet, I worry we're about to
see a challenge here because print,
up until now, has been putting new
lines everywhere automatically,
even without those backslash n's.
Well, let me propose that we do this.
for i in the range of 4.
If I want four question marks, let
me just print four question marks.
Unfortunately, I don't
think this is correct yet.
Let me run python of mario.py.
And, of course, this gives me a column
instead of the row of question marks
that I want.
So how do we do this?
Well, it turns out, if you read the
documentation for the print function,
it turns out that print,
not surprisingly, perhaps,
takes a lot of different
arguments, as well.
And in fact, if you go to
the documentation for it,
you'll see that it takes
not just positional
arguments-- that is, from left
to right, separated by commas.
It turns out, Python has
supports a fancier feature
with arguments where you can pass the
names of arguments to functions, too.
So what do I mean by this?
If I go back to VS Code here
and I've read the documentation,
it turns out that, yes, as before, you
can pass multiple arguments to Python,
like this.
Hello comma David comma Nalan,
that will just automatically
concatenate all three of those
positional arguments together.
They're positional in the sense that
they literally flow from left to right,
separated by commas.
But if you don't want to just
pass in values like that,
you want to actually print out,
as I did before, a question mark.
But you want to override the
default behavior of print
by changing the line ending,
you can actually do this.
You can use the name of an argument that
you know exists from the documentation
and set it equal to
some alternative value.
And in fact, even though
this looks cryptic,
this is how I would override the end
of each line, to be quote, unquote.
That is nothing because, if
you read the documentation,
the default value for this end
argument-- does someone want to guess--
is--
is backslash n.
So if you read the
documentation, you'll se
that backslash n is the implied
default for this end argument.
And so, if you want to change it, you
just say end equals something else.
And so, here, I can change it to nothing
and, now, rerun python of mario.py.
And now, they're all in the same line.
Now, it looks a little stupid
because I made that week
one mistake where I still need to
move the cursor to the next line.
That's just a different problem.
I'm just going to go over
here and print nothing.
I don't even need to print backslash
n because, if print automatically
gives you a backslash n,
just call print with nothing,
and you'll get that for free.
So let me rerun python of mario.py.
And now, it looks a little
prettier at the prompt.
And to be super clear
as to what's going on--
suppose I want to make
an exclamation here.
I could change the backslash n
default to an exclamation point,
just for kicks.
And if I run python of
mario.py Again, now, I
get this exclamation with question
marks and exclamation points, as well.
So that's all that's going on here.
And this is what's
called a named argument.
It literally has a name that you
can specify when calling it in.
And it's different from positional in
that you're literally using the name.
Let me propose something else, though.
And this is why people like Python.
There's just cool ways to do things.
That's a three-line, verbose way of
printing out four question marks.
I could certainly take the
shortcut and just do this.
But that's not really that
interesting for anyone,
especially if I want to do it
a variable number of times.
But Python does let you do this.
If you want to multiply a
character some number of times,
not only can you use
plus for concatenation,
you can use star or an asterisk for
multiplication, if you will-- that is,
concatenation again and again and again.
So if I just print
out, quote unquote, "?"
times 4, that's actually going to be
the tightest way, the most distinct way
I can print four question marks instead.
And if I don't use 4, I use n,
where I get n from the user.
Bang.
Now, I've gotten rid of
the for loop entirely,
and I'm using the star operator
to manipulate it instead.
And, to be super clear
here, insofar as Python
does not have malloc or free or
memory management that you have to do,
guess what Python also doesn't have.
Anything on your minds in
the past couple of week?
Doesn't have--
AUDIENCE: Pointers.
DAVID MALAN: Pointers, yeah.
So Python does not have pointers,
which just means that all of that
happens for you automatically,
underneath the hood,
again, by way of code
that someone else wrote.
How about one more throwback with Mario?
We've talked about, in week one,
this two-dimensional structure where
it's like I claim 3 by 3-- a
grid of bricks, if you will.
Well, how can we do this in Python?
We can do this in a couple of ways, now.
Let me go back to my mario.py, and let
me do something like for i in range
of-- we'll just do 3, even though
I know, now, I could use get_int
or I could use input and int.
And if I want to do something
two-dimensionally, just like in C,
you can nest your for loops.
So maybe I could do for j in range of 3.
And then, in here, I could
print out a hash symbol.
And then, let's see if
that gives me 9 total.
So if I've got a nested loop
like this, python of mario.py
hopefully gives me a grid.
No, it gave me a column of 9.
Why, logically, even though
I've got my row and my columns?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the line ending.
So in my row, I can't let print just
keep adding new line, adding new line.
So I just have to override this here
and let me not screw up like before.
Let me print one at the end of the
whole row, just to move the cursor down.
And I think, now, together,
we've got our 3 by 3.
Of course, we could
tighten this up further.
If I don't like the nested loop,
I probably could go in here
and just print out, for
instance, a brick times 3.
Or I could change the 3 to a variable
if I've gotten it from the user.
So I can tighten this up further.
So, again, just different ways to solve
the same problem and, again, evidence
of why a lot of people like Python.
There's just some more
pleasant ways to solve problems
without getting into the weeds,
constantly, of doing things,
like with for loops and
while loops endlessly.
All right.
Well, how about some
other building blocks?
Lists are going to be so incredibly
useful in Python, just as arrays
were in C. But arrays
are annoying because you
have to manage the memory yourself.
You have to in advance
how big they are or you
have to use pointers and malloc
or realloc to resize them.
Oh my god.
The past two weeks have
been painful, in that sense.
But Python does this
all for free for you.
In fact, there's a
whole bunch of functions
that come with Python
that involve lists,
and they'll allow us, ultimately, to
do things again and again and again
within the same data structure.
And, for instance, we'll be able
to get the length of a list.
You don't have to remember
it yourself in a variable.
You can just ask Python how
many elements are in this list.
And with this, I think we can
solve some old problems, too.
So let me go back here, to VS Code.
Let me close mario and give us
a new program called scores.py.
And rather than show the C and the
Python now, let's just focus on Python.
And in scores.c way back when, we just
averaged three test scores or something
like that--
72, 73, and 33--
a few weeks ago.
So if I want to create a list in
this Python version of 72, 73, 33,
I just use my square bracket notation.
C let you use curly braces if
you know the values in advance,
but Python's just this.
And now, if I want to
compute the average--
in C, recall, I did
something with a loop.
I added all the values together.
I, then, divide it by the
total number of values
just like you would in grade school,
and that gave me the average.
Well, Python comes with a lot
of super handy functions--
not just length, but others, as well.
And so, in fact, if you
want to compute the average,
you can take the sum
of all of those scores
and divide it by the length
of all of those scores.
So Python comes with
length, comes with sum.
You can just pass in a
whole list of any size
and let it deal with
that problem for you.
So if I want to, now,
print out this average,
I can print out Average colon--
and then, I'll plug in my average
variable for interpolation.
Let me make this an fstring
so that it gets formatted,
and let me just run python of scores.py.
And there is my average.
It's rounding weird because we're
still vulnerable to some floating point
imprecision, but at
least I didn't need loops
and I didn't have to write
all this darn code just
to do something that Excel and Google
Spreadsheets can just do like that.
Well, Python is closer
to those kinds of tools,
but more powerful in that you
can manipulate the data yourself.
How about, though, if I want to get a
bunch of scores manually from the user
and, then, sum them together.
Well, let's combine a few ideas here.
How about this?
First, let me go ahead and import the
get_int function from the CS50 library,
just so we don't have to deal with
try and except or all of that.
And let me go ahead and
give myself an empty list.
And this is powerful.
In C, [SIGHS] there's no
point to an empty array
because, if you create an empty
array with square bracket notation,
it's not useful for anything.
But in Python, you can create
it empty because Python
will grow and shrink the list for you
automatically, as you add things to it.
So if I want to get three
scores from the user,
I could do something like
this-- for i in range of 3.
And then, I can grab a variable
called "score" or anything.
I could call get_int, prompt
the human for the score
that they want to type in.
And then, once they do, I can do this.
Thinking back to our object-oriented
programming capability now,
I could do scores.append, and
I can append that score to it.
And you would only know this from
having read the documentation, heard it
in class, in a book or
whatnot, but it turns out
that, just like strings have
functions like lower built into them,
lists have functions like append built
into them that just literally appends
to the end of the list
for you, and Python
will grow or shrink it as needed.
No more malloc or realloc or the like.
So this just appends to the scores list.
That score, and then
again and again and again.
So the array starts at--
sorry, the list starts at size
0, then grows to 1 then 2 then 3
without you having to do anything else.
And so, now, down here,
I can compute an average
with the sum of those
scores divided by the length
of the total number of scores.
And to be clear, length is the total
number of elements in the list.
Doesn't matter how big
the values themselves are.
Now I can go ahead and print
out an fstring with something
like Average colon
average in curly braces.
And if I run python of scores.py--
I'll type in, just for the sake
of discussion, the three values,
I still get the same answer.
But that would have
been painful to do in C
unless you committed, in advance, to
a fixed size array-- which we already
decided, weeks ago, was annoying--
or you grew it dynamically
using malloc or realloc or the like.
All right.
What else can I do?
Well, there's some nice things
you might as well know exist.
Instead of scores.append, you can
do slight fanciness like this.
If you want to append
something to a list,
you can actually do
plus equals, and then
put that thing in a
temporary list of its own
and just use what is
essentially concatenation--
but not concatenation of strings,
but concatenation of lists.
So this new line 6 appends
to the score's list--
this tiny, little list
I'm temporarily creating
with just the current new score.
So just another piece of
syntax that's worth seeing that
allows you to do something
like that, as well.
All right.
Well, how about we go back
to strings for a moment?
And all of these examples, as always,
are on the course's website afterward.
Suppose we want to do something like
converting characters to uppercase.
Well, to be clear, I could
do something like this.
Let me create a program
called uppercase.py.
Let me prompt the user for a before
string as by using the input function
or get_string, which is almost the same.
And I'll prompt the user
for a string beforehand.
Then, let me go ahead and print
out, how about, the keyword "After,"
and then end the new line
with nothing, just so
that I can see "Before" on one
line and "After" on the next line.
And then, let me do this--
and here's where Python gets
pleasant, too, with loops--
for c in before--
print c.upper end equals quote, unquote.
And then, I'll print this here.
All right.
That was fast, but let's try
to infer what's going on.
So line 1 just gets input from the user,
stores it in a variable called before.
Line two literally just
prints "After" but doesn't
move the cursor to the next line.
What it, then, does is this.
And, in C, this was a
little more annoying.
You needed a for loop with i.
You needed array notation
with the square brackets.
But, Python, if you say
for variable in string--
so for c, for character,
in string, Python
is going to automatically
assign c to the first letter
that the user types in.
Then, on the next iteration, the
second letter, the third letter,
and the fourth.
So you don't need any square
bracket notation, you just use c,
and Python will do it for
you and just hand you back,
one at a time, each of the letters
that the user has typed in.
So if I go back over here and I run,
for instance, python of uppercase.py
and I'll type in, how about, "david"
in all lowercase and hit Enter,
you'll now see that it's all uppercase
instead by iterating over it,
indeed, one character at a time.
But we already know, thanks to
object-oriented programming,
strings themselves have
the functionality built
in to not just uppercase single
characters, but the whole string.
So, honestly, this was a
bit of a silly exercise.
I don't need to use a loop anymore,
like in C. And so, some of the habits
you've only just developed in recent
weeks, it's time to start breaking them
when they're not necessary.
I can create a variable called
after, set it equal to before.upper--
which, indeed, exists,
just like dot lower exists.
And then, what I can go ahead
and print out is, for instance--
let's get rid of this print
line here and do it at the end--
"After" and print the
value of that variable.
So now, if I rerun uppercase.py,
type in "david" in all lowercase,
I can just uppercase the whole thing
all at once because, again, in Python,
you don't have to operate
on characters individually.
Questions on any of these
tricks up until now?
No?
All right.
How about a few other techniques that
we saw in C that we'll bring back,
now, in Python.
So it turns out, in Python, there
are other libraries you can use, too,
that unlock even more functionality.
So, in C, if you wanted
command line arguments,
you just change the signature
for main to be, instead of void,
int argc comma string argv, open
brackets for an array or char star,
eventually.
Well, it turns out, in Python, that,
if you want to access command line
arguments, it's a little simpler, but
they're tucked away in a library--
otherwise known as a module--
called sys, the system module.
Now, this is similar, in
spirit, to the CS50 library,
and that's got a bunch of
functionality built in.
But this one comes with Python itself.
So if I want tot create a program
like greet.py, in VS Code,
here, let me go ahead and do this.
From the sys library, let's import argv.
And that's just a thing that exists.
It's not built into main because
there is no main, per se, anymore.
So it's tucked away in that library.
And now, I can do something like this.
If the length of argv
equals equals 2, well,
let's go ahead and print
out something friendly,
like hello comma argv bracket
1, and then, close quotes.
Else, if the length of
argv is not equal to 2,
Let's just go ahead and
print out hello, world.
Now, at a glance, this
might look a little cryptic,
but it's identical to what
we did a few weeks ago.
When I run this, python of
greet.py, with no arguments,
it just says "hello, world."
But if I, instead, add a command line
argument, like my first name and hit
Enter, now, the length
of argv is no longer 1.
It's going to be 2.
And so, it prints out
"Hello, David" instead.
So the takeaway here
is that, whereas in C,
argv technically contained the name of
your program, like ./hello or ./greet,
and then everything the human typed.
Python's a little different
in that, because we're
using the interpreter in this way--
technically, when you run python of
greet.py, the length of argv is only 1.
It contains only greet.py,
so the name of the file.
It does not unnecessarily
contain Python itself
because what's the point of
that being there, omnipresently?
It does contain the number of words that
the human typed after Python itself.
So argv is length 1 here.
argv is length 2 here.
And that's why, when it did equal
2, I saw "Hello, David" instead
of the default "Hello, world."
So same ability to access command line
arguments, add these kinds of inputs
to your functions, but
you have to unlock it
by way of using argv
instead, in this way.
If you want to see all of the words,
you could do something like this.
Just as-- if we combine ideas, here--
for i in range of, how about, length
of argv.
Then, I can do this--
print argv bracket i.
All right.
A little cryptic, but line 3
is just a for loop iterating
over the range of length of argv.
So if the human types in two words,
the length of argv will be 2.
So this is just a way of saying
iterate over all of the words in argv,
printing them one at a time.
So python of greet.py, Enter just
prints out the name of the program.
python of greet.py with David prints
out greet.py and, then, David.
I can keep running it
though with more words,
and they'll each get
printed one at a time.
But what's nice, too, about Python--
and this is the point of this exercise--
honestly, this looks pretty cryptic.
This is not very pleasant to look at.
If you just want to iterate over
every word in a list, which argv is,
watch what I can do.
I can do for arg or any
variable name in argv.
Let me just, now, print
out that argument.
I could keep calling it i, but i
seems weird when it's not a number.
So I'm changing to arg
as a word, instead.
If I now do python of
greet.py, it does this.
If I do python of greet.py,
David, it does that again.
David Malan, it does that again.
So this is, again, why Python
is just very appealing.
You want to do something this
many times, iterate over a list?
Just say it, and it reads
a little more like English.
And there's even other
fanciness, too, if I may.
It's a little stupid that I keep seeing
the name of the program, greet.py,
so it'd be nice if I could remove that.
Python also supports what
are called slices of arrays--
sorry, slices of lists.
Even I get the terminology confused.
If argv is a list, then it's going
to print out everything in it.
But if I want a slice of it that starts
at location 1 all the way to the end,
you can use this funky syntax in
between the square brackets, which
we've not seen yet, that's
going to start at item 1
and go all the way to the end.
And so, this is a nice,
clever way of slicing off,
if you will, the very
first element because now,
when I run greet.py, David Malan,
I should only see David and Malan.
If I only want one
element, I could do 1 to 2.
If I want all of them,
I could do 0 onward.
I could give myself just
one of them in this way.
So you can play with the start
value and the end value in this way,
to slice and dice these
lists in different ways.
That would have been a pain in
C, just because we didn't really
have the built-in support for
manipulating arrays as cleanly as this.
All right.
Just so you've seen it, too-- though,
this one is less exciting to see live--
if I go ahead and create a quick
program here, it turns out,
there's something else in the sys
library, the ability to exit programs--
either exiting with status code 1 or 0,
as we've been doing any time something
goes right or wrong.
So, for instance, let me whip up
a quick program that just says,
if the length of sys.argv does not
equal 2, then let's yell at the user
and say you're missing
a command line argument.
Otherwise, command-line argument.
And let's, then, return sys.exit(1).
Else, let's go ahead and, logically,
just say print a formatted string that
says hello-- as before--
sys.argv 1.
Now, things look
different all of a sudden,
but I'm doing something deliberately.
First, let's see what this does.
So, on line 1, I'm importing
not argv, specifically.
I'm importing the whole sys library,
and we'll see why in a second.
Well, it turns out that the sys
library has not only the argv list,
it also has a function called exit,
which I'd like to be able to use,
as well.
So it turns out that, if you import a
whole library in this way, that's fine.
But you have to refer to
the things inside of it
by using that same library's name and
a dot to namespace it, so to speak.
So here, I'm just saying, if the
user does not type in two words,
yell at them with missing command
line argument, and then, exit with 1.
Just like in C, when you do exit
1, just means something went wrong.
Otherwise, print out hello to this.
And this is starting to look cryptic,
but it's just a combination of ideas.
The curly braces means interpolate
this value, plug it in here.
sys.argv is just the verbose way
of saying go into the sys library
and get the argv variable therein.
And bracket 1, of course,
just like arrays in C,
is just the second
element at the prompt.
So when I run this version,
now-- python of exit.py--
with no arguments, I get
yelled at in this way.
If, however, I type in
two arguments total--
the name of the file and my own name--
now, I get greeted with hello, David.
And it's the same idea before.
This was a very low-level
technique, but same thing here.
If you do echo dollar
sign question mark Enter,
you'll see the exit
code of your program.
So if I do this incorrectly again--
let me rerun it without my name, Enter--
I get yelled at.
But if I do echo dollar
sign question mark,
there's the secret one that's returned.
Again, just to show you
parity with C, in this case.
Questions, now, on any of
these techniques, here?
No.
All right.
How about something that's
a little more powerful, too?
We spend so much time in
week 0 and 1 doing searching
and, then, eventually,
sorting in week 3.
Well, it turns out, Python can
help with some of this, too.
Let me go ahead and create
a program called names.py
that's just going to be an
opportunity to, maybe, search
over a whole bunch of names.
Let me go ahead and import sys,
just so I have access to exit.
And let me go ahead
and create a variable
called names that's going to be a
list with a whole bunch of names.
How about here?
Charlie and Fred and George and
Ginny and Percy and, lastly, Ron.
So a whole bunch of names here.
And it'd be a little
annoying to implement
code that iterates over that, from
left to right, in C, searching for one
of those names.
In fact, what name?
Well, let's go ahead and ask
the user to input the name
that they want to search
for so that we can tell them
if the name is there or not.
And we could do this, similar to C,
in Python, doing something like this.
So for n in names, where n is just a
variable to iterate over each name--
if the name I'm looking for equals
the current name in the list--
AKA n-- well, let's print out
something friendly, like "Found."
And then, let's do sys.exit 0 to
indicate that we found whoever that is.
Otherwise, if we get all the way to
the bottom here, outside of this loop,
let's just print "Not found"
because if we haven't exited yet.
And then, let's just exit with 1.
Just to be clear, I can
continue importing all of sys,
or I could do from sys import exit,
and then, I could get rid of sys dot
everywhere else.
But sometimes, it's helpful to know
exactly where functions came from.
So this, too, is just a
matter of style, in this case.
All right.
So let's go ahead and run this.
python of names.py, and let's look
for Ron, all the way at the end.
All right.
He's found.
And let's search for someone outside
of the family here, like Hermione.
Not found.
OK.
So it seems to be working in this way.
But I've essentially
implemented what algorithm?
What algorithm would this seem to
be, per line 7 and 8 to 9 and 10?
AUDIENCE: Linear.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So it's just linear search.
It's a loop, even thought he syntax
is a little more succinct today,
and it's just iterating
over the whole thing.
Well, honestly, we've seen an even
more terse way to do this in Python.
And this, again, is what makes it a
more pleasant language, sometimes.
Why don't I just do this?
Instead of iterating one at a
time, why don't I just say this?
Let me go ahead and change
my condition to just
be-- how about if the name we're looking
for is in the names list, we're done.
We found it.
Use the end preposition that
we've seen a couple of times,
now, that itself asks the question,
is something in something else?
And Python will take care
of linear search for us.
And it's going to work
exactly the same if I
do python of names.py, search for Ron.
It's still going to
find him and it's still
going to do it linearly, in this case.
But I don't have to write all of the
lower-level code myself, in this case.
Questions, now, on any of this?
The code's just getting
shorter and shorter.
No?
What about-- let's see.
What else might we have here?
How about this?
Let's go ahead and
implement that phonebook
that we started, metaphorically,
with in the beginning of the course.
Let's code up a program
called phonebook.py.
And in this case, let's go ahead and
let's create a dictionary this time.
Recall that a dictionary
is a little something that
implements something like this--
a two-column table that's
got keys and values, words
and definitions, names and numbers.
And let's focus on the last of those,
names and numbers, in this case.
Well, I claimed earlier that
Python has built-in support
for dictionaries-- dict objects--
that you can create with one line.
I didn't need it for speller
because a set is sufficient
when you only want one of the
keys or the values, not both.
But now, I want some names and numbers.
So it turns out, in Python, you
can create an empty dictionary
by saying dict open parenthesis, closed.
And that just gives you,
essentially, a chart that
looks like this, with nothing in it.
Or there's more succinct syntax.
You can, alternatively, do this,
with two curly braces, instead.
And, in fact, I've been using
a shortcut all this time.
When I had a list, earlier, where
my variable was called scores,
and I did this, that was actually
the shorthand version of this--
hey, Python, give me an empty list.
So there's different syntax
for achieving the same goal.
In this case, if I want
a dictionary for people,
I can either do this or, more commonly,
just two curly braces, like that.
All right.
Well, what do I want to put in this?
Well, let me actually
put some things in this.
And I'm going to just move my
closed curly brace to a new line.
If I want to implement this
idea of keys and values,
the way you do this in Python
is key colon value comma.
Key colon value.
So you'd implement it more in code.
So, for instance, if I want Carter to
be the first key in my phone book and I
want his number to be +1-617-495-1000,
I can put that as the corresponding
value.
The colon is in between.
Both are strings, or strs, so
I've quoted both deliberately.
If I want to add myself,
I can put a comma.
And then, just to keep things pretty,
I'm moving the cursor to the next line.
But that's not strictly
required, aesthetically.
It's just good style.
And here, I might do +1-949-468-2750.
And now, I have a dictionary that,
essentially, has two rows, here--
Carter and his number and
David and his number, as well.
And if I kept adding to this, this
chart would just get longer and longer.
Suppose I want to search
for one of our numbers.
Well, let's prompt
the user for the name,
for whose number you want
to search by getting string.
Or you know what?
We don't need this CS50 library.
Let's just use input and
prompt the user for a name.
And now, we can use this super terse
syntax and just say if name in people,
print the formatted
string number colon and--
here, we can do this--
people bracket name.
OK.
So this is getting cool
quickly, confusingly.
So let me run this.
python of phonebook.py
Let's type in Carter.
And, indeed, I see his number.
Let's run it again with David,
and I see my number here.
So what's going on?
Well, it turns out that a dictionary
is very similar, in spirit, to a list.
It's actually very similar,
in spirit, to an array in C.
But instead of being limited to keys
that are numbers, like bracket 0,
bracket 1, bracket 2, you
can actually use words.
And that's all I'm doing here on line 8.
If I want to check for the
name Carter, which is currently
in this variable called
name, I can index
into my people dictionary
using not a number,
but using, literally, a string--
the name Carter or
David or anything else.
To make this clearer, too,
notice that I'm, at the moment,
using this format string, which
is adding some undue complexity.
But I could clarify this,
perhaps, further as this.
I could give myself
another variable called
number, set it equal to
the people dictionary,
indexing into it using the current name.
And now, I can shorten this to
make it clearer that all I'm doing
is printing the value of that.
And, in fact, I can do
this even more cryptically.
This would be weird to do, but if I only
ever want to show David's phone number
and never Carter's, I can literally,
quote unquote, "index into" the people
dictionary because, now, when I
run this, even if I type Carter,
I'm going to get back my number instead.
But that's all that's happening if I
undo that, because that's now a bug.
But I index into it
using the value of name.
Dictionaries are just so
wonderfully convenient
because, now, you can associate
anything with anything else
but not using numbers, but
entire key words, instead.
So here's how, if, in speller,
we gave you not just words,
but hundreds of thousands
of definitions, as well,
you could essentially
store them as this.
And then, when the human wants to look
up a definition in a proper dictionary,
not just for spell
checking, you could index
into the dictionary
using square brackets
and get back the definition
in English, as well.
Questions on this?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Is the way this
code does, as presented,
saying that Python has [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
So, to summarize, how is Python finding
that name within that dictionary?
This is where, honestly, speller in
p-set 5 is what Python's all about.
So you have struggled, are struggling
with implementing your own spell
checker and implementing
your own hash table.
And recall that, per last week,
the goal of a hash table is to,
ideally, get constant time access.
Not something linear, which is slow and
even better than something logarithmic,
like log base 2 of n.
So Python and the really
smart people who invented it,
they have written the code
that does its best to give you
constant time searches of dictionaries.
And they're not always going
to succeed, just as you
and your own problem
set are probably going
to have some collisions once
in a while and start to have
chains of length lists of words.
But this is where, again, you
defer to someone else, someone
smarter than you, someone
with more time than you
to solve these problems for you.
And if you read Python's
documentation, you'll
see that it doesn't
guarantee constant time,
but it's going to, ideally,
optimize the data structure
for you to get as fast as possible.
And of all of the data
structures like a dictionary,
a hash table is, really, like
the Swiss army knife of computing
because it just lets you associate
something with something else.
And even though we keep
focusing on names and numbers,
that's a really powerful
thing because it's
more powerful than
lists and arrays, which
are only numbers and something else.
Now, you can have any sorts
of relationships, instead.
All right.
Let me show a few other
examples before we
culminate with some more
powerful techniques in Python,
thanks to libraries.
How about this problem we encountered
in week 4, which was this.
Let me code up a program called,
again, compare.py here but, this time,
compare to strings and not numbers.
So let me, for instance, get one
string from the user called s.
Just for the sake of discussion, let
me get another string from the user
called t so that we can actually
do some comparison here.
And if s equals equals t, let's go ahead
and print out that they're the same.
Else, let's go ahead and print
out that they're different.
So this is very similar
to what we did in week 4.
But in week 4, recall
we did this specifically
because we had encountered a problem.
For instance, if I run-- whoops.
If I run-- what's going on?
[INAUDIBLE] Come on.
Oh.
OK.
Wow, OK.
Long day.
All right.
If I run the proper command, python
of compare.py, then let's go ahead
and type in something like "cat" in
all lowercase, "cat" in all lowercase.
And they're the same.
If, though, I do this again with
"dog" and "dog," they're the same.
And, of course, "cat" and
"dog," they're different.
But does anyone recall, from two weeks
ago, when I typed in my name twice,
both identically capitalized.
What did it say?
That they were, in fact, different.
And why was that?
Why were two strings in C different,
even though I typed literally
the same thing?
Two different places in memory.
So each string might look the same,
aesthetically, but, of course,
was stored elsewhere in memory.
And yet, Python appears to be
using the equality operator--
equals equals-- like you and I
would expect, as humans-- actually
comparing for us char by char in each of
those strings for actual [? quality. ?]
So this is a feature of Python,
in that it's just easier to do.
And why?
Well, this derives from the
reality that, in Python, there
are no pointers anymore.
There's no underlying memory management.
It's not up to you, now, to worry
about those lower-level details.
The language itself takes
care of that for you.
And so, similarly, if
I do this and don't
ask the user for two
strings, but just one,
and then, I do something like this.
How about give myself a second variable
t, set it equal to s.capitalize, which,
note, is not the same as
upper; capitalize, by design,
per Python's documentation, will only
capitalize the first letter for you--
I can now print out,
say, two fstrings here--
what the value of s is and,
then, let me print out,
with another fstring,
what the value of t is.
And recall that, in
C, this was a problem
because if you capitalize
s and store it in t,
we accidentally
capitalized both s and t.
But in this case, in Python, when I
actually run this and type in "cat"
In all lowercase, the
original s is unchanged
because, when I use capitalize on line
3, this is, indeed, capitalizing s.
But it's returning a copy of the
result. It cannot change s itself
because, again, for that
technical term, s is immutable.
Strings, once they exist,
cannot be changed themselves.
But you can return copies and modify
mutated copies of those same strings.
So, in short, all of those
headaches we encountered in week 4
are now solved, really, in
the way you might expect.
And here's another one that
we dwelled on in week 4,
with the colored liquid in glasses.
Let me code up a program called swap.py.
And in swap.py, let me set
x equal to 1, y equal to 2.
And then, let me just
print out an fstring here.
So how about x is this comma y is that.
And then, let me do that twice,
just for the sake of demonstration.
And in here, recall that we
had to create a swap function.
But then, we had to pass it in
by reference with the ampersand.
And oh my god, that was
peak complexity in C. Well,
if you want to swap x
and y in Python, you
could do x comma y equals y comma x.
And now, python of swap.py.
And there we go.
All of that's handled for you.
It's like a shell game without
even a temporary variable in mind.
So what more can we do here?
How about a few final building blocks?
And these related, now,
to files from that week 4.
Suppose that I want to save some
names and numbers in a CSV file--
Comma Separated Values, which is
like a very lightweight spreadsheet.
Well, first, let me create
a phonebook.csv file
that just has name comma
number as the first row there.
But after that, I'm going to
go ahead, now, and code up
a phonebook.py program
that actually allows
me to add things to this phonebook.
So let me split my screen here so
that we can see the old and the new.
And down here, in my
code for phonebook.py,
in this new and improved
version, I'm going
to actually import a whole other
library, this one called CSV.
And here, too, especially for
people in data science and the like,
really like being able to manipulate
files and data that might very well be
stored in spreadsheets or CSVs--
Comma Separated Values, which
we saw briefly in week 4.
In phonebook.py, then,
it suffices to just
import CSV after reading
the documentation therefore
because this is going
to give me functionality
in code related to CSV files.
So here's how I might
open a file in Python.
I literally call open-- it's
not fopen now; it's just open--
and I open this file
called phonebook.csv.
And just as in C, I'm going
to open it in append mode--
not right, where it would
change the whole thing.
I want to append new line at a time.
After this, I want to get,
maybe, a name from the user.
So let's prompt the user for
some input for their name.
And then, let's prompt
the user for a number,
as well, using input
prompting for number.
All right.
And now, this is a little
cryptic, and you'd only
know this from the documentation.
But if you want to
write rows to a CSV file
that you can, then, view in Excel
or the like, you can do this--
give me a variable called writer--
but I could call it anything I want.
Let me use a csv.writer function
that comes with this CSV library,
passing in the file.
This is like saying, hey, Python,
treat this open file as a CSV file
so that things are separated
with commas and nicely formatted
in rows and columns.
Now, I'm going to do this--
use that writer to write a row.
Well, what do I want to write?
I want to write a short list--
namely, the current name
and the current number--
to that file, but I don't want to use
fprintf and %s and all of that stuff
that we might have had in the past.
And now, I just want to close the file.
Let me reopen my terminal.
Let me run python of phonebook.py,
and let me type in David and then
+1-949-468-2750 and,
crossing my fingers,
watching the actual CSV at top-left.
My code has just added me to the file.
And if I were to run
it again, for instance,
with Carter and +1-617-495-1000,
crossing my fingers again--
we've updated the file.
And it turns out, there's code now,
via which I can even read that file.
But I can, first, tighten this
up, just so you've seen it.
It turns out, in Python, it's so
common to open files and close them.
Humans make mistakes,
and they often forget
to close files, which might, then, end
up using more memory than you intend.
So you can, alternatively,
do this in Python
so that you don't have to
worry about closing files.
You can use this keyword instead.
You can say with the
opening of this file
as a variable called file do
all of the following underneath.
So I'm indenting most of my code.
I'm using this new, Python-specific
keyword called width.
And this is just a matter of saying,
with the following opening of the file,
do those next four lines of code, and
then, automatically close it for me
at the end of the indentation.
It's a minor optimization, but
this, again, is the pythonic way
to do things, instead.
How else might I do this, too?
Well, it turns out that the code
I've written here-- on line 9,
especially-- is a little fragile.
If any human opens this
spreadsheet-- the CSV file in Excel,
Google Spreadsheets, Apple Numbers--
and maybe moves the columns around
just because, maybe, they're fussing.
They saved it, and they don't realize
they've, now, changed my assumptions.
I don't want to, necessarily,
write name and number
always in that order because what if
someone screws up and flips those two
columns by literally
dragging and dropping?
So it turns out that,
instead of using a list here,
we can use another feature
of this library, as follows.
Instead of using a
writer, there's something
called a dictionary
writer or dict writer
that takes the same argument as input--
the file that's opened.
But now, the one
difference here is that you
need to tell this dictionary writer that
your field names are name and number.
And let me close the CSV here.
Name and number are the names of the
fields, the columns in this CSV file.
And when it comes time
to write a new row,
the syntax here is going to be a little
uglier, but it's just a dictionary.
The name I want to
write to the dictionary
is going to be whatever
name the human typed in.
The number that I want
to write to the CSV file
is going to be whatever the
number the human typed in.
But what's different,
now, about this code is,
by simply using a dictionary writer
here instead of the generic writer,
now, the columns can be in this
order or this order or any order.
And the dictionary writer
is going to figure out,
based on the first line of text
in that CSV, where to put name,
where to put number.
So if you flip them, no big deal.
It's going to notice, oh,
wait, the columns changed.
And it's going to insert
the columns correctly.
So just, again, another more
powerful feature that lets you
focus on real work, as
opposed to actually getting
tied up in the weeds of writing
code like this, otherwise.
Questions on this one, as well?
But what we will do,
now, is come full circle
to some of the more sophisticated
examples with which we began,
and I'm going to go back
over to my own Mac laptop
here, where I've got my own
terminal window up and running,
and I was just going to introduce
a couple of final libraries
that really speak to just
how powerful Python can be
and how quickly you
can get up and running.
To be fair, can't necessarily do
all of these things in the cloud,
like in code spaces, because you
need access to your own speakers
or microphone or the like.
So that's why I'm doing
it on my own Mac, here.
But let me go ahead and open
up a program called speech.py.
And I'm not using VS Code here.
I'm using a program called VI that's
entirely terminal window based.
But it's going to allow me, for
instance, to import the Python
text to speech version 3 library.
I'm going to give myself a
variable called engine that's
going to be set equal to
the Python text to speech
3 libraries init method, which is just
going to initialize this library that
relates to text to speech.
I'm going to, then, use the engine's
say function to say something
like, how about, hello comma world.
And then, as my last line, I'm going
to say engine.runAndWait, capitalized
as such, to tell my program, now, to run
that speech and wait until it's done.
All right.
I'm going to save this file.
I'm going to run python of speech.py.
And I'm going to cross my
fingers, as always, and--
INTERPRETER: Hello, world.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So now, I have a program that's
actually synthesizing speech
using a library like this.
How can I, now, modify this to
be a little more interesting?
Well, how about this?
Let me go ahead and prompt
the user for their name,
like we've done several times here,
using Python's built-in name function.
And now, let me go ahead and use
a format string in conjunction
with this library, interpolating
the value of name there.
And-- at least, if my name is
somewhat phonetically pronounceable--
let's go ahead and run python of
speech.py, type in my name, and--
INTERPRETER: Hello, David.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
It's a weird choice of
inflection, but we're
starting to synthesize voice, not
unlike Siri or Google Assistant
or Alexa or the like.
Now, we can, maybe, do something
a little more advanced, too.
In addition to synthesizing
speech in this way,
we could synthesize, for
instance, an actual graphic.
Let me go ahead, now, and
do something like this.
Let me create a program called qr.py.
I'm going to go ahead and
import a library called
OS, which gives you access to operating
system related functionality in Python.
I'm going to import a
library I've pre-installed
called qrcode, which is a
two-dimensional barcode that you
might have seen in the real world.
I'm going to go ahead and
create an image variable using
this qrcode library's make function,
which, per its documentation,
takes a URL, like one
of CS50's own videos.
So we'll do this with
youtu.be/xvF2joSPgG0.
So, hopefully, that's the right lecture.
And now, we've got img.save,
which is going to allow
me to create a file called qr.ping.
Think back, now, on problem set 4
and how painful it was to save files.
We'll just use the save function, now,
in Python and save this as a PNG file--
Portable Network Graphic.
And then, lastly, let's just go ahead
and open with the command open qr.png
on my Mac so that, hopefully,
this just automatically opens.
All right.
I'm going to go ahead and just
double-check my syntax here
so that I haven't made any mistakes.
I'm going to go ahead
and run python of qr.py.
Enter.
That opens up this.
Let me go ahead and zoom in.
If you've got a phone handy and
you'd like to scan this code here,
whether in person or online--
I apologize.
You won't appreciate it.
Amazing!
OK.
And, lastly, let me go back
into our speech example
here, create a final ending
here in our final moments.
And how about we just say something
like "This was CS50," like this.
Let's go ahead, here.
Fix my capitalization,
just for tidiness.
Let's get rid of the name.
And now, with our final flourish and
your introduction to Python equipped--
here we go--
INTERPRETER: This was CS50.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
We'll see you next time.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]