BRIAN YU: In this lab,
your task is going
to be to determine which sorting
algorithm various different programs
use.
We've been introduced, now, to
three different sorting algorithms--
selection sort, bubble
sort, and merge sort.
Recall that in selection sort,
the way the algorithm works
is by taking an array of numbers
and repeating some process--
the process of looking through
that entire array of numbers
to try and find the smallest
item in that entire array,
and then bringing that smallest
item to the beginning of the array.
Then we search through the
remainder of the array,
looking for the next smallest
item, and when we find it,
we bring that next smallest item
back to the beginning of the array,
and we repeat that process, continually
looking through the remaining
unsorted portion of the array,
finding the smallest element,
and swapping it with the
element in the next position.
Once we repeat that process
through the entire array,
we'll end up with a sorted array.
Meanwhile, bubble sort works
a little bit differently.
It also makes passes through the array,
but it compares two values at a time.
It looks at every pair
of values and tries
to determine whether that pair of
numbers is in the correct order.
That is to say, if you're trying to sort
from smallest to largest, making sure
that for any pair of two
numbers, the smaller number is
to the left of the larger number.
And what bubbles sort does is
that if it finds two numbers that
are out of order, then it swaps them.
And bubble sort will continually
go through this process
of considering pairs of values and
swapping them if necessary, until it
gets to the end of the array.
Finally, merge sort works
fundamentally differently.
It works by taking an array and dividing
it into a left half and a right half,
and sorting each of those halves
first, and after we've recursively
sorted each of those halves, we
merge those halves back together.
By repeating this process
recursively again and again,
we can build up an entire
sorted array very quickly.
Each of these algorithms can be
analyzed in terms of their running time,
in terms of big O--
the upper bound on the number of
steps required to complete the sort--
and as well as big omega--
the lower bound on the number of
steps required to complete the sort.
In this case, we can see that for a
selection sort, it has both a big O
and a big omega of n squared.
That is to say that if there are n
numbers that we are trying to sort,
it might take about n squared steps in
order to actually complete that sorting
algorithm.
Bubble sort, meanwhile, also
has a big O of n squared.
As an upper bound, it still might take
on the order of n squared steps to sort
n numbers, but it has a big omega of n.
That is to say, if we
were to get lucky and we
were given an array that's
already sorted, for example,
bubble sort could sort n
items and using just n steps
by making one pass through
the array, concluding
that no swaps are necessary, and then
not continuing on with anything else,
because the array is already sorted.
Meanwhile, merge sort has a running time
of big O of n log n, and big omega of n
log n as well, meaning that if there are
n numbers that we are trying to sort,
this algorithm is going to take on
the order of n times log n steps
in order to sort all of those numbers.
That's better than n squared, though
not nearly as good as big omega of n,
for example.
Your task now, in this lab, is that we
are going to give you three programs--
sort1, sort2, and sort3.
One of them uses selection sort.
One of them uses bubble sort.
And one of them uses merge sort, but
we're not telling you which is which.
Your task is going to be to
run these sorting algorithm
programs on various different inputs--
lists of numbers of different
sizes and different orders--
and to try to determine which
algorithm corresponds to which program.
The files we give you
are going to be these.
We'll give you a file
called random5000.txt,
for example, which will
be a text file that
contains 5,000 numbers in random order.
Likewise, random10000.txt
and random50000.txt
will contain 10,000 50,000 numbers,
respectively, all in random order.
In addition to files
in random order, we'll
also give you files called
reversed5000.txt and reverse10000.txt,
and so forth, each of which will
also contain numbers, but this time
in reverse order, from
largest to smallest.
And finally, we also give you
sorted5000 and sorted10000.txt,
which again will be text files that
just contain numbers, one on each line,
but this time the numbers will
already be in sorted order
from smallest to largest.
Let's take a look at what you
might do with these files.
Here's the distribution
code for the sort lab.
You'll notice that we
have our three programs--
sort1, sort2, and sort3--
and we also have these files.
Random5000.txt, for example, is
going to be a file with 5,000 lines,
each with numbers, where those numbers
are not in any particular order.
Meanwhile, reversed5000.txt is
going to be a text file that
also has 5,000 numbers, but this
time they're in reverse order,
from largest to smallest.
And finally, files like
sorted5000.txt will give you
5,000 lines of numbers, where they're
in sorted order in ascending order
from smallest, all the way to largest.
You can then use these sorting
programs-- sort1, sort2, and sort3--
to try to see how you
would go about sorting,
and how long it might take
to sort any of these files.
For example, I might run ./sort1
on, let's say, random5000.txt.
And what you'll see when I run
that program is the program
will sort those numbers
using some sorting algorithm,
and then print those numbers in
sorted order from smallest to largest.
Now, how long did that take?
It turns out there's also
a program called time
that can time how long it takes
for some other program to run.
So I might say time ./sort1, and then
random5000.txt, and if I run that,
after everything is sorted, I'll see
that the amount of time that took
in real time was 0.168 seconds.
And depending on which
sorting program I use,
and depending on what file I run that
sorting algorithm on, and the number
of values that are in that file, as well
as what order that file is already in,
I might get different values
for the amount of time
it takes to sort and print
out all of those numbers.
Using that information,
your challenge is
to solve that puzzle, to figure
out which algorithm does sort1 use,
and which algorithm does sort2 use,
and which algorithm does sort3 use?
Again, you can test any of these sorting
programs by running ./sort1 or ./sort2
sort3 on a text file that's
provided as a command line argument.
For example, in this case, we're
running sort1 on reversed10000.txt.
And to time how long any of these
commands take, all you need to do
is prepend the time command
in front of whatever command
you would otherwise want to run.
For example, here we're timing how
long it takes to use sort1 to sort
and print out all of the
values in reversed10000.txt.
Ultimately, what you'll
need to do is test and time
each of these programs on some of
the sample files that we give you.
Don't have to test it on all
of them, but you'll likely
want to test on at least a few to get
a sense for how these programs behave
depending on the size of the input,
and depending on how well-ordered
the values inside of that
text file already are.
And using that
information, you should be
able to determine which program
corresponds to which sorting algorithm
by taking advantage of what
you know about the running
times of those sorting algorithms.
If one sorting algorithm has a much
better big omega then it does big O,
then you might expect that it would
be much faster on a text file that's
already sorted, for example.
And you might examine what happens
with each of these programs
as you try to run them on larger
and larger inputs of inputs that
have more and more values to see how
long that takes in comparison to files
that have fewer values.
Using all of that as your
clues and information,
you should be able to piece
together and draw conclusions
about which of these sorting algorithms
we're using in each of those programs.
My name is Brian, and this was sort.