[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50 and this
is already week seven.
And this is the week where
we'll continue where we left off
with Python, introducing
you to a bit more syntax
and capabilities of the language so
you can solve interesting problems.
But a lot of those problems
increasingly are now
going to involve data in some form.
After all, if you think
of most any website
or mobile app or process nowadays
that involves solving problems,
it almost always involves some amount
of data and often data at scale.
Lots and lots of data.
And so what we're going
to see first today
is that, yes, you can use Python to
solve all the problems past that we've
seen and also some data specific
ones, but sometimes it's
just going to be annoying.
It's going to be a little painful.
It's just going to be more work than you
might like to just get to some answer.
And so today we'll too
introduce you to a new language
called SQL, Structured Query Language.
And this is a language that rest
assured is actually much smaller,
relatively speaking, than C and Python.
It sort of does less, but
it doesn't really well.
And it's a language for querying
databases, storing data in it,
updating it, inserting it,
deleting it, and so much more.
And it's the kind of
technology that's used nowadays
in, indeed, web apps and mobile
apps, data science, analytics,
and so much more.
It's really good at storing
lots and lots of data.
Now, this is yet another language.
And believe it or not, next
week we'll introduce you
to three more languages, HTML and
CSS, which are not technically
programming languages.
They're all about aesthetics
and markup of information.
But also JavaScript, which is,
in fact, a programming language.
But the goals here in
CS50 really are going
to be to empower you to
program more generally.
And indeed, when you're out there in
the real world some years from now,
invariably there's going to be some
new other popular language out there.
And hopefully in this week and next
week and beyond, among the goals
is not just to teach you these
languages specifically but again,
how to teach yourself the future
languages that we've not even
heard about just yet.
So with that said, let's
begin with a survey of sorts.
If you go to this URL on your
phone or laptop, cs50.ly/favorites,
a very simple Google Form awaits you
that's just going to ask you a couple
of multiple choice questions.
So go to cs50.ly/favorites, and that
should lead you to a Google Form that
looks a little something
like this asking you first,
as of now in week seven, what is your
favorite language among those options
here.
And then further down,
one more question.
If you think back on problem sets
0 through 6, what was, if any,
your favorite problem set problem?
Be it in Scratch or C or Python.
So answer those two questions.
And in a moment, I'll flip over to
my screen here where you'll see,
and anyone who's used Google Forms
knows, the spreadsheet that's
collecting now this data.
Microsoft Office 365 can do the
same if you use one of those forms.
And what you see here
now is a spreadsheet
in Google Sheets enumerating
all of the audience's questions.
Language is in column B,
problem is in column C,
and each row represents one
student who has responded.
A few of you were super eager for
class today at 8:33 AM Eastern time.
10:32, 11:10.
OK, so now we're getting into
the actual class time here.
And if I scroll down, we'll
probably see a few dozen,
a couple of hundred answers by now.
And yeah, so we're getting
a whole lot of answers here.
And I'm seeing some
patterns emerge, but it's
not necessarily obvious to the
human eyes what those patterns are.
Now of course, you can
use Google Spreadsheets.
You can highlight the data and you
can create charts magically out of it.
But you can only do what Google
lets you do with the data.
And same thing for Microsoft
Excel or Apple Numbers.
But wouldn't it be nice to just be
able to manipulate the raw data,
relatively simple though it is, to
just answer questions about the data?
Maybe long term create your
own charts, customize it
just the way you want
rather than beholden
to software that's off
the shelf like this.
Well, how could we go about doing this?
Well, let me propose that
we treat this data set now
as what we're going to call
for now a flat file database.
We'll see today that
there's fancier databases,
but the simplest database in the
world is really just like a .csv file.
And we saw that a couple of weeks
ago in C. We wrote a bit of C code
that used fprintf to write data to a
file using commas as the separator.
We didn't really do much
more with CSVs at the time
though, because it's really
annoying, painful, time consuming,
not fun to use C for something like that
because of malloc and memory and all
that stuff.
But with Python, it's
going to be much easier.
And so any time you have access to some
data set where you can just download it
to your own Mac or PC or
your cloud environment,
it's sort of a candidate for now writing
code to do something with the data.
Maybe analyze it right away.
If it's been human imported
manually, maybe you
have to clean it up by doing
a lot of find and replace
but not with your keyboard
but rather with code.
And so let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go back to my
Google Sheet here that has
all of the data that's come in now.
And let me go ahead and download
this via the File menu here.
And let's see.
Download.
And you can see a
whole bunch of options.
Most formats might be
familiar, but today we'll
focus just on this one, Comma
Separated Values or CSV.
That's going to go ahead and download
it on my Mac here into my own Downloads
folder.
And now I'm going to
go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and pull up
VS Code in the cloud here.
And if you've never done this before,
there's a couple of ways to do it.
But the simplest way to upload a
file to your code space, so to speak,
is just a sort of drag and drop.
That's going to magically
upload it to the server there.
And we'll see that, one, it has a very
long file name, which I'm actually
going to clean this up
because that's going
to be very tedious to type in my code.
So I could either right
click, of course, up here,
but I'm going to use my Linux command.
So let's move this file called CSV
50 2022 something or other and let's
just name it more simply favorites.csv.
So all lowercase, no
spaces, sort of good basics.
And let me go ahead now and open up
this file with code favorites.csv.
I'll close my File Explorer and
we'll see exactly the same data
as before but not quite as pretty
as Google Sheets makes it be.
Rather we see here that I still have
three columns, timestamp, language,
problem, and then all of the values
down below, including the timestamps
and the answers they're for.
But it doesn't have proper columns.
It just has commas separating them.
Now, we could very
easily write Python code
just like we wrote C code to
manipulate files like this
either to write or read.
But instead let's do
something that's a little more
pleasant, which is indeed
in the form of Python.
So Python actually comes
with native support for CSVs.
It has indeed a package
called CSV that just
lets you read and write and do
a whole bunch of useful stuff
when it comes to CSV files.
So let's go ahead and do
something with this file.
Let me go back here to VS Code.
I'm going to close
favorites.csv for now.
But just remember in your mind that
timestamp was the first column,
language was the second column,
and problem was the third.
And notice because we're using commas,
they don't again line up perfectly,
but that's not a problem.
There are two commas in
every line presumably.
And I'm going to go ahead and now create
a file called how about favorites.py so
that I can start writing some
code to manipulate this data.
And let's do something simple.
Let's just write a simple program
in Python that opens this file,
reads it, and print something
out just as a safety check
that I know what I'm doing, even
though it's not going to be useful.
So in Python, if you want
CSV support, you import CSV.
And that gives you access to all
the magical capabilities thereof.
Let me now go ahead
and use this technique
to open a file in Python,
which is similar in C.
But with Python, we're going to do this.
The keyword with.
I'm going to open a file
called favorites.csv,
which was the shorter name I gave it.
This is optional, but
just for explicitness, I'm
going to open it in read mode
explicitly, just like f open
took a second argument as well.
And I'm going to name this file
once open quite simply file,
though I could call it anything I want.
And now it's just an open file.
So far as Python knows at this
moment, it's just text, or better yet,
it's just zeros and ones.
If you want this Python package
called CSV to actually do
something useful with it, you have to
load this file now into the library.
And the simplest way to do this is to
give myself a variable called reader
because I want to read this file.
Though this too I could
call anything else.
I'm going to then set that equal to
the return value of a function called
csv.reader.
And I pass to that per the
documentation the open file.
So step one, I open the file.
And this just gives me
access to the bytes therein.
Step two now with csv.reader
tells the Python package
called CSV to do something useful
with it and start analyzing the commas
and allow me to parse it further.
So let's go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead now and within
this loop let's say this.
Sorry, within this open
file, let's do this.
For every row, if you will,
or line in the file, a.k.a.
reader, let's go ahead and print
out just how about row bracket 1.
Now what's going on here?
Well, it turns out if you read the
documentation for the CSV reader
function, what it hands you back is
essentially this special object, so
to speak, that allows you to
treat it as though it's just
a really big list of lines
from the file, a.k.a. reader.
So by saying for row in reader,
this is a way more succinct way
of saying give me the first
line in the file plus plus,
give me the second line
in the file plus plus,
and so forth that we would have done
what much more mechanically in C.
This is just much more Pythonic
and English friendly, if you will.
So in every iteration of this loop,
row is going to contain all of the data
from the current row.
But better yet, what
the reader function does
for me is it hands me each row
not just as a big string or STR
of text in Python.
It gives me what apparently
based on the syntax on line six.
Any instinct?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: A list.
DAVID MALAN: It's giving
me back indeed a list.
And I presume the visual
clue for you was the fact
that we're using square brackets here.
And indeed, row bracket 1
is going to be not the first
but the second element in that list.
And so just take a guess.
When I run this code in a moment,
what's going to get printed?
The timestamp, the
language, or the problem?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: The language.
DAVID MALAN: The language because
it's the second column that is
in the file delimited by those commas.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me clear my terminal down here.
Let me run Python of
favorites.py and Enter.
And there's everything.
It was super fast.
But there's a really long list here.
And in fact, if I increase the size
of my terminal and start scrolling up,
you'll just see all of the raw data.
Now, this isn't that useful yet.
I could have just glanced at the CSV.
But clearly now I have the
ability to open the file,
parse it, so to speak, that is break
it up into its constituent parts,
and do something with
specific parts therein.
All right.
So if I want to do this a
little more pleasantly though,
let me at least make this
semantically a little cleaner.
And you know what, just for clarity,
let me just give myself a variable.
It's not strictly necessary,
but I know that this is
the favorite, for instance, language.
So let's just call it favorite.
Set it equal to row bracket 1.
And now just to be more
explicit in my code,
even though again, we don't
need the variable per se,
this code is, of course,
going to do the same thing.
It's just using an additional
variable called favorite.
If I go down here, scroll
up, run the program again,
I get back to the exact same data.
But this is a stepping
stone to something
that's even more powerful
about Python support
for CSV files is that you don't
have to just treat the return
value as a list with 0 and 1 and 2.
So just thinking intuitively here,
why is this maybe not the best design
to hand you, the programmer,
back the data in a list
that's numerically indexed with 0, 1, 2?
It clearly works, but critique this.
What could go wrong?
What's a little poorly designed?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: You have to always
remember what the things are,
what the order is [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So yeah, so it's up to you to repeat--
it's up to you to remember what
column the data is actually in.
And God forbid you're collaborating
with someone else on the spreadsheet.
If you've used Google Spreadsheets,
you can move columns around
maybe just because you want
to visually reorganize things.
And if you do this and then someone
else downloads that same data,
all of their code is going to break.
So that's just really bad design.
It's fragile just because you're
sort of on the honor system
that one means the data that you want.
So wouldn't it be nice if it
could be a little more explicit?
Well, recall that the very first
line in this file is actually this.
And I paused the output this time
so that we can see more optionally.
I just reran favorites.py.
And notice one of these
things is not like the other.
Every output was either scratch or C
or Python except for this first one.
Why am I seeing the word language here?
Where did language come from?
You didn't have the
ability to manually input.
No.
Where did it come from?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: That would be the header.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the header.
The very first row in the
file, which by human convention
generally just defines what the
columns represent so that there's
some human useful information there.
Now, that's not really intended to
be part of my output at the moment,
so there is a way to skip this.
If you want to skip the first row, you
can actually do something like this.
You can say next row, and that
will just ignore that row.
So then I'm starting really
with the every row thereafter.
But there's a better way
to handle this than that.
That will get rid of the row in
the output, but let me go ahead
and use a different
feature of the CSV package
that's just going to make this
a little cleaner all together.
So let me clear my terminal window here.
Let me undo this next
thing that I just added.
And instead of using a reader, let me
go ahead and use a dictionary reader,
abbreviated dict reader, that's going
to now return me the equivalent of all
of the rows one at a time.
So I can still call it
reader just as before.
But as the name implies, what
this reader is going to return
is not a list after list
after list but a dictionary,
a dictionary, a dictionary.
And remember, a dictionary is just
a collection of key value pairs.
So what does that mean?
What are the keys?
What are the values?
Well, now that I'm using a dictionary
reader, I can actually do this.
Instead of on the honor system
remembering that I want column one,
I can treat row now not as
a list but as a dictionary.
And that means I can go in here
and say quote unquote "language."
And we saw that back in week six.
Python allows you to
index into dictionaries
using square bracket notation in
strings or STRs on the inside,
just like lists allow for numbers.
But this now I think is going
to be a little more robust.
If I run this again, Python of
favorites.py, of that worked out fine.
And let me pause the output too
by using this program called more.
Now I don't even see the header.
So now whoever works with Python
wrote the code for this package
to just analyze that first
line of code, use the header
as you just called it as the
keys, and then every time you
iterate through this loop, it updates
the values, the values, the values,
but the keys stay the same.
Any questions then on this technique?
Suffice it to say this
would be painful in C. Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So the keys are always going to be
quote unquote "timestamp, language,
and problem."
But on each iteration of
this loop here, the row
is going to contain a different row
of values, different row of values,
different row of values.
So you're going to get back one
dictionary for every student who
submitted the Google Form, if you
will, while iterating through it there.
All right.
So once we have this ability here, why
don't we go ahead and transition to
how about not just using
that dictionary reader, which
it makes the code a little more robust.
Because now if you move the
columns around, no big deal.
It doesn't matter if the
numeric indices change.
You can still use
those keywords instead.
But let's actually analyze the data now.
I'm just spitting it out, which is
not solving any problems for anyone.
So let's go ahead and count the
popularity of Scratch, C, and Python
and see what everyone's
been thinking here.
All right.
So how might I do this?
Well, let me go ahead
and do this up here.
Before I start iterating, let me give
myself, let's say, three variables.
And to keep things simple, I'll
say one variable called Scratch.
Set it equal to 0 for 0 students so far.
C is going to equal 0 and
Python is going to equal 0.
There's a slightly
prettier way of doing this,
just because this is like three lines
of code to do something very simple.
You could alternatively
in Python but not C
do Scratch comma C comma
Python equals 0 comma 0.
So kind of slightly more elegant
just to fit it all into one line.
But now let's just do
something more interesting.
On line seven, I'm still
going to figure out
what the current favorite language is.
And now I'm just going to
do some conditional checks.
How about if that favorite equals
equals quote unquote "Scratch,"
Let's go ahead and
increment Scratch by 1.
We can't do plus plus in Python,
but we can do plus equals 1.
How about elif if favorite equals
equals C, then let's do C plus equals 1.
We could do else.
This is actually a good design question.
Should I do else?
Should I do elif?
Any instincts here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
really good instincts.
Just in case someone goes
and adds another language
to the form next week
because we're obviously
going to introduce
another language today,
you don't want your code
to now artificially inflate
the scores for Python
just because you're
conflating multiple languages together.
So the more defensive sort of better
way to write this code, I agree,
would be elif favorite
equals equals Python.
Then let's go ahead and
increment Python plus equals 1.
And if there's a new
language next week, we're
obviously going to have
to update the code,
but at least we're not miscounting.
We're just missing the new language.
So I think that's slightly more robust.
All right, now at the very bottom of
this program and outside of the loop
when I'm all done counting,
let me go ahead and print out
using some f strings.
How about the total number of
people whose favorite is Scratch?
So this is just week
six f string syntax.
Let me go ahead and print out another
f string for C. And I'm, of course,
putting the variables in
curly braces, all lowercase,
but the English words I'm
doing capitalization for.
Let's do a final one with f Python
colon and then in curly braces
Python close quote.
And I think I'm done.
So let me just hide my
terminal for a second.
Here's the total program.
Same stuff as before.
Open favorites.csv.
Open it further with the dictionary
reader to do that processing for us.
Initialize three variables to 0 just
so we have something to count with.
And then iterate over
the file row by row.
And this is just some sort of
week one style conditional logic,
albeit in Python, counting things.
All right.
So how can we now execute this?
Let me go back to my terminal.
Python of favorites.py.
And here we go.
As of today, everyone who's reporting
in live via the Google Form,
their favorite languages are--
interesting.
That's pretty interesting too after
just one week of Python no less.
But Scratch is a
healthy contender there.
A lot of C. So a pretty good mix here.
So is this going to be the best way
to write this program long term?
Well, as you noted, if there's
a new language next week,
this week we're going to have
to constantly update this.
And here's where you should let
your mind wander to the future.
If we have a fourth language, fifth
language, sixth, seventh, eighth,
which aspects here might kind
of have some code smell to it?
This probably isn't the best
design to set us up for the future.
What might be better than this?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: We need to add
a language to line five.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
We have to keep adding
a language to line five.
And OK, not a big deal.
We could add SQL today and
maybe JavaScript next week.
But any time a line of
code, a line of logic,
it's just going to grow out of control.
We've had this chat a couple
of times with different syntax.
There's probably a better way than that.
So let's do that.
Instead of using these individual
variables, we could maybe use a list,
but a list would be a little confusing
because what does bracket 0 mean?
What is bracket 1, bracket 2?
But a dictionary, recall, is this
Swiss army knife of data structures
whereby you can associate anything
with anything else, keys with values.
So I dare say a cleaner way to
solve this problem that sets us up
for less work or confusion later would
be to create a new variable called
counts, if that's what we're
doing, counting things up,
and just set it equal
to an empty dictionary.
And you can literally say dict with
the open parenthesis, close parenthesis
and nothing or the more
Pythonic just use open
and close curly braces
with nothing inside.
That gives me an empty dictionary just
like square brackets gives me a list.
Now, my logic down here
has to change a little bit.
But what's nice is I don't need
one conditional for every language.
Because again, if we have a fourth,
a fifth, a sixth, that chunk of code
is also going to grow a
bit out of control too.
So I can get rid of this here.
And what I think I'm
going to do is say this.
Whatever the current favorite is
from the current row in the file,
why don't we go into our
counts variable at that key?
And again, favorite is a variable.
It's not quote unquote "favorite."
It's going to be Scratch or C or Python.
And then why don't we go ahead
and just increment whatever
the value of that count is at that key?
Now, this is technically buggy.
We're really close, but there is a bug.
Does anyone want to
conjecture what the bug is?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: A good question that
answers my question nonetheless.
So no.
The magic you describe will not happen.
And to repeat the hypothesis,
will this automatically
create a key for every
language that we try
plugging into those square brackets?
Short answer no.
Odds are this is going to
create a key error, one of those
traceback error messages
that you've probably
seen by now either in
class or in problem sets
whereby if Scratch hasn't appeared in
the dictionary before or C or Python,
then the dictionary has no
clue what you're talking about.
So I think we actually still need
some conditional logic but not
that's going to grow longer
and longer with each language.
What I think we probably
want to do is this.
If the current favorite is
in the count dictionary,
and this is the Pythonic way of just
saying is this key in this dictionary,
then go ahead and safely do
counts favorite plus equals 1.
Else, to your conjecture
now, else what I want to do.
Counts favorites equals, yeah, 1.
So initialize a brand new
key to a brand new value of 1
because I'm obviously
just seeing this language.
Otherwise increment again and again.
And now down here I just need
to tweak my syntax a little bit.
I don't need to print out all of
these things one at a time manually.
I can actually get away I think with
another loop at the very bottom here.
So how about I do this?
For each favorite in
those counts, and this is,
again, the Pythonic way to iterate
over all of the keys in a dictionary,
go ahead and print out using an f
string whatever the current favorite is,
Scratch or C or Python, and then a colon
and then figure out what its count is.
And you can do that by going
into the counts dictionary,
looking at the favorite
key, and get back its value.
So I close my curly braces.
I close my quotes.
And even though this looks ugly at the
moment, now this is much more dynamic.
Because if we go and add
SQL to the CSV file tomorrow
or we add JavaScript next
week, this will just work.
It will keep working now automatically.
All I change is the Google
Form, not my actual code.
All right.
Let's try Python of favorites.py.
Cross my fingers as always.
And there now is the data as of now.
Questions on this code here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
What if you wanted to print
it in a particular order?
Well, I could give you
a couple of solutions.
If you want to print it out in--
it's already coincidentally
in alphabetical order.
So you got that for free although
that's just by chance here.
But there is a way to do this.
And let me propose that we
go down here to my loop.
And I explicitly use a function you
might not have seen in Python yet,
but it's literally
called sorted, which is
going to take either a list
or, in this case, a dictionary
and by default sort it
by key alphabetically.
Now, if my intuition
is correct, this is not
going to change the output,
because it's already alphabetical.
But if you read the documentation
for the sorted function,
it takes multiple parameters
potentially, some of which
are named parameters.
And so you can actually do this.
If you want to the counts
but you want to reverse
the order for whatever reason here so
that it's reverse alphabetical order.
Now let me go ahead
and rerun this and I'll
keep the previous output on the screen.
Enter and now it's backwards
alphabetically, if you will.
Other questions on this here?
No?
How about then we transition
to changing sorting by value.
And this is going to escalate
a little quickly briefly
but then we'll tone it down again.
Notice that right now this
is indeed sorting by key.
What if, especially if
I have lots of data,
it'd be nice to make a top 10 list
or, in this case, a top three list
and actually see in order of the counts,
the values what these popular ones are.
So it's not C, Python, Scratch.
It should ideally be
Python, then C, then
Scratch because of the values
and the magnitude thereof.
So how can I do this?
Well, it turns out there is another
key, another parameter that you
can pass to the sorted
function that is typically
implemented as a function itself.
And so I'm going to
go ahead and do this.
I'm going to temporarily
define a function called
get value just to make my life easier.
And this get value function is going
to take I'll say a language parameter.
And then all I'm going to do is return
whatever the count is of that language.
So out of context, this is
just a super simple function
that you hand it a language
like Scratch or C or Python,
it's just going to tell you
what the count is thereof
in that dictionary called counts.
But what I can do now down here in my
newly introduced call to sort it is I
can tell it what to use as its key.
Instead of using literally
the key, Scratch, C,
Python, I can sort of override that
behavior and say, you know what?
To figure out what to sort by,
go ahead and call this function
called get value.
Notice that I have not put
parentheses after get value
because I don't want to call
get value right then and there.
I want to pass the get value function
as itself in argument to the sorted
function so that the sorted function
written years ago by the people
at Python can call my version
of get value again and again
and again when they try
to sort this actual data.
So now if I add that and I leave reverse
equals true, let's see what happens.
Python of favorites.py.
Enter.
And now I get my top 10, or
in this case, top three list.
And if I had more sophisticated
data with more columns
all together that I
actually care about, I
could even sort this
more powerfully as well.
But let me clean this
up a little bit, just
so you've seen it, even
though we won't use these
that often in CS50 until the end of
the class will they come up again.
Technically this is a little bit--
this isn't necessarily the best
design to spend all this time
implementing a function and
then only use it in one place.
In general, we've argued
that you don't necessarily
need a variable if you're only
going to use it in one place.
You don't really need a
function if you're only
going to use it in one place.
And here we kind of have
a good candidate for that.
And so it turns out
in Python if you don't
want to bother creating a
function just to use it once,
you can create what's called
an anonymous function, a.k.a.
a lambda function, like
the lambda symbol familiar.
And a lambda function, the syntax
is a little strange looking,
but you say this.
You literally say lambda.
You literally then say
the name of the argument
that you want this anonymous
function with no name to take.
Then you have a colon.
And then quite simply, you
write what you want the return
value of this function to be.
You don't even say return literally.
These lambda functions
are meant to be used
super tersely so that you can in one
line express something like this.
And I admit this looks more cryptic,
I think, than the previous version.
But as you get more comfortable
with Python or other languages that
support this feature, it allows you to
not bother with lines of code like that
and just tighten up
your code a little bit.
So this line here, lambda
language colon counts language,
is the one line version of this.
And you don't even need to
bother picking a name for it.
Lambda tells Python I
didn't waste any time
thinking of a name for this function.
So questions then on this technique of
using Python to analyze data like this?
Any questions?
We're almost done with Python.
Questions?
No?
OK.
So why don't we make things
a little more interesting?
Because we had a much juicier
data set with the problems
that we've assigned over
the past several weeks.
Why don't we go ahead
and, quite simply, I think
we wrote pretty darn good code here.
So I think we can pretty much
just change a bit of it to say,
let's see, if I don't want
language, I want problem.
And if I want to sort by not language
but problem, I think that's it.
I think if I didn't
overlook something here
just by changing what column I'm
reading the data from and then
just to be consistent
renaming my variables
just so I know what I'm looking
at, what will this program now
do after those minor changes?
What will I see when I run this?
What would be the first
thing I see when I run this?
Tough crowd today.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: The problem.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
The top problem.
So the most popular problem,
which I'm a little worried
it might be hello or just Scratch,
but let's go ahead and see.
So let me go ahead and
open my terminal window.
I'll even maximize my terminal
window so we can see a lot.
Let me go ahead and run
Python of favorites.py.
I'm going to go ahead now and cross
my fingers that I didn't mess up
and hit Enter.
And OK, great.
We peaked early.
So Scratch was the most
popular program according
to the data at the time I downloaded it.
I'm sure other votes have come in since.
Filter in week four was tied
then with Tideman as well.
Mario is a close third
there and so forth.
So this is helpful for us on
staff that not so much love
down here at the bottom of the list.
So it was a bunch of
code to write, but now
that we've written it in this
very versatile dynamic way,
it's pretty good for just like
crunching data and doing some analytics.
But it's still a decent number of
lines to have had to write manually.
And this is where sometimes it isn't
necessarily the right tool for the job,
but rather a candidate for using
some other language altogether,
especially when it's not just
a one time program that you run
and you want to see the answer.
What if you want to take input from the
user and answer questions dynamically
like a mobile app would,
like a website would,
like Microsoft Excel or Apple Numbers
or Google Sheets would for you.
Well, let's make one final change for
now to this version of the program
and actually take in some user input.
So besides just loading all
of the data into memory,
let's go ahead and down below
here not just print out the top 10
list, if you will, but prompt
the user for their favorites.
I'm going to use Python's
input function and I'm
going to prompt them with "favorite,"
quote unquote, like tell me what
your favorite problem--
what problem rather
you are interested in.
And now let me go ahead and say if that
favorite is in the count's variable,
so you didn't type in something
random that we didn't actually
assign as a problem,
then let me go ahead
and print with a format string whatever
that favorite is of yours and show you
the actual popularity
thereof by indexing
into counts using that favorite
as the key and printing this.
So now it's a dynamic program.
It doesn't dump all of the
data and all of the summations.
Rather it's going to allow me to
see what my choice of favorite is.
And I'm going to go ahead and say,
let's see, I'm a fan of Mario here.
So Enter.
And indeed, we see the same value we
saw a moment ago but just for Mario.
But the point now is that,
one, all of this is possible.
Two, it's way easier and more pleasant
than this would have been in C.
This is still only 15 lines of code.
And in C, again, there's
the memory management.
There's the iterating over the
strings trying to find the commas.
There's just a lot more work.
But honestly even when you just
want to answer a question like this
in Excel and Apple Numbers,
Google Sheets, generally, you
can just highlight things.
You can click a button and boom, you get
your answer for summation or max or min
or any of those sort of basics.
Wouldn't it be nice if we weren't
taking a step backwards as programmers
and being more powerful and yet we
now have to do more of the work?
So maybe sometimes Python's
not or any language
is not the best tool for the job.
And that's going to now allow us to
introduce more generally something
called a relational database.
Graduating from mere flat
file databases like text files
or binary files in
which all of your data
is stored to something more proper.
But first, questions.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
To reiterate, if I were--
is this case sensitive?
So if I were to type in Mario
in all lowercase and hit Enter,
I actually get no such response.
Now that might be acceptable, because
the problem technically is a capital M.
But that's a little ridiculous to
be that pedantic about the input.
So how could we solve this?
Any tips for how we can make
this a little more robust?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, yeah.
Yeah.
So we could use a few different
functions, one of which
is called title, which will change it
to title case where it capitalizes,
like in most English sentences,
the first letter of that sentence.
We could use capitalize.
We could use upper.
We could use lower.
But indeed, we could just decide how we
want to standardize the capitalization.
Either uppercase, lowercase,
or some combination thereof.
And just make sure that you
change the counts themselves.
Make sure that you do
the same to favorite
and make sure that maybe you
keep a backup of the data
if you want to show the original
version that came from the CSV
without presuming to just
capitalize everything for the user.
But indeed, that would be
the most common scenario.
You just make things case
insensitive when doing those matches.
Other questions now on Python before
we leave it behind for the coming week?
All right, well then let's introduce
these relational databases.
So relational database is what every--
it's a super popular way
of storing lots of data.
This is what the Twitters of the
world, the Googles of the world,
the Metas of the world use to
store some of their data at scale.
There are alternatives
to relational databases.
Indeed, today we'll talk
about a language called SQL.
There's also a movement, if you
will, or an alternative generally
called NoSQL, which
is just the opposite.
You don't use SQL.
There are things called object
oriented databases and the like.
But if you've ever heard of MySQL
or PostgreSQL or Microsoft SQL
Server or Oracle or MariaDB
or a bunch of other products,
both free and commercial, this
is what they're talking about.
Databases that are designed
to store lots of data.
And what's nice about
relational databases
is that they're really similar to
the spreadsheets with which you
were presumably familiar
long before today's class.
So a relational database
is going to store,
as you'll see, all of the
data in rows and columns.
Now, the terminology will
thereafter be a little different.
Instead of having sheets,
you're going to have tables.
But those tables are still
going to have rows and columns.
And you're going to have even
more control over the performance
of your data when you start to access
it using this Structured Query Language
or SQL.
This is a language you can
use for web apps, mobile apps.
A lot of analysts would
sit down at their Mac or PC
and actually ask questions of
data to get back the answer.
And wonderfully, even though there
will be some new syntax today,
SQL really just does four basic things.
CRUD is the sort of crude acronym here.
CRUD is a way of remembering that
a relational database supports
ultimately creating data, reading
data, updating data, and deleting data.
So even if you're
feeling like, wow, this
is a lot of new syntax, which it
isn't relative to our past languages,
the only things you're doing really are
creating data, reading data, updating,
and deleting the same.
Now a little confusingly in SQL, the
corresponding functions or commands
that exist that map to
CRUD are actually this.
So it's still create, but there's
another one called insert.
It's not read, which is more of the
computer scientist way of saying it,
but select, which is a
little more explicit.
Like select data you care about.
Update is still update.
Delete is still delete.
But there's another command called drop,
which lets you drop, that is delete,
entire tables as well.
So you can create tables
using syntax that's
generally going to look like this.
You'll say create table.
You'll give the name of the
table, which you can call most
anything you want, but generally
all lowercase, no spaces is best.
Then in parentheses, you can specify
a comma separated list of the columns
that you might want in this table.
So this is the code
equivalent in the SQL language
of manually opening Google
Sheets or Excel or Numbers
and clicking in the top left
cell and like typing timestamp
and then in the next typing language
and then the third typing problem.
This is the way to define what
your headers are, if you will,
in a spreadsheet.
But now it's called a table.
Now, we won't use this
command manually first.
Let's do something a little simpler.
We're going to start off by just
importing this data ourselves.
And I'm going to go ahead and do this.
Let me go back to VS Code here.
I'm going to leave behind
favorites.py for now,
because now we're going to transition
to this other language called SQL.
And to do this, I am going to
create a new database file.
And I'm going to do so using
a command called sqlite3,
which is just the third
version thereof, and I'm
going to give the database
a name of favorites.db.
There's different conventions, but
this is one of the most common.
When I hit Enter, this is going to
create for me a new empty database just
like opening an untitled spreadsheet in
Excel, Google Sheets, or Apple Numbers.
I'm being prompted do I
want to create favorites.db.
I'll hit Y for Yes.
OK, we're up and running.
Now, you're going to
notice a different prompt.
I'm not in my Linux prompt per se,
which is always the dollar sign.
I'm now inside of the
program called SQLite.
And we're going to use SQLite, SQLite3,
as just an interactive way for now
of playing with SQL code.
At the end of today, we'll show you
how you can use SQL in Python code
so that you still write Python
code to do whatever you want,
but you can talk to
databases using Python.
And this is exactly how
web apps, mobile apps work.
For instance, on iOS, on an
iPhone, an iPad, or the like,
if you want to store data, it's
very often stored in a SQL database,
as we're about to do.
But you might use a language
called SWIFT or Objective C.
And the same exists in
the world of Android
using Java or Kotlin or something
else to query the database.
So we're going to see SQL in isolation
for now like an analyst might just
use with their Mac or PC, but we're
going to tie it together by day's end.
So at this terminal SQLite, let me go
ahead and execute this command first.
I'm going to first put
SQLite into CSV mode,
because I'm going to cut
some corners initially.
And I'm just going to
automatically import
all of the data that was submitted
via the Google Form, which I exported
as a CSV and uploaded to my code space.
And I'm just going to automatically
say turn this CSV file into a SQL
database for me just so I
don't have to figure out
what those create table commands are.
So to do this, I'm
going to say mode csv so
that SQLite knows that this is the
command, knows that this is a CSV file.
It's literally .mode.
So the dot comes before
the keyword there.
And now I'm going to say .import
and then the name of the file I want
to import, which is favorites.csv.
And now the name of the table that
I want to create with that data.
And just for consistency, I'm
going to call it favorites.
I could change these things
to be anything I want,
but I'm going to do that.
And voila, nothing
seems to have happened.
But just like in C and in Python and
Linux when nothing seems to happen,
that's usually a good thing.
It means I didn't mess up.
So if I want to see what just
happened, there's this other command.
And these commands that
start with dots, these
are SQLite specific, which is
indeed a lightweight version of SQL.
They're not SQL, per se.
So if you're using Oracle
or something else like that,
you're not going to use
these exact commands.
You'll see the ones we
use in just a moment.
And here's the first.
When I type .schema, the schema of a
database is the design of the database.
What are the tables?
What are the columns and all of that?
So when I type .schema, this actually
in this case shows me the create table
command that was automatically drawn
for me by just doing this import line.
Once I get more comfortable with SQL,
I could literally type this out myself
or use some program to
generate that as well.
But what it's creating for me is this.
Create table if it doesn't exist,
even though it's more terse than that.
I want to create a
table called favorites.
And then the columns
for that table are going
to be timestamp, which is going
to be text, comma, language,
which is also going to
be text, comma, problem,
which is also going to be text.
That was just inferred very trivially by
the .import command to just figure out
that, yes, just give me a three column
database table based on the Google
Form.
Questions on this?
These are commands you run
once to get up and running.
You don't run these commands
frequently, but we have them
on the slide just for reference.
All right.
So now let's do something
a little more interesting.
I'm going to clear my SQLite terminal
here, but I'm still in SQLite.
I'm going to now use some of
my first SQL commands, which
recall were among them select.
So CRUD, C-R-U-D. The R was select.
This is maybe the most
common, the most useful,
the most powerful thing
to use with a SQL database
selecting data to answer
questions akin to the ones we
were trying to answer with Python.
This is the general syntax.
Any time you want to select data from a
SQL database, you literally say select.
You then specify the column or columns
that you want to select data from.
You literally write the word from and
then you specify the name of the table.
You want to get that data
from semicolon, in this case.
Everything that's in capitals
here is a SQL keyword.
Strictly speaking, you don't
have to capitalize things,
but we would encourage you
to do so stylistically.
And especially as you're learning
and even as you're writing it,
it just helps to distinguish SQL
from words you chose, like the names
of the columns and the data therein.
So do adopt early on this convention.
So let me go back now
to my code space here.
I'm running my terminal window
with SQLite3 inside of it.
Suppose that I just want
to get all of the data
from the favorites table, which
was automatically imported.
Let's do this.
Select.
I want everything.
Well, I can do timestamp
comma language comma problem.
But you know what?
Here's a convenience already.
If you want everything, there's
what's called a wild card character
in SQL, which is just a
star, an asterisk, which
means give me every column without
my knowing even what they're called.
Let me go ahead now and say
from favorites semicolon.
And this is the SQL way of opening
the database, iterating over
every row therein, printing
out every row therein, done.
So those three steps, which was
like nine lines of Python code
give or take earlier,
is now one line of SQL.
I hit Enter.
There is all of the data.
So I see now all of the data.
Just output it as a CSV here.
But it's not the CSV file.
It's now actually the table.
And in fact, just for
good measure, let me
do this, because you'll see the behavior
a little differently the next time we
open the file.
I've just exited out of SQLite3.
I'm going to rerun it, but I'm
not going to reimport the data
or do anything like that,
because my file now exists.
In fact, let me take one step back.
If I type ls at my Linux prompt,
there's my favorites.py from before.
There's my favorites.csv from before.
And here's a third file that I did
create a moment ago when I first
ran SQLite3.
So the data is persistent.
It's not using RAM or memory.
Anything I do now is saved there.
So let's go ahead and rerun
SQLite3 with the same file.
But I'm not going to--
I don't have to reimport everything,
because the file already exists.
Let me now do that same thing again.
Select star from favorites
to get all of the data.
And what you'll see now is the same
data, but it's a little prettier now.
Because I reran it, I effectively
disabled CSV mode this time.
And what I'm now seeing is the
entire contents of this database
table called favorites.
Now, there's nothing new
here, but you're just
seeing now like an ASCII
or Unicode version of all
of the same data from that database.
Well, suppose I want to
get a subset of the data.
Well, let me clear my screen.
And just like in Linux, I can Control L
just to clean things up aesthetically.
Suppose I want to get
just the languages.
So I could do select
language from favorites.
And this will now select not
all three columns, a.k.a.
star, this will only select the language
column and all of the data therein.
If I hit Enter, voila.
Now I just see those there.
No timestamps, no problems.
It's just a slice of
the table, if you will.
All right, not that interesting still
because it's just a big column of data.
But now things get more interesting.
It turns out in SQL that there are
functions that come with this language,
just like C, just like Python.
In SQL, some of the more useful
ones, some of the simpler ones,
are these here.
Average, count, distinct,
lower, max, min,
upper, which pretty
much do what they say.
And count is a particularly useful one.
Let's start with that.
It's a reasonable question to be asked
how many people submitted the Google
Form by the time I actually
downloaded the CSV.
Well, why don't we go ahead and do this?
Let me go back to VS Code
here in my terminal window.
Let me select not star
but the count of star.
So give me the count of
the rows that are being
returned from the database called--
the database table called favorites.
Now when I hit Enter, I'm not
going to get all of the data.
I'm just going to get simply a number.
430 rows came back.
So that's pretty good.
I now know how much data is in there.
Well, what languages were in there?
Well, I could do select language
from favorites just as before,
but that's not that useful,
especially if I'm inheriting the data.
Like I'm the analyst who's been
handed a data set by my boss
and they want me to crunch some numbers.
OK, I could load this into Excel.
I could sort it.
But you can use SQL now to answer
pretty basic questions too.
If you want to select the distinct
languages in the data set because you
weren't privy to the Google
Form, let me go ahead
and select only the distinct
languages from the favorites table.
And now I hit Enter and I get
back a much more succinct answer.
Just the three languages in question.
Not really that useful since
I created the Google Form,
but certainly if you're
inheriting data from someone else,
you've just downloaded
a data set, at least now
I'm arguably wrapping my
mind around what's going on.
Now, this is not necessary
for such a small data set,
but I can combine these things.
Select the count of the distinct
languages in this data set
called favorites.
And now I should get back what answer?
So hopefully indeed an
answer called three.
And what you're getting
back notice aesthetically
too is like a mini temporary table.
When I asked for just the
distinct languages, what SQL hands
me back is this
temporary table in memory
that has one column called
language and then three rows.
Now, this is not saved anywhere.
It's just executed
ephemerally like this.
But that's why it's
depicted in this way.
What you're getting is
subsets of your data, smaller
tables containing some of your data.
And same thing down here.
This is a crazy long column name.
You can rename it if you really want.
But that's all we're seeing there.
And in fact, if that's a little ugly,
we can actually alias these things.
N is a common name for a variable, a
number in any programming language.
So I can actually alias this
to be a column called n.
Hit Enter.
And now I'm getting a tiny, tiny
table whose column is called
n that just has the one value there.
All right, questions on these
application of these functions here?
Questions, yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Say a little louder.
AUDIENCE: A-S.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, A-S. As.
Literally in English.
So rename this column as this.
Technically it creates
an alias for the column.
So that's all.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Distinct will operate on whatever
you hand it in parentheses
and get rid of all of the duplicates,
giving you back just the uniques.
Correct.
Other questions here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
When you define an alias
like n, which I just did,
does it become like a
variable you can reuse?
Short answer, no in this case, but you
can reuse it within your same query.
Even though these queries are
getting a little longer, admittedly,
statements that they
are, you can actually
reuse n in an even longer query.
So later in your query.
And we'll see a few that are
going to start to grow in length.
So it's a nice way of
nicknaming things just to be
a little more terse in your query.
So we can transition to some of
these more sophisticated queries
because it turns out there
are some other techniques we
can introduce as well.
Here are some other keywords in SQL.
And again, even though this
is another list of things,
there's only four things
fundamentally we're doing.
Creating, reading,
updating, and deleting data.
These are just allowing us to
fine tune how we do it exactly.
So where is going to allow us to filter
data, as we'll do in just a moment.
Like select data where
this conditional is true.
Like is going to be an
alternative to an equal sign.
So instead of looking for exactly
Scratch or exactly Python or exactly C,
you can look for
something like dot dot dot
and it can be a little bit of
a fuzzier match, if you will,
with other characters as well.
Order by is going to deal with sorting.
Limit is going to just let me limit
the total number of rows that come back
to 1 or 10 or finite
if I don't want to see
all 400 plus rows all at
once, because I'm just
trying to wrap my mind around it.
And group by is best shown by example.
So let's play with just a
couple of these as well.
Let me go back to VS Code here.
I'll clear my screen.
I'm still in the same SQLite instance.
And let's count how many of you liked C
without writing Python code as before.
So let me go ahead and
select the count of the rows
from favorites where the
language in each row equals C.
And the convention in SQLite is
to use single quotes any time
you're surrounding a string that's meant
to represent a literal piece of text
as opposed to C, which was double
quotes, or Python, which was either.
So this is selecting the count of
rows from favorites table where
the language in question is C. Enter.
And this gives me 98.
Notice, though, if I omit that
predicate like we did before,
you'll get back the total number
of rows that were in the table.
So where is what's called
a predicate that just
allows me to filter things just like an
if condition or the like in a language
that we've seen before.
You can be a little more specific
like how many people really liked
C and the Mario problem specifically?
Well, let's do this.
Let's go ahead and do select the
number of rows from the favorites table
where the language is C and.
So it's still literally
the word ands and or, just
like in Python but not like in
C. And problem equals Mario.
So let's see if there's any fans
of both C and the Mario problem.
And three of us really like those
two things together in this case.
All right, what else can we do?
Well, more compelling might be
to see, kind of like in Python,
for each language, what
was the popularity thereof?
And at the moment, we
don't really have a way
of doing that except in
Python where we had the loop
and we had those variables and the
dictionary that did all of that
counting for us.
Totally doable but tedious, especially
if your job is to analyze data.
My God, even writing 15 lines of
code to answer simple questions
is kind of ridiculous.
SQL can do better for us.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and select
every language and the count
thereof from the favorites table
but this time group by language.
So this was another one
of the keywords that we
can use in this abbreviated
list of extra features of SQL.
And this one takes a moment
to wrap your mind around,
but this is going to give me a
two column temporary table where
the first column is a
language and the second column
is the count thereof from this data set.
And group by language just means
that only show me Scratch once,
only show me C once,
only show me Python once.
That is group all of the
identical values together,
but keep track of how
many of them there are.
And so now if I go over to SQLite and
I hit Enter, now I have in SQL version
the exact same output
that I had from Python
that took me, what,
15 plus lines before.
Now we're down to just one because
SQL, Structured Query Language,
is all about constructing queries like
this to answer questions and get back
answers quickly.
If we want to clean
this up a little bit,
you asked earlier about sorting order.
Well, we can do that too.
There's another key
phrase we can use here.
We can order by the count of those
rows and then run that query here.
So now unfortunately they're
from smallest to biggest,
but we can reverse that.
It turns out, and my query's
starting to wrap here.
I'll zoom out for a moment.
If you want to order by count,
the default is in ascending order,
abbreviated A-S-C. If you want
to reverse the sort in SQL,
instead of using reverse equals
true like we did in Python,
you say D-E-S-C for descending order.
And now we get almost the same
output but flipped in reverse.
So it's just a lot faster to
answer questions once, of course,
you get some muscle memory
and some comfort with it.
Well, what else can I do?
What if I just care about
the most popular language?
I don't care about the second
place or the third place
languages or anything else.
Well, let me add one more clause here.
Limit the answer to one.
And no matter how many
rows should come back now,
I just get the number one
language as of the data
set we collected with 270 votes for it.
Questions on this?
Any questions here?
No?
Well, what if we're
starting to introduce SQL
and it was kind of too late to
make it into the Google Form?
So it turns out there's
syntax for this too.
You can create data, of course.
Not just the tables, but the data
therein and here's the typical syntax
for inserting data into a SQL database.
You literally say insert
into the name of the table.
And then in parentheses, you specify
one or more columns for which you
have values that you want to insert.
This is to say you don't
have to give values
for every column in the given row.
If you only have answers
to some of those questions,
you can enumerate them here like this.
But the values you insert
are going to be these.
So you literally say after
the close parenthesis values.
And then in a second set of
parentheses with a same length
comma separated list, you specify
what values do you want to insert.
So it's a little verbose.
And frankly longer term, you're going
to use Python code to automatically do
these kinds of insertions, but
let's go ahead and try this.
Right now if I do select distinct
language from favorites, again,
we see this.
Just these three candidates.
But we've now taught you a bit of SQL.
So let's do insert into favorites
the column called language.
And you know what?
I'm going to give a problem here.
The values for which,
and let me zoom back out,
are going to be quote unquote "SQL"
and quote, unquote "fiftyville."
You'll soon see what that's all about.
Semicolon.
Nothing seems to happen, but
that's usually a good thing.
And now if I scroll
back up in my queries,
in SQLite3 you can scroll back and
forth in time to avoid retyping things,
now I should see indeed four
candidate languages here.
Now, suppose that you were never really
a fan of C and maybe you programmed
a little bit in high school or in
the real world and you liked C++.
Well, there's a whole lot of answers
for C. So select star from favorites
where language equals quote unquote "C."
So here's everyone who submitted the
answer for C. Let's presume that, no,
they didn't really want
C, they wanted C++,
which is not a language
we teach in the class.
But I could also now do this.
You can use the update command to set
a column or columns to different values
where some condition is met.
So if I do update table name set
column name equal to some value
filtering it perhaps by
where some condition is true.
So suppose I've changed
my mind, or you know what,
let's go ahead and do update favorites
set language equal to maybe C++ where
language equals C.
Now, this is destructive,
so you generally
don't want to do this unless
you have a backup of your data
too, overriding what
people's answers are.
This seems to have been successful,
because no error messages.
And if I rerun the previous
select that gives me
all of the favorites where language
equals C, now indeed I get none.
But if I search for
C++, now I get a lot.
And if I get rid of that where
clause altogether and just look
at the contents of my database, now you
see that indeed C++ is comingled with
all the other data.
This is not what you all intended,
of course, so I can undo this.
Let me go ahead and
undo what I just did.
Let me set my favorite language
to C where language equals C++.
But the predicate is important.
This I'm not going to do.
What if I accidentally omitted
this predicate, the where clause?
How would that screw
things up might you think?
Yeah, in the back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: It would set every
row's language to indeed C.
And this is dangerous.
And if you start googling around
for SQL mistakes or the like,
people in the real world have
accidentally run commands like this.
And without naming
names, a former member
of our teaching staff at one point
accidentally ran a command like this
and changed every student's name in
our database to Bobby I think it was.
The same name for every row because
they simply forgot a predicate.
So here too there's
dangers in code, and you
should adopt the habit
quite quickly of always,
one, backing up your data
like with CP, for instance,
in Linux or any other technique or just
making sure before you hit Enter that,
yes, this is indeed the
query I want to execute.
And generally speaking
in the real world,
there should be process
controls in place.
Like the intern should not
have access to the production
database, the live
database, and the like.
But you have a lot of power
now with these queries.
So just be all the more careful, because
very easily can you do bad things.
So let me undo this.
Where language equals
quote unquote "C++."
And I'll zoom back out.
Enter.
And now I think we're back in business.
C is among the answers.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: It's essentially
doing what at the end?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: It's
essentially find and replace.
Yes.
In layperson's terms, this is find
and replace implemented with SQL.
And in fact, the authors of
Microsoft Word or Google Docs
might very well be using
language like this SQL
when you go to the nice graphical
user friendly find and replace box.
This may very well be what they're
doing underneath the hood or, of course,
they could be using some
other language altogether.
There's one last syntax
that's worth knowing,
delete, which for better or for worse
is even more destructive whereby it
allows you to delete rows from tables.
It's distinct from drop, which
lets you delete tables themselves.
This focuses on rows.
So suppose that you
really, really didn't like,
let's say, Tideman was a
little challenging if you
tackled that more comfortable problem.
So if you really don't want to
even think about Tideman anymore,
so why don't we do delete from
favorites where problem equals, and I
won't execute it for real, Tideman.
This would have the effect of
deleting every row, including
the language therein and the timestamp,
where the student answered Tideman.
Worse than this would be this.
Why might this be bad?
OK, chuckling because
there's no predicate.
There's no filter, which means literally
this would delete all of the data.
So again, with great power here
comes great responsibility.
Now, this has just been a data set of
430 rows by us dynamically created.
There's, of course, some really
juicy data sets in the real world.
And one website you might have
heard or an app you might have used
is IMDb, the Internet Movie
Database, which wonderfully
makes some of their data available
for download as CSV files
or technically TSV files,
Tab Separated Values.
But what we did in advance of class was
download some of that data for both TV
shows in the real world and
movies in the real world.
And what's wonderful
about this data set is
it's not just dozens or hundreds
or even thousands of lines.
There are millions of rows of
juicy data, TV shows and movies
with which most folks are probably
familiar, at least with a subset.
And we'll see in just a
little bit that this data
comes in the form of now six
different tables that we've given you.
And the tables in question
for today are going
to be the people in the TV business,
the stars therein, the shows that people
are producing and the like.
This is a picture
we'll revisit to enable
you to wrap your minds around
what the actual data is.
This feels like a good
opportunity though for a snack.
In fact, in just a moment, we have a
whole lot of Rice Krispie treats out
in the lobby.
But if folks could perhaps acknowledge
this mini wedding cake here.
CS50 zone Carter Zenke is
getting married this week.
So congratulations to Carter as well.
Congrats.
All right.
[APPLAUSE]
There's only one piece of cake in
that box but a lot of Rice Krispie
treats in the transept.
Let's take 10 minutes and we'll be back
with Internet Movie Database in 10.
All right.
We are back.
So if you've never been, you can
actually go to imdb.com right now
and play around or
download the mobile app.
And it's just big database of
a lot of TV shows and movies
and actors and the like.
But what indeed is nice is you
can download some of that data.
And that's what I've done in advance.
And what we've done is
we wrote some Python code
to convert some of the flat file
databases that they let you download
and we converted it into a
SQL database with six tables.
So not just one but six that
ultimately are these here.
And let me just help you wrap your
minds around what this picture is, which
is an entity relationship diagram,
which is just to say each of these boxes
on the screen represents a table.
And each of the arrows or edges
represents some kind of relationship
across the tables.
Because up until now,
the only data we had
were those three columns
in the favorites table.
But what gets really
useful about SQL databases,
just like a Google
Spreadsheet or an Excel file,
is you can have multiple sheets
or in a database multiple tables.
And so what we're about to see is that
in the IMDb database for TV shows,
there's going to be a dedicated table
for all the people in the TV business.
There's going to be a dedicated
table for all of the TV shows
that are in their
database as of right now.
There's going to be a dedicated
table for writers in that industry,
for the ratings of shows, for
the genres to which shows belong,
comedy and the like.
And then lastly, there's
going to be this table,
which somehow associates people
with the TV shows that they star in
and vice versa.
And so let's consider first
what this looks like in code.
And we'll see that it's going to
overwhelm intentionally at first,
but I'm going to do this.
I'm going to go back
to my terminal window.
And during the break, I downloaded
from the course's website
a file called shows.db, which
we made in advance for you.
And if I type ls, I'll see all of
my favorites files from before.
The CSV, the DB, and the Python file.
But now they're shows.db.
So I'm going to go ahead in my
full screen terminal window here.
I'm not using actual tabs or code files.
Now I'm going to run sqlite3
on the file called shows.db.
And I'm just going to see
this version information here.
Let me clear my screen
and run the one command
I ran earlier to show us the
schema of the favorites database.
Now we'll see the schema
for the shows database.
And there's a lot going
on here, but let me scroll
back up to the very top, the beginning.
And we see this here.
So when I run .schema,
we see a dump, really,
of all of the SQL create table commands
that were run in order to create this
database for you.
And one of those tables is
called genres and another people,
ratings, shows, stars, and so forth.
And the columns therein,
even though it's
formatted a little more prettily than
the automatically generated create
table statement for favorites whereby
we have one column per line of output
here in the, for instance,
people table, there's
going to be an ID column, like a unique
identifier like a Harvard ID, a Yale
ID or the like, a name column, a
birth year, and then some other stuff.
If I scroll down to shows,
every show in the world
is going to have a unique ID as well,
a title of course, the year in which it
debuted, and the total
number of episodes
as of the time we downloaded the data.
And then what else is there?
Some of these are a little
less obvious like ratings here.
So ratings don't have
an ID column, but they
have a show ID column and a rating like
on a five point scale or a 10 point
scale or the like and
then the total number
of votes that were collected
to contribute to that rating.
IMDb allows people to upvote and
downvote shows and movies and the like.
And then similarly is genre structured.
There's a show ID and
then there's a genre,
which is going to be an English word
like comedy or drama or something else.
And then what else?
Let's go a little further at the
bottom here for stars and writers.
If we go to the very bottom
here, stars and writers
are similarly structured too.
They have a show ID and a person ID.
So show and person.
And then this writers table
has a show ID and a person ID.
And there's a whole lot of other words
that we'll come to in just a moment.
But what is this code hinting at?
Well, if I go back to the
picture from earlier here,
you'll see that this picture
captures the relationships
among these various tables.
So for instance, if we focus on
shows for just a moment, a show,
again, has a unique ID, a title,
a year in which it debuted,
and a total number of episodes.
If you want to figure
out what genre or genres
a show belongs to, because
some shows are just comedies,
some shows are just dramas, but some
shows are arguably comedies and dramas
depending on the episode or the like.
So you can imagine wanting to associate
two or three or even more genres
with a show.
This line here in this second
table allows us to do that.
Every row in the genres table
we'll see has two items, a show ID
which relates to the ID of a show.
And that's why these lines literally
line up with that specific column name.
And a genre, which is going to
be like, quote unquote, "comedy,"
quote unquote "drama,"
or something else.
Now with that said, design question.
Why have we deliberately not just
gotten rid of this genres table
and made our lives simpler by just
adding a genre column to this show's
table?
And again, a table is just like
a sheet with rows and columns.
At the moment, shows only have four
columns, ID, title, year, episodes.
Why not just add a fifth column called
genre and put the show's genre there?
Any intuition here?
Why not just keep things simple?
Yeah, in back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
If you add a fifth column
here and call it genre,
then you have to pick
a genre specifically.
You have to put in that cell presumably
comedy or drama or musical or something
else.
Now, you could write
multiple words in the cell,
but generally speaking, that
would be sloppy, bad design.
Like every cell just
like in a spreadsheet
should really have one value.
It might have multiple words, but it
shouldn't be a weirdly comma separated
list of multiple things.
It should just be in a
different cell in that case.
So if you instead were to design this
with just a single column called genre,
you're imposing what
a computer scientist
would call a one to one relationship.
Every show has one genre.
And that's not necessarily a good thing.
Or strictly speaking, it
would be a many to one,
because the same genre could
belong to multiple shows,
but each show could only
have one genre in that case.
What a relational
database allows you to do,
and relational is indeed
the operative word,
it allows you to factor out
some of your information
and then have maybe one show here in
one row but then in this genres table,
you could have one row
for that one show genre,
or you could have two rows in the
genres table for comedy and for drama.
Or if it has a third genre, you
could just add another row here.
So you still have one
row for the show itself
with all the juiciest details
but a variable number of rows
by having this relationship
with another table.
Meanwhile, ratings work the
same way, at least in this case.
A show has ID, title,
year, and episodes.
But if you want to
figure out its rating,
you have to follow the arrow
here, so to speak, and look up
the corresponding show ID in this table.
Find the rating of that show
and the total number of ratings.
So that's been factored out
too, for better or for worse.
Now let's consider people.
People have just three
columns, ID, name, and birth.
But there's no mention of the TV
show in which people have starred
or the TV shows that
a person has written.
Well, why is that?
Well, if you just had a fourth
column here called show,
well, you would have to decide
what show is that person in.
And no one could ever act
again in another show,
because there's no
room to store the data.
But if someone, of course, a popular
actor can star in multiple shows,
well, we could have one ID for that
person, one name, one birth year,
obviously.
Like there's only one Steve Carell
as an actor in the world of people.
But Steve Carell in this example
could have his person ID,
whatever his Harvard ID
equivalent, Yale ID equivalent is,
appear in multiple rows
in this table so that it
can be associated with multiple shows.
And this allows you to create what's
called a one to many relationship,
or technically it's bidirectional.
It's a many to many relationship.
Why?
Well, one show can certainly
have multiple people in it
and multiple people writing
for it, just in the real world.
But conversely, one person could
certainly act in multiple shows
or write multiple shows.
So this is what you get
with relational databases.
You put your sort of canonical
data for people in one place,
for shows in another place, and
then you use these additional tables
to relate one thing to another.
So we won't dwell on the pictures.
That's just if you sort of can
wrap your mind around the data
set better that way, that's
one way of thinking about it.
But recall that the code we just saw for
the schema, again, escalated quickly.
There's a lot of keywords
I haven't mentioned yet.
But some of these are perhaps familiar.
They're capitalized differently here.
But integer is on the list here.
Null is on the list, albeit
technically not null.
So let's tease apart
some of these keywords
and consider what they're
actually doing for your database,
because now we're exploring
features that do not exist
in the world of spreadsheets alone.
So it turns out in a SQL
database, specifically
SQLite which is the version
of SQL we use in CS50
and which is commonly used for things
like mobile applications nowadays.
It's like a lightweight version of SQL.
It's when you aren't trying to
run Twitter and have billions
and billions of rows necessarily.
You've got hundreds, thousands, tens
of thousands, maybe even a few million,
but not crazy numbers,
crazy amounts of data.
In the world of SQLite specifically,
there's these five data types.
So just like in C, we had
int and char and the like.
In SQL, we have these.
Blob, which is kind of funny, but
it just means binary large objects.
So it's like a binary data type.
Zeros and ones that aren't necessarily
fitting into the other categories.
Integer, which of course,
is an integer as we know it.
Numeric, which is kind of a catchall for
numbers that are formatted specially.
So like a date would be like year,
year, year, year, dash month, month,
dash day, day.
And this is actually a wonderful thing.
Depending on the
country you're from, you
might think your date system in your
country is great or it's horrible.
The US system is horrible because
we have month, day, and then
year, which is impossible to sort.
It is the wrong way
objectively to store data.
And yet here we are using this at scale.
Other countries have gotten this better.
Numeric in SQL itself
standardizes that stuff.
So it doesn't matter
what country you're from.
You're storing your data in this
particular way for instance.
Times are standardized and other
types of numeric data as well.
Real is synonymous with flow.
So something with a decimal point
and some number of digits thereafter.
And then text is just
for strings and the like.
With other even fancier databases
like MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle,
and other products you
might have heard of,
there's even more data
types where you have
to make even finer grained decisions.
But for SQLite, it's
indeed pretty lightweight
and you or we just have to decide the
data types for each column in a table.
But there's these additional
constraints in the world of SQL.
You can additionally say that cells
in this column may or may not be null.
So if you want to protect yourself
from yourself so you don't screw up
and insert a null,
that is a blank value,
you can explicitly design a table to
have a column that cannot be null.
And so in fact, someone
came up during the break
to ask me about my having
manually inserted SQL,
quote unquote "SQL," into
our favorites database.
You might recall that I kind of cheated.
I just inserted "SQL" quote
unquote and "fiftyville,"
the name of a new
problem, quote unquote.
But what did I not
insert into the database?
A timestamp.
And I could have.
I could have put the current day and
time a few minutes ago, but I didn't.
And that's fine if it's acceptable to
you and the product you're building.
But I could have prevented that.
If we had defined the table to have a
timestamp column that isn't just text
but it's text that's not null,
SQL would have complained
and would not have let me
complete that insertion.
So there's these kinds of built in
defenses that you don't necessarily
get with a spreadsheet alone.
And unique means exactly that.
If you want to make sure
that every row in that column
is unique, maybe for email addresses
or in the US Social Security
numbers or anything
that you want to make
sure you don't have two versions of, you
can specify that the column is unique.
And there's other such
constraints as well.
But again, this is
just a list of features
that you get from a proper
relational database.
But perhaps the most
intellectually interesting one
and the most powerful
one is what's called
here a primary key and a foreign key.
And let me go back now to this output.
If we look at shows, you'll
see that a show, again,
has an ID, a title, a year,
and a number of episodes.
And now the data types might make sense.
The ID it turns out, just
like a Harvard ID, a Yale ID,
is going to be an integer.
So a simple number.
The title, of course, is
going to be text but not null.
It would be weird if
a TV show had no name.
That can't be.
The whole world would break
or your TV Guide and whatnot.
So that makes sense
there to say not null.
Year is numeric.
So it's a standardized form.
Episodes is an integer, like how
many episodes have been produced.
And then lastly, notice this.
The primary key of the
show's table is apparently
the column called ID
mentioned a few lines earlier.
This just means that the
database will use the ID
column as the unique identifier.
So it's similar to the unique
keyword, but primary key just
means the database is going
to treat it as special too
and make sure that it is
uniquely identifying your data.
But what's interesting is this.
Notice if I scroll back
up to people, people
were sort of similarly structured
but with different attributes.
Like up here we had a person
has an ID, a name, a birth
year, and a primary key of ID.
So a ID is, again, integer.
Name is text but not
null, because it'd be
weird to have a human with
absolutely no name textually.
Birth is going to be numeric.
But the primary key of
people is ID as well.
So those are the unique columns that
the database will just treat special.
Why?
Well, we just looked at shows.
We just looked at people.
Let's focus now on this
one down here, stars.
How do you determine
who stars in a TV show?
Well, we had two columns.
The show ID and the person ID.
This is the incarnation of
a many to many relationship.
One person could be in many shows.
One show could certainly have many
people in it or writing for it.
But notice this.
Within this table of two
columns, show ID and person ID,
there's what's going to be
called a foreign key called
show ID that references the
show's table's ID column
and then another foreign
key called person ID,
though I could call these
things in parentheses anything
I want, that references the
people table's ID column.
Now, you're not going to often
have to type commands like this.
Again, you set the database
up once in the beginning
typically, maybe with
some help from a TF,
maybe with help of Google or the like.
But once your database is
designed, it's back to the CRUD.
Create, read, update, delete, the
selects, the inserts, the deletions,
and the like.
But what's this implying?
These keywords like
primary key and foreign key
are what are doing in code what this
picture was painting a moment ago.
These lines here are drawn literally to
line up with the corresponding things.
People's ID lines up with person ID.
Show's ID lines up with show ID.
And so you're just seeing graphical
version, code version, graphical,
code that creates these relationships.
Now, given that, let's actually
see what these things look like.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
Let me clear my screen.
I'm still within SQLite with shows.db.
Let me go ahead and do what
I do with any new database.
If I ever download
something or I'm trying
to wrap my mind around
a problem, usually it
doesn't come with a pretty
picture or a three hour lecture
to explain what the data set is.
Rather you just have the data
set in your own knowledge of SQL.
So let me play around.
So .schema shows me all of the tables.
That might be a starting point.
OK, this is interesting.
I know what people are.
Let's go ahead and
show me all the people.
So select star from people.
I'm just trying to wrap my
mind around what this data set
looks like in a more user friendly way.
That's already a lot of people.
As you see the years
flying by, there's been
a lot of people in the TV business.
So this was maybe not
the best query to run.
But this is indicative of just how
large this data set is from IMDb.
When in doubt and whenever you
lose control over your computer,
Control C is your friend to interrupt.
What would have been
better, because I don't
think I need to know all of the
million people in the world,
I could do limit me to 10 people.
And that's enough now to
get a sense of Fred Astaire
has an ID of one, the first person ever.
Birth year of 1899.
Lauren Bacall and all of these
other people from yesteryear.
You see that they are the first
10 people in the database.
So there's an example
of some of the data.
Now if I want to wrap my mind around
what a show is, I know it technically.
I know it from the picture.
But let's just look at some raw data.
So instead of saying select star
from people, let me go ahead
and select star from shows limit 10.
And OK, I've only heard of
or seen a couple of these,
but these are older shows at that.
But I see that every show has an ID,
a title, a year in which it debuted,
and a number of episodes.
But perhaps most opaque
is going to be this.
Select star from stars where this
is the table that associates people
with shows.
Am I going to see any
names or show titles here?
Not according to the
definition we saw earlier.
Oh, I should have done my limit.
Let me interrupt that.
Let me do that again.
Limit 10.
No.
And this is where now you're
definitely in the programmer world,
because this would be the most annoying
spreadsheet to use on your Mac or PC
ever.
If you just had a sheet
with all of these numbers
that associates one thing
with the other, my God,
how do you figure out who
this is or what this is?
You have to manually Control F or
Command F looking for the data.
But a database doesn't care.
Once you know SQL, you can stitch
these things back together.
So what you're seeing
here are foreign keys.
Foreign keys.
Why?
Because show ID corresponds to the
same numbers from that other table
called shows that has a
proper primary key called ID.
Person ID is a foreign
key in this context,
because it refers to numbers that belong
to really the people table and its ID
column.
So this is just a way
of somehow linking them.
And so if you think of I always think
of this in my mind's eye as this.
If this is the people table,
this is the shows table,
and there's this middle table
in between, the stars table.
There's some way of stitching those two
together by lining up the IDs of one
with the other and getting
back some more data.
So let's actually play
with some of this data.
How about we start where we
emphasized earlier, genres.
So let me go ahead and take a quick look
at all of the genres in this database.
So select star from genres.
Star is usually going to
be a little overwhelming,
but it just gives me a
sense of what the data is.
But let's actually look at--
let's go look at all of them there.
OK, that's a lot.
These are all official genres from IMDb.
OK, it wasn't terribly long.
Let me filter that down.
So from genres where genre equals
Comedy, capital C just based
on the data I'm seeing.
OK, so what am I seeing now?
And in fact, let me limit
this arbitrarily to 10,
though I could limit
it to anything I want.
Here are 10 comedies.
What are they?
Well, who the heck knows?
All I know are the 10 show IDs.
Now, I could do something like this.
As we've seen before with SQL,
I could do, all right, well
let's figure out what this show ID is.
Select star from shows where the ID of
the show I'm looking for equals what?
62614 semicolon.
So I could manually look it up by
cross referencing the other table.
So that was the show in question there,
the first comedy in the data set.
Let me look up the second one.
So instead of that,
let's do 63881 Enter.
OK.
So that's that show.
And let's do one more.
And suffice it to say, this is
just getting tedious and vulnerable
to mistakes quickly.
This surely can't be the way to do this.
And indeed, SQL is going to let us do
this a little more powerfully instead.
Let's do this.
Instead of getting
this table temporarily
with all these show IDs and all
these genres, let's refine the query.
So let's just select the show ID from
the genres table where the genre equals
quote unquote "comedy."
Now I have a big list of show
IDs, all of which are comedy.
How many?
Well, I can combine ideas from earlier.
I can just count all of those show IDs
or star if I want to just do that too.
But I can count all those show IDs.
48,706 comedies on IMDb's
database for TV shows.
So feels like a lot.
But how can I now use that
information and get back
the titles of comedies in the
database without doing it manually?
Well, let's do this.
I have a moment ago this query.
Select the show ID from
genres where the current genre
is quote unquote "comedy."
What if I kind of nest these
queries, kind of like grade school
math in parentheses?
What if I combine this
whole thing in parentheses?
And now let me select
what I really want.
Let me go ahead and select
how about the title of all
shows where the idea of the show
is in this list of show IDs.
So if you agree that the shows table
has an ID column, which is otherwise
known as its primary key, the
unique ID that identifies it, just
like our Harvard IDs, our Yale IDs,
and you agree that per a moment ago
this shorter query will
give me back just the show
IDs of all of the
comedies in the database,
you can actually combine or
nest these queries together.
It's going to respect
SQLite order of operations
with parentheses, just
like grade school math.
So the thing in parentheses
will be executed first.
That gives it back a list
of IDs, like 48,000 IDs.
And then this query, the
outer query, is going
to get the title from all of the
shows where the ID of the show
is in that big list of 48,000.
So if I now execute
these together, I think
the list is still going to be a little
long, but let me execute it together.
Now I see this long list of outputs.
A little overwhelming.
Let's go ahead and maybe
limit it to just 10
as before for discussion's sake.
And now I see 10 comedies
ordered arbitrarily
from however they're in
the database that happen
to indeed have comedy as their genre.
If I want to do this a little
more cleanly, I could do this.
Let's see.
Why don't I order by title ascending
order, which is alphabetically,
or the default is also an ascending.
Limit 10.
Now I see the top 10, I mean, weirdly
named things with hash symbols
presumably to get their titles up to the
beginning or maybe these are hashtags.
Here now we have alphabetically the
first 10 shows that are comedies.
Any questions on these kinds of queries?
It's kind of a lot, but
at the same time it's
just like composing the smaller
ideas from before into slightly more
useful queries.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Do foreign keys
have to set the relationship?
When you create the table,
the programmer or the database
administrator would
create that relationship
by using those keywords primary
key and foreign key that
teaches the database what is
related to what per the picture.
So you do that once.
And now I being the sort of programmer
who's familiar with the database,
I am just using these foreign keys in
a manner consistent with their design.
And this is where it's
useful at some point,
even if no one hands you a picture, to
make sure you understand the database,
because that's going to inform
literally what you type in SQL
to get the data you care about.
Well, let's do something
a little more precise.
How about-- very reasonable question.
And honestly, this is exactly
what imdb.com and the app or for.
What if you want to find all of
the shows that Steve Carell is in?
Kind of a reasonable query.
Literally something someone might type
into Google or more specifically IMDb.
It's not really obvious
at first glance how
to do that, though,
because from my database,
if these are my six tables,
well, I can pretty easily get
Steve Carell from here.
But I can really only get his
ID number, whatever that is,
his name, which I know
already, and his birth year.
OK, interesting but has nothing
to do with the shows that he's in.
I can look at shows over here, but
there's no mention of Steve Carell
because there's no person ID here.
Where is that relationship implemented?
Well, it's implemented down here.
So how do we do this?
Well, here's the perfect
example of a lesson
we've been trying to emphasize for
weeks of taking these baby steps.
Break larger problems down into smaller
ones and let's do something like this.
Let's just get everything I know
about Steve Carell from the database.
Let's select star from people
where the name of the person
is quote unquote "Steve Carell."
I just want to see what data we've got.
And here's what we have.
There's only one Steve
Carell born in 1962
and his unique ID is
136797 according to IMDb.
This isn't some global
actor identifier, per se.
All right, well how do I get now all
of the shows that Steve Carell is in?
Well, I could do this.
Select star from stars,
not to confuse the two.
One's the symbol, one's the table name.
Where person ID equals 136797.
So I think this will now give me
everything from the stars table
that relates to Steve Carell.
And you'll see person ID is
the same because I'm literally
searching for just Steve Carell.
But there are like 20 or
so shows that he's been in.
All right, well here's where
things would get tedious.
What are those shows?
Well, I could do select title from
shows where the ID of the show equals.
And here's whenever you copy paste,
you're probably doing something wrong.
OK, he was in The Dana Carvey Show.
Familiar with that.
Let's do another one.
We'll copy paste this.
Where ID equals this.
Over The Top.
Another.
And if we keep digging, we'll
probably find The Office.
But my God, that's going to take
forever to do 20 queries manually.
It's not very dynamic.
But what if we just nest these
queries a little more dynamically?
So let me start from
the beginning again.
What if we go ahead
and select everything
we know about people whose
name equals Steve Carell.
That gave us earlier this data.
I don't need all of that data.
I know his name.
I don't care about his birth year.
So let's change this to just be
give me the ID of Steve Carell.
And that gives me back now this
smaller temporary data set.
All right.
Can I now use this
inside of another query?
Well, let me wrap the whole
thing with parentheses.
And now let me say select
star from the stars table
where the person ID equals this.
So I'm deliberately not
using in because I'm
assuming there's indeed only
one Steve Carell in the world.
So I'm not getting back
a list of Steve Carells.
I'm getting back the one
and only in this case.
So equal is fine.
In is when you have multiple.
Equal is when you have one.
Let me go ahead and hit Enter now.
OK, that's more data than I need.
I don't need like 20 copies
of Steve Carell's person ID.
So let me hit up.
Let me go back and let me just
get show ID from Steve Carell.
And now I have a list of just the 20
or so show IDs that he has been in.
All right.
How can I now use this?
Well, let me hit up.
Let me put the whole
thing in parentheses.
And now let me select
what I really want.
Select title from shows where.
And here's the final flourish.
The shows table has an ID, has a
title, has a year, and has an episode.
And what I really want, though, is to
check which shows have ID that is what?
Anyone want to finish the thought?
I just want to-- yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
ID in this.
And this is getting ugly.
And when you actually write
your queries in a text file,
you can format them
nicely and indent them.
My font is just getting--
I don't want to make it too
small to fit everything.
But now we have three queries.
One is in doubly nested parentheses,
then there's the middle one,
then there's the outer one.
So this last query is going
to get me the title from shows
where the ID of the show
is in this big list of 20
or so show IDs that Steve Carell is in.
And I knew that because I
looked up his name here.
And notice what I did not do
this time is I didn't manually
hardcode his ID number.
There's no need.
That would be kind of a bad way
to implement a website if you're
using a database underneath the hood.
You want the IMDb for real
to search for whatever
the human typed in and no one's going
to know Steve Carell's person ID
or anything else.
So here we've done this all dynamically.
And now if I hit Enter, I
think I get all of his shows.
Let's go ahead and order this
by title just to make it tidy.
And you probably will see at
least one or more shows that.
And probably the most popular
is, dot dot dot, The Office.
So this is literally
the kind of query that's
being executed underneath the hood when
you go to websites or apps like IMDb.
Your textual query is probably being
plugged into a longer SQL query
like this where some
programmer at IMDb probably
wrote this whole query in
advance weeks, months, years ago
and they're just somehow plugging
in the value that you the human
typed into the search box or the like.
Questions now on finding
this data or any other?
No?
OK.
So where else could we go with this?
Well, let's consider how
else we might combine data.
Suppose that the next question
actually perhaps appropriately
would be focusing in on not just
people and shows and these stars,
but how do we gather more information
about the shows themselves,
like the genres, the
ratings, or the like.
So indeed, let's focus on
just these two tables here.
Recall that every show has an ID,
a title, a year, and episodes.
But it also might have one or
more relationships with rows
and this other table called genres.
And this is so that a show can
be a comedy, can be a drama,
can be any number of other things.
One row per.
So you would see the same
show ID again and again
and again with a different
genre written in English
like comedy, drama, or the like.
Well, how do I kind of
reconstitute that data?
Well, turns out there's a few
different ways to do this.
And let me propose that we
introduce this keyword here, join.
And this is really the most powerful
of the keywords in SQL itself.
It doesn't have to be used.
We've seen with nested
queries that you can still
select data across multiple
tables, but here is another way.
So let me do this.
Let me go back to my SQLite database.
And let me select sort of in one
breath exactly the data I want.
Select star from shows.
And let's just limit this initially
to 10 to see what it looks like.
All right.
That's, again, the shows data.
Select star from genres.
Let's limit that to 10 too, just
to wrap our minds around it.
And now this is not that useful.
However, the data in
the leftmost column here
is the primary key in the shows table.
These are just unique IDs.
The data here in the genres table,
recall, show ID is the foreign key.
So it's the same numbers but
just copied into another table
so that we can have this
relationship across them.
How do I kind of line up these
numbers with these numbers
to get back a wider table that has title
and year and episodes and genre and,
heck, ratings and all
of that too if we want?
Well, you can join these
tables by just telling
the database what to join on what.
So let me do this.
Select star from shows.
Join that table though
on the genres table.
Well, how do you want to
join those two tables?
And again, the two tables from
the picture looked like this.
How do you tell SQL
programmatically to put one of them
right next to the other,
line up all of the ID
so that you just get
one larger data set?
Well, we can use indeed
this syntax called join.
So back to VS Code here.
And let me join these two tables.
Sorry, typo here.
Join genres on the shows
table's ID column, a.k.a.
its primary key, equaling the genres
table's show ID column, a.k.a.
the foreign key.
So in other words, it
looks a little cryptic,
but I'm just telling SQL how to line
up these two tables and what column
to match with the other so
that the numbers line up
and I get essentially a wider table.
Let me go ahead and hit
semicolon and Enter.
And this is now going to
give me a lot of data.
We might have to interrupt it.
But notice even at a glance, we're
getting the ID, the title, the year,
the number of episodes,
the ID again redundantly,
but that's to be expected
if I'm joining them,
and the genre all the way on the right.
Let me hit Control C to interrupt.
Let me just limit this to The Office.
So where title equals
quote unquote "The Office"
so we can focus on just one sample data.
And here, fun fact, there's
been more than one Office.
The one that you all
probably like is this one
that started in 2005 with 188 episodes.
Its ID in the shows table is 386676.
That's confirmed over here too.
So again, we've just
joined the two tables.
How?
By lining up those fields.
But now that we can see that
almost all of The Offices
produced over the decades are
comedies except for this one.
There was a version of The
Office produced in 2001
that was considered more of a drama.
Unsure if it's related to the other.
How can we link in other data?
Well, let's go ahead and link
in ratings too or instead.
So instead of joining this with
genres, let me go ahead and rewind here
and join shows on ratings on
shows.id equals ratings.show_ID.
And let's limit it to The Office too
for discussion's sake where title equals
quote unquote "The Office" semicolon.
And now you can see that
among the various Offices,
it looks like the one that most
of us probably know and love
is the highest rated also with a
9.0 with like 585,000 people having
cast votes for whereas this other
shows seem to have been less popular.
And perhaps that's why indeed you
see fewer episodes for them as well.
So even though we've put
the data in multiple places,
you can still kind of reconstitute
it by lining things up in this way
and rejoining the tables.
Questions now on this?
This is the heart of what SQL does and
what relational databases do for you.
Questions?
All right.
A few final features.
There's not all that much that--
SQL takes practice like anything else.
But in terms of syntax
and capabilities, let's
just introduce you to a couple of final
features here and problems that arise
and how we might solve them.
Let's do this as well.
So let me go back into VS Code here.
And let's just find out Steve
Carell's information again.
Last time we did it
with this nested query
by getting his ID and then the show IDs
and then the titles for those show IDs.
With join, you can do
it a little differently.
And any of these ways are fine.
One might become easier
to mentally than another.
Let's go ahead and select
the titles from what.
Let's select the title
from the people table.
And I'm going to hit Enter.
And when you're using
SQLite3 interactively,
if you ever find yourself with a prompt
that says dot dot dot angle bracket,
it means you're continuing your
thought onto the next line.
If you didn't intend
that, you can sometimes
hit semicolon to just
end the thought and hit
Enter even if it triggers an error.
But this is one way of formatting
my queries now a little more nicely.
I'm just going to add some white space
so that it's a little easier to read.
What do I want to select?
Well, I want to select
the title of shows
from the people table joined with the
stars table on the people table's ID
column equaling the stars
table's person ID column.
So in other words, if you think back
to what people are and what stars are,
one has an ID, one has a person ID, I'm
just now connecting those two tables.
I'm joining those two.
But I want to do this as
well with another table.
Let me additionally join in.
So now I only have two
hands, but now I'm putting
a third table joined in together here.
Join shows on stars.show_id
equals shows.id.
So this is now linking
three tables together.
But I only care about this for one
person, so where the name of the person
equals quote unquote "Steve Carell."
So more cryptic, to be sure, but
what we're doing with this query
is just taking all three
tables that we care about
and we're joining them
all together at once
using this new join syntax
literally telling the database what
columns to line up with what.
And then we filter at the very
end just like before to get back,
if I hit Enter, the answer
we want, which in this case
is a little slower at the moment,
but that same list of 20 or so
shows that he's been in.
There's one other way to do this.
And again, these are all
in the slides online.
So you can repeat them without having to
jot down everything and we'll put them
in the notes too.
But there's another way to do this.
I could also use an implicit join.
So that was an explicit join
because I literally typed
the word join multiple times at that.
But let me go ahead and select
the title from these three tables.
People, stars, and shows.
And this might just be
nicer because if you
know what tables you
want to select data from,
just enumerate them separated by
commas, which you might prefer
in your mind, where the people ID
equals the stars person ID and the stars
show ID equals the shows ID and the
name of the person equals Steve Carell.
So this is an implicit join.
And honestly, I constantly reference
my notes for some of this stuff too.
It's not the kind of thing that's
going to come like this to you
after just one day.
But it's just a different way
of expressing the same thing.
I want to select data from
three different tables.
And hey SQL, here is how I want you
to line those tables up so that I can
get like related data for Steve Carell.
And this now will achieve
the same results ultimately.
Let me hit Enter.
And there we go.
So a little slower.
And performance might
vary based on computer,
based on implementation of SQL, but I
think I still have the same answers.
Now suppose, as I often do, and I
had to look it up again last time,
suppose you forget how to
spell Steve Carell's name.
Is it two R's, two L's, or the like?
Well, I could also do
something like this.
Well, let's just keep this simple.
Select star from people
where name equals.
I've been deliberately getting it
right so as to not embarrass myself.
That's the Steve Carell I keep querying.
If you forget, well you could
try searching for just Steves,
but interestingly,
there's a bunch of Steves.
We don't know when they were born.
But that's probably not the Steve Carell
we want if we don't have his last name.
So I could alternatively do, well it's
Steve and then it starts with a C,
I think.
Well, it turns out there's another
wild card you can use in SQL.
We used the asterisk to
select all of the columns.
You can in quotes use a percent
sign to say C something.
So there's 0 or more
characters after the letter C.
And now this doesn't work because
now I would be literally looking
for Steve space C something.
But recall earlier I mentioned
that one other keyword,
which is for fuzzier
matching, so to speak,
where it's not exactly what
you're looking for but it's
like what you're looking for.
If you instead say where his name
is like Steve space C something,
now we'll get back a
whole bunch of Steves.
But I think now I could probably
find the one I'm actually looking
for if I don't remember his name.
You can use multiple percent signs.
If you forget what his first name
is, you could reverse the order.
But that too is a very
powerful SQL feature at that.
Questions on these queries here?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sorry?
DAVID MALAN: What about it?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Oh yeah, sure.
So the query I used here.
There's a lot of Steves whose last
name starts with C. Oops, too far.
The last query I executed
was this one here.
So where the name is like
quote unquote "Steve C%."
So that's just another
tool for your toolkit here.
But you'll perhaps have
notice that those two--
prior to that query, the
joins I did were sort of slow.
And honestly, this database
isn't even that big.
Like yes, it has tens of
thousands of rows in it.
But in the real world and most of the
apps you and I use a lot every day
or websites, there's millions,
even billions of rows of data.
And if I had to wait on my computer
here or my code space a second or two
to get the data, that's not going to
work for millions of users or customers
certainly.
So how can we actually improve things?
Well, it turns out another upside
of a proper relational database
is that it's not just a spreadsheet
where the onus is on you to find
the data you're looking for.
You can also tell the database
to index the data for you.
An index is an efficient cheat
sheet for finding data fast.
Like books in the real world often
have indices at the end of the book
where you can look
things up alphabetically
and then you can cross reference it
for the pages that topic appears on.
Same idea in a database.
If you tell the database in advance that
you want to search on a certain column
frequently, you can tell it to
build a fancy index that will just
allow you to search that column faster.
By default, these columns
are going to be searched
most likely by a linear search.
Not even binary search,
because the data might not
be sorted because it came in any order.
But if you create an
index, you're probably
going to get something closer
to logarithmic than linear,
and that's going to
be a big plus overall.
So let me do something simple here.
First let me turn on a SQLite specific
feature that just is going to time all
of my queries by writing .timer on.
I just want to keep track of how
long each of these commands takes.
This one is not a slow command, so
this is just going to be relative.
But let's just select
everything from the shows table
where the title thereof is The Office.
Let's see how long this
relatively simple query takes.
All right, not very long at all.
In real terms less than
a second, 0.035 seconds.
So not slow by any means.
But if you've got hundreds,
thousands, millions of users,
every one of those milliseconds
could very well add up.
So can we do better?
Well, we can if I do this.
If I use syntax like this once in the
beginning of the design of my database,
I create not a table but an index with
some name on a specific table on one
or more columns.
I can give a clue, a hint
to the database in advance
saying please optimize with some
secret sauce searching or selecting
on this column in this table
so that my searches are faster.
So let me do this.
Let me go back to VS Code here.
Let me create an index
called how about title index.
I could call it anything I want, but
I want to search faster on titles.
So I'm going to call this a title index
where rather title index on the table
called shows.
And then in parentheses is the syntax.
The column called title.
So again, I've just borrowed
this canonical syntax
and I've just translated it into
something that's TV show specific.
All right.
What is this going to do for me?
Once I hit Enter, this is going to
create in the computer's memory,
the database's memory
something called a B-tree.
It's not a binary tree.
A B-tree is actually a potentially
more efficient data structure
that we didn't talk about a
few weeks back in week five,
but it looks a little
something like this,
which looks similar to a binary tree.
But does anyone notice what
makes this not a binary tree?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Binary tree, bi implying two, has
no more than two children per node,
but here's a perfect
example, one, two, three.
And there could be four
children, five children or more.
But the effect of that, if
you have a very wide tree,
the upside is that it's very short.
It pulls the data higher up closer
to the node, to the root node.
And recall that the root node is where
we began our searches in the past,
whether it was a BST, a Binary
Search Tree, even a tri or other data
structures.
We always began at the top.
So the higher up you
can pull the data, even
if it makes the data
structure very wide,
you're going to be able to do boom,
boom, boom, look up queries or look up
data probably much faster
certainly than if it's just
a very long list like
a column by default.
So with that said, let
me go back to VS Code.
I didn't create the index yet.
Let me go ahead and hit
Enter and create it.
All right, it took a minute, a moment.
It took like half a second,
which obviously is not that slow.
But with more data, that
could have been even slower.
But it's a one time operation as of now.
And now let me hit up and let me
select the same data from shows
where title equals The Office.
Last time just a moment
ago it took 0.035 seconds.
Not slow but also that's going to add
up if I have lots of users of IMDb.
Let's go ahead now and
execute the same query again.
How long did that take?
0.001 seconds now.
I mean, practically nothing.
And so that's the sort
of opportunity now.
When you've got lots of data
and you want to really speed up
these searches, these indexes,
these indices that just create
for you these magical data
structures in the databases memory,
it allows you to search on columns
that you are pretty sure you
want to search on more effectively.
Now, by contrast, if you've ever
used Google or Bing or some search
engine that has advanced
search, some of those text boxes
that you can search more precisely
in might very well be slower.
Why?
Well, probably you don't want
to go crazy and just index
every column on every table.
Why?
What might be the intuition?
If logically indexes speed things
up, why not index everything?
There's always going
to be a trade off here.
What might that be?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's going
to take a lot of storage.
This is just a slide on the screen.
But this has to go somewhere.
This needs space in
the computer's memory
or on the hard drive or the like.
And that's fine if you have unlimited
space, but odds are you don't.
And that's going to get
expensive for different reasons.
So maybe you only want to index
certain columns and certain tables
and not all of them.
Because you know what?
What even if a user
really wants to search
maybe via advanced search on some
other column or table altogether, fine.
If once in a while a
query is slow, we're
probably getting the bigger bang for
our buck by optimizing the common cases,
the more popular queries that
people actually care about too.
All right.
So let's come full circle and bring
this now back to how we actually
began, which was with some Python code.
So it turns out these are
not either or decisions.
It turns out in the
real world, developers
are constantly using one,
two, three languages at once.
And in fact, next week I rattled off
HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, one of which
is a proper programming
language, but those languages
are often used together.
Totally normal and common to use
Python and SQL or Java and SQL
or SWIFT and SQL or any number
of different combinations
with a database language.
You might use your preferred
programming language, Java, Python,
C++ to create the user interface and
the logic that implements the program
itself.
But for your data, SQL's
a really good candidate.
And indeed, we've seen already that SQL
can just speed up certain operations.
You can change.
You can collapse 15 lines
of code into just one
and you can use these things together.
So let me come back to--
I'm going to quit out of SQLite.
I'm going to minimize
my terminal window.
And here's where we left off
before with favorites.py.
With favorites.py, everything was
being stored in favorites.csv.
And recall that we eventually imported
that CSV file into favorites.db
automatically with .import just so we
could start playing around with SQL.
But we can now tie these two together.
And a way to do that is as follows.
CS50 has a library for Python.
You might recall having available
get string, get int, get float.
You don't strictly need
to use them in Python
because it's much easier to
just use the input function
and then try, accept, and convert
things to int or float or the like.
But it's a lot more work to use SQL in
Python without a third party library.
A lot of the commercial options
or popular open source options
are actually just complicated to use.
So CS50 does have a very useful function
inside of its library for Python
that you should use and must
use for the problem set that
just makes it easy to execute Python,
execute SQL inside of your Python code.
But it's built on top of a very
popular open source alternative.
So you can use that
too in the real world.
So the documentation for
that is at this URL here,
but I'll show you what we need to know
here by focusing back on favorites.py.
So what I'm going to do
here is follows is this.
Let me delete everything from
favorites.py except for let's say this.
From CS50 import SQL in all caps.
So that's importing a SQL
feature from CS50's library
that's going to allow me
to open a DB file in code.
How do I do that?
Well, let me create a variable
called DB for database,
though I could call it anything I want.
Let me call this SQL function and
pass in using special syntax that's
not CS50 specific.
It's an industry thing. sqlite:///.
Unlike every other URL you type, this
one literally has three in this context
here.
And then the name of the database,
which in this case is favorites.db.
So this is just a way of telling
this SQL library that we wrote
but that works exactly like third party
alternatives open favorites.db using
the SQLite technology, if you will.
All right.
Let's just ask the user a question.
Give me your favorite problem.
So we're going to use input
instead of get string,
but we could use get string, but they're
pretty much the same for our purposes.
Let's ask the user for their favorite.
And now in Python code, let
us select from favorites.db
all of the rows where students specify
that problem as their favorite.
So in SQL alone, it would be this.
Select star from favorites
where problem equals
and I'll do, well, whatever
my favorite's going to be.
Like problem equals Mario, for instance.
So if I were just using SQL, I would
literally write something like that.
But I'm in a .py file now.
I have to use Python syntax.
But Python supports strings.
SQL is just text.
It's just a string.
So I could certainly just
put my SQL code in a string
perhaps and then pass
it to a Python function.
And here's the bridge between the two.
If you just treat SQL as any old
text, we can put it in a string
and execute it.
So let me actually do this.
Let me go ahead and
create a variable called
rows, which is eventually going to
contain all the rows from the database.
Let me go ahead and select db.execute.
This is the one function you need to
know about inside of CS50's library,
and it literally
executes a SQL statement.
And then in quotes, you pass it
literally what you want to execute.
And let me go ahead and close
the parenthesis at the end there.
And now let me just try this.
So for row in rows, let's iterate
over all of the rows, let me go ahead
and print out how about
row, quote unquote.
And what do I want here?
Let's print out the timestamp
of that person for kicks.
All right, let me open
my terminal window.
Python of favorites.py.
Crossing my fingers here for sure.
Enter.
There we go.
Favorites.
I'll type in Mario.
OK.
So I got back--
it's not very interesting,
but I got back
all of the timestamps of students
who typed in Mario that we
imported into this database.
Well, what I really care
about is how popular Mario is.
So let me change this a little bit.
Let me change this to
count the number of rows.
And let me keep it simple.
Let me give an alias like I proposed
earlier like as n, where n is a number.
So that now down here, I
can actually just do this.
Print out the value of n.
All right.
Let me go back to my terminal window.
Run Python to favorites.py.
Let me type in Mario.
Enter.
OK, 39.
Now, technically I'm cheating.
Honestly if I'm executing
select count, we've
seen before it only ever
returns one row, not multiple.
So there's really nothing to
iterate over, but it's working fine.
It's just iterating once,
but I'm getting lucky.
So technically what I should
probably just do is this.
I should probably give
myself a variable called row,
set it equal to the very first
row and only row that came back,
and now print out that rows and column.
Let me rerun the program.
I'll type in Mario again.
Enter.
And I still see 39.
So of course, I don't
strictly need to do this.
I don't really need a variable.
I can do rows bracket 0 instead.
But let me focus on what
this library is now doing.
So per the documentation, what the CS50
execute function always does for you is
it returns a list of dictionaries.
So if your query returns nothing, like
no matches, you get back an empty list.
Like open bracket, closed
bracket, nothing in it.
Any loop is not going to
execute anything useful,
because there's nothing in it.
If, though, you get back
one row, you're going
to get back a list of size one inside
of which is a single dictionary.
That dictionary is
going to have keys that
correspond to whatever you selected,
be it the columns or the count.
So when I selected star before, I
would have gotten all of the columns.
That's how I was able
to access timestamp.
Here I'm just selecting
count and I don't
want to have to type this down here.
That would just look kind of atrocious.
It would work, but it would
look weird to just keep
retyping count paren star close paren.
So I just created an alias called n just
to make my life easier or cleaner down
here.
So to be clear, the CS50 execute
function returns a list of dictionaries
when you're using select.
And that is how I can now get
back the first and only row
and then print out that row's end value.
It is identical to--
let me do this.
Let me highlight this
whole line of text.
Let me in my terminal window
run SQLite3 of favorites.db
like we did before break.
Let me just copy paste this query.
Enter.
That's the table I got back earlier
when we played with SQL manually.
And so when I get back this table,
here's the key, here's the value,
and I only have one row, which
is why I'm just blindly indexing
into rows bracket 0, because
I know there's always
going to be an answer there.
It's going to be 0 or 1 or more.
But I know now it's going to be
called n because of this here.
So what have I just done?
Well, this is SQL down here.
And this is just me being like a
data scientist asking questions
about my data just using
black and white SQL queries.
This is me now being a Python programmer
who wants to talk to a SQL database
using Python.
And the bridge we're using
happens to be the CS50 library.
But again, there's third party free
libraries you can also use as well.
Ours is just very simple.
And indeed, the
documentation will explain
how execute behaves a little differently
for inserts, updates, and deletes.
You don't get back a list because
you're not selecting anything,
but you do get back some return values.
Questions on this?
That's the last of our Python code.
That ties everything together in spirit.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: This one here?
Yes.
So db.execute by definition
returns a list of rows.
And each of those rows happens to be
a dictionary because its convenient.
Key value pairs.
If I'm selecting the
count of rows, I just
know from having learned SQL
an hour ago that this is always
going to give me a single row whose
column in this case is called n.
So if I know it's a single row, I
can just blindly, just like in C,
go into that list or an array in
C and go to the first location
and then treat that as the single row.
What you don't want to do is this.
Even if you the human know
the query returns one row,
you can't just magically
change the variable name
to be singular and expect
to have only one value.
You will always have a list.
So even if there is only one value
in it, it's up to you to do something
like this to get at it.
Or if you prefer more succinctness,
you can do rows bracket I bracket n.
That'll achieve the same
thing without a variable.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Good.
So I have been misleading
this whole time
and cheating because this is
only ever going to return Mario.
I'm ignoring the favorite that the
human typed in here on line five.
So let me fix that.
And that's going to lead us to some
of the problems that arise ultimately
with SQL.
The right way to solve that problem--
let me get rid of my terminal window
here.
The right way to solve
this problem is not
to use an fstring like we
did in Python generally,
because SQL queries, as we'll see
in a moment, can be dangerous.
When you want to plug in
users' data into a query
that you've written most of
in advance, you should, you
must, you had better use a placeholder,
namely a question mark in this case.
This is somewhat specific
to CS50's library,
but we just borrowed the convention
that every other library uses too.
In the world of SQL, single question
marks are used as placeholders.
And the way you do this is as follows.
If you want to plug-in a
value for that question mark,
just like in printf in C, you specify as
a second or a third or fourth argument
all of the values you
want plugged into this.
So in C weeks ago, we were using %s.
Same exact idea.
In SQL it's a question
mark that you use instead.
This now, if I open
back my terminal window
and I run Python of favorites.py,
type in Mario, I should still get 39.
But now I can also type in
Scratch perhaps and get 44
for that very first piece at 0.
And that one is even more popular here.
So this now is correct.
It would work to use an fstring here
and then plug in a value like favorite
here.
But you'll see in just
a moment don't do that.
You will expose yourself to
potential hack or attacks
by trusting the user's input.
And so in fact, let's
transition from that
to exactly some of these
kinds of challenges,
namely two before we wrap up.
So in the world of SQL, especially when
it's used at scale with the Twitters
and the Googles of the
world, a lot of data
is probably coming into
the database all at once
because multiple people
are opening their phones
at the same time around the world.
They're clicking on
the same links roughly
at the same time around the world.
When you have thousands of people
all using your site at once,
order of operations is
going to be important.
But unfortunately in SQL and
in other contexts of computing,
there's this risk of what's
known as a race condition.
So for instance, has anyone
ever seen or liked this?
This is the world record egg.
Or it's this thing that was
very popular a while back.
It's still kind of going strong.
But if you go to the Instagram
profile for World Record Egg,
the goal was to make the most
liked Instagram post ever.
And they did pretty well.
It's just this.
It's just a picture of an egg.
Now, at the height of
the popularity, like
there might have been hundreds,
thousands, tens of thousands
of people clicking pretty much
at the same time on this egg.
So it actually creates
a potential problem
with the integrity of Instagram's data.
Why?
Well, if you have all these
requests coming in at once,
how do you possibly keep
track of all of them
and update your counter in a way that
can keep up with all of that traffic?
Why?
Well, let's just hypothesize
what Meta, formerly Facebook,
was doing underneath the hood with
Instagram if this were their code.
So suppose for the sake of
discussion that Instagram servers
are using a mix of Python and SQL.
Probably not using the CS50
library, but they could absolutely
be using those two languages
or two others together.
Suppose they do this in order to update
the number of likes for that post.
They first execute a SQL query like
select the current number of likes
from a table called posts
where the idea of the post
equals whatever the unique identifier
is for that specific egg in the table.
And then they store the result in
this rows variable, just like I did.
And then they do this.
They create a variable called likes.
They set it equal to rows bracket 0.
So the very first row in the result set.
And they get the likes key.
So this is literally what
I just did with the count.
Let me hypothesize that
Instagram does something similar
with the total number of likes.
Why are they doing this?
Because they then want to execute
a third line of code that executes
update the posts table.
Set the new number of likes equal to
something where the idea of the post
equals this other thing.
Now, notice just like in printf there's
the comma separated list of values.
They want to update the current
number of likes from the current value
to the current value plus 1.
So it's likes plus 1.
And then we plug in the ID for this.
So suppose this is what
Instagram is doing.
Unfortunately, whenever you execute
multiple lines of code independently
and you're so popular like
Instagram that you have thousands,
hundreds of thousands
of servers potentially,
it is quite possible that if you
and I and everyone else in the room
clicks that egg at the
same time, it's not
going to be the case statistically that
three lines of code are executed for me
and then three lines for you
and then three lines for you.
They're probably going
to get interspersed.
This gets executed for me and
then this gets executed for you
and then they get back to doing work
for me and so forth just to kind
of multitask, just like a human
might, but at a super speed here.
The problem, though, is
if these lines of code
get interrupted, what could go wrong?
Well, suppose that Carter and I
both click the egg at the same time
and suppose the current number
of likes back in the day is 100.
That stores in this
variable the value 100.
But if we click so close in time,
we might get back the same answer
to this select query.
As of that moment in time when David
and Carter clicked, it had 100 likes.
But then this last line of code is
executed for me and then maybe Carter.
Because that answer, the state of the
database, was stored in this variable,
then both Carter and I will
result in this line of code
being executed with the same value.
Update the post table setting the
likes equal to 101 for that post's ID.
Why?
Because again, if each of these lines
of code running on different servers
are checking the value of
the current number of likes
but then getting interrupted because
Carter clicked the darn thing too
and then resuming their
work on my behalf,
we might have a race condition where
the code is sort of racing to finish
but getting interrupted
by other users' clicks.
And the problem with
that is that if you are
inspecting the value of some variable,
or in this case a database cell,
and making a decision based
on it, like how to update it,
you might now lose data.
And Instagram is probably not good for
advertising if they're losing likes.
And so that's probably a problem
not to retain the value 102
and instead insert the number 101 twice.
It's actually similar in
spirit to a story that
was told in a databases course I
took myself years ago whereby--
it's somewhat analogous to
kind of a contrived scenario
involving a refrigerator.
And this is the closest thing to a
refrigerator we could get on stage.
But imagine you've got one
of these little dorm fridges
in your dorm too and your roommate.
And maybe both of you, as the story
was told to me, really like milk.
And one of you is at class,
but the other of you comes home
and you open your dorm fridge and you're
like, oh darn it, we're out of milk.
And so you close the fridge.
You walk across the street
to CVS or some other store
and you get in line to buy some milk.
Meanwhile, your roommate
gets out of class.
They come back to your dorm room.
They're really thirsty for some milk.
They open up the fridge.
They say, oh, we're out of milk.
And then they take a
different route perhaps to CVS
or some other store nearby,
get in line to buy some milk.
Fast forward some amount of time in this
very contrived story and what happens?
Oh damn it, we now ended
up with two gallons of milk
and there's no way we can fit gallons
of milk in there, let alone two of them.
So that's a problem.
But what's the
relationship to this here?
Well both of us, yeah, did what?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So to summarize, both of us had
a very similar thought process,
made a similar decision based
on the same information,
not realizing that the
information, the fridge,
was in the process of being updated.
And of course, in the Instagram
world, it happens like this.
In the fridge world, it
might take a few minutes.
But the problem is
ultimately the result of our
having made a decision about the state
of the world and the state of the world
was in the middle of being updated.
The queries got comingled with others.
Or, in this case, someone was
already on their way to the store.
So what's the solution
in the real world?
Well, you could very simply take a
post it note and put like gone for milk
so as to communicate to your
roommate that they should not
inspect the value of that variable
and make a decision on it.
Why?
Because it's not yet consistent with
the outcome that's about to happen.
You could be more dramatic
and you could actually
lock the fridge somehow,
put a padlock around it
or the like so they
can't even get in there.
And that would achieve
the same effect too.
And that is actually pretty much the
solution to this problem in code too.
It's not safe.
It's not sufficient to only execute
three lines of code like this.
Rather, what you probably want to
do is use additional SQL keywords
that we won't spend much time on
in the class itself, but these.
There are solutions to this problem.
You can begin what's
called a transaction
and you can more explicitly
commit to making a decision,
like updating the
database to 101 or 102.
Or if you realize, wait a minute,
Carter's query is interrupting mine.
Let me roll back to the
previous state and just rewind.
Let me undo.
Control Z, if you will.
There's also another keyword
that's not so much used anymore
in SQL which is locking.
You could literally back in the day.
Lock the entire database table,
preventing anyone from updating it
or making changes or even reading it
while someone else was accessing it.
That was a very heavy handed solution
because it slowed everything down.
But in short, transactions
are now a feature of SQL
that you won't necessarily
need to use yourselves
that do solve this problem by doing
the equivalent of saying while David's
like counter is in the process of
being updated, keep Carter at bay,
ideally briefly, and then
let his data go through too.
It's equivalent too to putting
a note or a lock on the fridge.
And indeed, I mean lock literally.
They were once upon a
time called and still
are in some contexts called
locks on databases too.
And the code for which you might
do this is almost the same.
You simply wrap the three queries with
a transaction statement and a commit.
And the term of art here is that
this makes your statements atomic.
So atomic means they're either
all executed or not at all.
That is they're all very tightly
coupled together without interruption.
Transactions solves that problem and
avoid having two gallons of milk.
And the last problem that
arises that is tragically
so darn common in the
real world today is
what's called a SQL injection attack.
And it's what I alluded to
earlier with the question mark.
So suppose you're in
the habit of logging
into Yale websites with
your net ID or password
or at Harvard, your Harvard
key and password as well.
Suppose for the sake of
discussion that the people that
implemented Harvard key log in allow
you to type in your email address,
of course, and your password.
But suppose that they are
using SQL underneath the hood
to check your username
and password to make sure
that you are David Malan or Carter
Zenke or whoever you claim to be.
I haven't shown you the syntax yet,
but it turns out that in SQL, --
is a special way of
indicating a comment.
It means ignore everything to the right.
So it's just like // in C or
the hash symbol in Python.
-- just means ignore
everything to the right.
And we've, of course,
seen single quotes.
So one way to wage a
SQL injection attack
is to try to inject malicious SQL
code into someone else's database
without them realizing it.
How do you do this?
Well, suppose I log in as
malan@harvard.edu single quote dash,
dash.
I'm not double quoting anything clearly
and there's nothing to the right
of the --
anyway.
But this imbalance is
going to be useful.
Why?
Because if I'm a hacker and I'm
presuming someone at Harvard probably
is using single quotes to
wrap the user's email address
and wrap the user's password, what if I
try to complete their thought for them
and close one of those quotes for them?
What might happen?
Well, we could do this.
Here for instance, let me hypothesize
is the code that Harvard wrote,
hopefully not, underneath the hood.
So they're using CS50's library in
Python and they're using SQL inside.
Suppose that they have
a query like this.
Select star from users where username
equals question mark and password
equals question mark.
And then suppose they just plug in
whatever username and password was
typed in.
And then if they get back some
number of rows dot dot dot,
they assume I am David.
They assume Carter is Carter if
both the username and password are
in the database.
Just end of story there.
This is good.
This has the question mark
placeholder, as we discussed earlier.
But what if you don't
quite remember that?
You don't quite take that to heart and
you use your more familiar last week
fstrings whereby we use these
curly braces to plug in values.
What if you do this instead?
So it's almost the same idea.
It's still db execute but now
it's select star from users
where username equals.
And now notice I'm doing the single
quotes, which is required by SQL,
but I'm using fstrings
with the curly braces.
And the password equals single quote
password and then close single quote.
The problem is if you're just
blindly pasting effectively
the user's input into that web form
into the username field and the password
field, there's nothing stopping a
malicious user, student, faculty,
staff from including a
single quote in their name.
Or maybe even benevolently
if their name happens
to have a single quote, as some
last names in particular do.
So this is very fragile.
Why?
Well, suppose that if
we plug in my malicious,
malan@harvard.edu single quote --
notice what happens to username here.
The username variable
inside of the curly quotes
will get replaced with this.
And notice single quote, which
the Harvard programmer wrote,
malan@harvard.edu single
quote which I wrote --
which I wrote single quote which
Harvard wrote and whatever else
they want after that.
What's the implication,
though, of the dash, dash?
Everything to the right
is going to be ignored.
So the password is never even
checked in this scenario.
I'm tricking the server into
ignoring everything after the --
but I have constructed very cleverly,
very maliciously a syntactically valid
query.
Why?
Because I provided the
single quote that's
going to finish the thought
of that first single quote.
And now I would only know how
to do this if I saw the code
or if I just randomly try putting
apostrophes into web forms
and see if things break.
That's often how
adversaries attack systems.
They type in potentially
dangerous characters, hit Enter.
If something breaks, they're
not necessarily into the system,
but they know that there
might be a vulnerability.
And then they start trying more
methodically things like this.
So this then is going to be
bad, because it effectively
grays out the rest of the query.
And this query is surely
going to return some rows
without even knowing my password.
And so this logic here
dot dot dot means, well,
if a data came back
from this query, Harvard
is presumably going to
assume that Malan logged in.
Show him his account or whatever
is being protected here.
So in short, using fstrings bad.
Using any equivalent like %s in C, bad.
When it comes to SQL,
using question marks
or whatever a third party
library like CS50 prescribes
is the way to solve this.
Why?
Because libraries like ours are designed
to at least be smart and be paranoid.
And what we will do is this.
When you use the question marks
and the values are plugged in,
we will escape any potentially
dangerous characters
inside of those placeholders.
And so effectively, the
single quote will no longer
be considered a
grammatical single quote.
It will just be literally a character
in the username or password.
So the library takes
care of this for you
because you're plugging in the username
and password as separate arguments.
And then we or the third party
you're using actually sanitize.
That is clean up the data and
prevent those bad characters.
Now, this is kind of an internet
meme that went around for a while.
If you've ever driven
a car or been in a car
where there's the automatic
readers for tolls.
This person thought it might be funny
to try doing something like this.
What are they presumably doing?
The presumption here is, whether
or not it worked is unclear,
is that here's the end of
actual license plate number,
but here's an interesting
single quote and a semicolon.
That's especially bad because
it means you can maybe
execute a second query on the database.
This is someone having fun trying
to drop the entire database
table for whatever municipality is
scanning through cameras their license
plate code.
And I would be remiss if
we didn't end on this note.
At least in computer
science circles, there
is someone named, no relation to the
TF name we put in the database earlier,
little Bobby Tables, which
ends with this XKCD comic.
And if you chuckle, if you laugh,
you're now legit SQL programmers.
Nice, nice.
Every CS student out there
knows about little Bobby Table.
So if you name drop little
Bobby Tables now, you're in.
All right, that's it though for today.
We will see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]