[MUSIC PLAYING]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- All the way to the top
and then you pass it down.
- This is for you, Yale.
We love you, Yale.
- We're here to cheer for Harvard.
- Yeah.
Go Harvard.
- Take one and pass it down.
- Pass them down.
- It's not gonna say something
like Yale sucks is it?
- It says go Harvard.
- We're nice.
- You see that [BLEEP]?
Look at them.
They passed the paper.
It's gonna happen.
It's actually gonna happen.
I can't [BLEEP] believe it.
- What do you think of Yale?
- They don't think good.
- It may be a complete
mess, I don't know.
- You can't really fix it now.
- Does everyone have it?
Does anyone have their stuff?
Does everyone have their stuff?
- The probability that it's going
to be legible is very small.
- I agree.
- It's too complicated.
- Look at all the signs.
- I know, but it's too complicated.
- What houses are you guys in?
That's not a real house.
- How many extra are there?
- Ho-fo?
- Yeah.
- You guys aren't from Harvard are you?
- No, Pfoho.
Pforzheimer.
- Yeah, but she said ho-fo.
- Well, she's probably drunk.
- Does everyone have their stuff?
- Are all the cards distributed?
- All right, let's do it now.
[CHEERING]
- Yeah, look.
- Oh my God.
It's gonna work.
[CHEERING]
- Hold up your signs.
[BLEEP]
- You suck, you suck, you suck,
you suck, you suck, you suck.
- We [BLEEP] did it.
[BLEEP]
- You suck, you suck, you suck,
you suck, you suck, you suck.
- What do you think of Yale, sir?
- They suck.
[LAUGHS]
- They suck?
- One more time.
One more time.
[CHEERING]
- Oh, there it goes again.
- Harvard sucks, Harvard sucks, Harvard
sucks, Harvard sucks, Harvard sucks,
Harvard sucks, Harvard sucks.
[END PLAYBACK]
ADAM: All right.
This is CS50.
Welcome to week eight.
Last week we learned how to create,
read, update, and delete databases
using SQL.
But this week--
- Adam, everyone.
Happy Halloween.
[LAUGHS]
[APPLAUSE]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So this is the CS50 and
this is week eight already.
My thanks to Adam on today,
this Happy Halloween.
In the coming moments,
we're going to learn
all about how the internet
itself works, which of course,
is a technology that we all use every
day, probably using in some form
right now.
But we'll see that if you start to
understand some of the underlying
building blocks that
power the internet itself,
we can actually start to build
interesting things on top of it.
And a lot of the apps,
the websites that you all
use every day should become all the more
familiar, things that you yourselves
can create.
And honestly when
things go wrong, you'll
have all the more of a mental model for
how things work or are not, in fact,
working so that you
can ultimately diagnose
all the more issues yourselves.
So if we take a look at the
internet in the early days,
it pretty much was just this.
This happens to be, of course, the
geography of the United States.
And just some of the first points
on the internet were these here.
This was so called ARPANET back in 1969.
And indeed, the internet had its
origins here in the United States
with just a few computers
interconnected somehow initially.
That, of course, began
to grow over time such
that we eventually had the West
Coast connected to the East Coast.
And nowadays what you can think
of these dots on the screen
as representing are these
things called routers, sort
of computers or really servers
that somehow have wires or maybe
wireless connections between them
that allow data to flow from point A
to B to C. And then this, of
course, has been now magnified
across the entire globe
and even above ground
as well so that we can connect all
the more readily to systems anywhere.
Now, in order to route the data
from one router to another,
we need to somehow
make routing decisions.
And this is the kind of thing that the
internet service providers, the ISPs
of the world just handle for us.
You and I plug our Macs, our PCs
into the network here at Harvard
or equivalently at Yale
or we somehow get online
via Wi-Fi or cellular technology.
And then some of these larger entities,
these bigger companies or countries,
handle most of the data
getting from point A
to point B. And if you think about
what these routers represent,
they're indeed just servers
somehow interconnected,
not unlike this grid of tiles here,
for instance, back in the Zoom days.
And in fact here we have,
I claim, a grid of routers
implemented here by the course's
teaching fellows and course assistants
and TAs.
And if the goal at hand,
for instance, is for Phyllis
to route some piece of
information, maybe it's an email,
maybe it's a request for a web page
in the bottom right hand corner,
all the way up to, say, Brian
here in the top left hand corner.
Suffice it to say if each of these
tiles represents a router, a server that
can move the data back,
forth, left, and right,
that packet of information, so
to speak, from Phyllis to Brian
could take any number of
different possible routes.
Up, down, left, right to go
from the one corner to another.
So let me go ahead and
hit Play on this video
here wherein the teaching
fellows play this same role.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right, so
in this particular case,
the data was routed
pretty straightforwardly
up and then to the left.
But suppose that one or more
of the staff were a bit busy.
Maybe one of the routers is congested.
That is to say, just
get way more envelopes
at a moment in time that it can handle.
Thankfully the design
of the internet is such
that there's often multiple ways
the data can get from point A
to point B, maybe going through
point C or point D instead.
And so there's a resilience there
even as some of the servers themselves
might go down.
So allow me to propose that we
use the same grid of routers
now to route the data in a
slightly different way this time.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: So success.
You'll see perhaps later
just how many takes it took
us to actually get that routing right.
But it does in fact manifest that you
can travel different paths in order
to get the data from point A to
point B. So as we talk about routers,
as you think of the internet,
I mean, think of those humans
as just representing these routers.
Points A to P and everywhere in between.
Now, how do the teaching staff know
to route that packet up and then
down or left and right in order
to get to the destination?
Well, all of them were programmed,
so to speak, to understand protocols.
It's called TCP and IP otherwise
known together typically as TCP/IP.
And you've probably seen
these acronyms at some point
in the real world, on the internet,
on some kind of documentation, a text
even if you haven't really
thought hard about it.
But IP is certainly the more common
of the two perhaps in common culture.
So what does TCP and IP do for us?
Well, really two primary things.
Any computer or any teaching staff
member who understands TCP/IP
knows how to get data from
point A to point B. But how?
Well, let's break down what
that problem to be solved is.
IP, otherwise known
as Internet Protocol,
is a protocol that computers
speak that allow them to know how
to address computers on the internet.
And a protocol is just a set of
conventions that computers adhere to.
So someone wrote code that probably
has a whole lot of conditionals
that tells the computer what
to do if something happens.
Like if I receive a packet,
then send it to the next server
or something like that.
In the human world,
we have protocols too.
In healthier times, it was quite common
to extend your hand to another human
in order to greet them.
And if they're following human protocol,
they would presumably grab your hand
and shake it, at least in a culture
like this one here on campus.
And now that is a human protocol
in that someone initiates it,
someone responds to it, and you
both sort of know what to do.
Your programmed to know what to do.
So same idea with internet protocol.
Computers just know what to do when
they've been programmed to do so.
So what does this mean?
If IP decides that every computer in
the world will have a unique address,
just like the Science Center around the
corner might have a unique address of 1
Oxford Street, Cambridge,
Massachusetts, 02138, USA.
IP dictates that every
computer on the internet
have a unique address of this form.
And this too is probably something
you've seen in the real world
even if you haven't
thought too hard about it.
It's a number and what's called
dotted decimal notation, which
means it's a decimal number dot
something dot something dot something.
So four digits separated by
convention by decimal point,
although there are newer and
bigger versions of the same.
And these so called IP
addresses that might
be as simple as 1.2.3.4 uniquely
identify a computer on the internet.
The numbers have to
range from 0 to 255 each.
And that's a bit of a hint just as you
start to think more computationally.
If each of these is a
number from 0 to 255,
how many bits does that
suggest each number is using?
Feel free to shout it out.
How many bits gives us 255?
256 total possibilities.
So eight bits.
That should just be sort of
a heuristic in your mind.
Anytime you hear something that's in the
range of 0 to 255 or 256 values total,
think back to week 0, which gives us
eight bits plus another eight bits
another eight bits and
another eight bits,
which is to say an IP address
typically is 32 bits in total.
Now, if we do another bit of quick
mental math or think back to week 0,
if every IP address is 32 bits, how many
computers can we have on the internet
at once?
Give or take.
Roughly 4 billion is the ballpark.
And we don't need to be super
precise for discussion's sake.
But roughly 4 billion
is how high you can
count, assuming no negative numbers,
if you have 32 bits in total.
Now, that's not terribly
many numbers of addresses,
especially considering the
number of humans in the world,
the number of us that do have laptops
or desktops or devices more generally,
phones in our pockets and the like.
So let me just stipulate
for today's purposes
that there's even a newer and
improved version of IP otherwise known
as version 6.
This is version 4 but
still super popular.
Version 6 uses 128 bits, which is a
huge number of possible permutations.
I daresay I can't even pronounce
that number it's so big.
So there are ways around
even this limitation already.
So every computer has
an address like this.
What does that really mean?
Well, suppose that I was Phyllis
in the story told visually earlier
and I want to send a message to Brian.
Well, both Phyllis and
Brian have IP addresses.
And suppose that Brian's
IP address happens
to be 1.2.3.4 in that
top left hand corner.
Well, Phyllis's Mac or PC
or phone would essentially
do the equivalent on this human
envelope by writing the two
address in the middle of the envelope,
as is our human convention, like this.
So this is an envelope,
a piece of information,
an email, a text message,
whatever destined for Brian.
And so she would have her computer
put Brian's IP address in the middle.
Her IP address is maybe 5.6.7.8.
So just like our human
convention, I might write 5.6.7.8
at the top of the envelope.
Five, six, seven, eight.
Thereby indicating what
the return address is.
And this is helpful, because if Brian's
computer needs to acknowledge receipt,
if he needs to reply in some
form, this way the envelope has
all the information we need.
But in the real world, servers
do a lot of things nowadays.
Not just email but maybe chat,
maybe video conferencing, maybe
any number of other services as well.
And so it turns out that an address
alone might not be sufficient,
because how does Brian's computer
know when he opens the envelope,
so to speak, that this should
be interpreted as an email
or interpreted as a chat message or
interpreted as a video attachment
that Phyllis has sent?
Well, we need some other mechanism,
some other hint on this envelope
to distinguish one type of
internet service from another.
And so that's where the other acronym
in TCP/IP comes in, which is TCP.
So this stands for
Transmission Control Protocol,
which is just a different
set of conventions
that computers adhere to in order to
solve a couple of different problems.
One is this problem of distinguishing
one type of service from another.
Now, what does that mean?
Well, humans decades ago
decided as they started
inventing all of these various
internet services, the web being
the first one, how they might-- or the
web now being the most popular ones.
They decided to assign
different services that can
be used on the internet unique numbers.
And so two of the most common are these.
80 is the number that a bunch
of humans decided years ago will
represent what you and I know as HTTP.
And we'll talk more technically
in a bit about what HTTP is.
But obviously it's the thing that's in
the beginning of every URL nowadays.
Or HTTPS, which, of course,
has the S added to it.
And that has its own unique number.
And for now, the S just means Secure.
One is encrypted or scrambled
somehow for privacy's sake
and the other is unencrypted.
It's a little more
vulnerable to interception.
So these two numbers are what the world
decided when implementing TCP shall
uniquely identify those services.
So what does this mean?
Well, this means that if Brian's
computer in the story from before
is hosting not like an email
server but maybe he has a website
and Phyllis is requesting Brian's
home page or something like that.
She would have her Mac
or PC or phone not only
write Brian's IP address in the middle
of the envelope but also the number,
otherwise known as a
port number that she
wants this envelope to be routed to.
Now, 80 would be insecure nowadays.
HTTP:// is sort of passe and we
almost always see HTTPS:// now.
So I'm just going to
go with best practice
and I'm going to add a
colon and then the number
443 at the end of Brian's IP address.
So now I have an IP address for
Brian, the port number for the service
that this is relevant to, and I'm
not going to bother writing it,
but it turns out that
Phyllis's computer would also
choose a port number,
maybe a random port number,
so that Brian can conversely reply.
And then the computer
can know which response
is coming back for which request.
But the most important one
is this one in the two field
whereby this distinguishes
this from an email, a chat
message, a video conference
session or a Zoom or whatnot
from anything else happening on
Brian's computer at the same time.
So all this time if you've
seen these terms TCP and IP,
those are really two of the most
important things that they do.
But TCP does one other thing
that's super useful too.
It turns out that it's super
common nowadays especially
to transmit a lot of media on the
internet, whether it's an image
or maybe it's a movie file, and
it would be a little obnoxious,
to say the least, if your
downloading a really big file
meant that no one else in your
dorm room or your household
could actually download anything
until you're actually done.
So of course, multiple people
nowadays can be on the internet
at once even if all of the
connections are a little slower.
But one person's usage does
not block someone else's.
Now, how does this work?
Well, TCP/IP in conjunction
with IP can also
allow you to take a really big image
of a cat, which the internet of course
is filled with, and take
a big image of a cat
or a big video file of a cat and
fragment it into multiple pieces.
So I'm just going to roughly
tear it down the middle
and then maybe tear it
down the middle again.
So now it's four different fragments.
And I'm sorry, but the computer
will be reassembling these for us.
And what Phyllis's computer
could do now if she's
uploading this picture of a
cat to Brian's web server,
well, she could put one
fragment in this envelope
and then have three separate envelopes
for the other three fragments.
And what she could then do on
the outside of this envelope
is just kind of number them somehow.
And in fact, this is something else that
TCP and IP together would do for us.
This first envelope now might say
something like one out of four
in the memo field, so to speak,
of the metaphorical envelope here.
Now, this should be enough information.
Because now if Brian gets
all four of these envelopes,
he presumably knows how to reassemble
the picture of the cat in order top
to bottom, left to right.
But more importantly, suppose
that one of the routers, one
of the TFs in the video
is sort of distracted
and they sort of drop
one of the packets.
And that's a metaphor
actually in practice
for when a router gets really busy.
It's got way too much data coming in.
It might metaphorically drop packets.
What does that mean in practice?
I mean, it literally just
ignores the zeros and ones.
It doesn't save them to its memory,
because there's just no room left.
So it's equivalent to
dropping the packet.
So suppose now that Brian gets one of
four, three of four, and four of four.
What can his computer infer now
after receiving those three packets?
One of four, three of
four, and four of four.
What's the use there?
Yeah, I think you're signaling
with your fingers which one--
can I call on you?
Yeah, so he's missing two out of
four, the second of the packets.
And this is useful now
because you could imagine
he can send some message
back to Phyllis saying, hey,
please retransmit number
two of four without having
to redownload the entirety of the cat.
So there's an efficiency there as well.
So TCP/IP allows data
really to go from point A
to point B while solving a bunch
of these problems along the way.
So nowadays if you ever see mentioned
on your Mac or PC of your so called IP
address, that is the sort of
problem that's being solved.
Questions now on these protocols,
these conventions called TCP and IP?
That's the extent to which
we'll need to understand them.
Won't have to implement them, per se.
We'll just take them
hereafter for granted.
Any questions that you've ever been
wondering about your home network?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: What happens when TCP--
like, when you try to send a message?
Does it know if that user
got the message or not?
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
How does TCP know that
a user got a message?
Another aspect, another
feature of TCP is
that Brian's computer by
design of this protocol
will also acknowledge the
packets that he's received.
And it will do it efficiently.
If Brian receives all four packets
in a pretty narrow window of time,
his computer will send to Phyllis's
computer a quick message saying
essentially received all four.
Otherwise he'll say the
opposite, which is that I'm
missing for instance two out of four.
And that just ensures
ultimately that all of the data
is indeed arrived so
that you're not missing
like a quadrant of the cat in question.
All right, but that's
not the only problem
that needs to be solved ultimately.
We also need to make the internet
user friendly, if you will.
And it would be really tedious if you
had to visit websites, for instance,
by way of their IP addresses.
1.2.3.4 is pretty memorable, but there's
like 4 billion other possible addresses
available.
And it would be super
tedious to remember those.
It would be bad marketing
to advertise those.
In fact, most of you probably don't even
know the phone numbers of your closest
friends and family members anymore
because you instead store them
in your contacts or in your
address book associating
with numbers that are completely
opaque with actual names or strings,
if you will.
The same goes for the internet
too, even though every computer
does have and must have a
unique IP address numerically.
Why?
Won't routers or computers, computers
just crunch numbers very readily,
but we humans work better
with strings of text.
We need some system for
converting user friendly strings
like harvard.edu or yale.edu or
google.com to the underlying IP
addresses.
And that's where the next
acronym comes in today,
which is DNS, Domain Name System.
So this is just another technology
that's been in use for some time now.
And it's a collection of servers on
the internet whose purpose in life
is to convert domain names to IP
addresses and maybe vice versa as well.
So let me stipulate
for today's purposes,
there are some root DNS servers in
the world that, long story short, know
about all of the dot coms, all
of the dot edus, all of the dot,
dot, dot, all of the other top
level domains around the world,
as well as in the US.
And then there are some
smaller DNS servers
owned by companies, owned
by universities, and even
in your apartments or homes most likely.
Indeed, if you have a home router
plugged into the wall somewhere,
that's not only routing
your data in and out
of your apartment or home or dorm room.
It's also typically serving as a local
therefore faster DNS server, a cache
if you will.
It's sort of locally saving your
most frequently accessed websites
in their IP addresses just to
avoid bothering the bigger, more
expensive, busier servers all day long.
So there's DNS servers all over.
If you poke around your settings in
Windows or Mac OS or Android or iOS,
you'll see mention of
DNS, and you'll probably
see the IP addresses of the
servers whose purpose in life
is to do this conversion for you.
But this is a requisite
feature if we just
want the internet to be
user friendly and allow us
to use words instead of numbers alone.
What's inside of these DNS servers?
It's essentially a spreadsheet.
Or if we can say it more
geekily, it's essentially
like a hash table of some sort,
which it has keys and values.
The key is the domain name.
Harvard.edu, yale.edu, google.com.
And the value is the corresponding
IP address, or in many cases
IP addresses plural, of
the corresponding servers.
So here already even though
I've drawn it fairly abstractly
like you would on a chalkboard,
it's really probably implemented
as some kind of table.
Maybe a hash table,
maybe a database table,
maybe SQL or something like that.
Or maybe it's even just a
linked list or an array.
We just have to somehow enable this
computer to convert one to the other.
Now, just to be super
precise, DNS servers actually
convert what are called fully qualified
domain names, which is generally
not just harvard.edu but more verbose
www.harvard.edu and www.google.com.
So the whole thing that you would
see as a substring of the URL.
So that's what DNS does.
And that's what your university,
your company, your home router
are doing for you.
Let me pause here to see
if there are any questions.
This too is just a technology
now we'll take for granted.
It just works.
Questions at all?
No?
All right.
So let's now transition
among our protocols
really to the last for
today, which will set
the stage for actually
solving problems with these
and writing some code ultimately.
HTTP.
This is something that
you see or hear all day
long even though you rarely have
to bother typing it anymore.
Odds are if you go to
harvard.edu, yale.edu, google.com,
you don't bother typing HTTP, let
alone HTTPS, manually anymore.
Why?
Because your browser auto completes that
kind of thing just to make life easier.
But it is officially at
the beginning of every URL
you visit, either HTTP
or the more secure HTTPS,
whenever you're using your
browser to access some website.
So HTTP stands for
Hypertext Transfer Protocol.
And it's easily one of the most popular,
daresay one of the most powerful
features of the internet nowadays.
But the mental model to have
here is that HTTP or the web more
generally is kind of a service
that runs on top of the internet.
And maybe Zoom or Microsoft
Teams is another service
that runs on top of the internet.
And iMessage and technologies
like it is another service that
runs on top of the internet.
So the internet is really the lower
level plumbing, the TCP/IP stuff,
the DNS stuff, that just gets
data from point A to point B.
But now, and we're in a
software development class
ultimately here in CS50, HTTP is
the application level protocol.
It's sort of what programmers
use, what companies use,
what developers use ultimately to
use the underlying plumbing to build
interesting and powerful things.
So what does this mean when it
comes to accessing services via HTTP
or the more secure HTTPS?
Well, here is a representative URL.
Even though you might
not type the whole thing,
if you poke around your address
bar, this is what's up there.
With that said, a lot
of browsers nowadays
are kind of simplifying if not dumbing
down what you see with your human eyes
just to shorten the strings,
especially on mobile devices.
But almost always, if you
click the URL or highlight it,
then you see the whole thing.
But on many browsers, you might
only ever see example.com.
But all of this information is there.
It's just getting more and more
hidden just for user interfaces sake.
Well, it turns out when you
visit a URL, by default,
especially if you type nothing
after the dot com in this case,
you're technically implicitly
adding a single slash.
So a single denotes
the root of the server.
That is the default page
or folder in the server.
And the slash, whether or
not you type it or not,
is implicitly going to be there.
And that just means give me the
default. Whatever is at www.example.com,
give me that page or that folder.
But URLs can be longer than this.
And more generally, there
can be a path, so to speak.
And this is a term of art.
A path is some sequence of folder
and/or file names after a URL like this.
And so you might see more
specifically that a URL contains
a very specific file.
This isn't as common nowadays
anymore, though we will begin today
by using this technique.
But if there is a file called
literally file.html or something else
on the server, that file is going to be
what this URL pulls up on the computer.
Meanwhile, you might have
/folder/, which just means show me
whatever's inside of this folder.
Or you might have more
verbosely /folder/file.html,
which will show you that
file in that folder.
And meanwhile, just to give
some other terms of art,
this is the so called fully
qualified domain name.
And again, these vocab words
don't matter all that much,
but you'll hear or see them over time.
We generally colloquially
just refer to this
as the domain name, which
is a little less precise
but gets the job done
certainly in conversation.
And this part here I
described briefly earlier.
What's the name for this suffix at the
very end of the fully qualified domain
name?
The?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Top Level Domain.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Top Level Domain or TLD.
And this is just some form of
categorization of the URLs.
Now, the internet got its
start within the United States
and a lot of the first websites,
of course, came from the US.
And so for better or for worse, the
sort of stake was planted in the ground.
So generally .com indicated at
least early on that it was some kind
of commercial enterprise, a
business that owned a domain name.
.edu is an educational institution.
.net was some kind of network.
.gov was the US government.
Now, there are also country code TLDs.
CCTLDs like .uk or .jp.
Every country in the world
has its own two letter
TLD that might very well be restricted
to only servers or companies or people
in that country.
Many of them can be used by anyone.
You've used a lot of URLs in
this class ending in cs50.io.
That doesn't mean input output.
It actually is a TLD
from another country
that lets anyone on the internet
pay for and on an annual basis
using that domain.
.tv for instance you might see in some
cases, like twitch.tv and the like.
That too is owned by
another country that
allows others in the English
speaking world in this case
to use it as though it connotes TV.
But those are just
different types of TLDs
that roughly categorize
where the domain lives.
But it doesn't necessarily
mean it's commercial anymore.
It doesn't necessarily mean
it's a network anymore.
For the most part, there
are hundreds of TLDs
now, for better or for
worse, most of which
are less common than these big ones.
But most anyone can buy most of them
with just some restrictions on things
like .edu and .gov that are
still very much regulated.
This, meanwhile, is what we might call
the host name. www, It's obviously
a super common convention.
Almost every website uses
www as its host name.
But that's a human convention.
It's not a requirement.
And indeed, some websites don't
even bother having a host name.
They just use their domain
to advertise their websites.
This now is going to be
the scheme or the protocol
and this is just going to indicate via
what protocol the computer, your Mac,
your PC, your phone should use when
accessing content at that address.
Because indeed, there are
other protocols you can use.
But for the most part, we'll only
focus on HTTP or equivalently HTTPS.
All right.
Any questions now on those just
definitions, building blocks of URLs,
just so we all sort of
share a common vocabulary?
Any questions at all?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: What is the local post IP?
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
We'll come back to this
actually later today.
There's a technical term
known as local host, which
is a generic name for your computer,
your Mac, your PC, your phone,
especially when you're
doing software development.
And by convention, your
own computer has not only
whatever IP address you get from your
university or your internet service
provider.
It also has a reflexive IP address,
one that just always refers
to itself, which is 127.0.0.1.
And that's just a human convention.
Humans decided that shall
refer always to your computer.
And it's actually going
to be useful today
and onward, because we can use that when
doing development on our own computers
ultimately.
Other questions on URLs, IP, DNS,
or any of these building blocks?
All right.
So what do we mean by
HTTP being a protocol?
When I extended my hand
earlier as a human handshake,
a typical human in healthy times
would know to respond in turn.
Well, how does Brian's computer to
respond to Phyllis's envelope, whatever
message is therein?
Well, assuming that Brian is indeed
still a web server in the story
and Phyllis was trying
to upload a cat or maybe
download a cat from Brian's web
server, inside of Phyllis's envelope
would have been a message
literally in text.
And it's English for the most part.
And it would contain at the beginning
of that message literally one
of these English verbs.
Either get, which means just that.
Get me the home page.
Get me a picture of a cat.
Get me a picture of a dog
or a video or anything else.
Or post, which often means post.
That is put, that is upload
a picture of a cat or a dog
or something else to the server instead.
That's not strictly the
only use cases for these,
but you can generally think them
as one is just getting information
and the other is posting from the
client, from Phyllis to the server,
in this case, Brian.
So those are the two
keywords that we might see.
And why is this useful?
Well, it turns out we can start
to see in our own Mac or PC
some of these very same messages.
For instance, if Phyllis were visiting
not Brian's but example.com, that web
server, inside of her
metaphorical envelope,
there would be a textual
message that literally
starts with get slash then the word
HTTP then the version she's using.
1.1 is very common.
Two and three are becoming more common.
But HTTP generally looks like this.
The next line of text in her
envelope would probably say host:
then literally the fully qualified
domain name of the server
she's accessing, just in case.
And this happens super commonly,
especially on small websites.
If one server is hosting multiple
domain names, multiple websites,
this just distinguishes
which one she actually wants.
And then there's usually a whole
bunch of other lines of text as well.
So where can you actually see this?
Well, let me actually
go ahead and do this.
Give me just a moment, and I'm
going to open up on my computer here
an empty Chrome window
in incognito mode.
Generally speaking, incognito
mode or private mode
is used when you don't
want there to be left
remnants of what websites you visited.
And it has the effect
for software developers
of just forgetting any things you might
have tried already within your browser,
including things called cookies.
More on those another time.
Your autocomplete history and the like.
So for development
purposes, incognito mode
is especially helpful because it's sort
of like starting with a clean slate
every time you open a new
private or incognito mode.
So there's not going to be any
remnants of previous testing or code
that you've been playing with.
And I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and right
click or Control click on Chrome.
I'm going to choose Inspect.
And it's going to pull up this
window, sometimes on the side
sometimes on the bottom.
I'm going to move it to the bottom just
so we can see it a little more readily.
And I'm going to zoom in.
And it's going to look a
little arcane at first.
And I'm going to just
highlight a few of these tabs.
We'll see here along the top that
there's elements, console, sources,
network, and a whole bunch
of other things as well.
This is the advanced mode in Chrome.
And Safari and Firefox and
Edge have their own equivalents
of these features.
They've always been there, even if
you've never clicked the right button
to enable these features.
And I'm going to focus for a
moment on network like this.
This is a feature of the browser
that's going to allow me,
the programmer in this
case, so the engineer,
to just kind of look at what
messages my browser is actually
sending to a server.
So let me go ahead and
do something like this.
Let me go ahead and visit for
instance in my browser here,
and I'm going to shrink the window just
a little bit so we can see it exactly,
I'm going to visit
https://www.harvard.edu.
And now I'm going to hit Enter.
And a whole bunch of stuff just
happened along the bottom of my screen.
And I'm going to try to pull
my window up just a little bit.
So we can focus on a subset of this.
Let me pull this up, covering up
really the content of the page,
focusing on these lower
level details down here.
And what I want to see first is--
let me-- oh, sorry.
Let me go ahead and
reload this page here
after retaining the
log so that we can see
absolutely everything on the screen.
And to be clear, I just checked
because I forgot earlier preserve log
because I wanted to preserve
everything on the screen.
I want to see everything all at once.
And we'll see this.
The very first line of output is
completely overwhelming with detail
at first glance.
But what you'll see here, if I start to
scroll down and down and down and down,
are the so called request headers.
And let me zoom in here.
And what you're seeing inside of Chrome,
inside of its Network tab in its so
called developer tools.
Again, this is just
for engineering types.
You'll see all of the headers,
all of the lines of text
that magically were sent by my Mac to
harvard.edu, much like from Phyllis
to Brian's server in that story.
So I can see exactly what
messages are being sent.
And a lot of this we
haven't talked about yet,
but we do see some mention of get
and we see some mention of slash
and a bunch of other arcane details.
But notice they're all sort of key value
pairs with the colon here indicating
what the corresponding value is.
Now, most of this is not
going to be interesting,
and we're not going to focus too
much on the weeds of all of this.
But it indeed gives us a sense of
what's inside of that virtual envelope.
Now, harvard.edu is one thing.
But there's other websites
we might visit as well.
And no matter what they are, we're going
to expect ultimately an HTTP response.
So in addition to a computer,
like my Mac or Phyllis's computer,
sending a request containing gets
and host and those details too,
you'll see here in my slide form
just representative response
from the server.
And notice that key here
is that the server is
responding in the same version
of HTTP in this example.
It's sending back this
so called status code.
Just a numeric code that indicates,
in this case, that everything's OK.
And it includes this
header, this HTTP header,
which again, is just a
key value pair saying
that the type of this content
that's coming back from the server
is text/html.
More on HTML in just a little bit.
But for our purposes now, this
just means that harvard.edu
is sending me back a web page.
And indeed, if we hide all
of this technical stuff,
that's the web page that
we saw up here with all
of the usual imagery and the like.
And in fact, I can see this if
I scroll back up not to request
headers but response headers.
You'll see up here that
we get back responses,
including the date that
the server responded
and a whole bunch of
other details as well.
And honestly, this has always
been under your fingertips
and it will soon be useful as we
start making web based applications
ultimately.
But this very quickly
gets overwhelming quickly.
And so better than this
might actually be a tool
that we can use within
our code space itself.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
I didn't open any code tabs.
I'm just going to use my
terminal window for a moment.
And I'm going to run
a couple of commands
that are going to allow
me to actually see what
is going on when I request one website.
Let me go ahead and use a command
called curl for connect URL.
And this is like a command line
black and white program that's
going to pretend to be a browser.
And it's going to connect to
the URL, show me the headers,
but it's not going to show me
the images of the graphics, which
might very well be useful
to the humans but not to me
right now as the developer.
So I'm going to do curl.
I'm going to do -i.
And then I'm going to do
https://www.harvard.edu/
as though I'm pretending to be a
browser requesting the home page.
And what's nice about curl
is, albeit overwhelming too,
you'll get back a whole response from
the server containing only those header
values, the key value pairs
inside of the envelope.
And we'll ignore almost all of these.
But here is the response
from the server.
It responded using a new and
improved version of HTTP.
In this case, version two,
and it gave me back a 200.
There's my content type, text/html.
And then this char set happens
to do with the encoding,
if it's Unicode or
ASCII or something else.
And then there's all this other
overwhelming detail for now.
But this is the beginnings of my ability
to just kind of poke around and see
how the server works.
And it turns out too that we'll be able
to see other potential responses as
well.
So for instance, HTTP
might not only return 100.
What if I do this instead?
Let me go ahead and visit curl
-i http://www.harvard.edu.
So notice I deliberately
used the insecure version
of the URL, which maybe Harvard's system
administration doesn't like anymore.
Well, how can they ensure that
I, the end user, the student,
nonetheless use HTTPS even
if I didn't type it myself?
Well, let me run just that
command with just HTTP, not HTTPS,
and you'll see that
everything is not OK.
It didn't come back with a 200.
It came back with 301 and this message
saying Harvard moved permanently.
But here's where you can
look for another clue.
Among all of these lines, most
of which I don't care about,
there's a location patient
header colon that's
a little hint to me that says where
Harvard University has apparently
moved to on the web.
And what's different about
this URL, just to be clear?
It has the S included.
And what your browser
will do by default,
because Google and Microsoft and
Mozilla programmed it this way,
whenever it sees a 301 response instead
of 200, it won't show you any web page.
It will look for a location
header, find that URL,
and then automatically quote
unquote "redirect" you there too.
So this is why it doesn't matter
what we type in the browser.
Harvard can have its servers send these
semi secret messages to our browsers,
and then it will just visit a
second URL all automatically.
And you can do this
with hostnames as well.
Suppose that Harvard does not want
to standardize on harvard.edu.
Why?
They just want it to always be www.
Maybe it's a branding thing.
Maybe it's a technical thing.
We can see the exact same response here.
This first tells me when I visit
HTTP harvard.edu with no www,
Harvard minimally wants me to
be using a secure connection.
If I then, OK fine, cooperate, let
me go ahead and clear my screen.
Let me add the S but not the www.
You can see here that it again
responded with 301 up here.
And the location now adds the www.
So it's just a way of bouncing
users from one place to another.
And this is all thanks to HTTP boiling
down to relatively simple messages
inside of the envelope that tell the
computer, the browser in this case, how
to respond.
Now, odds are you've
seen others besides 301
even though you've probably never
seen that actual number unless you've
done this kind of thing before.
But there probably is a number
that everyone in this room
has seen even if you never really
wondered why is it that number.
I think you're smiling.
What number are you thinking of?
Yeah, so 404.
Why is 404?
Well, 404 indicates by
convention not found.
And now why the world
decided years ago to show us
normal humans on the internet 404
is anything significant is unclear.
That's sort of bad design.
What do I care if the
status code is 404?
But it's common enough on the internet
that probably all of us have seen it.
But that just means that some server
when you visit a URL that's incorrect,
maybe it's outdated, the URL has
been changed, if you see a 404,
it just means that the virtual
envelope that came from the server
back to your Mac or PC or
phone contains not 200 OK,
not 301 moved permanently,
but 404 not found instead.
And it's usually accompanied by
a technical message, maybe a cute
picture of a cat sort of hiding
because it means not found
or something like that.
The aesthetics are
entirely up to the server.
But that's what the 404 means.
And there's other codes too, a few of
which you'll use in the coming weeks
as we transition from
command line programs in C
in Python to web based ones.
We've seen a few of these already.
And several of them are kind of variants
of the same thing, like these 300 ones
here.
But we'll see others.
Like 403 forbidden means you
probably forgot to log in
or you need to log in
or something like that.
Internal server error.
Right now know in the coming weeks you
will absolutely encounter 500 errors
and they're always
your fault. It's going
to be the equivalent of a
segmentation fault in C.
A 500 error means you or I
screwed up when writing some code.
So we're going to see that.
But it's just going to be an
opportunity for us to fix it.
If a server is overloaded,
you often see 503,
like something's unavailable because
something's too popular or is,
maybe worse, getting attacked.
This is an old April Fool's joke.
418 is not actually used in
practice, but someone took the time
to write up an entire formal
technical proposal so that servers
can respond saying I'm a teapot.
So it's kind of part of internet lore.
And there's other ones of
these status codes as well.
But this is useful,
because eventually we'll
see in code you can
use this understanding,
high level as it might be, of HTTP to
do some interesting and powerful things.
So for instance, we can even
send fancier URLs to servers.
It turns out, as we'll soon see,
if you send a message like this,
get/search?q=cats and then HTTP 1.1
or whatever version and you send that
message to Google
server, www.google.com,
this is how you can specify not just
the path of a web page that you want,
/search in this case.
The question mark it turns out is going
to be a convention in the internet,
in the web specifically, for passing
human user input to the server as well.
In fact, you've probably never
paid close attention to URLs,
but they very often have question marks.
They very often have equal signs.
And indeed, even google.com supports a
certain key, q in this case for query,
and you can put anything
you want after that in order
to search for actual cats.
So if I actually go back to Chrome
itself here for a moment, let me
pull back open my Chrome
browser here, previously
I was using incognito
mode for harvard.edu.
I've gone ahead and closed that
window and opened a new one
so we can start fresh
by visiting Google.
Normally you and I are in the
habit of going to google.com
and searching via the form.
Or nowadays you just
type your search query
in the browser itself and
it brings you automatically
to Google or Bing or something else.
But I can really be pedantic here.
Let me go ahead and zoom
in and I'll manually
go to https://www.google.com/search?q=
maybe cats.
Now, this would not be a very user
friendly experience if all of us
had to manually type out
something crazy like that.
But that's what the
form is redirecting you
to when you type in more user
friendly cats into a text box.
If I hit Enter here, we'll get back
indeed a whole bunch of search results
about cats.
If I zoom back in and maybe I
change it from cats to dogs,
that too is going to change.
And notice it's prepopulating the
text box because Google has written
its code in order to do so as well.
Now, apropos of the video
with which we began today
from yesteryear, one of the
better Yale pranks over the years,
has anyone actually ever
been to safetyschool.org?
And to our friends at
Yale watching live, hi.
Safetyschool.org.
So it's kind of fun if you actually
visit it depending on who you are.
So if I open up a new window here.
And I go to http://safetyschool.org,
zooming in, Enter, my oh my.
Look at where it goes.
Now, how does that--
[APPLAUSE]
This is not a CS50 thing.
Someone out there who I don't
know who they are for 20 years
has been paying annually for
that domain, safetyschool.org,
for just this joke.
But if I now go back into VS Code here
in my terminal window and a little more
sophisticatedly let me do curl
-i http://safetyschool.org,
the browser of course immediately
redirected me to the website.
But what's going on underneath the hood?
Well, 20 some years ago, someone bought
the domain, configured the server
quite simply to spit this out.
Safetyschool.org for years has
moved permanently to www.yale.edu.
So just a little
demonstration of what you can
do with just a little bit
of understanding of HTTP.
That's been a lot already.
We've laid the foundation for
understanding how the internet works.
Now we're going to use it with a
language called HTML, Hypertext Markup
Language, CSS, Cascading Style Sheets,
and JavaScript, a proper programming
language.
But first it feels opportune
to take a 10 minute break.
We have some wonderful
Halloween candy in the transept,
and we'll be back and
10 with those languages.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- We're headed up to Boston, checking
out the stadium for the prank.
A few years ago, I was
at a math conference
and I was sitting around the table at
dinner with a few other mathematicians.
And one of them went
to Harvard and started
telling the story of this amazing
prank that was against Harvard.
And at that point, I
felt I had to interrupt
and said, well, actually I can
tell you a lot more about that.
OK.
- The idea was perfected in a dorm room.
- We came up with the idea
actually to prank them
with signs of the football game.
We threw some ideas out there as
far as what the signs would say.
We eventually settled on we suck.
- And my immediate reaction
was, no, this will never work.
However, the problem solver in me
started thinking, well, maybe we
can make this work.
- The problem?
They had to infiltrate Harvard
stadium without getting caught,
sneaking 1,800 placards, distribute
them to unsuspecting Harvard fans,
and then convince those
fans to prank themselves.
- It's great.
We thought about basically every
possible thing that could go wrong
and tried to come up
with a solution for it.
- And then you put
two reds on top of it.
- They made fake Harvard IDs and fake
backstories, fake placard designs,
and a 28 member fake pep squad.
On November 20, 2004,
the fake Harvard students
smuggled the placards into the game.
- What do you think of Yale, sir?
- They suck.
- It's not going to say
something like Yale sucks, is it?
- It says go Harvard.
- But then trouble.
- What houses are you guys in?
That's not a real house.
- Ho-fo?
- Yeah.
You guys aren't from Harvard, are you?
Can I see your Harvard ID, because I
really think you guys are from Yale.
- I just showed him the front of this
ID and all of a sudden, he just ran away
and he felt so embarrassed.
- Having escaped one confrontation,
they couldn't risk another.
It was time.
- This just looks like a total mess.
We have absolutely no idea
if this is going to work.
- Look at them.
They have the paper.
It's gonna happen.
It's actually gonna happen.
I can't [BLEEP] believe this.
- What was once a prank became a legend.
- We [BLEEP] did it.
[BLEEP]
- And immediately we started
hearing chants from the other side.
You suck.
- You suck, you suck, you suck.
- And I think it was at that point in
time that we knew we had pulled it off.
- One more time.
Come on, Harvard.
- There it comes again.
[CHEERING]
- I really think it didn't matter
that Harvard won because of the prank.
For a lot of Yale students and
alumni, we definitely won that year.
[END PLAYBACK]
ALL: All right.
This is CS50.
Happy Halloween.
[LAUGHS]
[APPLAUSE]
DAVID MALAN: Thank you all.
OK, thank you.
Oh, here.
Oh, all right.
A little Halloween candy.
All right.
Thank you all.
So glad I wore the same thing today.
So in just a moment--
thank you.
OK.
So in just a moment, we'll
transition to understanding
all the more now what we can do
with this underlying infrastructure.
So again, HTTP and below
it TCP/IP is all about just
getting the data from point A to
point B in some standardized way.
But now let's talk about HTML.
This is the language in which
web pages themselves are written.
Hypertext Markup Language.
Now, some of you might have used this
before to make personal home pages.
Some of you might have dabbled
even if using some website
to create your own home page.
But understanding this
language is useful certainly
for creating the aesthetics of a
web page, conveying data that's
of interest.
But at the end of the day, it and
the language we look at next, CSS,
are not programming languages.
There's going to be no functions,
no loops, no programming logic.
But we will end today with a teaser of
a proper programming language called
JavaScript via which you can manipulate
all of these various other languages
as well.
So ultimately HTML has two features.
And this is a language that we
spend very brief amount of time
on because it really boils down
to just a couple of basic ideas
and then vocabulary that
you'll build out over time
just by Googling, looking up references,
looking at other pages' source code.
But tags and attributes
are what characterize HTML.
Now, what do I mean by that?
Here, for instance, is
the HTML code via which
you can make probably the
simplest of all web pages, one
that quite simply says in the browser
window, hello title and hello body,
for instance.
Now, what does this actually mean?
If you imagine opening up this code in a
browser, be it on a Mac or PC or phone,
you'll see typically some
kind of rectangular window.
And there's usually a tab that
has the title of that page.
And then most of the rectangular
region is the web page itself.
What you're looking at
then is the code that's
going to put hello title in the title
bar, in the tab at the very top.
And down at the bottom,
hello body is going
to be all that's in the big
black and white box that composes
the rest of the browser window itself.
Now, what are the salient
characteristics here
that we'll now start
to take for granted?
Well, first, whoops, first let's go
ahead and, give me just a moment here,
and actually do
something with this code.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
Back in VS Code here, I'm going to first
create a file called, say, hello.html.
And in this tab, I'm going
to go ahead and really repeat
exactly that same code.
Now, I had this line
first, doc type HTML.
Then I had this line, HTML lang
equals quote unquote en close quote.
Then I had inside of that head,
then I had inside of that title,
then inside of that I had hello title.
And I'm doing this quickly
because we'll tease apart
in a moment what it actually all means.
And then down here below that so called
head, I had just the text hello body.
So at the moment, that I claim
is the entirety of a web page.
But it currently lives in
my code space, so to speak,
in a file called hello.html.
That's fine if I want to create it.
But how do I, how do you, how
does anyone on the internet
actually view it?
Well, to serve a web page,
you indeed need a web server.
And it turns out that Codespaces
comes with one of these pre-installed
because we CS50 staff did so for you.
And what you can do in a
terminal window once you
have an HTML file ready to go
that you want the world to see,
you can literally run in your
terminal window http-server.
Single command.
And what that's going to do
for you is start a web server.
That is to say, a program whose purpose
in life is just to serve web pages.
And even though probably up
until now for years you probably,
if you're like me, equate "server"
quote unquote with a physical device.
Server is really a piece of software.
It just tends to run
on big fancy devices.
So when we say server,
we often all think
of in our minds eye big,
expensive devices, perhaps.
But a server is just a
program whose purpose in life
is to respond to
requests with responses.
And that's the vernacular there.
Now, once you run HTTP server,
and I'm going to do a bit of magic
because I set this up before class
just to make sure it goes smoothly,
you'll see some output like
this whereby your server is now
available on a very long URL.
Mine here is a very long URL that
will be different from yours.
But what this is is a unique identifier
that your Codespace has temporarily
generated so that you can
now access and ideally
only you can access that
file using your browser.
Now, if I flip the URL or you flip
the URL to public by right clicking
or control clicking the
right features of VS Code,
you can enable anyone in
the world to visit it.
But we're not going to ultimately
host our websites in your Codespace,
because as soon as you log off for
the night and the thing shuts down,
the website will go down.
But at the end of the semester,
particularly for final projects,
we'll show you ways that you can
put your own website, your own code
on the actual internet 24/7, 365
even with your own domain name
if you want to get one so that it lives
independent of your own sleep schedule
and usage schedule a VS Code here.
So I'm going to go ahead now and visit
this URL in another tab of my browser.
And what I'll see here is this.
This is the output of that
program called HTTP server.
And essentially what it is doing is
it's using TCP and IP in conjunction
with HTTP to just run your very own web
server on GitHub's own servers as well.
And that's because of different ports.
Again, we won't go too much into the
weeds of the TCP, the IP, and all
of that stuff.
But recall that different
port numbers can
allow you to distinguish
one service from another.
Now, one of the services is, of course,
your Codespace, VS Code in the cloud
that we've been using for weeks.
But if you want to use the same
physical server that GitHub controls
but actually visit your own web server
that I just ran in my terminal window
in another tab, that's fine.
They're just going to be
using different TCP ports.
And you and I don't have to care
what they are but just that this
is a feature that TCP supports.
So what you see here is somewhat arcane.
This is not a thing that most people
on the internet should ever see.
I'm just doing this for
development purposes.
But this is the index.
That is the directory, the
folder contents of my Codespace,
and because I deleted everything
from prior weeks already,
all we see right now is
hello.html, which I just created.
So if I click on hello.html
within this folder listing,
you'll be a little underwhelmed.
And I'll zoom in just so there's
something more interesting there.
But now you see hello comma body.
But what's interesting, perhaps,
is that after this long,
very cryptic and uninteresting
URL, notice at the very end of it,
and I'll zoom in in a moment,
what do you see? /hello.html.
Which follows the convention
I claimed before break
is how a browser would allow you to
access a specific file on a server
by doing slash and then
the name of the file name.
Everything before it is very cryptic.
It would be better if I
buy a domain name that's
a little more easy to remember
and set that up some other time.
But for now, let's just
focus on only the file names
that I'm actually creating.
All right.
So the code is up and
running, underwhelming
though it might be with the
body in the middle of the page.
And let me zoom in up here too.
Hello comma title is indeed
in the tab, just as promised.
So what's actually going on with
code like this that we just created?
Well, let's go back to the
slide version of the same.
And let me just highlight
a few of these lines.
The very first line is what's called
your document type declaration.
Doesn't really matter to
remember that by phrasing.
And this is just something you copy
paste or do from memory at the top
of any .html file that you create
when making your own web page.
It's a implicit indicator
to the browser that you're
using the very latest version
of HTML, which is version 5.
You don't mention the number 5.
Just browsers nowadays are
programmed look for this
to know that you're using the very
latest version of the language.
Languages, just like human
languages, evolve over time.
We're up to version 5 of HTML, but new
features get added every few years.
So indeed, this lecture, this class
has been evolving over time too.
So let's now focus on the next
line as well as the bottom line.
And you'll notice some
deliberate symmetry here.
This here is what we're
going to call a tag.
And it's technically
different from this.
This is a document type declaration.
It's got the weird exclamation point.
That's the only anomaly.
Everything else follows a pattern.
This is a tag in HTML
and it's the HTML tag.
And a tag generally both starts
and stops or opens and closes
at some point.
So this is the so called
start tag or open tag.
And this just means essentially
to the browser, hey, browser,
here comes some HTML, the language
in which web pages are written.
This here with the forward
slash after the angled bracket
means hey, browser, that's
it for the HTML of this page.
So that's what I mean by symmetry.
I started a thought here,
finished it down here.
What's in between those two thoughts?
Well, here browser, or rather
let me clarify one thing.
This thing here is that
other keyword, an attribute.
An attribute is something that
modifies the behavior of a tag.
So it's similar to an
argument in C or in Python
like a parameter to a function.
These aren't functions,
but it's the same idea.
Just modifies the default
behavior of something instead.
Lang equals en.
You can probably guess just means that
hey, browser, assume that everything
hereafter is in English.
And that might be useful for Google
Translate or just search engine
optimization so that just
the server, the browser
know what human language
you have actual content in.
Like hello title, hello body, even
though a good computer can probably
infer from context often.
All right, so that's an attribute.
That's a tag.
And the whole thing here, everything
in between the start tag and end tag,
we would also call an HTML element.
That just means everything related
to that open and close tag.
All right.
Now notice indented
inside of, so to speak,
the HTML open and close tag are another
pair of tags, the head tag and the body
tag or the head element collectively
and the body element collectively.
And same idea.
Hey browser, here comes
the head of my page.
Hey browser, that's it for the head.
Hey browser, here comes
the body of my page.
Hey browser, that's it for the body.
The head is essentially the tiny
little strip at the very top,
including the tab itself.
The body is like 95% of everything
else, the big rectangular region.
What's inside of your title,
of your head of the web page?
At the moment, just the title.
So this indicates, hey
browser, here comes my title.
Hey browser, that's it for the title.
The title of course, is literally
quote unquote "hello comma title."
Meanwhile if we bounce back out
here is the second element inside
of the HTML tag.
This says, hey browser,
here comes the body.
Hey browser, that's it for the body.
And hey browser, this
is the contents, these
are the contents of the body itself.
Now, the indentation
is a stylistic thing.
I did it just to be sort
of neat and tidy because it
suggests what is inside of what.
But it also suggests
a sort of hierarchy.
And in fact, we'll use terminology
from the world of family trees.
If this is a parent, so
to speak, head and body
would be the child
elements of the HTML tag.
Meanwhile title is a
child of the head tag.
Or equivalently, title
is a grandchild of HTML.
So you can use the
same sort of vernacular
as in the human world when it comes
to familial relationships too.
And that just hints at,
again, this same hierarchy.
So we have tags and they
include HTML head, title, body.
And that's it for now.
We have attributes.
We've seen one example of them, lang.
But we'll see many other
examples of the same idea.
But these building blocks
are exactly the same.
Generally, you start a
thought, you finish a thought,
and you might do something in between.
Questions on this basic
structure of any web page?
Any questions at all?
No?
All right.
So let's now allow things to ramp
up a little more interestingly
and do something with
these building blocks.
But so that you have a mental
model for everything that's
going on here on after,
think of this same HTML
being related in spirit
to week five when
we talked all about data structures.
If I really wanted to,
I could take to heart
this idea of children and
parents and grandparents
and really depict this
thing graphically.
And in fact, this tree here, if you
will, and it's not a binary tree,
it's not a binary search
tree, it's just a tree.
Using week five's terminology, if
this special node here represents
the whole document, well the root
element, as I called it, is HTML.
HTML has two children, head and body.
The head tag has in
turn a title child and
in turn has some text, just
as the body has some text.
And so this is what
your browser is doing.
You and I, the programmers,
write this stuff.
The browser reads this code
top to bottom, left to right
whenever you visit a website.
And inside of the computer's memory,
Chrome, Edge Firefox, Safari, whatnot,
they build this data structure
in the computer's memory
so as to know what it is
you have told them to do.
And we'll see over time
at the end of today,
you can write code in an actual
programming language, JavaScript,
to maybe dynamically add or
remove things from this tree.
And this is how things like Gmail work.
When you open up your
email inbox, if you're
a Gmail user, if you just
stay there long enough,
you'll probably get more and more mail.
And what happens?
You don't have to reload the
page or rebuild the tree, per se.
It just all of a sudden it appears
at the top, at the top, at the top.
What's happening there is that Google
wrote some code that just keeps
adding more nodes to
this tree every time
they realize you've got a
new message again and again.
So that's the relationship now
even with this world of HTML,
with all of the programmatic
ideas we looked at in the past.
All right.
So let's go ahead and
do something with this
that's a little more interesting
than just hello itself.
I'm going to go ahead and hide my
terminal window because the server is
now running and all I want
to do now is experiment
with hello and other examples as well.
Let me go ahead and actually
before I do that, let me go ahead
and run code of paragraphs.html
just so I can keep my code separate.
And now I'll hide the
terminal window again.
Paragraphs.html.
I'm going to do almost exactly the same.
Let me go ahead and start
with something familiar.
And eventually I'll start copying
and pasting just to save time.
So doc type HTML is always there.
Open the HTML tag.
And now notice I didn't
type the rest of that.
Just like with C, just
like with Python, we
try to save you some keystrokes by
closing parentheses, adding quotes.
The HTML support in VS
Code is pretty good too
and it tries to finish your thought
when it comes to tags as well.
It can screw things up if it does
something you don't want it to do.
So sometimes you have to delete.
But it's just autocomplete,
as we've seen before.
Let's go ahead and let me add lang
equals en as all of my examples
today will be.
Let's add the head tag.
Let's go and proactively
add the body tag.
And now let's go ahead and give
this a title tag, which has a--
I'll just call this paragraphs just
so I remember which example is what.
Now notice all of this white space and
all of this neat and tidy indentation
the browser ultimately is
not going to care about.
This is just for us humans to
kind of keep ourselves sane
when we look at the code.
It's just easier to read.
But strictly speaking, I could
minimally delete all of this white space
and I could just move all of
this tag up to the same line.
Both I think are fine.
I'll just kind of follow
a certain convention.
But this too would have
the exact same meaning.
But we'll see where that
detail about white space
could potentially get
us into trouble later.
In my paragraphs tag, let's do this.
In advance I've written up some
Latin-like text, a really long
paragraph of Latin-like text like this.
It's actually random nonsense.
It's not real Latin even though a
couple of the words might look familiar.
And so here we have
three paragraphs of text.
And I've deliberately
hit Enter in between them
so that just like an essay in Google
Docs or Microsoft Word, hopefully
I'll see three separate paragraphs.
Let me now change tabs and I'll
close hello.html from before.
I'm going to go back
to my other tab here.
I'm going to click Back to go back
to that index of all of my files
which I started at earlier.
And you'll see now that I have two
files because I obviously just created
a second file called paragraphs.html.
So let's click on this to see our
three paragraphs of Latin-like text.
And voila.
I'll zoom out.
All right.
First bug, if you will.
This just looks like one massive blob
of text, not three blobs of text.
And why might that be?
Borrowing the hint I
offered a moment ago.
Why are we not seeing break?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so we need
some kind of line breaks here.
Because the browser turns out is
only going to take us literally.
And if you just give it text, text,
text, it's just going to show you text.
And any time there's more
than a single white space,
whether it's two or
20 or 200, it's going
to just assume that you did
that just to be neat and tidy
and it's going to collapse them into
just one space visually like this.
So there are, in fact,
a couple of solutions.
One is this here.
I could add some explicit line breaks.
And it turns out that
there's a VR tag like this.
And just for visibility's
sake, let me do two of them.
So hitting Enter, Enter on my keyboard.
I'll do it here too.
BR for break, break.
And now let me go back to my other tab.
Nothing's changed yet, but
that's because I have to reload.
I've changed it on the server, but
now I need to change it in the browser
by reloading.
And now it looks a little
better, albeit nonsensical.
But you'll notice a curiosity.
Per this BR tag, this is
kind of poorly designed.
It's a little hackish to just say Enter,
Enter and make the browser do this.
Breaks, line breaks, don't actually
require close tags or end tags.
So not all tags need to be closed,
at least those that it just
makes no semantic sense to close them.
Like the break is there or it's not.
You can't imagine starting
to move to the next line
and then eventually getting
around to finishing.
It's either there or it's not.
So some tags do not have
close tags as necessary.
But there's a more elegant
way here, I daresay,
not just sort of hackishly
putting in these line breaks.
Let me do this instead.
I'll delete those.
And let me go ahead and, as
the name of this file suggests,
let me add a paragraph tag.
Now, here I need to fight
with VS Code's autocomplete,
because I don't want to
finish the thought there.
Let me go ahead and open the paragraph
tag and close a paragraph tag.
And just to keep things
tidy, I'll go ahead
and indent too, even though the
indentation itself doesn't matter.
Let me go ahead and create another
tag for opening this paragraph.
And I'll close this one here.
And now let me see.
Sometimes it's fighting
with my autocomplete,
but that's fine, because I did
this the wrong way at first.
And now let me go ahead
and finish this thought
by closing this paragraph tag here.
And I've manually fixed
all of my indentation.
So now on line 10, I have the equivalent
of hey browser, start a paragraph.
And then it does the Latin-like text.
Then on line 12, hey browser,
that's it for this paragraph.
And repeat, repeat.
If I now go back to my
other tab and reload again,
shouldn't be all that different.
But semantically, it's
a little bit better.
Why?
Because you saying break, break
doesn't really mean anything.
But by saying paragraph,
paragraph, paragraph, now
there's some more semantic
information there.
Now if Google is analyzing your
page or if the programmer is
trying to understand what it is you
did in the past when writing this code,
you just know semantically,
oh, this is a paragraph,
this is a paragraph,
just like in a book or an essay.
So it's a little more clear
focusing more on what it is,
not how you want to display it.
Any questions then on these paragraphs?
All right.
So a few more tags.
And indeed, these first few
examples will really just
be sort of bang, bang, bang.
Just a bunch of different vocabulary
words in the form of these new tags.
But we won't go through the
entire laundry list of tags.
This is indeed the thing for which
web references and books and the like
are ultimately helpful, just like
a dictionary in the real world.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and copy this.
Let me create a new file
called headings.html
just so we have a new file for this.
To save time, I'm just going to
paste that exact same code just
to get me started.
I'm going to change the title
of it for clarity for the code
online to headings.
And now just like a book
or an essay or a thesis,
let me actually put some
actual headings here.
Now, if my first heading
like chapter one,
I could do something like this up here.
I could have a paragraph like I just
learned and I could say something
like chapter one here.
But that's not really a paragraph.
And so it's sort of better
design to tell the browser
and really tell the world what it is.
So it turns out there's another
tag I can use like h1 for heading
and most important heading.
And in here, I'm just
going to keep it simple
and I'm going to say something like one.
And in fact, this is so short.
Here's a good candidate for just
keeping this all in the same line.
But this has no functional
difference, but it'll just
make it a little more
terse on the screen.
Now let me go ahead down here.
And I could have multiple
headings so H1 two.
And down here I could have
another one, H1 three.
And if I go back to my
other tab, I reload it.
Now we should see, just like a book
or an essay, now we have some proper--
now we have some-- oops.
I have to go to the right file.
Sorry.
If I go back to the index,
now we see the new third file
called headings.html.
And now we indeed see some fairly
pretty, if simple, headings as well.
Now, if these aren't three
chapters, one, two, three, but maybe
it's a chapter, then a
section, then a subsection
such that just visually you want
things to get smaller and smaller,
well those exist too.
And in fact, you can do H1 through H6.
H1, a little paradoxically,
is the biggest and boldest.
H6 is the smallest but still bold.
So it might make sense to make this H2,
both open and close, and maybe this H3,
open and close, if again, this
is a section or a subsection
inside of that chapter.
If I reload now, notice
just gets a little smaller.
So it's more similar to what
you'd see on the printed page.
But this now is just another three
tags that I might use in my own code.
All right, well how
about lists of things?
I have three paragraphs
here, but let's do this.
Let me go back to VS Code.
I'm going to copy this code
so I have a starting point.
I'm going to create a new
file called, say, list.html.
Here I'm going to copy paste.
I'm going to change my title
to be list just for clarity.
And in here I'm going to go ahead
and get rid of this whole body,
because let's move away from
these massive paragraphs
and keep it simpler for now.
If I want to have a list
of things, for instance,
if you haven't seen these already,
a computer scientist when they're
fishing for just some
arbitrary meaningless words,
they often use foo, bar,
and baz just as their go to,
just like a mathematician might
use x, y, z for variables.
So foo, bar, and baz are
on three separate lines.
And maybe this is my to do
list or my shopping list.
But you can probably imagine,
if I go back to my other tab,
go back to the index, I now
see my new file list.html.
But it's probably going to look wrong.
I think I'm just going to say yeah,
foo, bar, baz all in one breath,
if you will, not on new lines.
And you can try to fight this.
You can be like really want
to put some line breaks.
There go back and reload.
It's still not going to make any change.
How do I want to fix this?
Well, I can do this in a few ways.
I can make them paragraphs, but
they're not really paragraphs.
They're a list.
So I'm going to use a
different tag instead.
I'm going to create, for instance,
an unordered list using the UL tag.
Open and close.
Inside of that, I'm going to
use the list item tag, LI,
and I'm going to say foo.
Inside of another tag
I'm going to say bar.
Inside of a third tag open and
close, I'm going to say baz.
So it's getting a little verbose,
but it's still relatively succinct.
LI is all you need type for list item.
UL is all you need type
for unordered list.
So there's some shorthand
syntax here that's adopted.
If I now reload, you're going to
see a so-called unordered, list
like not sorted, which means by
convention to show it as bullets.
Though it could be displayed in
different ways visually as well.
If you actually change
your mind and you realize,
oh, I'd really like to number this,
well, you could obviously like just
add one and two and three, but
that's going to get annoying,
especially if the list grows.
You want to change something,
insert something in the middle.
Then you have to reorder it.
I mean, we're using computers here.
They can do this for us.
So we can change the UL to any guesses?
OL, maybe, for ordered list,
which is the opposite here.
So let's try changing that to OL.
Let me go back to my browser.
And I'm just hitting
Command R or Control
R to reload the page instead of
clicking the button every time.
Now I automatically get
one, two, and three.
And you can even override the
aesthetics using different numerals
or symbology instead, but that would be
perhaps the most common there as well.
All right.
It's a lot of tags quickly.
But any questions on lists,
paragraphs, headings, or the like?
No?
All right.
So let me go ahead
and propose this here.
Let's go ahead and create
what we'll call a table.
So let me copy and paste
this into a new file.
Code of table.html.
And in table.html, let me again
rename the title to table.
Let me get rid of that
ordered list from before.
And let me now use a
table tag open and close.
This one one's a little weird.
But inside of a table, you
typically have a head of the table.
So I'll say, well,
let's say the first row.
We'll keep this one simple.
A table row or TR.
Inside of a table row, you
would ideally have columns,
but that's not the nomenclature.
Instead you have data.
So TD for Table Data.
And let me go ahead and just
have the first datum be one.
I'm just going to arbitrarily
do one, two, three
just so we have something to play with.
And you know what?
Just for demonstration sake, I am going
to deliberately copy paste this twice
and I'm just going to
manually change the numbers
just so we can see what I'm creating.
Seven, eight, nine.
And then maybe just for good measure
if you're seeing where this is going,
let me copy this one
more time and give myself
a final row with an asterisk,
a 0, and a pound sign
if maybe you see where this is going.
Let me go back to my other tab.
Let me go back to the index.
There is my new file, table.html.
I'll click that.
And while it's not very
pretty, I'll zoom in.
It's indeed a table of data.
I happen to mimic a telephone keypad.
But you can imagine this
being much juicier, much
more interesting scientific
or financial data or the like
laid out into these rows,
TRs, and these columns, a.k.a.
table data as well.
So we have that ability as
well for structured data.
Now of course, the internet
has lots of images on it.
And in fact, this is all just text.
How can we introduce images?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me first sort of semi
secretly copy an image file
that I brought from earlier just
so we have something to play with.
And I have in my account here
now an image called harvard.jpeg.
And I uploaded this semi secretly
a second ago into my account
so that I can reference a second file.
Let me go ahead and copy this HTML
just to save myself some keystrokes.
Let me go ahead and
do code of image.html.
And let me paste that code
and hide my terminal window.
I'm going to get rid of all of this
table as just uninteresting now.
We're going to make this even simpler
by changing my title to image to keep
all these demonstrations separate.
And now if I want to make a
web page that when visited
shows us a picture of
Harvard, well, there's
an image tag abbreviated IMG for short.
I can specify what the
source of that image is.
And if my file, a JPEG in this case,
is literally in the same folder,
I can just say quote
unquote "harvard.jpeg."
If it's in a folder, I should
mention the folder name and a slash
or something like that.
If the image is on the
internet somewhere with a URL,
I could also have a whole URL,
https:// and then the URL of the image.
But I uploaded it in advance.
Now, this is just going to
visually display on the screen.
But not everyone, of
course, can see images.
Screen readers might
need a bit of assistance.
And even search engines might
want to analyze the page
and know what this is an image of.
Now, machine learning and
artificial intelligence
are maybe getting better,
to be fair, at figuring out
just by analyzing images what they
are, but they're certainly imperfect.
I am a human.
I know pretty well what I
took a photo of, for instance.
So maybe what I should do proactively,
which would be good for accessibility,
is have this alt tag
for alternative text.
And then literally
say Harvard University
so that someone who can't
see or so that a server can
actually with higher probability
what it is they're looking at.
And I could be even more
detailed than just a phrase.
I could describe the image as well.
All right.
Let me go back to my
index in the second tab.
Let me go back and zoom back out.
There's my new file and there's my new
JPEG that I quickly uploaded before.
I can click now on image.html
and, albeit a little
overwhelming, that is a
really big image of Harvard.
Now, apparently it's too
big to fit on the screen.
So this isn't the best user
experience to have to scroll up.
OK, so there's the image.
Horrible, horrible design, if you
will, at least in terms of my code.
But there's going to be ways where
I can rein that in and affect
the height or the width as well.
But for now it's just deliberately
a little overwhelming instead.
Now we can do something
a little more fun
and topical today, which might
be to use a video instead.
So let me go ahead here and very
quickly grab another file today,
which I brought in advance and
you might have seen briefly
earlier, which is an MP4,
an actual video file.
And what I'm going to do here by
revealing VS Code again is I'm
going to code a file called video.html.
Yet another demonstration here.
I'm going to change my title to video
just to keep these things straight.
And instead of the image tag, you might
imagine using now indeed a video tag.
And this is a relatively newer tag that
has increasing support among browsers.
So it's good now to use.
And inside of this, the
syntax is a little different.
You specify, and this is
weirdly annoyingly inconsistent,
not SRC for source.
You literally say source.
And then in source, you
use a source attribute.
Horrible design semantically, but
this is what we're stuck with.
Halloween.mp4 is the name of the video.
We uploaded in advance made by
some of Harvard's digital artists.
And the type of this video so that the
browser knows for sure is video/mp4.
That's a so called
content type that you just
know or you look up to figure it out.
And just so that this is
as animated as possible,
I'm going to tell the video tag
with a few attributes to autoplay.
And it turns out that attributes
often have key value pairs whereby
it's the key, the attribute name
equals quote unquote some value,
just like lang equals quote
unquote en for English.
But not all attributes need values.
In fact, if you read the
documentation for HTML's video tag,
there's an autoplay attribute where
you can literally just say the key
and it needs no value.
It's just going to mean autoplay.
And if you don't want autoplay,
you just omit it altogether.
So you don't necessarily
need a value on or off.
I want the thing to loop
just so it keeps going.
I want it to be muted so
that we don't hear any sound.
In fact, there is no sound,
but browsers nowadays
for anti-spam and
advertising reasons often
will not play a video if it has sound
because it's just kind of obnoxious
if you visit a page and all of a
sudden your speakers start blaring.
So I know this from
having read up on this
that I should mute it if I want
it to actually autoplay for real.
And then I'll set the
width manually for now
to be like 128 pixels across just
from some trial and error earlier.
And that width attribute
does have a value.
Now, I'm being a little uptight here
by alphabetizing all of my attributes.
Not at all necessary.
I do it just so I can skim things faster
and know if something is there or not.
So for me it's just a matter of style.
Let me go back to my other tab.
Go back to my index.
And you'll see two new files,
again, the MP4 file and video.html.
I'll click on the latter.
And if I did this well, here
we have thanks to our friends
in Harvard, our artistic
friends at Harvard, very--
like an ooh would help
with the drama here.
But we have a very dramatic, nice
Halloween type view here as well.
So we have videos embedded as well.
And suffice it to say there's
ways to embed YouTube videos
or Vimeo or other services as
well using yet more tags too.
But the web is, of course,
all about hyperlink,
hypertext markup language,
where you click on something
and you end up somewhere else.
And this is how the web is
so powerfully interconnected.
So how do we start creating links from
one website or web page to another?
Either that I made or someone else.
Well, let me go ahead and open
back up my terminal window.
And let's create a file
called link.html just
to demonstrate what you
and I know as a link.
I'll hide my terminal window now.
Let me copy paste just to
save myself some keystrokes.
And let me get rid of the video
tag so we can focus now on links.
Suppose that I want you to
visit Harvard virtually.
Well, I could say something
like visit Harvard, period.
This is uninteresting because
it's just going to be text.
I probably want you to actually visit
harvard.edu instead more specifically.
And I'll lowercase it just
to be consistent with what
browsers do in the address bar.
All right, let me go now
back to this video tab
and go back where we now see my index.
I'll zoom back in and there's link.html.
Unfortunately when I click
this, and I'll zoom in,
you literally just see
the text that I wrote.
And yet on every social
media platform nowadays,
except like Instagram, when you
type a URL or what looks like a URL,
even if you didn't bother
with the HTTP or HTTPS,
it usually automatically links it
for you on Facebook, on Twitter,
and other sites as well.
That's just a convenience.
Discord and Slack do that too.
But they're just doing it to
make things more user friendly.
But they have to generate HTML with
the proper tags and attributes.
So to get this to actually
work, it's not even good enough
to say https://www.harvard.edu.
Because if I go back now
and reload now, you'll
literally just see all of that as text.
If you want the browser to treat this as
a link, you need to use the anchor tag.
It'd be great if it were called
the link tag, but it's not.
It's called the anchor
tag or A for short.
And the way you reference the URL
to which you want to lead the user
is via href for Hyper Reference.
This is one of the earliest tags,
perhaps among the most arcane now.
But if I then put that whole
URL in quotes and close my tag,
I now have an opportunity to finish
my thought in between the start
tag and the end tag for this anchor.
And what I put in between
the start and end tag
is whatever the human's going to see.
So here I can say Harvard.
I can go back to my other tab.
I can reload the page and now you
see the familiar blue underline.
This now is an actual link.
And if I click it, I'll be whisked
away to the actual Harvard website.
But there's a risk here.
Can anyone imagine pretty simply after,
what, 60 seconds of the anchor tag,
how could someone, an adversary
misuse this tag alone?
How could a website run
by an adversary, how could
a spammer misuse this tag do you think?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Could you have
it say, like, Visit Yale?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, absolutely.
You could have it say one
thing but lead elsewhere.
So I could say Yale in here.
Nothing's stopping me as the developer.
Go back to the page.
Reload.
Now it says visit Yale.
You click on Yale, and voila, you end
up applying to the wrong place instead.
Now, there's some hints of this.
I could hover over this.
And super small.
Like this isn't very good for
your anti-hacking techniques.
But way down here, you can actually
see the URL that it's going to go to.
And most browsers indeed do this,
at least on desktops and laptops.
So it's a little bit of a hint.
But what you're seeing here, even
though this is kind of a silly playful
example, this is exactly how phishing
attacks work, P-H-I-S-H-I-N-G work,
whereby an adversarially tells you
to log into your PayPal account.
But it doesn't go to paypal.com.
It goes to some other
random website that they
bought and built that then tries to
collect your username and password
and store it in their database.
So now they can log into
your PayPal account as you.
And it boils down to
that simple primitive.
And you can be even
more manipulative too.
You can even say the whole URL
for Yale, like yale.edu or worse,
https://www.yale.edu and reload that.
And now, I mean, who among
you and people in your lives
are necessarily going to be so
paranoid as to not just blindly click
on that URL?
This is why just being a defensive
real world person nowadays
digitally is just ever
more so important.
So these same things that can be
used for good or benign use cases
can also be used for ill purposes too.
And it is literally that simple.
Questions now on any
of these tags thus far?
Just a few more to offer up.
Any questions on this here?
No?
Well, let me open up a couple that
I brought in advance just so we
don't have to type all of them here.
If you, for instance, have a web
page that's got quite a bit of code,
let me go ahead grab from the website
a couple of examples real fast here.
Namely one that will
call how about meta.html.
And in this example here, give me
just a moment to full screen it,
we're going to have a file.
So code meta.html.
I'll open this up next.
No relationship to what we
now know as Meta the company.
But rather this is going
to be a page that I
copied and pasted the same chunk
of Latin-like text from earlier.
So it's going to be a really
big paragraph of text.
And this is an example where if
you were to open this web page, not
on my own Mac or your
PC but on your phone,
the font might actually be really
annoying and difficult to read.
Why?
Because your phone is going to
try to squeeze all of the content
onto the tiny viewport, the rectangular
region of your phone instead.
So it turns out there are
ways, pretty easy ways,
to make your website mobile friendly
as well, otherwise known technically
as responsive.
And the easiest way to do this is to
include this tag here, a meta tag.
Again, no relationship to Facebook.
This has been here much longer.
And in this case here, this meta tag on
line five has its own sort of approach
to key value pairs.
This is a good example
of where it'd be nice
if it looked just like everything else,
but this is what we have historically.
You can have a meta tag
with an attribute called
name that refers to the name
of some feature of the browser.
In this case, viewport is the technical
term for the big rectangular region
to which I keep referring.
The body, really, of your page.
The content for the viewport, you can
say some esoteric details like this.
The initial scale should be one.
That is no matter who visits your
site, it shouldn't start zoomed in.
It shouldn't start zoomed out.
It should start at just
the default sizing.
And then this here, width
equals device width,
is a very arcane way of saying
if the user has a small screen,
show the text proportional to that size.
Don't just try to cram it all
into a tiny little window.
So it's super simple.
But if for the next problem
set or future projects
as well you find that just things look
really bad on mobile, this kind of tag
is the place to start, meta.
There aren't terribly many
of these that you'll use,
but they're useful for
other mechanisms as well.
In fact, let me go ahead and semi
secretly pull up one other example
as well whereby I'm going
to grab another example that
uses more of these tags.
And in just a moment,
I'll reveal it here.
Give me just one second here.
I'll propose that in
this example of meta,
we now add these properties instead.
So I copy pasted this
from an existing file
just so as to not waste time
typing all of these out.
If you've ever shared a
URL on Facebook or Twitter
or Slack or Discord or any
number of websites nowadays
that automatically show a nice
preview where you suddenly
see the default image of the page,
maybe a few sentences or words
of text or something like that.
Sometimes those
applications, those websites,
will just choose the
first image it finds
on the website or the first
sentence it sees and show that.
But that might not be very user
friendly or search engine friendly.
And so a developer might
want to control what
it is that Slack, Discord, Facebook,
Twitter, and other such sites
show by default.
For that you can use nowadays what are
called open graph tags, which is to say
there's other uses of the meta tag.
And you just look these things up.
Even I had to look this up to
remember what the key value pairs are.
The meta tag can also have
a property attribute that
can be these very specific strings.
OG title, OG description,
OG image, which
denotes Open Graph, which
again, is this standard that's
evolved in recent years.
And what you can do
here is tell browsers
and in turn servers what you
want them to show as the default
title of the page, the description of
the page, and even the default image
just so you can exercise more control
when sharing things socially nowadays
as well.
Again, it just boils down
to these key value pairs.
This is absolutely the kind of thing
you look up as needed to cross check.
But those capabilities are there.
And so literally the next time you
paste a link into Slack or Discord
or any online site that then
displays it in embedded fashion, just
know that all this time a little bit
of textual code like this in HTML
has been there by whoever
authored the site.
All right.
Let's do one final example in HTML alone
before we transition to just cleaning
up the aesthetics and improving
the visuals of everything
we've been creating.
Let me go ahead here
and close meta.html.
Let me code up a new file
called how about search.html
and see if we can't
draw some inspiration
from our cursory understanding
earlier of how URLs work to see
if we can't reinvent google.com itself.
So recall that a canonical
URL might look like this here.
And in particular, if you want to
pass in user input to that URL,
again, you can potentially
have a question mark
and then a key equals value pair.
Or for that matter, you can
even have multiple key value
pairs that by convention
are separated by ampersands.
These things are everywhere.
Later today when you pull up
almost any website in your browser,
look at the URL and you'll
just see a lot of this.
A lot of noise too and distractions.
But there's going to be
some equal signs most likely
and/or some ampersands as well.
And those are just
separating key value pairs.
Now, what can I do here?
Well, if you think back to how we
manually searched for cats earlier,
let me quickly do this.
I'll do this one manually.
Doc type HTML as my very first line.
HTML tag with how about my lang
attribute for English up here.
And then inside of this,
I'll have a head tag.
Inside of this, I'll have a title.
I'll call this example search.
And then down here I'll have
my beginning of the body tag.
And now let me introduce you
to really a final tag for now,
a form tag, which will create a
web form, the thing with text boxes
and buttons that you and I use
every day on any number of websites.
Inside of this form, I'm going
to have an input like a text box
whose name is going to be
q for query, because I'm
trying to reimplement Google here.
The type of that I
want to be a text box.
Or if I know I'm using
this for search, I
can actually change
this to a search box.
And it's going to let me-- it's going
to generally put a little x there
so you can clear it quickly.
That's a nice little
enhancement as well.
And then I'm going to give myself
a Submit button by doing input--
whoops.
I'm going to give myself a Submit button
by doing input type equals submit.
And then I'll leave that as such here.
All right.
Now I need to do a little bit more.
But let's see how this looks.
Let me go over to my other tab.
Let me go back to my index.
And if I zoom out, there is search.html.
I'll click it and there's not much
going on here, even if I zoom in.
But I do indeed have a really
big text box and a Submit button.
But I haven't in my HTML
told anyone anywhere
that I want this input, whether I
type cat or dog, to go to google.com.
So for that, I need a
couple of more attributes.
And I know this from
having done this before.
And any online reference
will say the same.
You can add an action attribute.
Like what do you want the
action of this form to be?
And you can put the URL to which
you want this form to be submitted.
And I know from tinkering that it
should be https://www.google.com/search.
I don't need to put any
question marks here myself.
But I do want the browser
to do that for me.
So let me go back to my other tab.
Let me reload.
And nothing visually has happened.
But watch this.
When I now type in cats
but before I hit Enter,
notice that I'm currently
at some long crazy URL slash
search.html as expected.
If I now go down to the Submit
button and click Submit,
watch what happens to the
URL and the page itself.
I'm whisked away to
the actual google.com.
And indeed, there are those same cats.
And if I zoom in here, you'll see
that my URL has changed to be indeed
/search?q=cats.
So this is just how web forms work.
When you submit any form
on the web in this way,
the browser automatically goes to
that action URL, adds a question mark,
puts any key value pairs that you
manually typed into the text boxes,
and lets the server do its thing.
Now here's where Chrome is
starting to simplify things.
Safari does this too.
If you double click on your
URL, now you see the full URL.
But if any parts are
missing, that's just
a UI thing to eliminate
visual distractions nowadays.
Meanwhile, if I go back to my own form,
if I search this time for dogs and hit
Enter, now again, the
URL changes to be q=dogs.
And it all reduces to this basic
building block of using a form tag.
Now I can be more explicit.
If I know I want to use get,
which is actually the default,
I can literally say quote
unquote "get" in all lowercase,
even though the verb earlier
was by design in uppercase.
But here now, I'm just
being ever more explicit.
If I don't want the label of this
button to be very generically Submit,
maybe I want it to be "Google
Search," quote unquote.
Well, if you read the
documentation for forms,
you can actually change
the value of the button
to be quote unquote "Google Search."
And if I now go back here and
reload, I get a fresh form.
And now I get a button that
literally says Google Search.
And if I tinker with this further,
because this isn't very user friendly,
there's even more attributes I can do.
I can add on my search
input a autocomplete
equals off if I don't want to see
my own history for whatever reason.
I don't want people knowing
I'm searching for cats and dogs
on this page.
I can auto focus on
the text box so that it
shows the cursor blinking
in that box by default.
And I can even do something like this.
I can have a placeholder attribute
that says something like query
or some other
documentation for the user.
And if I now go back and reload,
you'll see notice it says query
and it's subtle, but my cursor
is already positioned there.
It gave it focus.
And I can type cats now without
having to click in the box manually,
which is just marginally better
for the user's experience.
Any questions now on all of this here?
Any questions?
All right.
That too was a lot.
Why don't we take a
casual five minute break?
And when we resume, we'll take a
look at CSS, add in some JavaScript,
and then wrap up.
So five minutes only for now.
All right.
We are back.
So that's technically it for HTML.
Here on out, it'll be up to
online resources and references
we point you to just to fill in
your vocabulary for more tags
and attributes.
But conceptually, that's it.
There's attributes, there are
tags, and there are attributes,
and the rest of it really is just kind
of a laundry list of possible features.
But it turns out too
you'll see over time
that you can even see
the HTML for websites.
So for instance, if I go over to
harvard.edu in my browser, which
I'll go ahead in just a
moment here and do here,
and do https://www.harvard.edu/
Enter, it again
will pull up today's version
of Harvard's website.
And if I right click or Control
click on it again and go to Inspect,
you'll see those so
called developer tools.
And earlier we focused
on the Network tab
just so we could see
the HTTP stuff going on.
But what I glossed over earlier
was the so called Elements
tab, which actually shows you
the HTML underlying any web
page on the internet.
And so for instance, here
is the underlying HTML
for Harvard's homepage as of right now.
And aesthetically, some
of it's been collapsed.
So if I click on these
various triangles,
I'll see what's actually inside of.
That is the children of
some of these HTML tags.
But here on out if
you're ever curious as
to how a web page made
some feature visually,
you can just literally
use these developer tools
built into your own browser just to see
what the web developer actually did.
And you can do things too like this.
Like if you really
like maybe, let's see,
if you really like this menu in the top
right hand corner of Harvard's website,
you can even right click that or
Control click that specifically, choose
Inspect, and what browsers will do
is jump to the HTML corresponding
to that visual element on the page.
And here you can see that we've
not talked about this tag before.
There's a button tag,
there's an ID attribute,
and there's some other attributes
as well that define that button.
You can do other things
too in the web page.
Let me scroll down, for instance, here.
And actually, let's go to another one,
like yale.edu here in today's theme.
And suppose we want to do something like
change the aesthetics of this website.
Well, how about this?
Over here, Life At Yale.
Let's right click on this.
Choose Inspect.
That's going to jump to
that part of the page.
And notice what you can do
here in this Elements tab.
We can be a little
playful in return today.
Life At Harvard.
And voila, we've now changed
Yale's website, it would seem.
So have we really?
Hopefully hacking is
not actually this easy.
What did we actually do based
on today's mental model?
I have changed the page, but.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I've just
changed how it is for me.
Because my browser, just like with
Phyllis and Brian from the get go,
requested Yale's web page.
I got back a virtual envelope containing
that HTML, as we've now called it.
My browser has a local copy.
It's got its own tree, otherwise
known as a DOM, Document Object Model,
built up in its memory.
And yeah, I went to town
and changed my copy of it.
But of course, hopefully, I've
not changed the actual server.
And in fact, if I reload
Yale's website now,
hopefully it will revert back to,
indeed, what it should be instead.
Life At Yale.
But this ability in your own browser, be
it Chrome or Firefox or Edge or Safari,
to have these built in developer
tools are very powerful,
because it's going to enable
you to not only diagnose
problems that will invariably arise in
the coming weeks with your own code,
but it's also going to allow
you to learn from other sites
how you can do things
and tinker as well.
But up until now, we've focused
only on tags and attributes
and on the structure of a web page.
Let's now focus more on the
aesthetics and fine tuning that.
It turns out that HTML
has very limited support
for anything aesthetic like font
sizes and colors and so forth.
And in recent years, people have
used necessarily a second language
called CSS.
Not a programming language.
Again, a markup language,
if you will, to just fine
tune the aesthetics of a page.
Font sizes, colors,
margins, and all of that.
So CSS is going to allow us to
define a whole bunch of properties,
which is just another group of people's
terminology for key value pairs.
Indeed, ever since week five, key value
pairs are everywhere in the world,
not just at Sweetgreen and
restaurants, but indeed
under inline code and languages
and technologies like these.
So properties is the new word
in CSS for what a moment ago we
called attributes in HTML.
But it's the same idea,
just different vocabulary
that you get used to over time.
A few phrases I might use now and you'll
hear in the coming days would be these.
Type selector, class
selector, ID selector,
attribute selector, which just
refer to different techniques we're
about to see that are going
to allow you to control more
precisely the aesthetics of
specific things on the page.
And the way we're going
to do this is we're
going to take our basic
HTML, like we saw earlier,
and we're going to introduce in the next
few minutes just a couple of more tags
and/or attributes.
One, we're going to introduce you to
a tag called style, which nicely named
allows you to control the
style, the aesthetics,
the visuals of the web page.
Or we're going to
introduce you to a link
tag, which very confusingly does not
give you a link that you can click on.
It just links to another file that
then gets automatically included
or imported, to borrow our
language from C or in Python.
But same idea.
This will allow us to
include secondary files.
And we're going to ultimately show
you how you can leverage third party
frameworks, libraries
that other people wrote,
so as to not get stuck in the weeds
of all the fine tuning of aesthetics
and just make pretty things fast so you
can focus really on the intellectually
interesting part, if that's your choice,
of building the content, the site out,
the application out yourself.
All right, so with that said,
let me go back to VS Code here.
And let me go ahead and create a
simple example called home.html.
A very simple home page for
John Harvard, for instance.
Let me give myself three paragraphs
initially, the first of which
is just going to have the person's name.
The second paragraph is going to say
something like welcome to my home page
to greet visitors.
And the third is going to be
a little footer like copyright
how about John Harvard 1636
or something like that.
All right, let me go back
to my other tab as before.
Reload my index.
There's my new file.
Home.html and I'll click that.
And you'll see, OK, I mean, this
is sort of 1636 style web page.
Super simple, all text, nothing
really interesting going on there.
But we can start to style
it a little differently.
If the title of the page is
John Harvard and then it's
welcome to my home page and
then this less important footer,
why don't we have the text be
large, then medium, then small?
So something arbitrary
but a little more nuanced.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
And in my home.html file, let me
introduce not yet the style tag
but what I'm going to call
temporarily the style attribute.
Both indeed exist.
This one's simpler and
it's going to be correct,
but we'll see in a moment not
as well designed, arguably,
as is often our narrative.
So inside of the style tag, you
can put this language called CSS.
Key value pairs, otherwise
known as properties.
The only way you know what
properties exist, what keys exist,
is by taking a class, reading a
book, looking at an online reference.
And we're going to give you just
a sampling of what's out there.
So suppose I want to control the
font size of this first paragraph.
I can literally say font-size in all
lowercase, colon, and then a word
like large.
Or I can specify 12 point
or 18 point or something
more precise like from Google
Docs or Microsoft Word.
And suppose I want to make
this text down here medium.
Well, I'll do quote unquote
font size colon medium.
And down here or I'll do
style equals font-size small.
So I'm going to start with just
these three key value pairs.
Same key but different values.
I'll go back to my page and
in a moment I'll reload,
and it's going to be somewhat subtle.
But watch how the font size
do change when I reload now.
All right.
So I've got a little bigger.
Middle one is about the same, and
the last one is a little smaller.
What if I want to center it?
Just like many web pages have
the text like this centered.
Well, I can separate these key
value pairs with semicolons.
And I'm sorry, semicolons are
kind of sort of back with CSS.
But I can do text-align:center.
Strictly speaking, I don't
need the last semicolon
if there's no more key value pairs,
but I'll just do it to be consistent.
Text-align:center.
And then down here after another
semicolon, text-align:center.
All right, let's go back, reload.
Now it's going to be much
more obvious the change.
And we now have the
beginnings of a homepage.
Still pretty basic, but at least
it's a little more interesting.
Turns out we can do a little
better with the copyright symbol.
Like most computers actually have
support for a circle with a C in it.
But you can't just do
that with text like this.
There's different ways to do this.
You could copy paste it from
a website that already has it
so you don't have to figure out the
magical keystroke on your Mac or PC.
But there's also in HTML
what are called entities.
And you can actually specify
using hexadecimal or decimal codes
numbers like this, hash 169
semicolon after an ampersand.
And this is a special
symbol that you can look up
in any online reference
for special characters
that are hard or impossible to
type manually at your keyboard.
And this, let me zoom
in just so it's obvious,
if I reload now instead of being
two parentheses and a C character,
now it's a proper copyright symbol.
So you'll see these out there.
They're not necessarily that
frequently used nowadays,
but it's good to know that they exist.
But let me go back now to my code
and propose that while correct,
this is arguably not very well designed.
And even if you've never seen
HTML, never seen CSS before,
what instinct might you have
for why this is poorly designed?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: There's repetition.
In general in the past
several weeks, C, Python, SQL,
repetition generally bad and sloppy
and it's not going to scale well.
So the repetition I think
you're probably alluding to
is text align center, text
align center, text align center.
Well, we can factor that out in CSS.
The C in CSS means Cascading.
And this means that if
you move some properties
to a parent or a grandparent,
the children or grandchildren
will inherit those properties.
That is, they will cascade down
the family tree, so to speak.
And so let me go ahead
and remove all of these,
since I claim they're indeed redundant.
And let me preserve just one of
them by, well, let me do this.
It's not quite right to put a
paragraph inside of a paragraph.
That's just not a thing in English
writing or in writing more generally.
So I'm going to do one thing first.
It turns out that these two
are arguably not paragraphs.
This is like a header, the
body, the essence of the page,
and then the footer.
So if a paragraph isn't quite
the right English semantics,
you can actually use
more generically a tag
that's all over the internet called
div for division of the page.
And this is just a very generic
term for a big rectangular region
that divides the page again
and again, just so that you
can think about different regions.
Now that I have div, which really
has no more meaning than that.
It's a division of the page.
Interpret as you will.
Now I can have multiple ones of these.
And let me go ahead and
open a div tag here.
Let me close a new div tag here.
And then just to keep
everything tidy, I'm
going to highlight everything
in between and hit Tab.
And that just automatically
indents everything for me.
Now I have three divs inside of
another div, and that's totally fine.
This is very commonly done.
Now I'm going to do this.
Style equals quote unquote text
align colon center semicolon or not.
And now I have some
cascading capabilities.
Now the parent of those three children,
John harvard, welcome to my home page,
and the copyright will now
all inherit that property.
So when I hit reload, nothing
aesthetically has changed.
Whoops, sorry.
I should have done
reload slightly earlier.
When you use a div
instead of a paragraph,
it actually gets rid of the
space between those paragraphs.
It just sandwiches them
a little closer together.
I can fix this in another way.
But that aside, everything
is still centered
and the text is still
large, medium, and small.
But I should have called out that
change in the paragraph spacing.
But we could bring that back
before long if we wanted.
Now, what more could I
do to maybe improve this?
Well, strictly speaking, I don't
really need that parent div
because these three divs
inside already had a parent.
So let me actually get rid of that
new div just to undo what I did.
I'll highlight this.
And if you haven't seen
this trick, Shift Tab
will unindent nicely,
which is perhaps helpful.
I could just put that text
align center on the body tag.
So text align colon
center quote unquote.
This too would work as well so long
as you go up the family tree, so
to speak, reload, and now indeed
there's nothing aesthetically
that has changed this time.
But it turns out nowadays the web is
getting a little more sophisticated.
And even though you will see so
many examples online, in tutorials,
in books using div, div,
div all over the place,
there are newer semantic tags.
Semantic just means
they have more meaning
than this generic notion of a division.
And if you look up a
documentation for HTML,
you'll see that if you want to have
a header on a page, not a heading
like H1, H2 but a header, there's
literally nowadays a header tag.
And this is marginally better
because it now says what it is.
Search engines like Google
and Bing can detect, oh,
that's the header of the page.
Maybe we should use this and give it
more prominence in the search results.
You can then have a
main part of the page.
So literally a tag called main nowadays.
You can literally have
a footer of the page.
And again, these are often
useful for screen readers
to help recite things verbally
for folks who might otherwise not
be able to read them.
And probably the screen readers might
highlight the header and the main part
but maybe might not
spend time for the user
on the footer, which is arguably a
little less important semantically
usually.
Or search engines,
again, now know what's
the header, what's the footer,
what's the main part of the page.
So they know what to search and analyze.
So this would arguably be a
better design nowadays as well.
But what else remains as a problem?
Well, this is now getting a little bit
more subtle and takes some experience.
But this practice of putting HTML
and CSS all in the same file,
it's a little sloppy.
Why?
Because it means I'm comingling my
data with the presentation thereof.
The juicy stuff I care about,
like John Harvard and the phrase
welcome to my home page,
and all of the aesthetics
that I might want to change over time.
And honestly, because everything
is currently in one big file,
it's going to make it really
hard for me to collaborate
with a classmate or a colleague at work.
So that maybe I do the
HTML, they do the CSS.
Uh-uh, not if you're all
working in the same file.
It would be a nightmare.
Even if you use a VS Code
sharing feature like Google Docs
and both are typing at the same time,
you're going to mess up somehow.
It'd be nice if we could
separate these two languages.
Well, one way to do that
would be as follows.
Let me get rid of all of the style tags.
Sorry, style attributes
that I've added up until now
on all four now of these tags.
And let me introduce the style tag that
we saw on the slide earlier instead.
I'm going to go up here into
the head of the page, which
is where technically these style
tags must go so that they're already
loaded into memory before the body
is even analyzed by the browser.
And inside of the
style tag, I'm actually
going to select the HTML elements
that I want to stylize, if you will.
So if I want to change
the body's aesthetics,
I'm going to literally type
the name of that tag body.
And then, I'm sorry,
curly braces are back also
from C. Inside of these curly braces,
I'm going to put text align center.
So the key value pairs are the same.
The only new thing I've done is
I've moved some of the syntax
up to this new style tag in the head.
If I want to now control
the header tag as well,
I can use the same curly braces.
This is convention to put the open
curly brace on the same line, the closed
curly brace on another.
The browser doesn't really care, but
this is a common CSS style convention.
I'm going to do font
size large semicolon.
Then for the main tag, I'm
going to do font size medium.
And then for the footer tag,
I'm going to do font size small.
So same exact thing.
And it's admittedly a
little bit more verbose.
It's taking up more lines of code.
It doesn't all quite fit on the screen.
But if you scroll back down now,
and you'll acquire an eye for this,
this is just better.
It's just more compact.
It's more readable.
The content, the data jumps out,
and there's no visual distractions
like the CSS properties as before.
Upside here too is that we
don't actually need to--
this doesn't actually
change the aesthetics.
If I reload the same page,
it still looks the same.
But I've taken a step toward
some slightly better design.
But let me propose that there's
other ways to do this too.
We just selected things
by way of their type.
So that was a so called type
selector when I literally just
specified the type of tag.
Body, header, main, footer.
But there's other ways that
now we can lay the foundation
for making reusable CSS that you
and colleagues and classmates
can use and reuse in multiple files
and even in multiple projects.
So let me actually go ahead and do this.
Instead of just very explicitly
saying I want the body to be centered,
let me invent an adjective, if you will,
and let me change this to .centered.
And this new vocabulary word, centered,
will literally mean text align center.
Let me go ahead here and I'm just going
to create a new adjective called large,
a new adjective called medium,
and a new adjective called small.
They are deliberately consistent
with what the properties do.
But these are now my
own vocabulary words.
And they are called classes.
So a class is just a collection of key
value pairs, a collection of properties
that you get to invent for yourself.
And what it lets you do now is this.
Now if I want the whole body to
be centered, I can add this tag,
which we actually saw briefly
in Yale's HTML, class=center.
Down here in the header if I want this
to be large, I can say class="large".
Down here on main, I
can say class="medium".
And down here I can have class="small".
Now, I have taken one step backward
by re-adding some of the aesthetics
to the page.
But it's not the actual properties.
It's not the key value pairs.
It's now more semantically
nice, because now
I just know from reading the HTML what
these things are going to look like,
whereas the implementation details
for all four of those adjectives
is now relegated up above.
And these are literally my words.
I could change it to
.foo and use class="foo"
but obviously that would not be the
best choice of words in this case.
All right.
Any questions on this?
This now is what we would call a class
selector by using literally the dot,
even though the dot does
not appear elsewhere,
but dot means this is a class.
These are not always the best syntactic
design decisions that the world makes.
All right.
Well, one last trick then.
Notice that this is a little
annoying that I'm still
working in the same file.
And if my classmate wants
to clean up my aesthetics,
make my homepage look way better, if
my colleague wants to do the same,
wouldn't it be nice if we could
actually move all of this code
to a different file like a Python
library or a C header file?
Well, you can.
Let me go ahead and delete
that whole style tag.
Let me add a confusingly named link tag,
the href of which let's call a new file
styles.css.
And let's say that the relationship
of that file is that of stylesheet.
So this is a term of art in
the world of web development.
A stylesheet is a text
file that contains
lots of styles, lots of CSS properties.
Let me open my terminal real fast.
And let me do code of styles.css.
Enter.
And in this file, I'm going to paste
all of those same lines as earlier.
But now they're in a separate file.
And indeed, if I hide my terminal window
and I give this file to a colleague,
they can now work on the
aesthetics of the page
and make things a lot
prettier than this, maybe use
specific font sizes, maybe
add colors and the like.
Whereas I can focus entirely on
the HTML, because this file now
will reference that other.
And if I go back to my
other tab and reload,
the content's going to
be exactly the same,
but now I'm using some
separate file instead.
Any questions now about
these techniques here?
No?
All right, so with that said,
let me show just one example now
of what I called a
moment ago frameworks.
And this is where web
development gets kind of fun,
at least if you like
this, especially if you
like the sort of logical design,
the presentation of information
you care about, but
you really don't want
to struggle with font sizes and colors
and getting everything pixel perfect,
so to speak.
Let me propose that I open up here an
example in just a moment in VS Code
that I prepared in advance.
And this one is going
to be an opportunity
to consider how you might take
some of the data from last week,
wherein we collected
everyone's favorites,
and lay it out in a
really big HTML table.
So I wrote this out in advance
because it was a huge amount of data,
but it's the same data from
the Google Form from last week.
And you'll see already the hints
of a table tag and these TRs.
And I added a few other
tags for aesthetics.
It turns out when you have a
more visually interesting header
for your table, there's
another tag called thead.
There's another tag called tbody.
These are not all that
intellectually interesting.
I just read the documentation and
realized, oh, to make things prettier
I need a thead, a tbody, and so forth.
But what's interesting here
is that if I go to my index
here and open this file
called favorites.html,
here's all of the data from
last week's Google spreadsheet,
which we exported as CSV and I manually
before class converted to just HTML.
It's indeed a table, but
it's really not pretty.
The columns are really close together.
It's kind of hard to distinguish
one row from another.
But this is just raw HTML written by me.
Now, I could use CSS and
some of the tricks we just
saw to maybe change font size.
There's ways to change color, background
color, and a lot of things like that.
But honestly, surely
other people in the world
have presented tabular
data in pretty ways.
I've been to many websites that
have prettier tables than mine.
Can I maybe use someone else's
framework, someone else's CSS
included in my page but don't
stand on their shoulders
and just make my stuff look prettier?
Well, I dare say I can.
Let me go ahead here and semi
secretly open up VS Code again.
And let me grab a slightly
different version of favorites.html
that I also opened in advance wherein
I add this line of code instead.
Give me just a moment to
foreground this version.
And the data is all the same as before,
but I've added one of these link tags.
And I'm not linking
to my own styles.css.
I'm using a popular
library called bootstrap.
And bootstrap is just one
of many popular libraries
out there, free at that, that
has a whole bunch of CSS files
and soon JavaScript files that you can
just use for free in your own projects,
personally or professionally,
that just make things look
and behave better without you
having to reinvent wheels.
Now, to access their CSS, I
had to read their documentation
and grab this very long URL here.
But it's the same idea.
Link href equals quote
unquote something.
And I read their documentation
and they told me to add this.
They told me that if I want
my tables to be prettier,
I have to add a class
attribute to my own table tag
and specify, a little weirdly but
this is what bootstrap told me to do,
a class called table.
And that will make it a
prettier bootstrap table.
And if I want to stripe it, like every
other row is gray instead of white
just to make it pop a
little more visually,
I can also add a second class separated
by a space called table striped.
That's all I did.
I added line five and I changed
line nine and that is it.
The rest of the hundreds of lines
in favorites.html are the same.
But if I go back here now and reload
the browser, now thanks to bootstrap,
voila.
It's much prettier.
Now I can zoom out and that changes
the font size just locally for me.
And even if you don't love
their aesthetics, I mean,
this is easily better than my own there.
And it turns out we can do even better
by adding interactivity to this too.
But to do that, we're going to
need one final language for today.
And this one is an actual
programming language.
And we won't use it
all that much in CS50,
but we introduce it here as we
begin web stuff because there's just
so many free libraries and professional
libraries that you can use just
to make your web applications
fancier and more interactive.
Mobile applications as well increasingly
use HTML, CSS, and JavaScript
to power our iPhones and
Android devices as well.
So a quick tour of some
syntax and then we'll
conclude with just some
hopefully inspiring examples
to give you a taste of
what JavaScript can do.
So JavaScript supports conditionals,
just like C and Python before it.
If we rewind to our Scratch days,
here of course is a conditional.
Here is the corresponding
JavaScript code as of today.
It's pretty much identical
to C with this syntax here.
If we had an if else, in
Scratch it looked like this.
In JavaScript, it's going
to look like this instead.
So it's a bit of a
regression vis a vis Python.
The parentheses are back.
The curly braces are back.
The semicolons I mentioned in CSS are
also back in JavaScript potentially.
But it's familiar is the point here.
And it's a different language
that's frequently used for the web,
whereas you can't use Python in the
way we're about to use JavaScript.
It just wasn't designed
for that purpose.
Meanwhile, if you have an
if else if else in Scratch,
well in JavaScript just like in C,
it's going to look like this instead.
Variables in JavaScript,
of course, are a thing too.
And in Scratch, we might have
initialized a counter variable to 0.
In JavaScript a few
different ways to do this.
And just for now, the keyword is let's.
It's sort of a polite way
of asking for a variable.
Let counter equals 0 semicolon.
So you don't mention the type,
but you do use a keyword here
in this case called let.
If you want to increment counter by
one, few different ways in JavaScript
you can do this.
Just like in C, in
JavaScript you can do this.
Just like in C and in Python, in
JavaScript you can also get this.
So plus plus is back.
So maybe that counterbalances
the other syntax as well.
That was not the case in Python.
Loops are back, of
course, in JavaScript.
Whereas in Scratch you
could repeat three times
like this, in JavaScript
it's pretty much just like C.
The only difference here
is that you say let instead
of int for an example like this.
Meanwhile, if you want
to do something forever
in Scratch, in JavaScript just like
in C, you say while true in this case.
So this is to say we're
sort of comfortable
spending relatively little
time on JavaScript, at least
for today's purposes,
because syntactically it's
really the same as we've seen before
with maybe a slight variance here
or there.
But what's interesting today
arguably is just what kinds of things
you can do with it.
So with that said, what
kinds of things can we do?
It all comes back to this picture.
If this is a simple web
page on the left and this
is the corresponding tree
or DOM, Document Object
Model on the right, that is the tree the
browser automatically creates in memory
or RAM for you, JavaScript is
now a proper programming language
that lets us dynamically manipulate,
like read data from this, change this.
And this is how Google, for
instance, implements your inbox.
They might have in your
inbox it's like a table.
So TR, TR, TR, TR, probably
something like that.
Or heck, maybe div, div, div.
Using JavaScript, any time they
realize someone sent you new mail,
they can create a new node, a new
rectangle in memory and you, the human,
see a new div or a new TR
again and again and again.
So with JavaScript, you
just have the ability
to control the user's experience instead
of, like I've been doing, constantly
hitting reload in the page to see some
new content, to see some new content.
JavaScript can be running
24/7 so that you can actually
see all of these changes live.
All right.
So let's go about writing
some JavaScript code now.
Instead of writing it on the server
and executing it on the server,
we're going to actually
use a very common paradigm
whereas JavaScript is actually
executed in the browser client side.
That is to say we can actually start
writing some JavaScript code inside
of our own .html file so that when
a user visits that web page with
their browser, not only is the
HTML and any CSS downloaded
to the user's browser, so is that
JavaScript code so that it's executed
indeed client side on the
browser rather than server side,
as has been the case with
Python in previous weeks.
Well, where do we go about
writing some JavaScript code?
Let's go ahead and revisit
hello.html, which previously
was a completely static example
that literally just said
hello title, hello body.
Indeed, if I open this
up using HTTP server
and view it now in a separate
tab, all it said was exactly that.
Hello title in the tab and hello body
in the main part of the viewport,
so to speak.
Well, let's make this
example a little more
dynamic so it doesn't
just say hello body
but maybe says hello
to an actual person.
So let's go ahead and do this.
Let's go ahead and remove
the hardcoded hello body.
And let's actually go ahead
here and use a form tag.
But we're not going to use
this form in the usual way
whereby the data gets sent all
the way back to the server.
We're going to leverage control
over this form client side instead.
So I'm going to go ahead and create
this open form tag, close form tag.
Inside of that, let me give myself
a text input that's going to have
autocomplete="off" just to ensure that
what I previously type in my examples
doesn't reappear accidentally.
We're going to auto focus it
so that the cursor is blinking
right there in that text box.
And this time I'm going to
go ahead and give it how
about a placeholder
of quote unquote name
to make clear that I'm prompting
the user for their name.
And then the type of this text box will
be the default or more explicitly here
text.
And then I'm going to
have, as we've seen before,
a button, the type of which is submit.
Also our typically default.
And then inside of this button
is going to be the label.
How about something like how
about we'll call this greet.
So that's what the
button will actually say.
Well, let me actually go
back into my browser tab.
Let me reload this page.
And we should now see a
relatively simple form
whereby I have the
cursor blinking on a text
input prompting the user for
their name and then a greet button
that I can click.
But if I click this
button now, it's not going
to do anything useful because
I haven't written any code
to tell the browser what to
do when I click that button.
But it turns out there's all sorts
of events in the world of JavaScript
that you can listen for, so to speak.
In fact, here's just a
list of some of them.
Any time something changes in a
form field, any time the user clicks
or drags on something, any
time the user presses a key
and maybe lifts their finger up,
anytime the mouse goes down or over
or up on top of something, or
any time a form is submitted,
those are events in the
same way that we talked
about events back in week 0 in Scratch.
And in JavaScript, just like in
Scratch where you can do something
when green flag clicked,
in JavaScript you
can write code that actually listens
for any of these events or more.
So with that said, let's
go back to VS Code here
and let's make a couple
of changes instead.
Let's go ahead and add to
this form a new attribute.
That's not the best way to do
it, but it's perhaps the simplest
for version one here.
And let's say on submit,
do the following.
So on submit is an HTML attribute.
And curiously, its value
inside of the quotes
there can actually be
some JavaScript code.
And let's go ahead now and
let's assume there exists
a function in the world called greet.
And what I want to do is call that
function right then and there.
Well, now in JavaScript, how do I
go about making that function exist?
It doesn't come out of the box just
like print might or say might in Python
or scratch respectively.
But I can do this.
Let me go up into the head of this page.
Inside of a script tag
here, both open and close,
let me actually write
some JavaScript code.
And just so it stands out, I'm going
to give myself a couple of blank lines,
though not strictly necessary.
And let me define a new function
in JavaScript called greet.
And this is the syntax in JavaScript
for creating your own function.
Similar in Python instead of saying
def, in JavaScript you just say
function, then the name of the
function, and any arguments
within the parentheses thereafter.
But I'm not going to pass in any here.
Then inside of curly
braces, what I'm going to do
is use a built in
JavaScript function that
comes with any browser called alert.
It's not the best or
prettiest user interface,
but for now it's going
to get the job done.
What do I want to say to the user?
Well, let's first just say something
simple like hello comma world close
quote semicolon, thereby alerting
the user with precisely that message.
Now what I'm going to do down
here is make one other change.
I don't want this form to actually
get submitted to the server.
Just like we've seen in the
past when you submit a form,
it often goes to something
like google.com/search.
I actually want my JavaScript code
to take control over the entire user
experience of this form so that I'm
just using the form as a user input
mechanism, not to actually send via get
or post this data to some other server,
including my own.
So this is going to look a little ugly.
But after calling greet,
I'm actually going
to do this, which I've read
the documentation about
and I know that if you actually
hard code return false here,
that just tells the browser, please
don't actually submit the form.
Only call the greet function.
All right.
Well, let me go back to my browser here.
Let me reload this, because
I need to download the latest
version of the JavaScript code.
And I'm just going to go ahead
without even typing my name,
I'm going to click on the Greet button.
And you'll see that, albeit a
little cryptically at the top,
we see an alert that says hello world.
There's my ugly URL of my code
space there at the moment,
but we do indeed see that string.
But what I haven't, of course, done is
taken any actual name from the user.
So how can we go about doing that?
Well, ideally I want to alert the user
with hello comma David or hello comma
Carter, whatever name
I type into that box.
So how can I go about doing that?
Well, let me create a
variable called name.
And let me set it equal
to this function call.
Document.queryselector.
That comes with JavaScript itself.
Let me then in parentheses pass in
an argument that is going to be,
huh, the ID.
I need a unique identifier for
the thing I want to select.
So let me actually go
back to my HTML code here.
And instead of giving this form
field a name like q for query,
let me actually use another HTML
attribute called ID where now I
can call this anything I want.
And for clarity, I'm just going to
call this input element uniquely name.
Now up here in query
selector, just like in CSS
where you can use hashes
and dots and other symbology
in order to select certain nodes in your
DOM, that is rectangles in that memory
tree, well, I can go ahead
and select hash name, which,
again, is just the syntax for
uniquely selecting the element whose
ID is in this case name.
So you have the hash up here.
You don't need the hash as the value
of the attribute down here on line 20.
And now if I want to actually
get the value of that text box,
I literally just say .value.
So document refers to the
whole web page itself.
Query selector is a function that's
built into that object, so to speak.
And the value accessible via .value just
like a C struct or even a Python class
allows me to go inside of that text
field and get whatever the value
the user has typed in.
Now, as I've been able to do in
languages like Python fairly readily,
I can concatenate this name onto
the string hello comma space
so as to form a complete phrase.
And you'll notice here that I'm actually
using single quotes in my JavaScript,
double quotes in my HTML.
This is perhaps a common convention.
In JavaScript, the
language does not care
if you use double
quotes or single quotes,
but I dare say single
quotes are just more common.
And so that's what I've done here.
All right.
Now as always, I'm going
to cross my fingers.
Go back to this page.
I'm going to reload, because
I've changed the JavaScript
and I need my browser to download it.
And now I'm going to type in my
name for instance, D-A-V-I-D.
Click Greet with fingers crossed.
And voila, now I see hello comma David.
All right, so it turns out that while
functional, this isn't the best design.
And comingling your HTML
with your JavaScript code
as with this on submit attribute
isn't particularly clean.
It's better, as with CSS, to keep your
HTML over here, your CSS over here,
and your JavaScript now
over here, so to speak.
And better still perhaps
even in some separate files.
So how can I go about
changing this a little bit?
Well, let me go ahead and
actually let's go ahead
and delete all of this
code for just a moment.
And let me go and get rid of
this on submit handler down here
and really just distill my HTML only
into the HTML and the attributes
therefore.
And what I'm instead going
to do now is do this.
I can use JavaScript to achieve the
listening for that submit event or that
on submit event.
I don't need to actually
use HTML for that.
I can use JavaScript entirely.
So it turns out I can access some
other member of this document
by doing document.queryselector again.
But this time, let's
select the actual form tag.
And it doesn't have an ID
because it has no ID in its HTML.
But it does have a tag name.
So just like in CSS when you can
target elements by way of their name,
I'm just going to select the
one and only form on this page
by using that same
query selector function.
And now I'm going to use
another function that
just comes with JavaScript
in the context of browsers
whereby once you select
an element like that form,
I can call add event listener, which
is similar in spirit to Scratch's when
green flag clicked or
any block like that.
You can then tell the browser
what event you want to listen for.
I want to listen for the submit event.
So you don't say on submit here.
Now that we're in pure
JavaScript, you just say submit.
And now I can do something like this.
I can go ahead and say call
the following function.
And I'm not even going to bother
giving this function a name.
And that is allowed to in JavaScript,
as we saw briefly in Python.
And what I'm going to do
now inside of curly braces
after that keyword function is
the same kind of code as before.
I'm going to do let name
equals document.queryselector.
I'm going to select that same name
ID as before and get its value.
And then I'm going to do alert and then
pass in hello comma, a single quote
again after that.
Concatenate with that the
name and then semicolon.
But I need to do one other thing.
It turns out that this
function, and if you
read the documentation
for this technique,
actually takes automatically a special
argument called by convention event.
And this is just a variable, if you
will, that refers to whatever event
just happened.
In this case, it's of
course, going to be submit.
But in other contexts, it might be
a click event, a mouse down event,
or something else entirely.
So this allows me now to do
this, which is a little cryptic,
but you get used to these conventions.
I can use that event,
whatever it is, and then
prevent whatever the default behavior
is by calling a special function called
prevent Default with
a capital D. This is
the alternative to that
messier return false semicolon
that I had inside of my HTML before.
So all I've done here now is I've left
all of my HTML as pure HTML down here
and I've put all of my JavaScript
code as pure JavaScript up here.
This sort of separation
of concern similar to what
we started doing with CSS just a bit
ago in order to keep those two languages
separate too.
Well, let me go back to my browser here.
Reload the page.
And unfortunately, there's a
subtle mistake I've made here.
Let me go ahead and type in
D-A-V-I-D and click Greet.
And unfortunately, nothing
actually seems to happen.
Well, maybe it's just my name.
Carter.
Greet.
And nothing seems to happen.
That alert does not come up.
Well, why is that?
Well, let me go back to VS Code here
and point out that order of operations
in JavaScript matters
similar in spirit to C.
Because on line seven I'm selecting
the form and trying to add an event
listener for submitting that form,
unfortunately the form had better exist
at that moment in time, but it doesn't.
Because just like in C
and in some cases Python
where the compiler or the interpreter
reads the code top to bottom,
notice that the form doesn't
actually exist and therefore
get loaded into the computer's
memory until line 19.
So we've got to kind of
reorder these somehow.
Now, maybe the simplest
way to do this would just
be to perhaps do something like this.
Let me scroll back up to my script
tag and perhaps a little more
explicitly move it into the order
in which I want it to be executed.
So I'm going to go below my form
and inside of my body, which
is actually OK for JavaScript
here, and just use that same code.
And assuming I didn't make any
typos, let's go back to the browser.
Click reload again to get the latest.
Type in my name again using
that purely JavaScript solution.
And the only change I made was I moved
the code from up here to down here.
Clicking Greet now.
And wow, it's now back.
We get the alert with hello comma David.
So those kinds of things,
those kinds of principles
matter at least when
we're back in this world.
But there's other solutions too.
And just so that you've seen it, because
it's a common convention in libraries
as well, let me undo that change and
put that script tag back in the head
or really anywhere else in
the page where it might be.
And let me propose that there's
one other way to solve this problem
to postpone that code
on lines 7 through 11
getting executed until really the
whole DOM, the tree, is ready to go.
And the syntax for this
might be as follows.
I can do document and I
can add to the document
an event listener that's going to
listen for something a little special.
And I always have to look
this up myself to remember
the spelling and the capitalization.
But it turns out that
the browser itself,
once it's done loading all
of your HTML top to bottom,
left to right, it will raise an event
called DOM content loaded, capitalized
exactly as such.
And if you want to call some
function, and I don't even
need an event argument in this case,
you can open curly braces just as before
and put inside of those
curly braces the code
that you want to execute only once
the DOM's content has been loaded top
to bottom.
And now let me just finish my
thought with a closed curly brace,
close parentheses, and semicolon.
It gets a little annoying to
visually line all of this up,
but I think I'm still good.
And now even though this
code is at the top of my file
or really above the form tag
itself, I think we're OK.
So let's go back to the browser here.
Reload the page.
Type in D-A-V-I-D and click Greet and
we still get the same correct behavior.
And so this is just a very common
paradigm to use these kinds of events
to listen and listen and
listen for something to happen
and then only do something
once that thing has transpired.
All right, well let's take one
more step with JavaScript code
before we take a look at what's
really fun about this language
and what you can do with
browsers in particular
by just cleaning things
up a little bit further.
I'm going to go back into the
code here and I'm actually
going to remove or cut all of this
code out of the hello.html file itself.
And I'm going to change my
script tag to have nothing
in between the open
and closed tag, but I
am going to give it a source attribute.
And let's go ahead and call
this, for instance, hello.js.
So .js would be the convention for the
file extension for a JavaScript file.
And even though this is a little
weird that we have the script tag
and a source attribute then nothing
in between the open and close tag,
this is indeed the convention when
you want to put all of your code
in a separate file.
And let me go ahead and do that.
Let me go ahead and
open my terminal window.
Create a new file called hello.js.
And then in that file, I'm just going
to paste the very code that I just
cut from the previous file.
So no changes to the code.
All I'm doing is factoring it out.
And now I'm doing something just
like our CSS factorization before,
which confusingly used the link tag.
This uses the script tag.
This just now allows me to collaborate
with someone like Carter or someone
else so that they can
do the JavaScript code,
I can do the HTML, maybe a
third person can do the CSS.
And indeed, maybe we can
build even grander things
by designing things in this way.
All right.
Well, let me go back
to my browser again.
Reload the page.
I shouldn't see any visual changes,
but if I type in my name again, David,
and click Greet, this still now works.
And what my browser has just
done underneath the hood
is not only download the hello.html
file as always, because there's now
this script tag that's referencing
the source of another file,
just like an image tag might
reference the source of an image,
the browser is automatically helping
me out by loading that into its memory
as well.
And now how about one final example?
And for this one, I'm
going to go ahead and not
write it live but open it
up as prepared in advance
just to show you what you
can do by listening for some
of these other events as well, like
the key up, the finger going down,
the finger going up, and listening for
exactly that so as the user is typing
something you can do
something interesting as well.
I'm going to go back into
my directory listing here.
And I click on this
source, a directory which
has all of the examples that
I wrote here in advance.
And I'm going to scroll down
to one called hello5.html.
And in hello5 now we've
gotten rid of the button
and we just have this text box.
But notice now what happens if I
start typing my name as D-A-V-I-D.
I'm not typing Enter at all.
And in fact, if I start
deleting and I change my mind
and start typing
Carter's name, notice now
that the web page, the DOM
inside of the computer's memory,
is now automatically updating itself.
So it's not even
listening, it would seem,
for a submit event anymore but
maybe for a key up event instead.
So let me go back to VS Code here.
Open my terminal window.
And in my source directory,
let me open up hello5.html.
Inside of the script
tag, you'll see some code
that's similar in
spirit to before whereby
I'm adding an event listener to the
document waiting for the whole DOM's
content to be loaded.
But then inside of that
function, I'm now doing this.
I'm creating a variable
called input and selecting
from the document the one and only
input tag that we saw just a moment ago.
I'm then adding on line
11 in event listener
for key up, which is exactly that
gesture so that I can execute
some additional code any time the human
lifts their finger from the keyboard
after typing a key.
What do I then do?
Well, I'm going to go ahead, it seems,
and declare another variable called
name.
And I'm just going to select
some p tag on the page.
And now we didn't really see a p tag, so
I think it's time to look at the HTML.
If I scroll down to the bottom of
the page where my actual HTML is,
you'll see that there's just a form
tag and no on submit handler anymore,
as before.
There's just an input
tag and no button at all,
but there is on line 29
here an open and close p tag
just so I have an empty placeholder
in which to put something
like hello David or hello Carter.
So that's why now on line 12 I
can define a variable called name
and I can select that p tag
so that what do I want to do?
Well, if inside of the
input there's a value,
so this is essentially checking for
null or the absence of a string.
So if input.value does
not equal nothing,
that is there is a value in that text
box, well, this syntax here on line 14
is a very clever way
of doing the following.
Go into that name tag.
That is to say, the empty paragraph.
Change the inner HTML of it, the HTML
inside of it, to be literally this.
Hello comma.
And then just so you've seen
an additional piece of syntax,
this is similar to Python's
f strings, the syntax
is a little weird in JavaScript.
You actually use not single quotes,
not double quotes, but back ticks,
which on a US English keyboard
are typically the top left hand
key of your keyboard or thereabouts.
And using dollar sign curly braces just
like the curly braces alone in Python
allows us to plug in whatever
the value is of that input.
However, if there's no value there, it
looks like I'm just going to say hello
whoever you are.
And in fact, we can see that
behavior now as I delete,
delete, delete, delete, delete,
delete, delete and nothing's there.
Now that if condition is no longer
true and so we see this default value
instead.
So this is only to say that by
harnessing these various events that
are constantly happening on most any
web page, we can now register code
just like we did way back in Scratch
to actually listen for those events
and do something with them.
Now, it turns out we can do some
interesting things even using
third party code.
And just as we used bootstrap a
bit ago to make our table prettier,
allow me to propose that we also take
a look at this version of favorites
as well.
Let me go back into
my source 8 directory
and open up favorites2, which I made in
advance, which looks almost the same,
though I've zoomed in here a bit.
But you'll notice somewhat subtly over
the leftmost column in this table,
you'll see now this arrow in gray
pointing up and pointing down.
Previously those were not there.
All I had was a static
HTML table with all
of this data sorted in
whatever order it was
inputted the other day in that form.
But now notice what I can do.
If I want to sort in one order, I can
click this arrow or the other order,
I can sort in this arrow.
So essentially doing it
chronologically forward or backward.
Now, how is that sorting happening?
It's presumably based on
all of the timestamps that
were registered when we submitted
that Google Form just a bit ago when
it was live.
But now using JavaScript, it turns
out that we can use some logic somehow
and sort this data by the same.
And you don't get that automatically
just by using HTML alone.
Now, how did I achieve that?
Well, it turns out if I go ahead
and close these hello files.
And in VS Code let's
open up favorites2.html.
You'll see that all of the
HTML is actually the same if I
scroll down and down through this file.
But I added a little
something interesting at top.
I copied and pasted the
appropriate URLs and HTML tags
from bootstrap's documentation.
And you'll see here that I have a
file called not only bootstrap.min.css
but also bootstrap.bundle.min.js
as well as a couple of other things
as well that allows me
ultimately using third party
libraries to add some special HTML
attributes that those libraries told
me to add.
And then as soon as those libraries
detect the presence of these attributes
now on my own raw data, they do
their thing and JavaScriptify,
not a technical term,
the entire table and now
make it interactive and not static.
So you'll see here that
the aesthetics of the table
are as before, table and table striped.
But I'm adding now another
HTML attribute called
data toggle whose value is table.
And I know that only from the
documentation of these libraries
indicating that that's how I can now
enable this table to be interactive
as I can too by adding
data sortabls="true"
on specifically the timestamp column.
And the only thing unfamiliar here
perhaps is I'm using TH for Table
Heading as opposed to
TD as I do elsewhere.
But that's all that it takes
to now focus on the raw data
you want to present and let someone
else do the heavy lifting of actually
implementing the logic.
Well, let's end with just a look at
what more you can do with JavaScript
and just how powerful
it is when you combine
a language like this with the data and
the user interface you want to convey.
Let's go ahead and open up
within source 8 directory
something called background.html.
Now this interface here is quite simple.
It just has three buttons, R, G,
and B. And the background of course,
notice by default, is just white.
But when I click on the R,
the background turns red.
When I click on the G, it turns green.
And the blue, it turns blue.
And again and again.
So how is this working?
Well, if you think back again
to the available events,
perhaps I'm just listening
for a click on those buttons
and then doing something with
maybe the CSS of the page
to allow me to see
those different colors.
So in fact, let's go back to VS Code
here and let's open up background.html.
And in here, you'll see
some simple HTML at the top.
Just three buttons.
But I've given each a unique ID so
that I can reference it in code.
And then inside of a
script tag here below,
because I didn't bother with the
DOM content loaded event here,
notice that I'm doing the following.
I'm creating a variable called body
that lets me select the body tag.
I then have in these three lines
some code that handles red.
What am I doing?
Well, I'm selecting from the document
whatever HTML tag has unique ID of red.
And then I'm adding an event listener
for any click on that button.
And any time someone
clicks on that red button,
I call this function anonymously.
It doesn't even have or need a name.
And this syntax here is powerful,
because now in JavaScript I
can alter the CSS of my page by doing
body, which is the tag that I selected
two lines ago, accessing its style,
accessing its background color
property, and setting it
equal to quote unquote red.
And I do the same down below for green.
I do the same down below for blue.
And the only thing worth
noting here is that in CSS, it
turns out it's the case that the
CSS property for the background
color of a page is actually
background-color in all lowercase
with a hyphen in between.
Unfortunately in the
world of JavaScript,
a hyphen would be mistaken for
subtraction, like background
minus color, which would be wrong.
So the convention in JavaScript is
when you're trying to manipulate CSS,
you take whatever the property name
is, font size, background color,
and you change it into so
called camel case here.
You get rid of the hyphen and you
capitalize the subsequent words
like color in this case here.
All right.
How about another?
Well, it turns out back in
the day, back in my day,
there was a HTML tag that would
actually allow you to do this.
Create blinking text on a screen.
It's rather unpleasant
at this rate certainly.
But how might this work?
Well, it turns out in JavaScript if
we take a look at the blink.html file
here, we'll see that you can in your
HTML do something literally as simple
as hello world in the body.
But then you can call
this function here.
It turns out just like document,
there's another global special variable
you can use in JavaScript
and browsers called
window, which refers to all things
related to the window itself.
The window comes with a
set interval function,
which lets you do exactly that.
Set an interval in milliseconds.
And after every expiration
of that interval,
some function will be called for you.
So in this case, it's saying
every 50 milliseconds.
But let's actually slow that down now to
500 milliseconds or one half a second.
Call a function called blink.
Notice I do not have
parentheses after the blink name
because I don't want to call blink now.
I want to tell the JavaScript
to call the function called
blink every 500 milliseconds.
Now we'll see in a moment
what that code looks like,
but let's go back to
the page and reload.
And you'll see now that it's
a more pleasant blinking,
if that's even the case, every
half second because I'm now
firing that event, that is I'm
calling that function now, every 500
milliseconds instead.
How am I doing that?
Well, in this same script tag, I've
invented my own blink function.
This has the distinction back in the
day of actually being an HTML tag
and among the few tags that the
world removed and got rid of
so that it's no longer used because
it's not all that user friendly.
But down here what am I doing?
I'm getting the body of the
document itself with this variable
and then I'm checking two CSS properties
that we didn't talk about before,
but it turns out that you can check
and set the visibility of an element
in JavaScript by going into
that tag, checking its style,
and getting its
visibility at a property.
And if it happens to equal hidden,
the next line of code here, 13,
sets it equal to visible instead.
Else if it's not hidden,
it must already be visible.
And so line 17 flips it the other
way and changes it to hidden.
Here left hand, right
hand clearly not talking.
No idea why the opposite of
visible is not invisible.
It's indeed visible and hidden.
But this just allows you
every time this function
is called to change the
property from one value
to another, achieving
that blinking effect.
You can do even more powerful
things that you and I
take for granted every day.
Let's go into source 8 and
go to autocomplete.html,
which I wrote in advance.
And this is a page that also loads
into memory a really big dictionary
that you might recall
from problem set five.
And if I go ahead and type
in something like C-A-T,
you'll notice dynamically
an unordered bulleted list
appearing below the
text box that shows you
all of the words in that dictionary
from p set five that start with C
and then C-A and then T
just like the autocomplete
you see every day on your phone
and Google or websites like it.
How is that working?
Well, probably I'm listening
for the key press going up.
As soon as that key is
pressed, I'm probably
searching through a big array
really of all of those words,
maybe using linear search, maybe
binary search if faster than that.
And then looking for any
string in that array that
starts with C or C-A or C-A-T. And
then I'm generating automatically
the HTML therefore.
But perhaps most familiar
nowadays is just how much
your phone and your
laptop know about you.
And let me go into a final example here
in source 8 called geolocation.html,
which is a term of art that just
refers to figuring out your geography.
For instance, your GPS coordinates.
Now here we have a third
and final global variable
that your browser provides
you with called navigator.
And in navigator,
there's a special object
called geolocation that comes with a
function called get current position.
So if you call
navigator.geolocation.getCurrentPosition
and then pass in a function of
your own that doesn't need a name
but does take an argument, in
this case I called it position,
as soon as the browser or as
soon as the phone has figured out
where in the world that user is
with that browser at some latitude
and longitude, the
browser will automatically
call that function for you.
And you can do anything you want
with the position that comes back,
the latitude and longitude respectively.
So I'm going to use a function
that's not often that helpful,
but for our purposes today it's just
going to write to the document itself
to my big rectangular region whatever
the latitude is, then a comma,
and then the longitude as well.
So if we go back with this
final flourish into source 8,
open up geolocation.html,
you'll see that my browser first
wants my permission to let this
website my own know my location.
I'm going to go ahead and click Allow.
Crossing my fingers,
because it might take
a moment for the phone or
the laptop to figure it out.
And it looks like
according to Google, I am
right this moment with my Mac at
latitude longitude 42.375 comma
negative 71.11.
Let's go ahead and
highlight and copy that.
Let's go to a website
like googlemaps.com.
Crossing our fingers.
If you've never done this, you can
search for GPS coordinates too.
Let's hit Enter.
And amazing.
We are indeed in Sanders
Theater, roughly there,
standing on this stage on Halloween.
And that then is week eight.
We will see you next time.
Happy Halloween.
[APPLAUSE]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Off you go.
Buffering.
OK.
Josh, nice.
Helen.
Oh.
[LAUGHS]
Moni.
Oh no, wait.
That was amazing, Josh.
Sophie.
[LAUGHS]
Amazing.
That was perfect.
Moni.
[LAUGHS]
I think I-- over to Yoel.
Guy.
That was amazing.
Thank you all.
- So good.
[END PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]