SPEAKER 1: Good afternoon.
My name is Sarah.
SPEAKER 2: And my name is Grant.
SPEAKER 1: And we are The Harvard
Crocodilians and the Radcliffe Pitches.
SPEAKER 2: Now, Sarah and
I understand that today
is the final lecture of CS50.
SPEAKER 1: It's been a tough semester.
We made it through P sets
4, 5, and even finance.
SPEAKER 2: Now, I know this
is an unpopular opinion,
but I particularly enjoyed finance.
I spent a lot of time with my flask.
SPEAKER 1: The P set?
SPEAKER 2: There was a P set?
SPEAKER 1: Well, at least
things are looking up.
Today is our last lecture.
And look how far we've come.
If I were an emoji right now, I'd
be the face with tears of joy.
SPEAKER 2: Sorry about that we're
just trying to work some CS50
references into the intro.
I mean, boy I sure hope this Tide
man doesn't run off my Mario filter.
SPEAKER 1: You could say that.
For loop x equals open bracket
1 comma 2 close bracket.
Boy, I sure wish we had Check
50 see if these jokes were funny
when we wrote them.
SPEAKER 2: Any who.
We hope that you'll enjoy
this brief serenade.
[SCATTING]
SPEAKER 1: (SINGING) Well,
you lace up your boats
and you walk on down to an
knocked down shack edge of town.
There's a landing [INAUDIBLE]
that just won't quit.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
SPEAKER 1: Well, there's fryers.
SPEAKER 2: Broilers.
SPEAKER 1: And [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER 2: Barbeque ribs.
SPEAKER 1: But the trick of
the train is what they're
serving at those fine [INAUDIBLE].
You're going to spend the rest
of your [? brights ?] down
at the house of blue lights.
[ALL SCATTING]
Down at the house, the
house of blue lights.
Well, you lace up your
boots and you walk on down
to a knock down shack
on the edge of town.
There's a landing [INAUDIBLE]
there that won't just quit.
You walk until you see a blue
light [INAUDIBLE] fall in there.
Can you dig them sights down at the
house, the house of blue lights?
[ALL SCATTING]
You lace up your boots
and you walk on down
to a knocked down shack
on the edge of town.
There's a lot of people coming
there that just won't quit.
You walk until you see a blue
light [INAUDIBLE] fall in there.
Can you dig them sights down at the
house, the house of blue lights?
[ALL SCATTING]
ALL: (SINGING) Be sure to
spend your brights down
at the house of blue lights.
[APPLAUSE]
SPEAKER 3: Good afternoon, everyone.
We are the Harvard Krokodiloes.
And it is such an honor to be
here with the Radcliffe Pitches
performing for CS50's final lecture.
Congratulations to everyone.
And we hope you'll enjoy
this our tribute to CS50.
1: 1 2, a, 1, 2, 3, 4.
ALL: [VOCALIZING]
SPEAKER 2: (SINGING) C is
for the language I once knew.
O is for O notation, I must do.
D is for dynamic, flask
run and finance it.
E is even more than
David Malan can adore.
So code is all that I can give to you.
ALL: (SINGING) He can give to you.
SPEAKER 2: Code debugging
it since, P set 2.
ALL: (SINGING) Bugs in P set 2.
SPEAKER 2: (SINGING) Soon
deadlines, I'll make it.
Hit Compile and please don't break it.
Code was made by me for you.
ALL: [VOCALIZING] (SINGING) C
is for the language I once knew.
O is for O notation I must do.
D is for dynamic, flask
run and finance it.
E Is even more than
David Malan can adore.
So code is all that I can give to you.
Code debugging, it says P set 2.
Soon deadlines, I'll make it.
Hit Compile, but please don't break it.
Code was made by me for you.
SPEAKER 2: (SINGING)
C is for the language.
SPEAKER 3: 0,1,0,0, 0.1,0, 0.
SPEAKER 2: (SINGING)
O is for O notation.
SPEAKER 3: 0, 1, 0, 0, 1, 0
SPEAKER 2: (SINGING) D is for dynamic.
Flask run and finance it.
E Is even more than
David Malan can adore.
So code is all that I can give to you.
Code debugging it, sends P set 2.
Soon deadlines, I'll make it.
Hit Compile and please don't break it.
Code was made by me for.
Code was made by me for you.
ALL: [VOCALIZING]
SPEAKER 2: (SINGING) Code.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
[APPLAUSE]
All Right.
This is CS50.
And CS50, this was the Harvard
Krokodiloes and the Radcliffe Pitches.
If one more time we can thank
them for joining us today.
[APPLAUSE]
So this is already week 10, our
last, and indeed among the goals
for today are to hopefully give
you all the more of appreciation
of truly just how far you've come.
Recall that in week 0,
we began with this visual
here whereby it was described this
class as a bit of a fire hose, whereby
drinking from that fire hose or really
a fire hose from a water fountain
is not unlike getting an
education down the road too.
And so this is to say, that if you're
feeling like you didn't quite get it
all down, like that's actually OK.
And that's to be expected.
And even if you felt that with each
passing week, 0, 1, 2 all the way up
now till 10, it never
really ever got easier,
perhaps just consider that what was
once hard like Mario and getting
"Hello, world" to compile
is indeed the right measure
of the delta between week
0 and now in week 10.
In fact, you might recall that again
in week 0, 2/3 of your classmates
had never taken a CS course before.
Now, of course, you all have.
And indeed, if you think back to
this final sentiment from week 0,
that indeed "what ultimately
matters in this course
is not where you end up
relative to your classmates,
but where you end up relative
to where you yourself began."
So I would take some pride, take
some satisfaction, take some relief,
even though, a little bit more
work does remain at really just how
far you've come since that week 0.
And recall that in week 0, we
literally started with just 0s and 1s.
And by now, many of you might have
gleaned that these 64 0s and 1s have
been spelling something week by week.
In fact, today is our very last message
here in binary encoded on stage.
But then quickly, we
introduced scratch and we
started to assemble some building blocks
of programming, loops, conditions,
loops, conditions,
functions and the like,
but without all the distractions
of semicolons and curly braces
and all of that which admittedly
we introduced the next week when
we introduced you to C.
But even now that we've
transitioned to Python,
hopefully even those kinds
of curiosities or confusions
are hopefully starting to
just get more familiar.
And so you finally start to see
the missing semicolon as opposed
to spending time on
that kind of struggle.
Recall too, that in week 2, we
started talking already about memory
and how you can manage
things in arrays that later
became, of course, in Python, lists.
The week after we talked not
only about debugging bugs in code
but how to debug those same programs.
Thereafter, we started
talking about algorithms,
and we took a step back
from code and looked
at the bubble sorts and the
selection sorts and the merge sorts
and all of the searches as well
that go hand in hand with that.
And indeed, this ultimately is what a
lot of problem solving moving forward
is going to be about, just solving
problems with some form of algorithm.
And you have so many different
languages in your toolkit
now with which to approach
problems like those.
We talked thereafter
about pointers, which
are not likely to come back
in any modern languages
that you now use but
hopefully you have an all
the better of a sense
underneath the hood
of like what's going on
inside of the computer
so that when you're designing
something, you're using something,
something crashes, you at least have
a mental model for what's going on
and it's no longer that week
0 Black box as it once was.
I mean, you built things like this.
Think back to week 5 when you
built your own hash table.
And those things are
everywhere, key value pairs,
whether it's in Python or in C or
if it's now in CSS and JavaScript
and even HTML, like that principle of
key value pairs is really everywhere.
And so, of course, now code doesn't
necessarily have to look like this.
It now wonderfully looks a
little something more like this.
But eventually, you're probably not,
I'm not going to use Python anymore.
Something new and better
is going to come along.
But odds are, like a lot
of the building blocks
from these past 11 weeks are still
going to be useful for wrapping
your mind around those new worlds.
And indeed SQL, we introduced
to you a little bit too.
And even if you don't feel
yourself yet an expert,
hopefully you have a sense
of what you can do with it
and what problems you can solve.
It's of course a better alternative to
something simple like a spreadsheet.
And now of course, web
stuff is everywhere,
whether it's on your laptop or desktop
or even a lot of the mobile apps
that you use on your
phone, even though they're
native applications, like you install
them from Google Play or the Apple App
Store.
They're implemented increasingly
with HTML, CSS, and JavaScript,
but they're put in a
little rectangular window
so you don't even notice that that's
actually really just an embedded
browser.
And then of course,
you can build things,
as you might for your final project,
that too might very well be web
based if you go that route.
I mean, I'm still clinging to
like the very first like web
app I ever made years ago.
But honestly, I do that in part
because I was just so darn proud
that like I taught myself
how to do something
and it actually worked and
was used by other people.
So whether it's just used by you or
your classmates or your roommates
or your family or your
company down the line,
there's a great sense
of satisfaction that
comes despite all of the pain
that might be along the way
when you just can't see or fix that bug.
Now, of course we'll
transition as you'll
see in the coming days to empowering
you to code client side as well.
Up until now, you've been using
our own VS Code installation
in the cloud, which is
nice because you've got up
and running super fast
in week 1, focusing only
on code challenges not on
technical difficulties.
But among the goals now, if you
so choose and want to program
after this class, even if you never
take another CS course before,
you can use these same real
world de facto standard tools
on your own Mac or PC.
And so pictured here is screenshot
of like VS Code on the Mac.
And even though, yes,
you're going to have
to jump through a couple
of more hoops to just get
Python or some other language
working on your own Mac or PC,
like that's what programming is
ultimately going to be about.
And we deliberately transition
you to this at term's end
so that now you have 11 weeks
of more comfort under your belt
with which to solve sort
of silly technical support
headaches that might have been
deal breakers so many weeks ago.
So there's still more to be
done in the coming weeks.
And indeed a support structure
therefore, the CS50 hackathon,
of course, will be this
7:00 PM till 7:00 AM
opportunity to dive into
your final project--
well, really continue diving
into your final project ideally
at that point alongside classmates,
perhaps your project partners
if you're working collaboratively.
And awaiting you will be such memories
and excitement hopefully as these,
even as you then turn your attention
back to your final project.
There of course, will be several meals
during the day culminating with 5:00 AM
shuttles to IHOP, the
local pancake place,
if you are so awake at that
point or even if you get there.
This is not an uncommon sight
as you might recall from week 0.
And then lastly is the
CS50 fair, which is finally
back after a couple of years
now of it not being on campus.
And this will be an
opportunity for everyone
to present their final
projects to passers by,
classmates, faculty and staff and
really just delight in what it
is you created on your Mac, your PC,
your phone, in the cloud or anywhere
else.
And indeed, it's just
going to be an opportunity
to bring your laptop to a
shared space or your phone
and introduce your project to
passers by such as might appear
and ultimately celebrate
what you all accomplished.
And indeed will you be handed at
the CS50 fair, your very own I took
CS50 t-shirt, which I daresay, I'm
still wearing all of these years later.
And so you too--
[APPLAUSE]
--will have that ahead of you as well.
So for what's on the agenda today, we
thought we would not only look back
but look forward.
But first, we wanted to thank
so many of the team members that
have been helping both
on stage and off who've
made this course and these sections
and so much more about CS50 possible.
Of course, the building
that we are now in,
there's a whole team downstairs
in Memorial Hall who helps
us get set up and organized each day.
Our thanks to them.
There's the education support services
team who makes everything look
and sound so well down here,
especially when we have all of them
more microphones as well.
Our friends, the Harvard
Krokodiloes and the Radcliffe
Pitches most recently and then of
course CS50's own team, that [INAUDIBLE]
CS50's own favorite restaurant,
Chang Chau, down the road.
Indeed if you find yourself in
Cambridge for the next 1, 2, 3, 4 years
or visiting from out of town,
do pay a visit to our friends
just down the road.
And in fact, we'll have our
very last CS50 lunch this Friday
if you're able locally to partake.
And then there are CS50's own
team, both on stage and off.
And my thanks, truly.
Because not only do they make
everything run so smoothly,
they capture it for students here who
might not be physically present here.
For our friends down in New Haven
at Yale and certainly for anyone
online who might be tuning in as well.
And then lastly, wanted
to thank, of course,
the huge team of your
classmates, your peers that
make CS50 possible in sections and
office hours, tutorials, and more.
Allow me to share with
you the outtakes, so
that even we, the teaching staff
sometimes struggle with computer
science, here are some of the clips
that we captured when just passing
packets via TCPIP a while back.
You saw the finally--
the nicely polished
version, but here are,
if I may, if we could dim the
lights, are some of the outtakes.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Buffering.
OK.
Josh, nice.
Helen, Oh.
[CHUCKLES] Yet, Moni, No, oh, wait.
That was amazing, Josh.
But.
Um, Sophie.
Amazing.
That was perfect.
Moni.
[CHUCKLES] I think I--
SPEAKER 4: Hey, un-mute.
DAVID J. MALAN: Over to Yoel.
SPEAKER 4: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Guy.
That was amazing.
Thank you all.
SPEAKER 4: So good.
DAVID J. MALAN: Indeed, in that
moment, if we could, just one round
of applause for everyone who's
helped out this semester.
[APPLAUSE]
So back in week 0, we
introduced you, of course,
to this idea of
computational thinking, which
is to think a little more methodically,
a little more algorithmically.
And by way of these various
languages, hopefully, that
is something you notice,
maybe not in the moment,
but in the months and the years to come
that you do find that your thoughts are
indeed a little more cleaned up and
you're just able to express yourself
a little more precisely and even spot
illogic in someone else's document
or statements as well.
But at the end of the
day, really a course
like this is also about
critical thinking.
And indeed, rewind
again to week 0 when we
frame the entirety of computer science
as really just this, problem solving.
And any problem in the world, be
it CS or otherwise, has some input,
and we decided how to
represent those inputs.
It needs some output,
the solution there too.
And then all of what you focused
on doing and learning and applying
these past several weeks is in that
proverbial black box, which hopefully
is not such an abstraction
anymore but is indeed something
that you know how to harness
and know what could be going on
underneath the hood, even if it's
in some technology or some language
that maybe we ourselves didn't cover,
because a lot of those first principles
remain the same.
Now, along the way, we talked about the
quality of solutions to those problems.
We happen to focus on
correctness, just does it work?
Design, which is a bit more
qualitative and subjective.
And then style, the
aesthetics of it all.
And these two are
characteristic, maybe not
with these same words, of just
how you might write or evaluate
other creations in life, be it
physical or written or the like.
So think about too,
as you solve problems,
just how you can frame for
yourself, like am I doing a good job
or not by quantizing it, along these
or perhaps other axises as well.
And we thought we'd highlight just
two topics from that week 0 that
have really been manifest for the past
several weeks, namely abstraction,
like taking complicated things and ideas
and trying to simplify them so that we
can operate at this level and
solve problems we care about
without getting into the weeds of
implementation details so to speak.
But there's this tension
because, you know now,
from all of these different languages,
that code is fairly unforgiving.
I mean, even omitting a stupid
semicolon sometimes breaks everything.
And so precision is sort
of at odds sometimes
with this idea of
leveraging abstraction.
And so we thought we would
try to tease this apart,
especially all these weeks later here,
but with a bit of a live demonstration.
So on the way in, you probably
all received a sheet of paper.
If not, but someone near you
did just tear theirs in half
and borrow half a sheet
if you can or any piece
of loose leaf paper or
the like will suffice
as long as you have a pen or pencil.
And for this, allow me to propose
that we invite up maybe two final CS50
volunteers this semester, and like
a lot of hands are going up in this.
A lot of hands.
How about, I saw the first hand there.
Yes, who's pointing at herself now.
Come on down.
We just need the one hand
for now but, oh, wait.
You'll be our number two.
Well, OK, we have way
too many volunteers now.
No, no please.
Please come down.
Yes, in the black shirt.
And if you guys, we will, we'll
do pair programming in just a bit.
If you want to hang
out in the wings here,
we'll have our second
demonstration as well.
So OK, now maybe round of
applause for our three volunteers.
[APPLAUSE]
Oh.
Come on up, first.
Oh, no.
Second and third.
OK, you come first.
We'll do it order No.
This is a queue.
Queue here.
What's your name?
DANI: I'm Dani.
DAVID J. MALAN: Dani.
OK, take this mic.
OK, so we will de-queue you momentarily.
All right, so Dani, come
on over to the middle here.
And in a moment, I'm going to
hand to Dani a sheet of paper that
has a picture on it.
And this picture is
going to be something
that I'd like you to verbally
program the audience to draw.
You can use any words, any abstractions,
any level of precision that you want,
but you just can't make hand gestures
or sort of show them what to draw.
But first, you want to tell us a little
something about yourself, including
everyone here.
DANI: I'm Dani, and I took CS50.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Wonderful.
So I'm going to reveal
the picture only to Dani.
And if each of you would like
to take out that sheet of paper
and just make sure that
no one else can see this,
if you want to hold it up this way.
Everyone here is now holding their pen
or pencil, and in some number of steps,
give them a verbal algorithm
for drawing what you see.
And you can say anything you
want, but no hand gestures.
DANI: OK, so you're
going to want to draw
a square in the center of the
paper with the diagonal pointing
to the center of the edge.
Wait.
No actually, scratch that.
Draw a rhombus in the
center of your paper.
DAVID J. MALAN: And for those
who forget what a rhombus is?
DANI: A diamond.
A square that's on its side.
And then from the bottom vertex,
draw a straight line down,
but not all the way to
the edge of the paper.
OK.
And then keep your pencil
or pen at that point,
and you're going to want
to draw a line that's
parallel to the line of the
original rhombus to the right.
And then keep your pencil
or pen at that point,
and draw a line straight up,
connecting to the side vertex.
Yes.
And then go back to the line that
you drew from the bottom vertex
to the bottom of the paper,
and then draw a line parallel
to the left edge of the rhombus.
And then keep your pencil at
that point and draw a line up
to the vertex of the rhombus again.
DAVID J. MALAN: The end.
DANI: The end.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
Well, thank you to Dani.
Hang on to your paper.
Thank you so much.
And if you want to step off to
the stage there, we will reveal.
Thank you.
A round of applause
if we could for Dani.
[APPLAUSE]
That is not an easy task, I'm sure.
And if Carter wouldn't mind just
grabbing a few samples here,
let's actually take a look
on the overhead if we could.
I'm going to pop down
over here real fast.
We don't need to collect
them all, but if you're
feeling either good or bad with what you
drew, happy to collect a few of them.
OK.
Thank you.
I hope you won't mind if
I can't reach everyone.
Just a couple more, over here.
OK.
All right, that's--
AUDIENCE: This one's really [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: This one's really funny.
I'm going to go with this one if I may.
And Carter has some too.
Thank you so much.
OK.
So just a random assortment here.
Let me turn on a camera so
I can show you what I see.
Here, for instance, is
one classmate's drawing
which might resemble
perhaps what you Drew here.
Here is the beginnings
of a house, it seems.
Nice.
This one, this one is larger.
And how about a couple of others
that were getting closer, I think.
So more edges and vertices there.
This one seems a little similar
in spirit, if not proportional.
This is Zac's the best one.
But it turns out if I may, Zac,
you're not all that far off.
Here, Dani, is what you were
reciting to everyone algorithmically.
Indeed, it was this here cube.
And so Dani, can you come
on back up for a moment.
So if you'd like to share
for just a moment like what
were some of the thoughts
going through your head
and why did you choose
the words that you did?
DANI: OK.
So what was going through
my head when I saw the cube.
I didn't know if I
could say, draw a cube.
So I decided to start
with the top and so
draw a rhombus in the
center of your paper,
and then draw a line down
and just do the first part.
Then the second part,
then the third part.
And then you would get a cube like Zac.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
and so had you said,
and you could have said, draw a cube,
which would be more of an abstraction.
Even that's not necessarily
sufficiently precise, right,
because you don't necessarily know
what the orientation of that cube
is, the size of it, the
positioning on the paper.
So you instead took a lower level
approach, which is not unlike Scratch.
If you think about Scratch,
being able to move up,
down, left, right, turn 90 degrees,
turn 15 degrees and the like.
I mean, that is ultimately how a
lot of graphical programs and games
even might be implemented by really
focusing at the level you do.
But of course, there's
this tension with us humans
whereby we prefer often
to think at this level,
but even that might not be sufficient.
Which is to say, here in
week 10, these are still
going to be in our hard problems,
but a hand, if we could,
one more time for Dani for
getting us that far along.
Thank you so much.
Let me give you a stress ball here.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
And if we could have both of
our volunteers come up here.
We're going to have-- yes, come on up.
Come on up.
And let me have you guys introduce
yourselves in the middle here.
EVAN: Hi, I'm Evan.
SADDIQ: Hi there.
I'm Saddiq from Turkey.
Nice to meet you all.
DAVID J. MALAN: Wonderful.
Welcome.
And this time we're going to flip
it around so as to have the audience
do what Dani just did for us.
The only catch here
is that the only means
we have for showing the audience
what they need to tell you to draw
is like literally right
above the chalkboard.
So on our system here, that your
eyes must stay on the chalkboard
and not look up.
And in just a moment, if
you guys want to both stand
in front of the chalkboard,
back to the audience.
And as you're talking with each other,
verbalize it through the microphone
if you will.
I'm going to show everyone else in
the room a second and final drawing,
and we'll just go rapid
fire around the room,
give us one step at a time
collectively, and we'll
see if these guys can't draw
exactly that same outcome.
AUDIENCE: Is there another chalk?
DAVID J. MALAN: What's that?
SADDIQ: Is there another chalk?
DAVID J. MALAN: Just the one, so
you'll have to collaborate and let's
give you a clean slate here, literally.
All right.
So no looking up.
That's the only rule for you guys.
Here we go.
For the audience, here is what we'd
like them, ironically, to draw.
Step one, from anyone in the audience?
Yes.
AUDIENCE: Draw a circle.
DAVID J. MALAN: Draw a circle.
Anywhere.
AUDIENCE: Not anywhere.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
That's step one.
Step two.
Someone else?
Yeah, in the middle.
AUDIENCE: Draw a line down
from the bottom of the stairs,
about halfway down to the--
half way down.
DAVID J. MALAN: Draw a
line down from the bottom
of the circle about halfway down.
I think there was a hand
in front of you too.
Number three?
AUDIENCE: From the point on the bottom,
draw a diagonal line to the left.
OK.
[INAUDIBLE]
[LAUGHTER]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
AUDIENCE: The overarching goal here
is you're trying to draw a person.
DAVID J. MALAN: The overarching
goal here, for those unable to hear,
is to draw a person.
EVAN: Oh, it's a stick figure.
SADDIQ: OK.
It may be a stick figure.
AUDIENCE: Draw the
left leg of the person.
DAVID J. MALAN: Draw the left leg
of the person, of this person.
OK.
Good job.
All right.
OK.
Next, step four.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Go to the vertice of
the line going up and the circle
and to the left, I'm sorry,
to the right, draw a V.
DAVID J. MALAN: To the right of the
vertex at the bottom of the circle,
draw a V.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, draw a V.
SADDIQ: A V.
EVAN: Like what V?
DAVID J. MALAN: Nope, not interactive.
Draw a V.
EVAN: Well-- Yeah, it
seems really weird.
DAVID J. MALAN: Get ready for--
EVAN: Maybe something like this?
DAVID J. MALAN: Step five.
OK, we'll go with that.
Step five.
Someone else?
Step five, someone else?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Draw the
right side of the leg.
DAVID J. MALAN: Draw the
Nice.
Step six.
SADDIQ: Happy face?
DAVID J. MALAN: Six.
Six.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Erase the line
you have on the left.
DAVID J. MALAN: Erase the line
that you have on the left.
AUDIENCE: On the left.
DAVID J. MALAN: Step seven.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Instead of that line that
was before going up, make it go down.
DAVID J. MALAN: Instead of that line
before going up, make it go down.
Step eight.
Step eight?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Connect that line to the hip.
DAVID J. MALAN: Connect
that line to the hip,
AUDIENCE: Not like, not touching.
DAVID J. MALAN: Not touching.
EVAN: Something like this, maybe?
DAVID J. MALAN: Compromise.
EVAN: Not touching.
SADDIQ: Not touching.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
All right.
Step nine.
Almost there, I think.
Step nine?
Yes, in back.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] write the word
"hi" on the top left of the circle.
DAVID J. MALAN: Right the word
EVAN: Put this right here.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
And step 10.
Almost there.
AUDIENCE: Draw a line pointing to "hi".
DAVID J. MALAN: Draw a
line pointing to "hi".
EVAN: This is like a
speech bubble, basically.
DAVID J. MALAN: And step 10, 11?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Erase the exclamation point.
DAVID J. MALAN: Erase
the exclamation point.
Nice.
12.
Do we want to give them one more?
12?
Or are we good?
Yeah, last one.
AUDIENCE: Erase the right arm.
DAVID J. MALAN: Erase the right arm.
I think we're going to need a 13 then.
And then?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Repeat the left
arm, but rotate it 90 degrees.
DAVID J. MALAN: Repeat the left
arm, but rotate it by 90 degrees.
SADDIQ: That feels wrong.
How would you like--
as an organic human being,
how would you use your arms?
DAVID J. MALAN: No.
No.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SADDIQ: Would you ever
stretch your arm like that?
DAVID J. MALAN: That would
not be a stick figure.
SADDIQ: Would you do this
or would you do that?
DAVID J. MALAN: All
right, little hint, maybe.
Give me a step 14.
Step 14 and final?
Step 14?
I think we just got to
tell him what to do.
Step 14?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Think of a walking man.
The right hand [INAUDIBLE]
normal [INAUDIBLE],, but just
rotate the edge of it
a little to a left.
DAVID J. MALAN: Think of a
walking man, and have the left,
the right hand walking to your right.
SADDIQ: It's like--
DAVID J. MALAN: Where could the hand go?
Where should the hand go on that arm?
But Yeah.
OK.
Yes.
No.
I mean, look right here.
Look right here.
Look right.
Yes, sorry.
Thank you.
14 is done.
[APPLAUSE]
That's pretty close, so
congratulations to you guys.
And thank you as well.
All right, so I mean, these
things too are not-- yes, round
of applause then, sure.
[APPLAUSE]
So this is to say these ideas
of abstraction and precision
and really every other term
of art that we explored
this term are sort of
omnipresent and can
be easier or harder
to implement depending
on exactly what the problem is.
But what we thought we'd
do now in our final day
is try to now similarly prepare
you for life after CS50.
And this is really going to be a
list of really potential to-do,
so that you can stand on your own
after the class, after the classes'
infrastructure, write actual code.
And then we'll come full circle
one final time with our friend
Jennifer 8 Lee to look
at the world of emojis
and how they relate to all
forms of representation
that we've talked about up until now.
So one, how can you go about
programming after CS50?
So one, you can actually install command
line tools on your own Mac or PC.
Perhaps unbeknownst to
you, Windows has what's
generally called a command prompt.
Mac OS literally comes with a terminal
program in your applications utilities
folder.
And so even if you've
never run those programs,
you've actually had a
sort of blinking cursor,
black and white prompt available to you.
Might not have all of the same
software installed as your code space
in the cloud, but you have that
command line interface even
within today's graphical tools.
And among the tools you can install
within that command line interface
would be something
called Xcode on the Mac
which comes not only with a GUI IDE,
integrated development environment,
but also those command line
tools and Microsoft for Windows
has something similar as well.
Learning Git, so we've used
Git, only unbeknownst to you
underneath the hood for the most part.
But Git is a very, very
popular tool, if challenging
to pick up for the first time,
that makes it easy to push code
to a website called
GitHub or any equivalent
and then collaborate more
effectively with classmates.
There's definitely a
bit of a learning curve,
but thanks to CS50's own Brian
Yu, you can start, for instance
with a video like this.
And this indeed is going to be
one of these de facto standards
in the real world, at least
for the next several years
that you'll probably encounter if you
work in tech or really any company
where you're doing some programming.
VS code itself, we'll walk you through
this process in the coming days,
but you can indeed install
it on your own Mac or PC.
And what can you do when you write code?
Well, you can certainly write
software for your Mac, for your PC,
for your phone, or of
course per week 9, you
can host your own website be it
static as in week 8, hosting it
at websites like these, which generally
have free or student-friendly accounts
via which you can put something
statically on the web at a real domain
name that you might choose.
Or you can host a full
fledged web app, and using
student tiers on Amazon and Microsoft
and Google's Cloud Services or others,
you can sign up for, being a
student certainly, a whole lot
of free software, free hosting so as to
if nothing else experiment and perhaps
maximally get your own app
or website up and running.
So know that those are
resources available to you.
And this is by certainly
a non-exhaustive list.
If you'd like to geek out in the
coming months, in the coming years,
these are just some of the places
that people who take computer science
classes, who write code, might
tend to hang out and ask and answer
questions of each other.
So keep an eye for
instance on these here.
And then CS50 has its own
communities as you'll see.
If you go to this URL here via
the OpenCourseWare version of CS50
which is open to the world,
there a vibrant community,
thanks to time zones, that's
pretty much active 24/7, 365.
Talking about not only CS50 goings
on and problem sets and projects,
but really technology
more generally, as well.
So certainly feel welcome to partake,
either asking or answering questions.
Now, speaking of asking and answering
questions, a couple of weeks
ago, you kindly gave us a
whole bunch of review questions
which we culled through and picked
out our favorite 20 of them.
These, of course, were
multiple choice questions.
And in preparation for this
week, in preparation for life
ahead, we thought we would
choreograph a bit of a quiz show here.
And indeed, as you came
in at the start of class,
you might recall being invited to go
to this URL here, CS50/ly, either here
in person or if you're watching
live from home at this URL here.
You can use a phone or a laptop.
And if it's easier on the phone, you
can point your camera at this 2D barcode
here, we'll give folks a
moment to pull that up.
And again that, URL was CS50.ly/poll,
and once it looks like most folks have
it up and running, our friend Carter
here will help us dive into this review
session, if you will, with
a bit of fun along the way.
All right, Carter, if
you'd like to take it away.
What do we have as our first question?
You should see on your phone or
laptop, this same question being asked.
The first question is, "How do
you print quote, unquote "hello,
world" in Python?"
So among the possible
answers are these here.
Buzz in on your phone or your laptop.
We've got a few hundred
responses already.
Seven seconds to make your decision.
This is question 1 of 20, going
into it with some confidence.
I think we're down to 0 on the clock
and Carter it looks like 98% of you
indeed said, "hello, world."
And Carter, per the check mark,
that's indeed the correct answer here.
Now, to make things interesting, know
that you'll see some number of points.
And we've deliberately anonymized
it so only what number you are.
So a whole lot of guests have a
perfect score of 1,000 at the moment.
Hopefully we'll see over
the next several questions,
things start to bridge out.
But know that the speed
with which you buzz in
will also factor into how
many points you now get.
So the faster you move,
the more points you get.
Question 2, if we could,
"What does DNS stand for?"
from just a couple of weeks back.
"Domain Number System.
Domain Name System.
Data Numbering Structure" and
"There's no such thing as DNS."
Few hundred responses
are in, 8 seconds remain.
Fewer points now, but
still a chance to buzz in.
And now as we hit zero, the responses
are these, "Domain Name System" which
is indeed correct, and 84% of you got
that one correctly, and indeed exists,
we talked about it a
couple of weeks ago.
So we're still seeing a
whole lot of ties at 2,000.
We'll see if someone starts
to pull away before long.
Question three, "What is the upper
bound of Merge Sort's run time?"
So that escalated quickly.
"Big O of n log n.
Big O of log n.
Omega of log n."
or "Big O of 1."
"What is the upper bound
of Merge Sort's runtime?"
That was the last of the algorithms
we saw for sorting, and in one second,
we'll see that the correct
answer is just edging out
everyone else, indeed, 46% it is, n--
I know.
It's n log n.
Now, if I may, as the
teacher, it can't be log n,
because log n is strictly less than n.
And you can't possibly sort n
elements unless you minimally look at
or touch each of them.
So it's got to be at least
greater than n intuitively.
We still have a whole bunch of ties.
Let's move on to number 4.
"What is stored in argc?"
Back to the language, C. Is
it "An array of arguments.
The maximum size of an array.
The count of arguments given
to a program when first run."
or "how much memory is
allocated to a function?"
Again, you wrote all of these questions.
And we have 5 seconds, for the reveal.
Argc is indeed "The count of arguments
given to a program when first run."
Think back to C when we did command
line arguments, there was argc and argv.
Argv was the array, but
argc was indeed the count.
The a and argc.
All right, we still have a
whole bunch of ties at the top
here, but let's move
on then to number 5.
"What is the duck
debugger's favorite hobby?"
According to one of your classmates,
"Dressing up like Dracula.
Swimming across the stage.
Filling up the entire
bathroom of a guy's house.
Sitting quietly on stage."
The third of course, is a
reference to a YouTube video
that was on the course's
website that week.
But according to your classmates,
number 2, seconds remaining,
sitting quietly on stage
is its favorite pastime.
So a little harder
perhaps than the others.
5,000, now we're starting
to see some spread.
So we only have six guests in
contention for first place.
And the next question now is 6, "What is
the function used to open a file in C?"
"fopen.
open. fileopen.
file."
"What is the function
used to open a file in C?"
7 seconds.
There's some differences between
C and Python here, and the reveal,
it is indeed fopen at 77% correct too.
All right, let's see the rankings now.
If you are Guest1590, 715, 6171,
3753 or 3273, you're now in the lead
as we move on to question 7.
"How does strlen compute the avg--
sorry, how does strlen compute
the length of a string in C?"
"It looks at how much
memory the string uses.
It counts the number of characters
until it reaches backslash zero.
It counts the number
of bits in the string.
It creates pointers for each
character and counts them."
10 seconds, strlen in C. Recall that
we implemented this ourselves in class,
but then we use the library thereafter.
And indeed, with 85%, it simply
counts the number of characters
until it reaches that sentinel,
backslash zero, a.k.a.
Null.
And in this case, we have 544
of you tied now for first.
All right, question 8, "Where
does malloc allocate memory from?"
The "Stack."
The "Heap" The "Pointers" or
the "Temp" "Where does malloc
allocate memory from?"
Responses are coming in, 8 seconds.
A good review question at that.
In 2 seconds we'll see that malloc
allocates memory from, close one,
the Heap is correct.
The Heap is correct.
The stack recall is
where functions store
their local variables
and their arguments
and that just happens automatically.
The Heap represented in our pictures
up top is where malloc draws from.
Now we have guest 15 has
made its way to the top here,
but others can catch up if
they don't buzz in fast enough.
So number 9, "How many
people flew from Fiftyville
to New York on the day of the crime?"
"16.
29.
8."
or "3."
Anyone with a laptop perhaps
has an advantage here.
5 seconds, and the answers are--
but the answer is 16.
Let's see if Guest15 got this.
They did not.
Goodbye to Guest15 at the top.
All right, question 10.
We're about halfway there.
"What are meta tags used for in
HTML? " "To describe a web page.
To define parameters for an element.
To group elements together.
To translate content into
machine-readable format."
"What are meta tags used for in HTML?"
We saw a few of them
for different use cases.
And with 1 second, we see that
indeed the number one answer
was to describe the webpage,
be it for a mobile device,
be it for screen scrapers
like Facebook and Twitter
and other such apps that grab
images and descriptions thereof.
All right.
We're in the second half
now, Guest4669 edged ahead.
Guest15 is now in sixth place.
All right.
Number 11 is "How do you find
the address of a variable in C?"
Think back a few weeks.
Star, dollar sign, ampersand Ask.
From one of your own
classmates, "How do you
find the address of a variable in C?"
And the number one answer
is ampersand which is indeed
the address of operator at 62%.
Nicely done.
Let's see who's the top of the list now.
Guest4669 has retained their
lead, so we move on to 12.
"What does the arrow
operator mean in C?"
A hyphen and a greater than sign.
"Nothing.
Starts a comment.
Replaces a star in dot operator.
Declares a pointer."
"What does this arrow
operator mean in C?"
Again from a few weeks back.
3 seconds, harder assortment perhaps.
And it's oh, "Replaces
a star in dot operator."
The number two answer
was indeed correct.
This was just a cleaner
way, syntactic sugar
for collapsing what would be a star
and then some parentheses and then a
dot into quite simply something
that looks like an arrow itself.
All right, Carter,
who's in the lead now?
Still that same guest, and
let's see what 13 has for us.
"Which of these is not
a data type in SQLite?"
"BLOB.
STRING, INTEGER.
TEXT."
We used a few of these more commonly
than others but not all of these
are for real.
5 seconds to make your decision.
And the results are BLOG is a
thing, STRING is not in SQLite.
It's of course called
TEXT, as we've seen it.
BLOB, as goofy as it sounds,
is just binary large object.
But indeed, it's how you might store
a binary file in your database.
All right.
The rankings now, oh,
Guest8444 has eked ahead.
So we move on to 14.
"Which of the following is a
valid way to print exclamation,
point exclamation, point exclamation
point, exclamation point, in Python?"
And I'll let you read these yourselves.
Which is a valid way?
OK, everyone got quiet and is thinking.
All right.
6 seconds, a few hundred
responses in so far.
All right, and yes, nicely done.
78% is correct.
You can use the star operator
to essentially multiply
the character at left.
All right, who's in the lead, Carter?
We now have still Guest8444.
And so we move on now to 15.
"What does the free function do?"
Deallocated memory from a primitive.
Deallocated memory at the given pointer.
Terminates a loop." or "Returns
a value from the function."
"What does the free function do?"
All right, 5 seconds.
Call to the opposite
essentially of malloc.
And it "Deallocates the
memory at the given pointer."
as well.
And in C, that's on you.
In Python, you don't need to worry
about allocating or freeing alike.
All right.
We now have at the top, still Guest8444
and seeing more and more spread.
16, "Which is not a step of compiling?
Think back now to week 2.
"Compiling.
Preprocessing.
Linking."
or "Threading."
"Which is not a step of compiling?"
We use it as a catchall,
but it technically
means a few different
things collectively.
All right.
And threading is indeed not on the list.
That is a technical
thing, generally meaning
a program can do
multiple things at once,
but that is not related
here to compiling.
All right Guest8444 still at the top.
We have just a few questions left.
And so, 17 "What was the surprise at
the beginning of the Halloween lecture?"
According to your classmates,
someone scared me,
"Someone hid candy under every chair."
Someone dressed up as me.
"The entire staff dressed up as Carter."
Oh, interesting litmus test of who
came to or watched lecture perhaps.
Let's see which guests got this correct.
Someones really dressed
up as indeed me at 64%.
So I think we have attendance here
essentially from that lecture.
So let's move on now to
the final few questions
after seeing that Guest8444
is still doing well.
Can anyone dethrone them?
"Why is it incorrect to use
the equals equals operator in C
to compare strings?"
"It is computationally inefficient.
You're comparing the
locations of the strings.
Strings don't exist.
Using equal equals will
lead to buffer overflow."
"Why is it incorrect to use equal
equals in C to compare strings?"
3 seconds.
We saw this live, and it
motivated like an entire week
because you're comparing the locations,
that is the addresses in memory
of those same strings.
All right.
Let's see if this leaves
the rankings the same.
Guest8444 is still at the
top and pulling ahead.
Two final questions, 19.
"What is the difference
between NUL" one L, "and NULL."
Two Ls.
NUL and NULL mean the same thing.
NUL refers to backslash 0, whereas
NULL" 2 L's "is the 0 address.
NUL is the zero address whereas NULL"
two L's "refers to backslash zero.
NUL is NULL but lazier."
5 seconds.
Subtle.
Not the best design perhaps
to have in technical terms,
but indeed 62% of you got that and N-U-L
is the first thing we talked about when
we talked about backslash
zero, and N-U-L-L is a pointer.
It's the zero pointer.
Same number, but different context.
All right, Carter.
Guest8444 is the person to beat
with our final 20th questions.
"What do the binary bulbs
on stage spell today?"
And these are your four
choices, different from usual.
We usually use 8-bit Ascii.
Today we are using UTF8
which is a form of Unicode,
which is the larger subset
that uses 1, or 2, or 3,
or even 4 bytes to spell
a single character.
And the answer, wow,
close, is indeed a cupcake.
Indeed, a cupcake.
Well done.
And let's see the final results.
8444 is the winner.
Are they here in person, perhaps?
8444.
You're 8444.
Come on down.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
There you go.
Congratulations.
GUEST8444: Thank you.
DAVID J. MALAN: Thank you.
All your.
All right.
Today if we may, give
me just one moment.
All right.
So today we are so pleased
to be joined by Jennifer 8
Lee who's an alumna of the
college, a dear friend,
and is actually really the reason why
there's evidence of Muppets in CS50.
In fact, some years
ago, I was visiting her
and she had on her shelf
like this custom Muppet.
It wasn't one that appears on TV, but
she had somehow gone on a website,
a former toy store called
FAO Schwartz at the time,
and you're allowed to configure
your own Muppet whatnot.
Choose the eyes, the nose,
the face and the torso.
And I just thought this
was the coolest thing.
And so in the taxi on
the way home, I was
like going on the website trying
to purchase our very first Muppet.
I then sort of woke up
the next morning thinking,
why did I just buy a puppet
in the back of a taxi?
And so it sat on the shelf
for really two years.
And then a colleague of
mine within CS50's team
decided, after I brought it into
the office to sit on a shelf there,
to actually bring it to life.
And indeed if you Google around and
CS50 Muppetry and puppetry online,
you'll see in fact these
as characters, not only
over the past couple of
years in COVID times, when
really there was next to no one
actually here, and so they were instead.
But indeed she's brought not
only this educational element,
this pedagogical element,
this playful element to CS50.
And we have her here today to speak
to exactly the sorts of encodings
that are here on stage.
Jenny is the former Vice Chair
of the Unicode subcommittee
on emoji, which is to say
that she and her colleagues
have been influential in
taking emoji from what
was a very limited character
set early on and by far
unrepresentative of much human emotion
in speech into really an initiative now
to capture digitally all
of the world's languages,
past, present and future, as
well as the range of emotions
that we might see here in
the form of that pillow
or even in the cake that await.
So allow me to introduce,
Jennifer 8 Lee.
JENNIFER 8.
LEE: Thank you.
I much drink.
Clicker.
Hi.
All right.
Hold on.
I have to hide my drinks.
I might need more water.
All right.
I'm really excited to speak.
So speak your last time.
Last year I was here.
One, I was wearing a mask, which is
like a real bummer if you're lecturing.
And then the entire front
part was all Muppets.
So I'm really happy to
see humans actually.
And it's always an honor
to speak at Sanders.
And then Dave and I were actually
classmates way back when.
So I do remember him when he
was an undergrad much like you.
So I am going to give a
talk on the world of emoji
and how I kind of became
an emoji activist.
So it kind of all starts
with my friend, Yiying Lu,
who is a designer who's well
known for doing the Twitter fail
whale, which was kind of laid to rest.
Except now, this week it seems
like it may be necessary again.
So she and I one day were texting.
This is back in 2015.
We're texting about dumplings
because we are Chinese-ish women
and we like to text about food.
And so I sent her this
picture of dumplings.
She was like yum, yum, yum,
yum, yum, yum, yum, yum.
And then she was like, oh, Apple
doesn't have a dumpling emoji.
And I was like, well,
that's kind of interesting.
I didn't really think anything about it
because people point things out to you
all the time, and then you just like
forget, and you just like move on.
But then half an hour later, on my phone
appears this dumpling with heart eyes.
And you don't see it because
this is a still shot,
but it actually had blinking eyes.
So she liked to call it
like bling, bling, dumpling.
So she as a designer had decided
to go in and make her own dumpling
emoji because she was like,
I'm a designer, I can fix it.
But that actually got me thinking.
I was like, where do emoji come from?
And how is there not a dumpling emoji.
Because from my perspective, dumplings
are this kind of universal food.
Right.
So and there are a lot of Japanese
foods on the emoji keyboard.
And I was not, this
was like back in 2015.
I was like not a big
emoji user like at all.
So I mean, you have things like ramen.
You have Bento boxes.
You have curry.
You have tempura.
You even have kind of
obscure kind of foods
like this thing, things on a stick,
turns out to be fish things on a stick.
Then this pink and white swirly
thing is also a fish thing.
And there's even like
that triangle rice ball
that looks like it's had a
bikini wax, all well represented
on the emoji keyboard, but no dumplings.
And it's very strange, because like all
cultures kind of have their dumpling,
whether or not it's khinkali
or ravioli or empanadas,
like essentially everyone
sort of like discovered
the idea of yummy goodness
inside a carbohydrate shell,
whether or not baked
or fried or steamed.
So I was like, OK, I literally
Google was like who controls emoji.
And you discover that they're actually
regulated by a nonprofit called
the Unicode Consortium.
And it is, and I just
went on their website
and I discovered that they had 12
full voting members as of 2015.
So this is 2015, and they were like
mostly US multinational tech companies.
It was Oracle.
It was IBM, Microsoft, Adobe,
Google, Apple, Facebook, and Yahoo.
And of the three that were not
multinational US tech companies,
there were, let's see a
German company called SAP.
A Chinese telecom company called Huawei,
and then like the government of Oman.
Those were basically the 12 full voting
members of the US multinational tech
companies.
So they at that point
paid $18,000 a year
to have full voting power
on the Unicode committee.
And I was like, oh,
that's a lot of money.
And I kind of felt indignant about this.
But then if you kind of keep
on digging on their website,
you found there was this kind
of interesting loophole, which
is could join as an individual for $75.
You don't get voting
power, but it gave you
the right to put yourself
on the email list
and also to attend the
quarterly Unicode meeting.
So I was like, I'll do that.
I had no idea what I was doing.
But I'm like, I'm going to go
fight for this dumpling emoji,
because from my perspective,
dumplings are universal.
Emoji are kind of universal.
So the fact that there was no
dumpling emoji meant like something
was wrong in the universe and
I was determined to fix this.
You know I was on this email list.
And then a couple of maybe, even
like a couple of weeks later,
I got-- they kind of sent
out this note that's like,
hey, who's coming to
the quarterly meeting.
And I was like, I
looked at the calendar.
I looked at my schedule.
I was like, oh, I'll be in
Silicon Valley at that time.
So I basically like RSVP and
I was like, I will be there
and took Caltrain to an Apple building.
It's a legal building in
I think it was Sunnyvale.
So I just like show up.
And I don't know what I was sort of
expecting like with like the Unicode.
I think I maybe that was going
to be like a baby Congress,
like with a little very formal
seats, people with gavels.
That is not what I found.
Basically it is, it
was a conference room
full of people who skewed wider, skewed
older, skewed male, skewed engineers.
And this is basically the
room where it happens.
So this is 2015.
These were the people who decided
your emoji, all very nice and.
There was one, even had a daughter
who had a sense of humor and made him
a shirt that said
"Shadowy Emoji Overlord."
So I just kind of listened to them
debate things like milk emoji and beans
emoji.
And it just seemed like
not quite right to me
that it would be this global
visual language that were basically
decided by like a small group of people
inside a conference room in Silicon
Valley.
So I decided to form a
group called Emojination,
whose motto is like "Emoji by
the People, for the People."
And it basically advocates for more
kind of representative inclusive emoji.
We start with a Kickstarter
campaign, dumpling emoji
process trying to right
the wrong in this world
and made this little cute
video sort of advocating--
NARRATOR: Dumpling are
one of the most universal,
cross-cultural foods in the world.
Georgia has khinkali Japan has gyoza,
Korea has mandu, Italy has ravioli,
Poland has pierogi, Russia has
pelmani, Argentina has empanadas,
Jewish people have kreplach,
China has potstickers,
Nepal and Tibet have momos.
Yet somehow, despite
their popularity, there
is no dumpling emoji
in the standard set.
Why is that?
Emoji exist for pizza, tempura, sushi,
spaghetti, hot dog and now tacos,
which Taco Bell takes credit for.
We need to right this disparity.
Dumplings are global.
Emoji are global.
Isn't it time we brought them together?
Oh, yeah, while we're at it, how
about an emoji for Chinese takeout?
JENNIFER 8.
LEE: So I did put together
a dumpling emoji proposal.
I wrote this, I remember
Thanksgiving Day 2015 on a plane.
And actually, and we got it
passed, basically dumpling,
takeout box, chopsticks
and fortune cookie.
I have to say, I don't think
fortune cookie would have made it
on its own merits, but
it kind of like slid
in on the coattails of the other ones.
And so these were the
proposals as we submitted them.
And then these are the ones that kind
of exist now on the Apple keyboard.
And I have to say, the
dumpling looks really,
really realistic, oddly realistic.
And whereas, like the fortune
cookie I think is like a big fail,
because first of all, there's
like, it has no-- it has no gap.
It looks like a dead 3D Pac-Man.
So I'm very disappointed in
the manifestation of that.
But that's OK.
That's OK.
And so it's kind of
interesting, like what is
the process of getting an emoji passed?
And I will walk you through it.
So first of all, you
come up with your idea.
And then you write
this proposal and then
you submit it to the Unicode emoji
subcommittee who then gives you
comments and then sends it back to you.
And you kind go around
and around the circle.
So these are things that we consider.
So somewhere in there, I also fought
my way onto the emoji committee
and then also became a Vice
Chair, became a Vice Chair.
Sort of an extracurricular just
like completely run amok in my life.
So things that matter popular demand,
is it a frequently requested emoji.
Multiple usages and meanings, so
that's actually kind of very important
for something like certain
animals have meaning.
So we did sloth a while ago, and that
also has not only the literal meaning
but sort of like connotations.
There are visually distinctiveness,
it can be recognized.
So this was a blocker
for one of the emoji
that I have worked on before which
is cave, which is kind of hard to do.
I think, meaning wise, is pretty
good, but it's really hard
to get a cave down in emoji sizes.
And then it filling a gap, completeness.
So a good example for that is like
for some reason, for many years,
we had red heart, yellow heart, green
heart, blue heart, purple heart,
and no orange heart.
So somewhat, so you
would do the rainbow,
but people would
substitute the pumpkin in.
So you would like have a rainbow heart
thing with a little pumpkin stuck
in the middle.
So orange heart obviously should be
added and give a sense of completeness.
And then something else is
existing vendor compatibility.
And so a good example for
that was many years ago
WhatsApp decided to add the
gender non-binary emoji.
And then once it did that, then all of
the other kind of vendors jumped on.
So what kind of knocks out an emoji.
So too specific or narrow.
So we'll often see that with very
specific animals or a very specific
group.
It's redundant so one year, oh
my God, who makes a Butterball?
Butterball makes the turkeys.
Butterball submitted an emoji proposal
that was like a cooked turkey.
But we already had a live turkey so it
seemed kind of redundant to have both,
like a cooked turkey for
Thanksgiving and a live turkey.
So not visually discernible.
This is a struggle for things
like, I know my friends have
kind of proposed kimchi.
Kimchi is really hard on emoji sizes for
many reasons and part of that tension
is because it's not
visually discernible.
Then there are no logos brands,
deities, or celebrities.
So no Nike swoosh, no
McDonald's M. And then
this is one that we decide in the last
year or so which is no more flags.
Flags are a very complicated thing.
And as a result Unicode
does not want to be
in a business of deciding what
is a country or not a country.
So like when you get a proposal
from like Kurdistan, you're like--
so right now, the way that
the emoji flags are decided
is they kind of depend
on what the UN recognizes
and then those get passed down to the
International Standards Organization
and then Unicode just does that.
It does not want to be in the
business of the geopolitical affairs.
So once it comes out
of the subcommittee,
it goes to the full Unicode
Technical Committee, UTC.
Those were the people that were
in the room that I showed you.
And they vote once a year
basically to pass all the emoji.
And it takes a while.
There's a lot of coordinating
with the International Standards
Organization and a lot of
working with the companies.
And eventually, it takes a long
time, but it ends up on your devices.
And that historically has
taken about 18 to 24 months
from when you put it in a
proposal to when you get it in.
It's going to be a little bit longer
going forward probably is my sense
as we're organized--
Unicode is designed to space out
some of the Unicode releases.
So Emojination kind
of has done its thing.
So one of the weird things
is like how did Unicode,
this kind of non-profit
organization based in Mountain View,
California end up controlling
this global visual language?
So a lot of it has to start,
has it has to do with the fact
that emoji started in Japan
back in the late 1990s.
The set from Docomo
in 1999 is considered,
is widely considered sort of like
the first like color emoji set.
It has been collected by
the Museum of Modern Art.
And so the Japanese telecom
companies would use basically,
would have their own sets of emoji.
And then there were different companies,
so they would have different sets.
So you could basically only send these
like visual characters with someone
who is on your same carrier.
So it's like basically equivalent
of if you were on like Verizon,
you could only text people
on Verizon with like emoji.
Or if you were on T-Mobile,
you could only do that.
So at a certain point, they decided they
the Apple and Google came into Japan.
They wanted to start
selling smartphones.
And they realized that it
was a hodgepodge of systems
and they wanted to unify it.
And so in 2007, they went to
Unicode and they're like OK,
help us unify the emoji, kind
of basically all the emojis
so that we have one standard system.
And part of the reason is why Unicode.
Because Unicode basically
has this mission
is to enable everyone speaking
every language on Earth
to be able to use your languages
on computer and smartphone,
so it basic unifies all written
languages into one ginormous set.
And that was not the case
actually when I was growing up.
There was a point where like
if you were Japanese on Apple
that would be different than
Japanese on DOS or Chinese or Arabic.
So it drove everyone
crazy and they basically
decided around the late '80s or early
1990s that they were going to come up
with one standardized
system that sort of encoded
all characters in one ginormous set.
So there's three main projects
for Unicode if you care.
So one is encoding
characters including emoji.
Now there are about 100,000
characters aside assigned,
so that includes Chinese, Japanese,
Korean, Arabic, Cyrillic, actually
all the hieroglyphics, all of the emoji,
a lot of things like the Bitcoin symbol
or like copyleft or whatever.
Those all assigned were about 100,000
characters, even those languages
that are basically out of use.
So the other thing it does, it creates
localization resources so things so
that you know, oh, if you're in this
country this is you're using a euro
or you're using the pesos or something.
So there's a lot of
localization data that
is needed depending on which geography
you're using your device from,
or that you know that the time is used
this way or dates are shown that way.
So that is called the common local data
repository or CLDR as they call it.
And the other thing they do is they kind
of maintain libraries for developers
in order to do all--
so they are not building everything
from scratch, and that is called ICU.
So it's very funny,
because it's called CLDR,
and then one day, one of
our friend's girlfriends
made him this thing which she
called a sealdeer, because whenever
he talked about CLDR, she thought
he was talking about sealdeers.
So now this is his little like mascot
for like Unicode related things.
So how does Unicode do this?
So basically it assigns code points.
And each code point is a unique number
assigned to each Unicode character,
so face with tears of joy, it can be
written like this with a code point,
or it can be written like this
in terms of decimal numbers.
And it can also written
in this in binary numbers.
So these are all basically the same.
And the key thing to know,
at least about emoji,
is that when your device, if
you're talking on your iPhone
with someone who's on a laptop or
an iPad or like an Android device,
it's not sending the
images back and forth.
It's sending just a
number of back and forth.
And then locally, your
phone, or like your laptop
decides like, oh this number
correlates with which image in terms
of our emoji font and then pulls it up.
So this is really key to know why
different emoji look different
on different platforms.
So 2007 to 2010, it
took about three years,
but Unicode 6.0 came out with our
first little baby set of emoji.
And it just kind of hung
out there for a year.
Like no one, it wasn't doing anything.
So 2011 though, Apple starts
adding the emoji keyboard
and it just like explodes, like I
feel like in some ways, emoji are
were not invented.
They were discovered.
They like obviously touch
something very, very primal
to like our human desire to communicate
in like little colorful glyphs
on electronic devices.
And you kind of have what's
kind of really interesting
is like the ambiguity that comes
with what emoji kind of mean.
And so one this is one
of my favorite emoji.
It's sort of like an upside down
smiley face, very, very ambiguous.
Clearly very ambiguous,
because if you start
typing into Google, like the top hits
are like what does it mean from a guy.
What does it mean from a girl.
It's clearly something
that a lot of people
are using in like complex
situation ships between each other.
So one of the fun things
is who can propose emoji.
Technically anyone can.
Anyone here can.
Normal humans can.
We have basically Google
Doc or Google Form
that we throw up historically
between August, sorry April
and August in the last two years.
And so this is one of
our favorite examples.
This is Rayouf Alhumedhl.
She was a 15-year-old Saudi Arabian girl
who was living in Vienna at the time
that she proposed the hijab emoji.
And then she was like Time
Magazine like coolest teens
she got like a whole
bunch of different things.
She got into Harvard and Stanford.
And she went to Stanford.
So this is a proposal we got.
Then there was a group
of folks from Argentina
who got the mate emoji, kind of
the symbol of their national drink.
Then we worked with, there was
a nonprofit that really wanted
to get a menstruation emoji and so
what they proposed to begin with
was like bloody underwear.
And I was just like no, no, no.
So many different reasons
why this is a terrible emoji.
So we did get blood drops
and you can do moon and blood
drop or underwear and blood drops.
There's a lot of different ways.
Actually it's really funny, because
I was polling my friends beforehand
what they would use to
indicate menstruation
before there was a blood drop.
So there was like red wine.
There was kind of that rose
with the like falling petal.
And then my favorite
is actually my friend
who used a Japanese flag
as a way to indicate
that she was having her period.
So one of the biggest
contributors, this skin tone emoji
appeared, I think in 2015.
It was amazing.
It is.
And it was proposed by
a mom, Katrina Parrott.
She is an entrepreneur and a
mom who is just like at home
one day and her daughter
comes home and is
like I wish there were
emoji that looked like me.
And her mom was like,
that's great, honey.
What's an emoji?
And so she, like me, I guess
googled and just figure it out
that Unicode controlled emoji.
And she just came up with a
proposal saying we should not only
have the yellow skin tones.
At that time, everything was
sort of Simpson's yellow.
It's really interesting to see how
race and nationality are depicted
in different parts of the world.
So originally in Japan, everyone
was yellow, but these were the non--
by default, everyone was
just like human or Japanese.
But they had like a couple
of things that were like not.
One was, you had a blonde person.
So there's an emoji
called like blonde woman
or whatever that
represents all Westerners.
So that was one.
And then they have one that's
like an Indian guy with a turban.
So that's supposed to
represent Indian people.
And then there's like a guy with a
little like little hat that's supposed
to represent like Chinese people.
So that was like that the Japanese view
of race which was like default, then
you were then you were like
blonde Western, Chinese or Indian.
And that is all there was.
And obviously in the United
States, we care a lot about race.
And then so she came up with
a system with five skin tones
like just like normal people.
Some guy in Germany
decided that he wanted
to do a face with one eyebrow raised,
or as we call it the [? cobara ?] emoji.
Oh, this one's fun.
So woman's flat shoe.
I have to say, not highly used
statistically at this point.
But I really kind of
appreciate it because it
was a mom who was very offended
that all women shoes had heels, even
the sandals.
So this is her, she had
like three kids at the time.
She now has four.
She was very fertile.
And she also did the women's flat--
she also did one piece bathing
suit because she was also
offended by the fact that the
only kind of bathing suit you
had was like this
little itsy bitsy polka
dot bikini thing, which is not great if
you're like taking your six-year-old.
So I would say that got passed,
but like it didn't go over
super well with everyone.
So you know Unicode, because it's very
public, submits things for comments.
And we got this comment back,
so one piece bathing suit, why?
A person wanting to indicate the use
of swimwear can't use existing bikini.
Is this really necessary?
What about a Victorian bathing
costume or wetsuit or [INAUDIBLE]..
This is like literally in like the
records, and like do not encode.
And so the person who did
this, actually very impressive.
He's actually the person who
created the middle finger emoji.
And actually if you've ever seen the
Vulcan emoji, the Vulcan hand emoji,
he's actually very active.
And I have to say this is actually I
think one of the more impressive emoji.
So obviously, obviously we
have a lot of active debate.
Sometimes you get like
whole countries submitting.
So literally the government of
Finland, as in like their equivalent
of the State Department,
their diplomacy kind of thing,
submitted a proposal for sauna.
And these were so creepy and so weird.
So much is wrong with this.
But I felt where they were coming
from, for like they're naked.
They have no-- they're club feet.
And so we decided to help them.
We're like OK, we see where
you're going with this.
Let's see if we can help you like come
up, you know like we had this spoon.
Like should there be
like steam around them.
Like should they be naked or wearing
a towel was like super dicey.
But we wanted to help them
because it was literally
a foreign government coming in front of
Unicode advocating for the sauna emoji
on behalf of their entire country.
So then this-- it's evolved into
this basically person in steamy room
which is the most sort of
like the PG version of sauna.
And there's no spoon.
They're all dressed.
It's very odd.
But so you can see the evolution
of what it started out.
What we submitted and
what it ended up so.
There's a lot of evolution
throughout the entire process.
And like companies can
submit emoji proposals too.
So Google actually worked on this one.
I love this one.
So just to give you some
context, as of 2015,
there are many ways you could
be or have an occupation
as a male on the emoji keyboard.
Like for example, you
could be a police officer.
You could be a detective.
You could be Buckingham Palace guard.
You could even be Santa Claus.
Like these are so many
jobs that you could have.
But if you were a
woman as of 2015, there
were four things that you could be.
You could be a princess.
You could be a bride.
You could be a dancer, or
you could be a Playboy bunny.
These were the sum total of all
the occupations that we could have.
So there was sort of this
movement at that time,
there was like this video on
YouTube that like went viral.
There was like a New
York Times op-ed that
was like, where are the
women with professions?
So basically they came up with
a set of emoji for professions.
And what's nice is not did women have
these professions, now men have them
too.
So of an Emojination emoji, these are
some of the ones that we've worked on.
I think about 130 of the
emoji on your keyboard
probably came through, touched
our system in some way, including,
I have to say microbe or virus.
I think, I have the opinion
that every emoji has its day.
It might not be like today.
It might not be next year, but I have
to say, virus was not doing anything.
Then came 2020, and that was like such
a good moment for it, along with soap.
We had also done soap.
So among the other emoji
that we have worked on
are, sorry, mooncake, llama, teddy bear.
There were no toys.
I felt really sad for toys.
We have giraffe.
There was hut.
Bubble tea.
Bubble tea was very
controversial, actually.
I have to say, we try to slide it
in originally with the takeout box
and the dumplings and
people were not having it.
And I understand that.
Because there's not a lot.
Like compared to beer or wine,
like bubble tea is not long,
does not have a long
history on this planet.
But I will say that they submit it
again, actually kind of originally
proposing that it was
not just bubble tea,
but like a black ball and milk and tea.
It was kind of cool.
And I have to say there was
definitely a generational divide
between the Asian women who
sit in that room and are
like this absolutely is
a thing that we consume
like almost like every week
of our life, and people
who are a little bit older who are
like, that looks like a parfait.
How do you not know
that's not a parfait?
We're like, we absolutely
know it is not a parfait.
And so it got in, eventually.
So it does sort of influence.
It kind of shows who is in the
room influences the decisions that
get made or sometimes in the room,
now sometimes more likely in the Zoom.
I actually had to say Beaver emoji,
if you see Beaver emoji, that's
one of the ones I'm most proud of.
So that is actually
co-authored by a professor
here at Harvard who is both lesbian
and was married to a woman from Canada.
So it was very important to her
to get the Beaver emoji passed.
And she promised me it would always
be the first line of her bio.
And indeed, if you go
to her Twitter handle.
It's like Joan Donovan, creator
of the Beaver emoji, comma,
is Head of Research at the Shorenstein
Center at the Harvard Kennedy School.
It's pretty impressive.
And then we did greens.
Actually greens was really
interesting because people,
this was also like a
generational, cultural thing.
People were like, why do we need greens?
We have salad.
And I was like, we're Chinese.
We don't eat raw greens because
like you don't know where it's been
or if it's clean.
So we cook our greens so salad
is not something that we have.
So eventually I got my greens
and so that was kind of fun.
And then so these were some of the
people who sort of have contributed
to our little Emojination things,
including a number of Native Americans
who help get feather.
So why do I care?
So part of it is because I'm Chinese.
I grew up speaking Chinese
and English at the same time.
And it's really interesting to see
like Chinese and English characters
in terms of emoji and
Chinese together, right.
So this is fire.
You have fire characters and
now you have the emoji things.
And it kind of shows that there is
a longevity in the human experience
of something that was designed for
4,000 years ago has the same visual cues
in the human experiences as now.
So mouth, tree, moon, sun.
They can mix and match
them, which is super fun.
So two trees kind of make
a forest, oops, sorry.
Oh well.
And then the moon and sun together
means bright, which I like.
I like this one.
So if you stop and you
think about this, so this
is basically a pig under a roof.
And what does that mean?
It does not mean farm
as you might think.
It actually means home or family.
So in the Chinese kind of
structure and outlook on the view,
it's like where you keep your pigs
is actually where your home is
and what your farm is.
So it gets kind of weird
in all kinds of ways.
So one of my favorite radicals,
so this character means woman, me.
And as I was learning Chinese, you
kind of notice like how it shows up.
So this is a woman underneath a roof
and you're like oh it means mom or wife
or whatever like home.
It does not.
It means peace, because things are
at home when the woman is or things
are at peace when the woman
is at home underneath a roof,
which I always thought
was little bit odd.
Then there is also woman plus child.
So you're like oh, and actually
specifically boy child.
The connotation there
is a little bit unclear.
So you're like a woman plus
child, family, mom, whatever.
It is not.
It means good.
So the standard for goodness in ancient
China was a woman who had a male child.
So that kind of just like
kind of irked me growing up.
And then three women together
means evil which is very Macbeth.
This character means greed.
This character means slave.
This marriage, let's see I
think this one is jealousy
and this means adultery or betrayal.
So like definitely not
loving the way women
were portrayed on the emoji keyboard.
So in case you're
wondering, we just came out
with a kids book called "Hanmoji" that
kind of compares emoji and Chinese.
And I think they sent
a whole bunch of books
so that you guys can do some kind
of contests like later on with CS50.
So but the mixing and matching
is really interesting.
For example, the skin tones are
actually the same yellow character
plus a layer of skin
tone on top of that.
So I kind of took my
lessons from Chinese
in terms of seeing how
things can combine.
So there's something that you
should know about, which is ZWJ.
This is also an invisible
emoji character.
It stands for zero with joiner.
And it was actually
originally created for I
think Arabic where you would
basically kind of force something
to have be in the beginning of
a word or an end of the word
by kind of having this
invisible character.
So the rainbow flag for example is
actually a rainbow plus the white flag.
And we could have all
kinds of fun combinations.
If you look at polar
bear, it actually is,
if you have an older device
where it breaks apart,
it is bear plus snow
which is really cute.
It was originally, I
had bear plus white,
and then we decided that bear
plus snow made a lot more sense.
So another one, this is
new, I think you guys
should have it if you've updated
your phones in the last year or so.
So mending heart is heart plus band-aid.
What is this one?
Oh, this is interesting.
There was a breastfeeding
woman for a long time
and people felt like there
was not gender parity.
It was actually really interesting,
all the people who wrote in and were
like I want to be a dad showing
that I'm holding my baby.
Why is there only a
woman holding my baby?
So we kind of created a whole set.
So this is man plus bottle.
Ta-dah.
And so this is an-- all
of these occupations
are actually oftentimes a
woman plus, like the fried egg
or like a school or a tractor and
that's how you got the occupations.
If you send an emoji over into an older
system, sometimes it'll break apart.
So one of my kind of favorite kind
of contributions in this world
is interracial couple emoji
which we did with Tinder
which is super fun because then you
could have different couples that
are, and like so many [INAUDIBLE].
This is a fun, if you guys ever have
to do a [? combinatoric ?] test.
This is really fun because
you have to genders
plus a third like neutral
gender plus two people
plus five skin tones plus yellow, like
how many emoji couples can you come up
with when you introduce this factor.
So this is-- and underneath
it, it's just a ZWJ sequence,
it's like two people standing
together that are like glued together.
Now this actually gets interesting
from a CS50 perspective because
in many cases, even though you only
see one character underneath the hood
depending on how your
system works, they're
counting each one of these
as an individual character.
So your string length actually
might be five instead of one.
And this kind of became a
problem with things like Twitter
where things had a hard skin length.
So gender inclusivity is
actually one of the things
that we've been dealing most
with in the last couple of years.
So it's kind of interesting
if you think about both
what a pictorial language
looks like versus
the abstractness of a spoken language.
So because we had boy and we had girl.
But there was no way
to say generic child.
Like if you were, you want to say
child, you had to pick a boy or a girl,
but not a way to say
just some little person.
And that's really key
because in English at least
there is no gender implied by child.
So how do we mimic that?
And also is key for something like
doctor, right, doctor and teacher.
Those don't have gender
implied, but when
we have them on the
emoji keyboard, you'd
pick a male teacher or a
female doctor or whatnot.
So there was actually a guy at Adobe
who considers himself non-gender binary
also the man behind the orange heart.
He fought and got basically the first
three non-gender, the non-gender binary
emoji.
So child, adult, and the older adults.
So those are creative.
And then we started
having to propagate them
through actually all the occupations.
So these are the gender neutral
versions of many of those.
But then we got into
this whole thing where
every emoji that had a gender
originally had to be mirrored.
So originally we had bearded
man, and then we're like, OK,
well we actually have
to get bearded woman.
So that is on your keyboard.
There is pregnant woman.
There is now pregnant
man, which is interesting.
There is woman in a bridal gown.
There is now man in a bridal gown.
And then there were ones
that actually had to be
created that were neither man or woman.
So this is a merperson.
So there was merman, there's
mermaid and there was merperson.
It was really interesting
to figure out, how
do you draw a gender neutral merperson.
Like a bunch of them in
the beginning actually
had the arms crossed around the chest.
Monarch, so there was prince and
princess, and now there is monarch.
And one of my favorite actually
is there was Santa Claus
and there was Mrs. Claus
and now there's Mx.
Claus.
Like the name of this
character literally in Unicode
is Mx Claus so I feel like it's
sort of like a very official
enshrining of gender
non-binaryness in like the world.
Not everyone loved it.
New York Post did not
love this, like we're
cutting of into like emoji woke wars.
So some emoji stats for you.
This is very fascinating.
This is sort of like the
general distribution.
By far, the single
emoji that you use more
than anything else is the
face with tears of joy,
about 10% of all emoji
sent is that one character.
And the number two is heart, red
heart, and then it kind of goes down.
So there's a frequency of emoji use.
This is sort of done
by order of magnitude.
So 1 is 1/2 of 2.
2 is 1/2 of 1 so duh, duh.
It's really interesting.
It's a very, very steep drop off
after the first couple in case
you ever want to go on to the
emoji kind of Unicode website,
you too can see all
the frequency things.
So I think it's really funny.
So basically if it's
green going this way,
it increased in usage
between 2019 and 2021.
And it's red going this way, it drop.
And so pleading face, which is a
relatively new emoji, just sort of
shot up on the charts.
And whereas actually like
smiley face with heart eyes
actually kind of slipt
which is interesting.
So we just closed our emoji
proposal around for 2022.
These were the breakdowns.
People love submitting smileys and
food and beverages, animals and nature.
I mean, these are very googly colors.
So what is the future of emoji?
I will tell you because we just
had a meeting two weeks ago
so I can now publicly talk about it.
So historically, there
was this whole idea
like Unicode doesn't want to be
in the world of like encoding
glyphs for like devices everywhere.
There was very controversial
when I started doing that,
because mostly what Unicode used to
do was you take an existing language.
It could be done, you know and then
it would just take it and digitize.
It took languages that existed
and just digitized them.
And then when it kind of wandered
into emoji world, suddenly
it's like deciding what deserves to be
like an emoji decides to be digitized.
So trying to get out of it and they have
proposals over time or it's like, oh,
maybe we should like come up with a way
to send pictures back and forth where
you it's a fixed
picture and you like use
a hash so that we would look
at the picture and then go
do a lookup somewhere.
That did not go over well.
Then there was actually a really
interesting proposal I kind
of like, didn't go over well, which is
using something called a queue ID which
is in the Wikipedia world.
So in Wikipedia world, items all have
numbers across the different language
Wikipedia.
So Obama, human, Earth,
they will have an ID number,
so that the page in English and the
page in German the page in Chinese
all know that they're
pointing to the same thing.
So the question, so one idea
came up, like why don't we
use the numbering system so we can use
like Eiffel tower and see the number
and then like, oh, people know like
oh you're, trying to say Eiffel tower.
That did not go over well.
So both of those proposals
seem dead as of yet.
And it's too bad because
you'll see what's happening.
So what's coming in 2022?
So these are the emoji that
I actually sort of thought
they would be on your phones by
now because we're in mid-November
and they usually update early November.
So three more hearts.
People love hearts.
Wing, blackbird, goose, birds
also, purple flowers, jellyfish,
moose face donkey, donkey
was a bit late for the kind
of elections, ginger, peapod, wireless,
khanda, shaking face, folding hand
fans.
That one was interesting because
when people first proposed it,
they proposed it as like an
electric fan and that didn't--
who knows what electric fans
will look like in 100 years?
Because the thing is, once
an emoji, always an emoji.
They never retire.
So they're always looking for things
that have a long visual longevity,
floppy disk, do not actually do that.
So there's always like, we
don't want another floppy disk.
And then hair pick is interesting.
So there was a whole debate about
how to convey like Afro African hair,
like the curly hair that they
introduced a couple of years
ago is supposed to do that.
And most of the vendors actually have it
in a sort of Afro way except for Apple.
So there's a lot of complaints.
But hair pick was sort
of an interesting way.
It means both comb but also has sort
of an interesting historic connotation,
and it's been around
for about 2,00 years.
A couple of music things,
maracas and flute.
Beyond 2022, one of the things that's
going to die, oops, can I go back?
No, I can't.
Oh well, we're going to
retire the family emoji.
They didn't go over so well.
There were so many of them.
It's combinatorically if you had all
the everything in all the races all,
the races, all because
you wanted to have
skin tones, because
you didn't want imply
that families can only be one race.
It was such a ordeal.
Essentially, we're all like, no one
uses them, and there are so many.
And it's like the fonts
like in terms of the load
is like too large so they're just going
to make them all into like basically
little like bathroom symbol type folks.
So I think that is,
those will disappear.
What's actually really interesting about
the family emoji is they had gay fam.
When they introduced the family
emoji, they had gay family emoji,
and the Russian government went berserk.
And actually you can Google this in
2015, you'll see a bunch of articles
about the Russian government considering
it homosexual propaganda to use.
And there was a big debate
about whether or not
they were going to ban Apple devices.
And so you can see a lot of the
media coverage from that time.
But I thought it was really interesting
how upset a national government can get
about little pictures on your phone.
Another thing that's on the
agenda as of a couple of weeks ago
is directionality in terms of emoji.
So as you know, most emoji kind
of just flip one way or another.
And the reason why it matters
is because not all languages
run in the same direction.
So for example, Arabic.
So we're used to left to right, but
a lot of languages go right to left.
So and kind of changes
the meaning of emoji.
For example, right to
left, I send this a lot
to my friends when I'm going flying
from the Bay Area to New York.
If you do it from left to right,
however, that is what it looks like.
So it looks like you're in a
Bay Area but the plane is still
going that kind of up and to the right.
And then now it looks like you're
going from New York to the Bay Area.
The other place is like, oh, it's a
girl, and she's running really fast.
Right.
That is right to left in our
world, wait left to right, sorry.
Sorry, that was supposed
to be left to right.
And in here it would be she's like
behind like pollution or something
like that.
So sorry about--
So an example, this is
actually in the proposal.
Like in one case, if it's
left or right, you're
running away from a line of cars.
And the other one, it's a warning
to not run behind car fumes.
So they are trying to figure out, how
do we mirror a bunch of the emoji.
But the main thing that I think sort of,
I don't know when it's going to happen,
I'm really hopeful
it's going to happen is
trying to come up with a system that
supports little stickers in line that
don't need Unicode.
So this is like Slack or on Twitch,
you can embed little pictures in line,
and all the vendors have to get
together and agree to come up
with a standard way to do that.
They'd have not yet come up with that,
but that is sort of one of the ways
that Unicode is like
it wants to back away
from actually being
like a global regulator
for like little colorful glyphs.
And so if you ever need to
reach me in my emoji world,
you can find me jenny@emojination.org.
There will be-- it will be actually
a while I think before we see
a next generation of emoji showing up.
It used to be like every year,
they would get new code points.
It might be a little
bit less than every year
now as they work on things
like directionality over time.
If anyone has questions,
you can ask questions.
You can find me afterwards.
I think I feel like there's supposed
to be some hubbub right now about maybe
microphones but maybe not.
But maybe I'm just done.
And if there are questions or
if David is around, I'm happy.
I'm happy to have to answer
any questions that folks have.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Hi.
Yes.
I was wondering what were your
thoughts on The Emoji Movie.
JENNIFER 8.
LEE: So the question is, what are
my thoughts on The Emoji Movie.
You're talking about
the Sony animated one?
Yes.
My thought on that is it is better
than a 6% rating on Rotten Tomatoes
would lead you to believe.
So that's my one thought.
And my next thought is that was a rush
job from an animation perspective.
That was about 18 months,
whereas a typical animated movie
takes four years.
So in my spare time, I also
produce movies and documentaries.
So one thing that is key to know
about movies and animated movies,
and this is very important.
They take a very long time,
but you can always fix it,
because you haven't shot anything.
And a very good example of that is
I assume you guys have seen Frozen.
If you haven't seen-- you seem of the
age that you would have seen Frozen.
I do not understand how
huge and a phenomenon or why
was such a huge phenomenon.
But they actually did an
original cut of Frozen and it--
So I don't know if you guys
know the Snow Queen thing,
but she's like super dark and not fun
and kind of evil and not someone you
want to get behind as a character.
So they actually did sort of
a rough cut of that of Frozen.
And they came out of that
with, it is just storyboarding.
They're like, that is not good.
And they killed it.
So they were like, we
can't go with this and then
started from scratch more or
less again, starting with a song.
"Let it Go," which is
actually written by a kid
from my elementary school, Bobby
Lopez, or co-written by Bobby Lopez.
I also-- actually fun
fact, I also went, I
would take the school bus
with a Lin-Manuel Miranda.
So I was a fourth grader when
he was like a kindergartener.
So we had a very musical
elementary school in New York City.
But the thing is, they could fix
it because they had enough time
and have enough money,
not like movies where
you shoot humans, much harder to fix.
You have the footage that you have,
and you can do little pickups,
but you can't fix it.
So essentially what happened in
that case, I think it's 18 months,
and it could have gotten better.
And a lot of the movies that you
see with Pixar, like it's very--
it's actually sort of emotionally
similar to the movie called Inside Out.
.
They just had more time,
and so it's better, so
as opposed to 18 months which is not
long enough to make an animated movie.
But the other fun thing is, it was so
weird because they sold sponsorships.
It was like, oh my God, here
comes the bots and the malware.
Let's go into Dropbox
and protect ourselves.
And so I think that it got
a lot of bad kind of vibes
from the press for
doing things like that.
But from a kid's perspective, it's fine.
I think if--
I don't know that I would put it
on my top 10 of animated pictures,
but it's better than
6% on Rotten Tomatoes.
And then actually if you guys
ever care, we have done--
I did a documentary about
emoji so and all the people
that helped create emoji.
And we did a CS50x movie night,
I think during the pandemic?
Was it during the pandemic?
Everything is sort of
like blurred together,
but it was during the pandemic.
Yeah.
More questions?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Hi.
I wanted to know that you mentioned
that one of the criteria for having
an emoji accepted is that it's popular.
How do determine whether--
JENNIFER 8.
LEE: Where there's demand, yeah.
AUDIENCE: Whether there's demand.
How do you determine demand?
Is it based on whether
or not [INAUDIBLE]??
JENNIFER 8.
LEE: Yeah, that's a very good question.
Yeah, so the question is
one of the proposals--
One of our criteria is of
getting an emoji accepted
is to try to demonstrate demand
and how do we demonstrate demand?
And I would say in a pretty
clumsy way actually at this point.
So the main thing that you have
in our current proposal process
is we have a median
emoji, which is elephant.
So elephant is like, you stack
ranked all the emoji for popularity,
elephant is like [CLICKS]
right there in the middle.
And it's also a concept
that's universally
understood across all languages.
So elephant shows up somewhere
between 500 million and 700 million
in Google search results, like
if you type it into a laptop,
you'll see elephant, 500
million search results.
And generally, you're trying to-- when
you're comparing your term to elephant,
you want to see very roughly how many
Google search results, Bing search
results, sometimes Instagram.
So actually something that
was really surprising to me
was someone proposed hummingbird.
I think hummingbird is a good proposal.
But if you look at hummingbird,
it's only like 21 million
in terms of the stats, so which I
thought was like very surprisingly low.
So that's one of the main ways that
we kind of see like, is it also
visually used and all of that.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
Are we good?
I didn't even need my water or anything.
Oh, can-- I'm going to take a picture.
I'm going to take a picture for
because now you guys are actually
human and not Muppets, so I'm
very, very excited about this.
So I will send this to my
block mates and be like, I just
lectured at CS50 in Sanders Theatre.
DAVID J. MALAN: My thanks to Jenny Lee.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
Yeah, you can stay up here if you want.
Give me one second.
So if up until now, thought it
would be appropriate to toss this up
on the board.
If up until now, you've not yet gotten
CS50 stress ball on the way out,
please do grab one.
We got some extras as
well off to the side.
But I would also keep
in mind, back in week 0,
where again we began, we asked
you to categorize yourselves
as to whether you are among those less
comfortable, those more comfortable,
or those somewhere in between.
Please know now that you
are officially all some--
Please know now that you were all
officially among those more comfortable
and indeed even though a couple
of more milestones await,
we cannot wait to see what you
accomplish with your final projects.
In the meantime, as always
this is and now this was CS50.
[APPLAUSE]
[HARMONICA]
ALL: (SINGING) Bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum.
Mr. Sandman, when I enrolled in CS50.
I'll say, truth be told, I
thought I'd be a real coding hero,
because I did so well on p-set 07.
It picked up so fast.
Turns out the C is harder than scratch.
Hello, world and goodbye
sleep because this is CS50.
Bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum.
Mr. Sandman, I was on
the [? fall grind, ?]
trying so hard to not fall behind,
attending section and wanting a tutor,
stuck in the entry point of my computer.
Sandman, finally getting ahead.
They would switch us to Python instead.
Why we spend five weeks
on C because this is CS50.
Bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum.
Mr. Sandman, we completed each task.
JavaScript SQL, CSS and Flask.
With every language,
our minds had to reset.
Don't get us started
on that finance p-set.
Sandman, now I return.
My friends asked if I would do it again.
I replied, obviously,
because this was CS,
no more p-sets because this was CS-fif
bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum,
bum, bum, T.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]