SPEAKER 1: In this
lab, your task is going
to be to write a program to
simulate population growth.
Let's imagine that we have a population
of animals, a population of llamas,
for example.
Every year, we lose some animals from
that population as older llamas die.
But we also gain some animals to that
population as new llamas are born.
We can model this kind of population
growth using a mathematical formula.
Let's assume, for
example, that every year,
if we have a population of n llamas,
we gain n divided by 3 llamas
and we lose n divided by 4 llamas.
So in a population of 12 llamas,
for example, in the next year,
we would gain 12 divided
by 3, or four new llamas.
And we would lose at 12 divided by 4,
or losing three llamas, in that case.
Given this setup, we could
ask ourselves a question.
For example, we could ask,
how many years would it
take to go from 20
llamas in a population
to 30 llamas in a population?
Right now for example, we have
20 llamas in this population.
But after one year we would
gain 20 divided by 3 llamas.
Now notice here that 20 doesn't
divide evenly into three.
And as a result, we
need to just truncate
whatever would come after the decimal.
The actual answer is going
to be six point something.
But because we can't have
a fraction of an animal,
we're just going to truncate
whatever is after the decimal
and say that we're gaining six llamas.
And we're going to lose 20 divided by
4, which nicely equals five llamas.
So after one year, we
will now have 21 llamas.
We can then repeat the
process and consider
what might happen in the next year.
In the next year, we would gain
21 divided by 3, or seven llamas.
And we would lose 21 divided
by 4, truncating whatever is
after the decimal, losing five llamas.
Meaning we have a net
change of two llamas.
Which means that after two
years, we now have 23 llamas.
After the next year, we
would gain seven llamas,
lose five, for a new total of
25 llamas after three years.
In the next year, we
would gain eight llamas
and lose six, for a new total
of 27 llamas after four years.
And then in the fifth year,
we would gain at nine llamas
and lose six for a total now
of 30 llamas after five years.
So the answer to the question,
how many years would it
take to go from a population of 20
llamas to a population of 30 llamas
is five years.
Now we did all of that math manually.
But your task now is going to
be to write a program in C that
can do that calculation for us.
The program will work like this.
At the command line, you'll
run a program, ./population.
And at that point, your
program should prompt the user
for a starting population size.
You might type of starting
population size of 100, for example.
Then your program should prompt the
user for an ending population size.
And the user will type in another
population size, say 200, for example.
Then your program should
figure out how many years
it would take to bring the population
of llamas from the starting size
to the ending size, and then
print out that number of years.
So in this case, our
program would print years
colon 9 because it would
take nine years to bring
the population from 100 to 200.
So in summary, here's
what you have to do.
First, start by prompting the
user for the starting population
size of your population of llamas.
And you should check to make sure that
the user's input is at least nine.
The population size
needs to be at least nine
so that we can actually start to
grow this population of llamas.
So if the user types in a
number that's less than nine,
you should keep re-prompting
the user to type in a number
again until they give you a
number that's at least nine.
Next, you should prompt the user
for the ending population size,
here making sure that
the user's input is
at least as large as the starting size.
It wouldn't make sense, for example,
to imagine the population going
from a population of 100
to a population of 50
because the population is
always going to be growing.
So you'll want to make sure
that the end population
size is greater than or equal
to the starting population size.
If the user tries to
type in an end population
size that is less than the
starting population size,
then your program should
continually re-prompt the user
to type in another
ending population size
until they provide you one that is at
least the starting population size.
After that, your
program should calculate
how many years would
be required to bring
the population from the starting
size to the ending size,
recalling that every year we are
going to add n divided by 3 llamas,
if there are n llamas to begin with.
And we're going to lose
n divided by 4 llamas.
And as with before, because we
can't have fractions of a llama,
if either of those computations ends
up with something after the decimal,
you're going to truncate or ignore
what comes after that decimal
when doing your math.
Finally, after you've
made that calculation,
you'll print the number
of years required.
Printing years colon and
then the number of years
that would be required to
bring the population up
to that ending population size.
As you start working
on this problem, there
are a few strategies
that might prove helpful.
One is a do while loop,
a type of loop that
lets you prompt the user one or more
times for something, in this case.
So in the loop you're seeing here, we
start by declaring a variable called n.
And then inside of a loop, we prompt
the user for a positive integer,
storing that integer inside of n.
But we're going to keep repeating
that loop as long as n is less than 1.
Meaning if the user doesn't
type in a positive integer,
then we're going to
prompt the user again.
You won't use this exact
code inside of your lab
but you might use
something similar, both
when you're prompting for
the starting population size
to make sure that the starting
population size is at least nine,
and also when prompting
for the end population size
to make sure that the end
population size is at least as
large as the starting population size.
You might also find it
helpful to update a variable
as you go about working on this lab.
You might want to repeatedly update
your population size variable,
for example, in order to add new
llamas and get rid of older llamas.
You might do that using
a formula like this.
If you have a variable called n inside
of which is your current population,
you can update the value
of n for the next year
using a line that says n equals n
plus n over 3, the number of llamas
we're adding, minus n over
4, the number of llamas
that we're losing in
that particular year.
And finally, once you've
completed the calculation,
you can print out a variable using
the print f function, saying,
printf years colon, and then %i, we're
%i is going to stand in for an integer.
Which Integer Well, that
you specify after a comma.
And here we're saying,
print out the value of n
as the integer to print to the user.
Let's now take a look
at the distribution code
that we give you as a starting
point for this problem.
Here in population.c, we've already
included cs50.h and stdio.h for you.
And then giving you a main function
with a few to dos to get started.
You're going to first prompt for the
start size, then prompt for the n size.
Then calculate how many years
it's going to take in order
to reach that threshold value
from the start size to the n size.
And then finally, once
you've done that computation,
printing out the number of
years that would be required
to take you from the start to the end.
Once you've written all
of those pieces, you
should then be able to compile
your program and then run it,
giving your program a starting
population size and an ending
population size.
And then your program
should be able to tell you
how long it will take to get from
point A to point B. My name is Brian.
And this was population growth.