[FILM REEL]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, this is CS50.
And this is Week 3 already, wherein
we'll take a look back actually
at Week 0 where we first began.
And in Week 0, recall that everything
was very intuitive, in a sense.
We talked not just about representation
of information, but algorithms.
And we talked about tearing
a phone book again and again.
And that somehow got us
to a better solution.
But today, we'll try to start
formalizing some of those ideas
and capturing some of those same
ideas not in pseudocode just
yet, but in actual code as well.
But we'll also consider the
efficiency of those algorithms,
like just how good, how well-designed
our algorithms actually are.
And if you recall, when we
did the phone book example
wherein I first had an algorithm
searching one page at a time,
and then second one two pages
at a time, and then third,
started tearing the
thing in half, recall
that we, with a wave of the hand,
kind of analyzed it as follows.
We proposed that if the x-axis
here is the size of the problem,
like number of pages in a phone book,
and the y-axis is the time required
to solve the problem
in seconds, minutes,
page tears, whatever
your unit of measure is,
recall that the first algorithm, which
is the straight line such that if you
had n pages in the phone book,
it might have this slope of n--
and there's this one-to-one
relationship between pages and tears.
Two pages at a time, of course,
was twice as fast, but still really
the same shape, the yellow
line here indicating that yeah,
it's n over 2, maybe plus 1 if you
have to double back, as we discussed.
But it's really still fundamentally
the same algorithm one
or two pages at a time.
But the third algorithm, recall,
was this one here in green,
where we called it logarithmic in
terms of how fast or how slow it was.
And indeed, the implication
of this algorithm
was that we could even double
the size of the phone book,
and no big deal-- one
additional page tear,
and we take yet another 1,000
page bite out of the phone book.
So today, we'll revisit some of
these ideas, formalize them a bit,
but also translate some of
them, ultimately, to code.
And all of that now
is possible because we
have this lower-level
understanding, perhaps, of what's
actually inside of your computer.
This, of course, is your
computer's RAM or memory.
And recall that if we start
to abstract this away,
your computer's memory is
really just a grid of bytes.
In fact, we don't have to
look at the hardware anymore.
And we looked at a grid of bytes like
this, whereby each of these bytes
could be used to store a char, an
int, a long, or even an entire string,
at that.
But let's focus perhaps
just on a subset of this
because last week, of
course, we emphasized,
really, arrays, storing
things in arrays.
And that allowed us to start
storing entire strings, sequences
of characters, and
even arrays of integers
if we wanted to have multiple ones and
not just multiple variables as well.
But the catch is that if you look inside
of an array in the computer's memory--
and for instance, suppose these
integers here are stored--
it's pretty easy for us
humans to glance at this
and immediately find the number 50.
You sort of have this bird's
eye view from where you're
seated of everything on the screen.
And so it's pretty obvious
how you get to the number 50.
But in the world of
computers, of course,
it turns out that this is hardware.
And computers, for today's purposes,
can only do one thing at a time.
They can't just take it all in and
find instantly some number like 50.
So perhaps a decent
metaphor is to consider
the array of memory
inside of your computer
really is a sequence of closed doors.
And if the computer wants to
find some value in an array,
it has to do the digital equivalent
of opening each of these doors one
at a time.
Now how can code do that?
Well, of course, we introduced
indices or indexes last week,
whereby we, by convention, call the
first element of an array location 0,
the second location 1, the third
location 2, and so forth-- so-called 0
indexed.
And this allowed us to now bridge
this conceptual world of what's
going on in memory with actual code,
because now we had this square bracket
syntax via which we could go searching
for something if we so choose.
And it turns out, if I now paint
these red instead of yellow,
it would seem that we actually have
a pretty good physical metaphor here
standing in place for what would
be a computer's array of memory
if, for instance, you're storing
some seven numbers like that.
And so today we begin with a look
of a specific type of algorithm.
That is for searching.
Searching is all over the place.
All of us have probably gone to
google.com or some equivalent already
multiple times per day.
And getting back answers fast
is what companies like Google
are really good at.
So how are they doing that?
How are they storing information
in computers' memory?
Well, let's consider
what this really is.
It's really just a problem
as it was back in Week 0.
The input, though, to
the problem, for now,
might be this array of seven lockers.
So that's the input to the problem,
inside of which is a number.
And maybe for simplicity now, we just
want a yes/no, a true/false answer--
a bool, that is to say--
of whether or not some number
like 50 is in that array.
It's not quite as fancy as Google.
That doesn't just tell you
yes, we have search results.
It actually gives you
the search results.
But for, now we'll keep
it simple, and just output
as part of this problem
yes or no, true or false,
we have found the number we're looking
for given an input like that array.
But it turns out inside of this black
box that we keep coming back to,
there's all sorts of
possible algorithms.
And we talked about this at a
high level conceptually in Week 0
with the phone book.
But today, let's consider
it a little more concretely
by way of a game that some of you might
have grown up with, namely Monopoly.
And so behind these doors,
it turns out, will be hidden
some denominations of monopoly money.
But for this, we now
have two volunteers.
If you'd like to greet the world?
JACKSON: Hi, I'm Jackson.
STEPHANIE: Hi, my name is Stephanie.
DAVID MALAN: And do you want
to say a little something
about yourselves-- years, house, dorm?
STEPHANIE: I'm a first
year living in Matthews.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
JACKSON: And I'm a
first year in Canaday.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
Well, welcome to our two volunteers.
So why don't we do this?
Would one of you like to
volunteer the other to go first?
STEPHANIE: I'll go.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
All right, so Stephanie's up first.
And behind one of these doors here,
we've hidden the monopoly money 50.
And so we'd like you to find the 50.
We'll tell you nothing
more about the lockers.
But we would like you to
execute a certain algorithm.
And in fact, I'm going to give
you some pseudocode for this.
And I'm going to give
you the name for it.
It's called linear search.
And as the name implies,
you're pretty much
going to end up walking in
sort of a straight line.
But how are you going to do this?
Well, let me propose that
in a moment, your first step
will be to think kind of like a loop.
For each door from left to right, what
do we want you to do on each iteration?
Well, if 50 is behind
that door, then we want
to go ahead and have you return true.
And hold up the 50 proudly,
if you will, for the group.
Otherwise, if you get
through that whole loop
and you haven't found the
number 50, you can just
throw up your hands in disappointment.
False-- you've not found the number 50.
So to be clear, step one is going to
be for each door from left to right.
How would you like to begin?
Yep.
Oh, and then-- yep.
There we go.
Yep.
And if you'd like to at least tell--
good, good acting here.
What have you found instead?
STEPHANIE: It's not 50, but 20.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, OK.
So step one was a fail.
So let's move on to step two.
Inside of this loop, what
are you going to do next?
STEPHANIE: I'm going to
move to the next door.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
STEPHANIE: Almost.
DAVID MALAN: OK, almost.
Sort of.
A 500 instead.
Next locker?
STEPHANIE: I would rather take that.
No.
DAVID MALAN: OK, we're
not telling the audience?
STEPHANIE: It was a 10.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so keep going.
This is step three now.
STEPHANIE: Oh, man.
DAVID MALAN: Five, OK.
A few more lockers to check.
STEPHANIE: A little sad, guys.
DAVID MALAN: All right,
second-to-last step.
STEPHANIE: It's 1.
Kind of close.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
And finally, the last step.
Clearly you've been,
perhaps, set up here.
STEPHANIE: Let's go!
DAVID MALAN: All right,
so the number 50.
And Stephanie, if I may, let
me ask you a question here.
So on the screen, this is the
pseudocode you just executed.
Suppose, though, I had
done what many of us
have gotten to the habit of doing
when you have an if condition.
You often have an else branch as well.
Suppose that I had done this now.
And I'm marking it in red
to be clear this is wrong.
But what would have been bad about
this code using an if and an else,
might you say?
Any instincts?
STEPHANIE: Then you
would end up canceling
the code before you found the 50.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
STEPHANIE: I mean, you'd
just be eternally sad.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
When Stephanie had opened the
first locker, she'd have found 20.
20, of course, is not 50.
She would have decreed false.
But of course, she hadn't checked
all of the rest of the lockers.
So that would seem to be a key
detail that, with this implementation
of the pseudocode, we actually
do go through-- as we did--
and only return false
not even with an else,
but just at the end of the loop such
that we only reach that line if we
don't return true earlier than that.
Well, let's go ahead and do this.
Let me take the mic from you.
If you'd like to take
a seat next to Jackson?
And Jackson, in just a moment,
we'll have you come up.
Carter, if you don't mind
reorganizing the lockers for us.
But in the meantime, let me
point out how we might now
translate that same idea to code.
Pretty high level, pretty
English-oriented with that pseudocode--
but really now, as of last week,
we have syntax via which Stephanie
and, soon, Jackson could treat this
locker, this set of lockers, as really
indeed an array using bracket notation.
So we can now get a little closer
in our pseudocode to actual code.
And the way a computer
scientist, for instance,
would translate fairly high
level English pseudocode
like this to something that's a
little closer to C or any language
that supports arrays would be a
little more cryptically like this.
But you'll see more of this
syntax in the coming days.
For i from 0 to n minus 1--
this is still pseudocode.
But that's the English-like
way of expressing what
we've known come to know as a for loop.
If 50 is behind doors bracket i-- so
I'm assuming for the sake of discussion
that doors, now, is the name of my
variable, this array of seven doors.
But then the rest of the logic,
the rest of the pseudocode
really is the same way.
And so you'll find in time that
programmers, computer scientists more
generally, when you start expressing
ideas, algorithms to someone else,
instead of maybe operating
at this level here,
you now have a new vocabulary,
really a new syntax
that you can be a little
more specific, not
getting so into the weeds
of writing actual C code,
but at least now doing something
that's a little closer to manipulating
an array like this.
So Jackson, would you
like to stand on up?
All right.
Yes, yes.
Support for Jackson here, too.
Nice.
And here now, I'm going to allow you an
assumption that Stephanie did not have.
Stephanie clearly was
really doing her best
searching from left to right using
linear search, as we'll now call it.
But they were pretty much
in a random order, right?
There was a 20 over there, there
was 1 over there, and then a 50.
So we deliberately jumbled things up
and did not sort the numbers for her.
But Carter kindly has just come
up to give you a leg up, Jackson,
by sorting the numbers in advance.
And we'd like you this
time, much like in week 0,
to do something again
and again, but this time
using what we'll now call binary search.
It's exactly the same algorithm
conceptually as we did in Week 0.
But if we translate it to
the context of this array,
we now might say something like this.
The first step for Jackson
might be to ask the question--
if 50 is behind the middle
door, where presumably he's
done some mental math to
figure out what the middle is,
then he's going to just return true.
And hopefully we'll get lucky
and 50 will be right there.
Of course, there's two other
possibilities at least,
which would be what?
50 is, with respect to these doors?
Yeah, so to the left or to
the right, alternatively.
So if 50 is less than the
middle door, then presumably,
Jackson's going to want to go left.
Else, if 50 is greater
than the middle door,
he's going to want to
go right, much like I
did physically last week
with the phone book,
dividing and conquering left to right.
But there's actually a fourth case.
Let's put it on the board first.
What else might happen here
that Jackson should consider?
Yeah.
Oh, it's not there.
So let me actually go back and amend my
pseudocode here and just say Jackson,
if we don't hand you any
doors at all, or eventually,
as he's dividing and conquering,
if he's left with no more doors,
we have to handle that situation
so that the behavior is defined.
All right, so with
that said, Jackson, do
you want to go ahead and
find us the number 50
and walk us through verbally
what you're doing and finding?
JACKSON: All right, so it looks
like this one is the middle door.
So I'm going to open it.
But it's 20, not 50.
DAVID MALAN: Aw.
What's going through your head now?
JACKSON: So now I'm looking--
because 50 is higher than 20,
I want to look to the right.
DAVID MALAN: Good.
JACKSON: And look for the new
middle door, which would be here.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
JACKSON: And it's 100--
bad.
But 50 is less than 100.
So now we to look left,
which would be here.
And ta-da.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
Very well done this time around, too.
So thank you, first,
to our volunteers here.
And in fact, since you're a fan
of Monopoly, as we're so informed,
we have the Cambridge
edition of Monopoly
with all your Harvard favorites.
JACKSON: No way.
DAVID MALAN: Here you go.
STEPHANIE: Thank you.
JACKSON: Thank you so much.
DAVID MALAN: Thank you to our
volunteers for finding us 50.
So-- that was more
popular than we expected.
So here, we can translate this
one more time into something
a little closer to code.
And again, still
pseudocode-- but here, now,
might be another formulation of
exactly what Jackson just did,
just using the
nomenclature now of arrays,
where you can be a little more
precise with your instructions
and still leave it to someone else
to translate this, finally, to code.
But here we have same
question at the beginning.
If no doors left, return false.
If 50 is behind doors bracket middle--
so I'm assuming here,
because this is pseudocode--
that somewhere I've done the
mental math or the actual math
to figure out what the
index of middle is.
For instance, if these are
seven doors in an array,
this would be location
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
So somehow I've taken the
total number of doors, 7,
divided by 2 to find the middle.
That's 3 and 1/2.
We have to deal with rounding.
But suffice it to say there's a
well-defined formula for finding
the middle index.
Given the total number of lockers,
divide by 2 and then round accordingly.
So that's presumably what
Jackson did just by counting
or in his head to find us door number 3.
Not the third door, the 4th
door, but door bracket 3.
So this is just saying if 50 is behind
doors bracket middle, return true.
That was not the case.
He found a $20 bill instead.
Else, if 50 is less than the
doors bracket middle, go ahead--
and now it gets interesting-- search
doors 0 through doors middle minus 1.
So it's getting a little
more into the weeds now.
But if middle is 3, this one
here, what we want to now
have Jackson search if 50 had been--
if the number had been less,
we want to start at bracket 0
and go up through this one.
And we deliberately
subtract 1 because what's
the point of looking in
the same locker again?
We might as well do 0
through middle minus 1.
Else if 50 is greater than doors
bracket middle, which it was,
what did we then do?
So Jackson intuitively searched
for doors middle plus 1
through doors n minus 1.
And honestly, it gets a little annoying
having the pluses and minuses here.
But just think of what it means.
This is the middle door.
And Jackson then did proceed to
search through doors middle plus 1
because there's no point in
searching this one again.
And then the last element
in any array of size n
where n is just our go-to number for the
size is always going to be n minus 1.
It's not going to be n.
It's going to be n minus 1 because
we always start counting arrays at 0.
So here then we have a translation
into pseudocode that's a little closer
to C of this exact same idea.
And here, we come full circle to Week 0.
In Week 0, it was pretty intuitive
to imagine dividing and conquering
a problem like this.
But if you now think back to actual
your iPhone, your Android phone,
or the like, when you're doing
autocomplete and searching the list,
it's possible, if you don't have
many friends or family or colleagues
in the phone, you know what?
Linear search, just checking every name
for the person you're searching for,
might be perfectly fine.
But odds are your phone's being
smarter than that, especially if you
start to have dozens, hundreds,
thousands of people in your contacts
over the years.
What would be better than linear search?
Well, perhaps binary search.
But, but, but-- there's an assumption,
a requirement, which is what?
Why was Jackson ultimately able
to find the 50 in just three steps
instead of a full seven, like Stephanie?
Because the array was sorted.
And so this is sort of a teaser for what
we'll have to come back to later today.
Well, how much effort did
it take someone like Carter?
How much effort does it
take your phone to sort all
of those names and numbers in advance?
Because maybe it's not actually
worth the amount of time.
Now someone like Google probably somehow
keeps the database of web pages sorted.
You can imagine it being super slow if,
when you type in cats or something else
into google.com, if they searched
linearly over their entire data set.
Ideally, they're doing something
a little smarter than that.
So we'll formalize, now,
exactly this kind of analysis.
And it's not going to be so much
mathy as it still will be intuitive.
But we'll introduce you to
some jargon, some terminology
that most any programmer or
computer scientists might use
when analyzing their own algorithms.
Let's formalize now what
this kind of analysis is.
So right now, I claim binary
search better than linear search.
But how much better and why, exactly?
Well, it all comes back
to this kind of graph.
So this, recall, is how we analyzed
the phone book back in Week 0.
And recall that, indeed, we had
these formulas, rough formulas that
described the running time
of those three algorithms--
one page at a time, two
pages at a time, and then
tearing the thing again
and again in half.
And precisely, if you counted up
the number of pages I was touching
or the number of pages
I was tearing, it's
fair to say that the first
algorithm, in the worst case,
might have taken n total pages.
It didn't because I was
searching for John Harvard
at the time, which is somewhat
early in the alphabet.
But if I were searching for
someone with the last name of Z,
I would have had to keep going
and going, in the worst case,
through all n pages.
Not as bad for the second algorithm,
and that's why we do n divided by 2.
And even that's a bit of a white lie.
It's probably n divided by 2 plus
1 in case I have to double back.
But again, I'm sort of
doing this more generally
to capture the essence of these things.
And then we really got into
the weeds with like log base
2 event for that third
and final algorithm.
And at the time, we claimed any time
you're dividing something in half,
in half, in half, odds are there's going
to be some kind of logarithm involved.
And we'll see that today.
But today, we're going to actually start
using computer science terminology.
And we're going to formalize
this imprecision, if you will.
We are not going to care, generally,
about exactly how many steps
some algorithm takes because that's
not going to be that enlightening,
especially if maybe you have a faster
computer tomorrow than you did today.
It wouldn't really be fair to
compare numbers too precisely.
We really want to, with the wave of
a hand, just get a sense of roughly
how slow or how fast an algorithm is.
So the notation here is deliberate.
That is literally a capital O,
often italicized, refer to as big O.
And so the first algorithm
is in big O of n.
The second algorithm is in
big O of n divided by 2.
The third algorithm is in
big O of log base 2 of n.
But even that is kind
of unnecessary detail.
When using big O notation, you
really don't care about, we'll see,
the smaller order terms.
We're not going to care about the
divided by 2 because you know what?
The shape of these algorithms
are is almost the same.
And really, the idea-- the algorithm
itself is sort of fundamentally
the same.
Instead of one page at
a time, I'm doing two.
But if you throw millions of
pages, billions of pages at me,
those algorithms are really going to
kind of perform the same as n gets
really large, goes off toward infinity.
And the same is true for logarithms.
Even if you're a little
rusty, it turns out
that whether you do the math with
log base 2, log base 3, log base 10,
you can just multiply one by the
other to really get the same formula.
So this is only to say a computer
scientist would generally
say that the first two algorithms
are on the order of n steps.
The third algorithm is on
the order of log n steps.
And we don't really care precisely
what we mean beyond that.
And this big O notation, as we'll
see-- and actually, let me zoom out.
If you can imagine suddenly
making the x-axis much longer--
so more pages on the screen at once--
it is indeed going to be
the shapes of these curves
that matter, because imagine in
your mind's eye as you zoom out,
zoom out, zoom out, zoom out, and
as n gets much, much, much bigger
on the x-axis, the red
and the yellow line
are essentially going to look the
same once n is sufficiently large.
But the green line is never
going to look the same.
It's going to be a
fundamentally different shape.
And so that's the
intuition of big O, to get
a sense of these rates
of performance like this.
So here, then, is big
O. Here is, perhaps,
a cheat sheet of the common formulas
that a computer scientist, certainly
in an introductory context, might
use when analyzing algorithms.
And let's consider for a moment
which of our first two algorithms--
linear search and binary search--
fall into these categories.
So I've ordered them from slowest
to fastest, so order of n squared.
It's not something
we've actually seen yet,
but it tends to be slow
because it's quadratic.
You're doing n times n.
That's got to add up to a lot of steps.
Better today is going to be n log n.
Even better is going to be n.
Even better than that is log n.
And best is so-called
order of 1, like one step
or maybe two steps,
maybe even 1,000 steps,
but a fixed, finite number of steps that
never changes no matter how big n is.
So given this chart, just
to be clear, linear search--
let's consider the worst case.
In the worst case, how many steps
did it take someone like Stephanie
to find the solution to the problem,
assuming not seven doors but n doors?
Yeah?
So on the order of n.
And in this case, it's exactly n.
But you know what, maybe it's
arguably 2n because it took Stephanie
a couple of steps.
She had to lift the latch.
She had to open the door.
Maybe it's three steps.
She had to show the money.
So now it's 3n, 2n.
But we don't really care
about that level of precision.
We really just care about the
fundamental number of operations.
So we'll say yes, on the order of n.
So that might be an upper bound,
we'll call this, for linear search.
And how about binary search?
In Jackson's case, or in general,
me in Week 0, if there's n doors,
how many steps did it take
Jackson or me using binary search?
In this case, it was literally three.
But that's not a formula.
Yeah so it's on the order of log n.
And indeed, if there are
seven doors, well, that's
almost eight, if you just
do a little bit of rounding.
And indeed, if you take log base 2
of 8, that does actually give us 3.
So the math actually checks out.
And if you're not comfortable
with logarithms, no big deal.
Just think about it intuitively.
Logarithm of base 2 is just
dividing something again and again.
So on this chart, when we
consider big O, which to be clear,
allows you to describe the order
of an algorithm's running time--
like the magnitude of it-- but it
also describes, more specifically,
an upper bound.
So in the worst case,
for instance, these
are pretty good measures of how good--
or rather, of how bad--
linear search and
binary search might be.
Why?
Well, suppose you're searching
a 1,000-page phonebook
and the person's name starts with Z.
The algorithm is still going to be
on the order of n steps.
Why?
Because it might take you as
many as all n steps to find it.
Now that's not necessarily going
to be the case in practice.
If I use big O as an
upper bound, well, it
would be nice if there's a
corresponding lower bound,
especially if you want to consider not
just worst cases, but maybe best cases.
So what might we use here?
Well, this is a capital
Greek omega symbol.
So omega is the symbol that a
computer scientist uses generally
to describe a lower
bound on an algorithm,
often in the context of best
case, though not necessarily.
So a lower bound means how few
steps might an algorithm take?
And here, too, same formulas.
And we'll fill in
these blanks over time.
Some algorithms might always take
a minimum of n squared steps,
or on the order of n steps.
Some might only take n log
n, or n, or log n, or 1.
So something like a linear search--
when Stephanie started
with linear search,
she didn't get lucky this time on stage.
But what if she had, and the
first door she opened were 50?
How might you then describe
the lower bound on linear
search in this so-called best case,
using this list of possible answers?
Yeah?
Yeah, so omega of 1.
So in the best case, the
lower bound on how many steps
it might take linear search to find
something might just be one step.
Why?
Because maybe if
Stephanie had gotten lucky
and we had prefilled these lockers
with the numbers in some other order
such that she might have opened
the first locker, and voila,
the number 50 could have been
there, so a lower bound arguably
could indeed be omega
of 1 for linear search.
And how about now for Jackson?
He used binary search.
So he dived right into
the middle of the problem.
But what would be a lower bound
on binary search using this logic?
Yeah?
Yeah, so again, omega of 1.
Why?
Because maybe he just gets lucky.
And indeed, right in the middle of the
lockers could have been the number 50.
It wasn't.
And so more germane in
Jackson's actual practice
would have been the big O discussion.
But big O and omega, upper
bound and lower bound,
just allow a computer
scientist to kind of wrestle
with what could happen
maybe in the worst
case, what can happen in the best case?
And you can even get even more precise
like the average case or the like.
And this is, indeed, what engineers
might do at a whiteboard in a company,
in a university when
designing an algorithm
and trying to make arguments as to why
their algorithm is better than someone
else's, by way of these
kinds of analyses.
And just so you've seen it, it turns
out that if some algorithm happens
to have an identical upper
bound and lower bound,
you can actually use a
capital Greek theta as well.
And this is the last of
the Greek symbols today.
But a Greek theta indicates
a coincidence of both upper
bound and lower bound.
That is, they are one and the same.
That was not the case for our discussion
a second ago of linear search,
not the case for binary search.
But you could use the
same kinds of formulas
if it turns out that your upper
bound and lower bound are the same.
So for instance, if I were to count
everyone literally in this room-- one,
two, three, four, five,
six and so forth--
you could actually say that counting
in that way is in theta of n
because in the best
case, it's going to take
me n points, people in the audience.
In the worst case, it's
going to take me n.
It's always going to take me n steps if
I want to count everyone in the room.
You can't really do better than
that unless you skip people.
So that would be an example
of the cuff of something
where theta is instead germane.
Are any questions now on
big O, on omega, or theta,
which are now just more
formal tools in the toolkit
for talking about the
design of our algorithms?
Any questions?
No?
Seeing none.
Oh, is this-- yes?
No?
OK, so we're good.
So let's go ahead and translate
this, perhaps, to some actual code.
Let me go over to VS Code here.
And let's see if we can't now
translate some of these ideas
to some actual code, not so
much using new syntax yet.
We're going to still operate in
this world of arrays like last week.
So let me go ahead and
create a program called
search.c by executing code
space search.c in my terminal.
And then up here, let's go
ahead and include our usual,
so include cs50.h so
I can get some input.
Include standard io.h so
I can print some output.
We'll do int main void, the
meaning of which we did start
to tease apart last week.
The fact that it's void again today
just means no command line arguments.
And let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and declare, just for
discussion's sake, a static array,
like an array that never changes.
And the syntax for this is going to
be give me an array called numbers
using the square bracket notation.
And I'm going to
immediately initialize it
to 20, 500, 10, 5, 100, 1, and 50,
reminiscent of those same denominations
as before.
So this is a slightly new syntax
that we've perhaps not seen.
And the curly braces here, which
are different from for loops
and while loops and functions, just
tell the compiler please give me
an array of whatever size this is
containing those numbers left to right.
I could alternatively use last week's
syntax of saying something like this.
Let's see, 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7 denominations.
I could alternatively do this.
And then I could say
numbers bracket 0 equals
20, numbers bracket 1 equals 500.
And I could do this five more times.
That's just a little tedious.
If you know the numbers
in advance, you don't
have to tell the compiler
how many there are.
You can just let it figure it out that
your numbers will be 10, 500, 10, 5,
100, 1, and 50.
So this is how you
statically define an array.
All right, let me just go ahead
and ask the user now for a number.
We'll call it n by using get_int
and prompting them for a number--
so nothing new there.
And now let me go ahead and
implement linear search.
And the pseudocode we had for this
before used some array-like notation.
Let me go ahead, then,
and start similarly.
For int i-- and you almost always
start counting at i by convention.
So that's perhaps a good starting point.
I'm going to do this so
long as i is less than 7.
Not the best design to hard
code the 7, but this is just
for demonstration's
sake for now, because I
know how many numbers I put in there.
And then I'm going to i++.
So now I have the beginnings
of a loop that will just allow
me to iterate over the entire array.
And let me ask this.
If the current number
at location i equals
equals n, which is the
number the human typed in,
then let's go ahead and do
something simple like printf,
quote unquote, found, backslash n.
And then per our discussion last week,
to indicate that this is successful,
I'm going to return 0 if I found it.
And if I don't find it, I'm just
going to go down here and, by default,
say not found, backslash n.
And just for convention-- whoops,
just for good measure, per convention,
I'll return 1 or, really,
any value other than 0.
0, recall, means success.
And any other integer tends
to mean error of some sort,
irrespective of the
number I'm looking for.
So just to revisit, the only thing
that's new here is the syntax.
We're creating an array of
seven numbers, these numbers.
And then after that we have
really highlighted here
an implementation of linear search.
I mean this is the C version, I daresay,
of what Stephanie did on the board,
whereas now the array is called
numbers instead of doors.
But I think it's pretty much the same.
Let me go ahead and open my
terminal window and run make search.
Seems to compile, ./search.
And let's go ahead and
search for a number.
We'll start with what we did before, 50.
And it's found.
Let's go ahead and run
it again, ./search.
Let's search for maybe
20 at the beginning.
That one, too, is found.
Let's run it one more time
searching for like 1,000,
which is not among the denominations.
And that one, indeed, is not found.
So we've taken an idea from Week
0, now formalized in Week 3,
and just translated it now to code.
Questions on this
implementation of linear search?
Linear search.
Nothing.
Oh, so successful so far today.
So let's see if we can't maybe
make this a little more interesting
and see if we can't trip over a detail
that's going to be important in C.
And instead of doing numbers,
let me go ahead and do this.
We'll stay on theme with Monopoly.
And I went down the rabbit
hole of reading the Wikipedia
article on Monopoly.
And the original pieces or tokens that
came with Monopoly-- and it turns out
we can represent those with strings.
So I'm going to create an array
called strings, plural, of whatever
size I defined here.
And the very first monopoly
pieces back in the day
were a battleship that
you could play with,
a boot, a cannon, an iron, a
thimble, and a top hat, some of which
you might from the game nowadays.
Turns out they've been changing these--
had no idea-- over the years.
So here is, now, an array of strings.
Let me go ahead and prompt the user
now not for an integer anymore.
I want to now search for one of these
strings still using linear search.
So let me create a string s,
set it equal to get_string,
prompt the user for a
string to search for.
And then I think my code here is
almost the same, except for one detail.
I now have an array called strings.
I now have a variable called s.
But it turns out, for reasons we'll
explore in more detail next week,
this line of code is not going to work.
And it turns out the reason has
to do with what we discussed
last week of what a string really is.
And what is a string, again?
A string is an array.
And it turns out, though,
that equals equals is not
going to generously compare all of
the characters in an array for you
just because you use equal equals.
It turns out it's not going
to compare every letter.
And so thankfully, there
is, in the string library
that we introduced last week,
a solution to this problem.
The reason for the problem, we'll
explore in more detail next week.
But for now, just know that when
you want to compare strings in C--
especially if you've come into the class
knowing a bit of Java or Python or some
other language-- you
cannot use equals equals.
Even though you could in
Scratch, you cannot in C.
So what I have to
actually do here is this.
I have to ask the question, does the
return value of a function called str
compare, or strcomp, equal 0
when passed in the current string
and that's user input?
So if you read the documentation for
this function called str compare,
you'll see that it takes two strings
as input, first one and second one.
It then-- someone decades
ago wrote the code
that probably uses a
for loop or a while loop
to compare every character
in each of those strings.
And it turns out it returns 0
if they are, in fact, equal.
Turns out, too, it will return a
positive number or a negative number
in other situations.
Any intuition for why
it might actually be
useful to have a function that allows
you to check if two strings are equal?
If they're not equal, what else
might be interesting to know
when comparing two strings?
If certain values are?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: OK, possibly.
Maybe you want to just
how similar they are.
And that's indeed an
algorithm unto itself.
But str compare is a
little simpler than that.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Exactly, if you're trying
to alphabetize a whole list of strings,
just like your phone probably is
for your contacts or address book.
It turns out that str
compare will actually
return a positive number
or a negative number or a 0
based on whether, maybe it comes
alphabetically first or later,
or in fact, equal.
So that can be a useful thing.
And that's just a teaser for
a lower level explanation
that we'll see next week.
So now, let me cross my fingers
and see if I got this right.
Let me go ahead and do make search.
Did compile, albeit slowly.
Dot slash search, and let's search
for something like the thimble.
And we see that that's, indeed, found.
Otherwise, let's search
for something that I know
isn't there, like a race car,
which was there when I grew up.
But huh, segmentation
fault, core dumped.
And actually, some of you have
tripped over this error before.
Anyone want to admit seeing this?
So yeah, not something
we've talked about,
and honestly, not something
I intended just now.
But that too, we'll see next week.
Any intuition for why
my program just broke.
I didn't really change the logic.
It's still linear search.
Let me hide the terminal so you
can see all of the code at once.
The only thing I did was switched
from integers to strings.
And I switched to str compare here.
But segmentation fault happened.
And the teaser is that that somehow
relates to the computer's memory.
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, and this
is subtle, but spot on.
So one, two, three,
four, five, six elements
total in this array, versus the seven
numbers of monopoly denominations
that we had earlier.
And this is where, see?
Sort of case in point,
this came back to bite me.
The fact that I hardcoded this value
as opposed to maybe separating it out
as a constant or declaring
it higher up, kind of
bit me here, because now, I'm
iterating over an array of size 6.
But clearly, I'm going one step
too far, because I'm literally
going to iterate seven times, not six.
So it's as though I'm looking
at memory that's over here.
And indeed, next week,
we'll focus on memory.
And that's just a bad thing.
So odds are, not even seeing your code
from this past week, if any of you
have had segmentation faults,
odds are, you touched memory
that you shouldn't have.
You maybe looped too many times.
You might have used a negative
number to get into your array.
In general, you touched memory
that you shouldn't have.
And you touched a segment of
memory that you shouldn't have.
The fix, though, at least
in my case, is simple.
Just don't do that.
So let me go ahead and recompile this.
Make search dot slash search.
And I'll search again
for race car, Enter.
And now it does not crash.
But it does tell me it's not found.
So subtle, but something you might
yourself have tripped over already.
Questions then, on what I just
did, intentionally or otherwise.
Yeah, in front.
STUDENT: One thing is the program
still works if you do return--
if you don't do return 0, return 1.
So what is the purpose
of doing [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
So the program will still work even
if I don't return 0 or return 1.
In fact, let me go ahead and do that
and just hide my terminal window
for a second.
Let's get rid of the return here.
However, watch what happens here.
Let me go ahead and
recompile this, make search.
Let me scroll up in my code here.
Let me go ahead and do dot slash search.
And let me go ahead and search
for the first thing in the list,
battle ship, so I know
that this should be found.
I hit Enter.
Huh, interesting.
So it's saying found not found.
But do you see why,
logically, in this case?
STUDENT: Is the loop still running?
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So the loop is still running.
So there's a couple
of solutions to this.
I could, for instance, somehow
break out of the code here.
But that's going to still
result in line 18 executing.
I could then instead just return here.
I don't strictly need to
return 1 down at the bottom.
But I made this claim
last week that it tends
to be helpful as your programs get more
sophisticated, to at least signify,
just like a real world programmer,
error codes when something goes wrong.
So returning 0 in main is the easiest
way to signify my code is done.
I'm ready to exit
successfully, that's it.
But down here, I could
absolutely still return 0,
because that's not a huge deal.
It's not really an error that deserves
annoying the user with some kind of pop
up that something went wrong.
But return 1 is just a lower
level way of signaling,
eh, it didn't really find
what I was looking for.
And remember from last week,
you can see this as follows.
If I recompile this again, now that I've
reverted those changes, so make search.
And if I do a dot slash search
and search for battle ship,
which is indeed found, recall I
can execute this magical command,
echo dollar sign question mark, which
you're not going to often execute.
But it shows you what main returned.
If I run search again and search
for race car, which is not found,
I see not found, but I can
also run this command again
and see that, oh, it returned 1.
So now if you fast forward a few months,
a few years, when you're actually
writing code in a company
or for larger projects,
you might want to be
automating software.
You might not want the human to
necessarily be running it manually.
You might want code to be
automated by some nightly process
or something like that.
Using these exit codes, can
a program determine yes or no
that other code succeeded or failed.
Other questions on linear
search in this way.
No?
All right, well, let's translate
this to one other feature of C
here by incorporating these two
ideas now into one other program.
So I'm going to create a phone book in
C by doing code space phonebook dot C.
And let's combine some of
these ideas and implement
this notion of searching a
phonebook for an actual name
and getting back a number.
So I'm going to go ahead and quickly
include some of the same things, cs50.h
so we can get input.
standard io dot h so
we can print output.
And I'm going to
preemptively include string.h
in case we need that one as well.
int main void, no need for
command line arguments today.
And let me give myself, now, an
array of names for this phone book.
So string names equals.
And then in curly
braces, how about Carter
will be one person in the phone book,
and David, myself, will be the other.
So we'll keep it short so we
don't have to type too many names.
But this is a phone book
with two people thus far.
Suppose, now, we want to also store
Carter's phone number in mind.
So it's not just saying
found or not found.
It's literally looking up our phone
numbers like a proper phone book.
Well, at the moment, there's
really no way to do this.
I could do something hackish like I
could put a number like 617-495-1000
after Carter.
I could maybe do something
like 949-468-2750 after me.
But now you're kind of doing the
whole apples and oranges thing.
Now, it's not strings.
It's a string int, string int.
All right, so maybe I could
just make all of these strings.
But now it's just a conceptual
mixing of apples and oranges.
Like yes, that's an
array of four strings.
But now you're on the honor system to
know that the first string is a name,
the second string is a
number, the third string is--
you can do it.
But it's a bit of a hack, so to speak.
So what might be cleaner than this?
Instead of combining our phone numbers
into the same array as our names,
what else might we do that's
perhaps a little better?
Say it little louder.
A 2D array, possibly
something we could do.
I'm going to keep it even simpler
now, because we haven't used those
by name, even though that is, we saw
last week, technically what argv is.
What else could I do if I want
to store names and numbers?
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, let me
go with this suggestion.
It's a little simpler.
Rather than complicate things in
literally different dimensions,
let me go ahead and do string.
Well, I could do int numbers.
But you know what?
So that we can support punctuation like
dashes or even parentheses or country
codes, I'm going to do this instead.
I'm going to do string numbers so that
I can represent Carter's number as quote
unquote plus 1 for the US,
617-495-1000, complete with hyphens,
as is US convention.
And then for mine I'll go ahead
and do +1-949-468-2750 semicolon.
And now down below, let's actually
enable the user to search this phone
book, just like in week 0 we did.
String name equals get string.
And let's ask the user for a
name, presumably David or Carter
or someone else.
And now let's re-implement
linear search.
So 4, int i get 0. i is less than 2.
And do as I say, not as I do.
I think we should
beware this hard coding,
but we'll keep it simple for now.
i++.
And then in this for loop, I think
we have all of the ingredients
to solve this.
So if the return value of str
compare of all of the names bracket
i comparing against the name that the
human typed in, if all of that equals
equals 0, that is, all of the characters
in those two strings are equal,
then I think we can go ahead and
say found, just like last time.
But you know what?
Let's actually print
Carter's or my phone number.
So found percent s, and we'll
plug in numbers, bracket i.
And then just for consistency,
I'll return 0 here.
And down here, how about I'll
say something like printf not
found, just to be clear.
And then I'll return 1 as well.
So just to recap,
here's all of the code.
It's almost the same as
before, except now it's useful.
I'm not just saying found or not found.
I found a number in monopoly,
or I found a piece in monopoly.
I'm looking up in one
array, one of the strings.
And then I'm printing from
the other array, the answer.
So let me go ahead here and run the
compiler, make phone book, Enter.
OK, that's promising, no errors.
Dot slash phonebook now.
And let's search, for
instance, Carter Enter.
All right, so we found Carter's number.
All right, let me do that again.
Phone book, let's search for David.
All right, we seem to
have found David's number.
All right, let's do it one last time.
Phone book, Enter.
And now we'll search for John Harvard.
Enter, not found.
All right, so I daresay, albeit with
minimal testing, this code is correct.
Would anyone now like
to critique the design?
Does something rub you the wrong way,
perhaps, about this approach here?
And as always, think about
how, if the program maybe
gets longer, more complicated, how
decisions like this might unfold.
Yeah.
STUDENT: If i is less than 2.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so if i is
less than 2, so technically,
if I change the number of
people in this phone book,
I'm going to have to update i.
And we've already seen that
I get myself into trouble.
So that's bad design.
Good.
STUDENT: Say you add someone's
name to the phonebook,
but you don't have the
corresponding number.
So then when you go
to pull their number,
it [INAUDIBLE] someone's number.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So again, I'm sort of trusting
myself not to screw up.
If I add John or anyone
else to the first array
but I forget to add their
number to the second array,
eventually things are going
to drift and be inconsistent.
And then code will be
incorrect at that point.
So sort of a poor design setting me
up for future failure, if you will.
Other thoughts?
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] so if you were
to switch the order of the numbers
but not the main [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, really good.
We're assuming the same order.
From left to right, the names go, and
from left to right, the numbers go.
But that's kind of
just the honor system.
Like, there's literally
nothing in code preventing me
from reversing the order for whatever
reason, or maybe sorting the names.
Like, they're sorted now, and maybe
that's deliberate, but maybe it's not.
So this honor system here,
too, is just not good.
I could put a comment in here
to remind myself, note to self,
always update arrays the same way.
But like, something's
going to happen eventually,
especially when we have not two, but
three, but 30, 300 names and numbers.
It would be nice to keep all
of the related data together.
And so in fact, the one new
feature of C we'll introduce today
is one that actually allows us to
implement our very own data structures.
You can think of arrays
as a very lightweight data
structure, in that it allows
you to cluster related data back
to back to back to back.
And this is how strings are implemented.
They are a data structure effectively
implemented with an array.
But with C and with other
languages, it turns out
you can invent your own
data types, whether they're
one dimensional, two
dimensional even, or beyond.
And with C, can you specifically
create your own types
that have their own names?
So for instance, wouldn't it
have been nice if C came with,
not just char and int and
floats and long and others.
Wouldn't it be nice if C came
with a data type called person?
And ideally, a person would
have a name and a number.
Now, that's a little
naive and unrealistic.
Like, why would they define a person
to have just those two fields.
Certainly, people could have
disagreed what a person is.
So they leave it to us.
The authors of C gave us all of these
primitives, ints and floats and strings
and so forth.
But it's up to us now to use
those in a more interesting way
so that we can create an array
of person variables, if you will,
inside of an array called people,
just to pluralize it here.
So how are we going to do this?
Well, for now, let's just stipulate
that a person in the world
will have a name and a number that
we could argue all day long what else
a person should have.
And that's fine.
You can invent your
own person eventually.
At the moment, I'm
using just two variables
to define a person's name and number.
But wouldn't it be nice to encapsulate,
that is, combine these two data
types, into a new and improved
data type called person.
And the syntax for that
is going to be this.
So it's a bit of a mouthful.
But you can, perhaps, infer
what some of this is doing here.
So it turns out C has a
keyword called typedef.
As the name kind of suggests, this
allows you to define your own type.
Struct is an indication
that it's a structure.
It's like a structure that has
multiple values inside of it
that you are trying to define.
And then at the very bottom here
outside of the curly braces,
is the name of the type
that you want to create.
So you don't have discretion
over using typedef or struct
in this particular case.
But you can name the
thing whatever you want.
And you can put anything in the
structure that you want as well.
And as soon as the semicolon is
executed at the bottom of the code,
every line thereafter
can now have access
to a person data type, whether as a
single variable, or as an entire array.
So if I want to build on this
then, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go back to my C code here.
And I'm going to go ahead and
change just a couple of things.
Let's go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and, first, get
rid of those two hardcoded arrays.
And let me go ahead and,
at the top of my file,
invent this type, so typedef struct.
Inside of it will be a string
name and then a string number.
And then the name of the
structure will be person.
And best practice would have me
define it at the very top of my file
so that any of my functions,
in fact, could use it,
even though I just
have main in this case.
Now, if I wanted, I could do this.
Person P1 and person P2.
But we know from last week,
that already is bad design.
If you want to have multiple instances
of the same type of variable,
we should probably use what instead?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: And--
STUDENT: An array.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, an array.
So let me not even go down that road.
Let me instead just do this.
Person will be the type of the array.
But I'm going to call it--
I could call it persons.
But in English, we typically say people.
So I'll call the array people.
And I want two people
to exist in this array,
though I could certainly change
that number to be anything I want.
How, now, do you put a
name inside of a person
and then put the number
inside of that same person?
Well, slightly new syntax today.
I'm going to go ahead and say this.
People bracket 0 just gives me
the first person in the array.
That's not new.
But if you want to go inside of that
person in memory, you use a dot.
And then you just specify the
name of the attribute therein.
So if I want to set the first
person's name to Carter,
I just use that so-called dot notation.
And then if I want to set Carter's
number using dot notation,
I would do this, +1-617-495-1000.
And then if I want to
do the same for myself,
I would now do people bracket 1 dot
name equals quote unquote David.
And then people bracket 1 still
dot number equals quote unquote
+1-949-468-2750.
And now, at the bottom
of my file, I think
my logic can pretty much stay the same.
I can still, on this line
here, prompt the user
for the name of the person
they want to look up.
For now, even though I admit
it's not the best design,
I'm just doing this for
demonstration's sake,
I'm going to leave the two there,
because I know I have two people.
But down here, this is
going to have to change.
I don't want to compare
names bracket i anymore.
What do I want to type here as
the first argument to str compare?
What do I want to do here?
Yeah.
STUDENT: People i dot name.
DAVID MALAN: So people i dot name, yeah.
So I want to go into the people
array at the ith location,
because that's what my loop is doing.
It's updating i again and again.
And then look at name, and that's good.
I think now I need to change this too.
What do I want to print
if the person is found?
Someone else?
What do I want to print here,
if I found the person's name?
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Say it a little louder.
STUDENT: People i dot number.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So people bracket i
dot number, if indeed I
want to print the corresponding
number to this person.
And then I think the rest of
my code can stay the same.
So let me go ahead and rerun make
phone book to recompile this version.
So far so good.
Dot slash phone book.
Let's go ahead and type
in Carter's name, found.
All right, let's go
ahead and run it again.
David's name, found.
Let's go ahead and run it one more time.
Type in John Harvard, for
instance, not found, in this case.
So fundamentally, the code
isn't all that different.
Linear search is still
behaving the same way.
And I admit, this is
kind of ugly looking.
We've kind of made a two line
solution five lines of code now.
But if we fast forward a week or
two when we start saving information
to files, we'll introduce
you to files like csv files,
comma separated values, or
spreadsheet files, which
you've surely opened on your Mac
or PC at some point in the past.
Suffice it to say we'll soon learn
techniques for storing information,
like names and numbers, in files.
And at that point, we're
not going to do any
of this hackish sort of
hard coding of the number 2
and manually typing my name and Carter's
name and number into our program.
We'll read the information
dynamically from a file.
And in a few weeks, we'll read it
dynamically from a database instead.
But this is, for now, just syntactically
how we can create an array of size 2
containing one person each.
We can update the name and
number of the first person,
update the name and the
number of the second person,
and then later search across
those names and print out
the corresponding numbers.
And in this sense, this
is a better design.
Why?
Because my person data
type encapsulates,
now, everything that it means to be a
person, at least in this narrow world.
And if I want to add something to
the notion of a person, for instance,
I could go up to my
type def, and tomorrow,
add an address to every person
and start reading that in as well.
And now it's not the honor system.
It's not a names array, a numbers array,
an addresses array, and everything else
you might imagine related to a person.
It's all encapsulated, which is a
term of art inside of the same type.
Reminiscent, if some of you have
programmed before, of something
called object-oriented programming.
But we're not there yet.
C is not that.
Questions on this use of
struct or this new syntax,
the dot operator being
really the juicy part here.
Any questions?
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: On what line number?
STUDENT: 16.
DAVID MALAN: 16?
So yes, so syntactically, we introduced
the square brackets last week.
So doing people bracket 0 just means
go to the first person in the array.
That was like when Stephanie
literally opened this door.
That's doors bracket 0.
But this is, of course,
people bracket 0 instead.
Today, the dot is a new piece of syntax.
It means go inside of that person in
memory and look at the name they're in
and set it equal to Carter
and do the same for number.
So that's all.
It's like, open the locker
door, go inside of it,
and check or set the
name and the number.
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] can you set default
values for each of the [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID MALAN: Attributes is fine.
Good question.
In the struct, can you
set default values?
Short answer, no.
And this is where C becomes less
feature-able than more modern languages
like Python and Java and others,
where you can, in fact, do that.
So when we transition to
Python in a few weeks' time,
we'll see how we can start
solving problems like that.
But for now, it's up to you
to initialize name and number
to something.
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
How can we adjust or critique
the design of what I'm doing?
This is one of the few situations
where I would say, hypocritically,
do as I say, not as I do.
I am using pretty ugly lines like
this, just to introduce the syntax.
But my claim, pedagogically
today, is that eventually,
when we start storing names
and numbers or other things
in files or in databases, you
won't have this redundancy.
You'll have one line of code
or two lines of code that
read the information
from the file or database
and then fill the entire
array with that data.
For now, I'm just doing it manually
so as to keep our focus only
on the new syntax, but that's it.
So forgive the bad
design by design today.
Other questions on this?
All right, that's been a lot already.
Why don't we go ahead and take our
10 minute break with snacks first.
We have some delightful
brownies in the lobby.
All right, we are back.
And up until now, it clearly seems to
be a good thing if your data is sorted,
because you can use binary search.
You know a little something
more about the data.
But it turns out that
sorting in and of itself
is kind of a problem to solve too.
And you might think,
well, if sorting is going
to be pretty fast, we absolutely
should do it before we start searching,
because that will just speed
up all of our searches.
But if sorting is slow, that kind
of invites the question, well,
should we bother sorting
our data if we're only
going to search the data
maybe once, maybe twice?
And so here is going to be,
potentially, a trade off.
So let's consider what it
means really to sort data.
In our case, it's just going
to be simple and use numbers.
But it might, in the case
of the Googles of the world,
be actual web pages or
persons or the like.
So here is our typical picture for
sorting, for solving any problem.
Input at left and output at right.
The input to our sort problem is going
to be some unsorted set of values.
And the output, ideally, will be
the same set of values sorted.
And if we do this
concretely, let's suppose
that we want to go about sorting this
list of numbers, 7, 2, 5, 4, 1, 6, 0,
3.
So it's all of the numbers from 0 to 7.
But they're somehow jumbled up randomly.
That's going to be the
input to the problem.
And the goal is now to sort
those so that you, indeed,
get out 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 instead.
So it turns out there's
lots of different ways
we can actually sort
numbers like these here.
And in fact, just to complement
our search example earlier,
could we perhaps quickly
get some eight volunteers
to come up if you're comfortable
appearing on the internet?
If you want to do 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7, 8, how about?
All right, come on down.
All right.
Come on over here, and I'll
give you each a number.
And if you want to start to organize
yourselves in the same order
you see the numbers on the board.
So look up on the overhead and
organize yourselves from left
to right in that same order.
And let's have the
first of you-- perfect.
If you want to come right over here,
how about right in line with this?
All right, and a few more numbers.
All right.
Number 2, 6, and perfect.
Just the right number, all right.
Uh oh.
All right, there we go, number three.
All right.
So let's just do a quick check.
We have 7, 2, 5, 4, 1, 6,
0, 3, very good so far.
Do you want to just scootch
a little this way just
to make a little more room?
All right, and let's consider
now who we have here on stage.
You want to each say a
quick hello to the audience?
RYAN: Hi, my name is Ryan.
I'm a first year from Pennypacker.
ITSELLE: Hi, my name is Itselle.
I'm a first year at Strauss.
LUCY: Hi, my name is Lucy.
And I'm a first year from Greenough.
SHILOH: Hi, my name is Shiloh.
I'm a first year in Wigglesworth.
JACK: Hi, my name is Jack.
And I'm a first year in Strauss.
KATHRYN: Hi, my name is Kathryn.
I'm a first year at Strauss.
MICHAEL: Hi, my name is Michael.
I'm a first year at Pennypacker.
MUHAMMAD: Hi, my name is Muhammad.
I'm a first year in Matthews.
DAVID MALAN: Hi, nice, welcome aboard.
All right.
So let's consider, now, how we might go
about sorting our kind volunteers here,
the goal being to get them into order
from smallest to largest so that,
presumably then, we can use something
smarter than just linear search.
We can actually use
binary search, assuming
that they are already then sorted.
So let me propose that we first
consider an algorithm that actually
has a name called selection sort.
And selection sort is going to
be one that literally has me,
or really you, as the programmer,
selecting the smallest element again
and again, and then putting
them into the appropriate place.
So let me go ahead and start this
here, starting with the number 7.
At the moment, 7 is the
smallest number I've found.
So I'm going to make mental note of that
with a mental variable, if you will.
I'm going to move on now.
Number 2 is obviously
smaller, so I'm just
going to update my mental reminder
that 2 is now the smallest,
effectively forgetting,
for now, number 7.
5, not smaller.
4, not smaller.
1, smaller.
And I'm going to make
mental note of that.
6, not smaller.
0, even smaller.
I'll make mental note of that,
having forgotten now everything else.
And now number 3 is not smaller.
So what's your name again?
MICHAEL: Michael.
DAVID MALAN: So Michael is number 0.
He belongs, of course, way down there.
But unfortunately-- you are--
RYAN: Ryan.
DAVID MALAN: Ryan is in the way.
So what should we do?
How should we start to sort this list?
Where should number 0 go?
Yeah.
Do you want to say it louder?
STUDENT: I will swap, I think.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so let's
just go ahead and swap.
So if you want to go ahead
and 0, go on where 7 is.
We need to make room for number 7.
It would kind of be cheating if
maybe everyone kind of politely
stepped over to the side.
Why?
Because if we imagine all of our
volunteers here to be an array, like,
that's a crazy amount of work to
have every element in the array
shift to the left just to make room.
So we're going to keep it simple
and just evict whoever's there now.
Now, maybe we get lucky, and number 7
is actually closer to its destination.
Maybe we get unlucky,
and it goes farther away.
But we've at least solved one problem.
If we had n problems at
first, now we have n minus 1,
because number 0 is
indeed in the right place.
So if I continue to act this out,
let me go ahead and say 2, currently
the smallest.
5, no, 4, no, 1 currently the smallest.
I'll make mental note.
6, 7, 3, and now let me pause.
1 is obviously the now smallest element.
So did I need to keep going?
Well, turns out, at least as
I've defined selection sort,
I do need to keep going,
because I only claim
that I'm using one variable in my mind
to remember the then smallest element.
I'm not smart enough like us
humans to remember, wait a minute,
1 is definitely the smallest now.
I don't have that whole recollection.
So I just am keeping
track of the now smallest.
So number 1, your name was?
JACK: Jack.
DAVID MALAN: Jack, where should Jack go?
Probably there.
And what's your name?
ITSELLE: Itselle.
DAVID MALAN: OK, so Jack and
Itselle, if you want to swap places,
we've now solved two of
the n total problems.
And now we'll do it a little faster.
If each of you want to start to swap as
I find the right person, so 5 smallest,
4 smaller, 2 is smaller.
Got to keep checking.
OK, 2 was smaller.
All right, now I'm going to
go back to the beginning.
All right, 4 is small.
5 is not.
6 is not.
7-- oh, 3 is small.
Where do you want to go?
OK, good.
I'm going to go back here.
And I can be a little smart.
I don't have to go all
the way to the end,
because I know these
folks are already sorted.
So I can at least optimize slightly.
So now 5 is small.
6 is small.
7 is 4, 4 is smaller.
If you want to go in place there.
And now, here things get interesting.
I can optimize by not
looking at these folks
anymore, because they're
obviously problem solved.
But now 5 is small, 6 is not, 7 is not.
OK, 5, you can stay where you are.
Now, a human in the
room is obviously going
to question why I'm
wasting any more time.
But with selection sort, as
I've defined it thus far,
I still have to, now,
check 6 is smallest, not 7.
And now my final step,
OK, they're all in place.
So here, too, is this
dichotomy between what we all
have is this bird's eye view of the
whole problem, where it's obvious
where everyone needs to go.
But a computer implementing this with an
array really has to be more methodical.
And we're actually saving a step here.
If we were really doing this, none
of these numbers would be visible.
All eight of our volunteers
would be inside of a locked door.
And only then could we
see them one at a time.
But we're focusing now
just on the sorting aspect.
So let me just, before we do
one other demonstration here,
propose that what I really just did here
in pseudocode was something like this.
For i from 0 to n minus
1, keeping in mind
that 0 is always the left of the array.
n minus 1 is always the
right end of the array.
For i from 0 to n minus 1, I found the
smallest number between numbers bracket
i and numbers bracket n minus 1.
And that's the very geeky way
of expressing this optimization.
I'm always starting from
numbers bracket i wherever I am.
And then everything else to the right.
And that's what was allowing me to
ignore the already sorted volunteers.
If, though, my last line says swap
smallest number with numbers i,
think that implements
what our humans were doing
by physically walking to another spot.
All right, so that, then, would
be what we'll call selection sort.
Let's go ahead and take
a second approach here
using an algorithm that I'm
going to call bubble sort.
But to do this, we need you all to
reset to your original locations.
We have a little cheat
sheet on the board
if you'd like to go back
to this position here.
And let me take a fundamentally
different approach, because I'm not
really liking selection sort
as is, because it's kind
of a lot of walking back and forth.
And the lot of walking suggests a
lot of, lot of steps again and again.
So what might I do instead?
Well, bubble sort is going to
have me focus a little more
intuitively on just smaller problems.
And let's see if this
gets me somewhere else.
So if I just look at this list without
looking at everyone else, 7 and 2,
this is obviously a problem.
Why?
Because you're out of order.
So let's just solve
one tiny problem first.
So 7 and 2, why don't you swap?
I know 2 is in a better place now,
because she's definitely less than 7.
So I think I can now move on.
7 and 5, problem.
So let's solve that.
7 and 4, problem.
Let's solve that, 7 and
1, let's solve that.
7 and 6, let's solve that.
7 and 0, solve that.
7 and 3, solve that.
OK, done.
Sorted, right?
Or obviously not, if you just
glance at these numbers here.
But we have, fundamentally,
taken a bite out of the problem.
7 is indeed in the right place.
So we maximally have n minus
1 other problems to solve.
So how do I do this?
I think I can just
repeat the same logic.
Let me go over here.
2 and 5, good.
5 and 4, no.
5 and 1, no.
5 and 6, yes.
6 and 0, no.
6 and 3, no.
So now we've solved two of the problems.
And what's nice about bubble
sort, at least as this glance,
it's nice and simple.
It's nice and local.
And you just keep incrementally
solving more and more problems.
So let's go ahead and do this again.
And I'll do it-- we can do it faster.
2 and 4, we know are good.
4 and 1, 4 and 5, 5 and 0, 5
and 3, 5 and 6, 6 and 7, good.
So we go back, 2 and 1.
Ah, now another problem solve.
2, and 4, 4 and 0, 4 and 3,
4 and 5, 5 and 6, 6 and 7.
And so notice 2, as per its
name, the largest elements
have bubbled their way up to the top.
And that's what seems to
be happening just as we're
fixing some remaining problems.
So almost done.
1 and 2, 2 and 0, 2 and 3, 3 and 4, 4
and 5, 5 and 6, 6 and 7, almost done.
Obviously, to us humans, it looks done.
How do I know as the computer for sure?
What would be the most surefire way
for me to now go, it's not done, sorry.
That's a bug.
OK, 1 and 0, 1 and 2, 2 and 3, 3
and 4, 4 and 5, 5 and 6, 6 and 7.
OK, so now it's obviously sorted
to the rest of us on stage.
How could I confirm as much as code?
You're doing it with your
mind, just glancing at this.
How would the computer, the code, know
for sure that this list is now sorted?
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] one more time.
DAVID MALAN: Let's do one more time.
And look, draw what conclusion?
STUDENT: That nothing
has to switch at all.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, let's
do it one more time,
even though it's a little wasteful.
But logically, if I go through the
whole list comparing pairs again, again,
and again, and I don't
do any work that time,
now it's obviously logically safe
to just stop, because otherwise, I'm
wasting my time doing the
same thing again and again
if no one's actually moving.
So I'm afraid we don't have
monopoly games for all of you.
But we do have eight stress balls.
And round of applause, if we
could, for our volunteers.
If you want to put your
numbers on the shelf there.
So if we consider for a moment--
thank you.
Thank you so much.
Sure.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Sure.
So if we consider now these two
algorithms, which one is better?
Any intuition for whether
selection sort the first
is better or worse than
bubble sort the second?
Any thoughts?
Yeah.
STUDENT: Bubble sort's even better
because it's less work [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: So bubble
sort seems like less work,
especially since I was focusing
on those localized problems.
Other intuition?
Selection sort versus bubble sort.
Well, let me propose that we try
to quantize this so we can actually
analyze it in some way.
And this is not an exercise we'll do
constantly for lots of algorithms.
But these are pretty
representative of algorithms.
So we can wrap our minds
around, indeed, the performance
or the design of these things.
So here is my pseudocode for selection
sort, whereby as per its name,
I just iteratively select the next
smallest element again and again.
So how can we go about
analyzing something like this?
Well, we could just
do it on paper pencil
and count up the number
of steps that seem
to be implied logically by the code.
We could literally count the number
of steps I was taking again and again,
left to right.
We could also just count
the number of comparisons
I was making with each
of the persons involved.
And I was doing it kind of
quickly in selection sort.
But every time I was looking
at a person trying to decide,
do I want to remember
that number is smallest?
That number, I was comparing two
values with an equals equals or less
than or greater than sign, at
least if we had done this in code.
So that tends to be the norm.
When analyzing algorithms like these,
counting the number of comparisons,
because it's kind of a
global unit of measure
we can use to compare
different algorithms entirely.
So think, too, that in
the general case, when
we have more than eight
volunteers, more than seven doors,
we can generalize our
array in general, as this
is the first element at bracket 0.
And the end of it is always n minus 1.
So arrays or doors, in
this case, or volunteers,
are always numerically indexed
from 0 on up to n minus 1,
if there's n of them in total.
So how do we analyze the
code of selection sort?
Well, how many steps did it take me
to find the first smallest element?
Or more precisely, how
many comparisons did I
need to make when I walked
to left to right to find
our first-smallest person,
which ended up being 0?
How many comparisons did I do
when walking left to right?
If there were eight people on stage,
how many total comparisons that I do?
Like if there's eight people,
I compared these folks.
Then this person, this person, yeah.
Yeah, so seven total, right?
Because if there's
eight people on stage,
you can only do seven comparisons
total, because otherwise you'd
be comparing one number to itself.
So it seems like, in the
general case, if you've
got n numbers that
you're trying to sort,
finding the smallest element
first takes n minus 1 comparisons.
Maybe n total steps left to right.
But the number of
comparisons, which I claim,
is just a useful unit of
measure, is n minus 1.
How about finding the
next smallest person?
How many steps did it take me to
find the next smallest number, which
ended up being the number 1?
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] n minus 2.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so just n minus 2.
Why?
Because I'd already solved one problem.
Someone was already
in the right position.
It would be silly to keep
counting them again and again.
So I can whittle down my number
of comparisons for the next pass
to n minus 2.
The third pass to find the third
smallest number would be n minus 3.
And then dot, dot, dot, presumably
this story, this formula,
ends when you have just one final pair,
the people at the end, to compare.
So if this is looking a little
reminiscent of some kind of recurrence
from high school or high school
math or physics or the like,
let me just stipulate that if
you actually do out this math
and generalize it, that is the
same thing as n times n minus 1
divided by 2.
And if you're rusty
on that, no big deal.
Just kind of commit to
memory that any time
you add up this kind of series,
something plus something slightly
smaller, plus something
slightly smaller, each of which
differs by 1, you're going to get this
formula. n times n minus 1 over 2.
If we, of course, multiply that out,
that's really n squared minus n,
all divided by 2.
If we keep multiplying it out, that's
n squared divided by 2 minus n over 2.
And now, we have kind of
a vocabulary with which we
can talk about the efficiency,
the design of this algorithm.
But honestly, I don't really care
about this level of precision,
like n squared divided by
2 minus n divided by 2.
As n gets really large, which of
these symbols, which of these terms
is really going to dominate,
become the biggest influencer
on the total value of steps?
Right?
It's the square, right?
It's definitely not n divided by 2.
That's shaving some time off.
But n squared, as n gets big,
is going to get really big.
If n is 100, then n squared is bigger.
If n is a million, n
squared is really bigger.
And so at the end of the day,
when we're really just talking
about a wave of the hand analysis
and upper bound, if you will,
let's just say that selection
sort, as analyzed here,
it's on the order of n squared steps.
It's not precisely n squared steps.
But you know what? n squared divided
by 2, the intuition here might be that,
well, it's half of that.
n squared is what really matters
as n gets really, really large.
And that's when you start
thinking about and trying to solve
the Google problems of the world.
When n gets large, that's
when you have to be smarter
than just sort of naive
implementations of any algorithm.
So where, then, does this algorithm
fall into this categorization here?
Well, n squared, it turns
out, is on the order
of n squared steps, in the worst
case, whether it's sorted or not.
It turns out, though, lower bound,
if we consider this same code,
suppose the best case scenario, like
our eight volunteers came up on stage.
And just because they already
sorted themselves, so 0 through 7.
Suppose they just happened
to be in that state.
How many steps would
selection store take
to sort an already-sorted
list of volunteers?
Any intuition?
Yeah.
STUDENT: Would it still be [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID MALAN: Would it still be n--
STUDENT: Still be 7 [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID MALAN: So for the
first pass, it would still
be 7 for the first
pass across the humans.
Because even though, yeah,
I'm claiming 0 is here,
I don't know that 0 is the smallest
until I make my way all the way
over there doing all seven comparisons.
OK, fine, first pass took seven
or more generally n minus 1 steps.
What if I look for the next smallest
element, and the humans in this story
are already sorted 0 through 7?
Well, yes, the number 1 is
here, and I see them first.
But I don't know they're the smallest
until I compare against everyone else
get to the end of the list.
And we're like, oh,
well that was stupid.
I already had the smallest
person in hand then.
And so this pseudocode, this
implementation of selection sort,
is sort of fixed like this.
There's no special case that says,
if already sorted, quit early.
It's always going to
take n squared steps.
And so in this case, if we
borrow our jargon from earlier
using omega notation, just
to be clear, selection sort
is also going to be in this
incarnation in omega of n squared,
because even in the best case,
where the list is already
sorted, you're going to
waste a huge amount of time
essentially verifying as
much or discovering as much,
even though we humans of
course could see it right away.
So selection sort would seem to take
both n squared steps in the worst
case, n squared steps in the best case.
And so you know what?
We can use our theta
terminology for that.
Here would be an algorithm,
just like counting earlier,
that always takes n squared steps,
no matter whether the array is sorted
or not from the get go.
All right, so hopefully
we can do better.
And someone proposed
earlier that bubble sort
felt like it was using fewer steps.
Well, let's consider that next.
With bubble sort, we had
this pseudocode, I claim.
Whereby, let's focus on the
inside of the code first.
Down here, what was I doing?
For i from 0 to n minus 2.
That's curious.
We've never seen n minus 2 before.
But I asked this question.
If numbers bracket i and numbers bracket
i plus 1 are out of order, swap them.
So that was when I was pointing
at our first two volunteers here.
I saw that they were out of
order, so I swapped them.
How come I'm doing that again and
again up to n minus 2, though,
instead of n minus 1,
which we've always used up
until now as our rightmost boundary?
Any intuition for why I'm
doing this from 0 to n minus 2?
Yeah.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE] number, you
can't get rid of the ith number.
There's no benign character
you can swap with.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Because I'm looking at the ith
person per this pseudocode here
and the ith plus 1 person, I
better make sure I don't go step
beyond the boundaries of my array.
So if you think of my left hand.
When my back was to you here,
pointing at the current person
at the first position, my right
hand for this if conditioner
is essentially pointing at
the person next to them.
And you want to iterate with your
left hand all through these people.
But you don't want your left
hand to point at the last person.
You want it to point at
the second to last person.
But we know that the last
person is always at n minus 1.
So the second to last person, just
mathematically, is at n minus 2.
So it's a subtlety.
But this is a seg fault
waiting to happen.
If you implemented bubble
sort using n minus 1,
you will, my right hand would go
beyond the boundaries of the array,
so just bad.
All right, so why am
I saying this n times?
Well, we did it very
organically with humans.
But each time someone--
each pass I did through
the array, someone
bubbled their way up to the end.
Number 7, then number 6, then number 5.
So if on each pass through
the array of volunteers,
I was solving at least one problem,
it seems like bubble sort can just
run n times total to
solve all n problems,
because the first pass will get
at least one number into place.
Second pass, second number into place.
You might get lucky,
and it would do more.
But worst case, this feels like enough.
Just do this blindly n times,
and they'll all line up together.
Well, technically-- all right,
now we're getting into the weeds.
Technically, you can just
repeat it in minus 1 times,
because if you solve all
n minus 1 other problems,
and you're left with 1, literally
that person's where they need to be,
just logically.
If you've already sorted everything
else and you've got just the 1 left,
it's already bubbled up.
So how do we analyze this?
Well in bubble sort, we
might do something like this.
I'm essentially doing n minus
1 things n minus 1 times.
Now, let me back up to the
pseudocode, because this one's
a little less obvious.
This is where you can actually
mathematically infer from your loop
how many steps you're taking.
So this first line literally says,
repeat the following n minus 1 times.
So that's going to translate
very straightforwardly
to our mathematical formula.
Do something n minus 1 times.
This loop, just because I'm
using for loop terminology,
it's framed a little differently.
But if you're iterating
from 0 to n minus 2,
you're iterating a total
of n minus 1 times.
And again, the arithmetic is
getting a little annoying.
But this just means do the
following n minus 1 times.
So do n minus 1 things n minus 1 times.
We can now run out the math as follows.
We have the formula n
minus 1 times n minus 1.
We do our little FOIL method
here, n squared minus 1 times n,
minus 1 times n, plus 1.
We can combine like terms.
n squared minus 2n plus 1.
But at this point, when
n gets really large,
which term are we really
going to care about?
This is on the order of?
Yeah, n squared.
So at least asymptotically.
Asymptotically means, as n approaches
infinity, gets really large.
Turns out that the upper bound
on selection sort and bubble sort
are essentially the same.
Now, if we really nitpicked and compared
the total number of comparisons,
they might differ slightly.
But as n gets large,
honestly, you're barely
going to notice the difference, it would
seem, between these two algorithms.
But what about the lower bound?
If the upper bound on bubble sort is
also big O of n, what about the lower
bound here?
Well, with this pseudocode, what would
the lower bound be on bubble sort?
Even in the best case when all
of the volunteers are sorted.
Any intuition?
In this pseudo code.
Yeah, in the middle.
STUDENT: Sorry, quick question.
Isn't bubble sort
structured such that you
wouldn't need to compare numbers
that have already bubbled up?
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
Isn't bubble sort designed
such that you wouldn't
need to compare numbers that
have already bubbled up?
That's what's happening here
in the middle, implicitly.
I'm always going from left to right.
But remember that even when
I screwed up at the end
and the last two people were
out of order, I do always
need to restart at the beginning,
because the big numbers are
going that way, and the small
numbers are coming this way.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: So that is true.
There are some slight optimizations
that I'm kind of glossing over here.
Let me stipulate that it would still
end up being on the order of n squared.
But that would definitely shave
off some actual running time here.
But what if the list is already sorted?
Our pseudocode, at the
moment, has no allowance
for if list is already
sorted, quit early.
So we're going to blindly
do n minus 1 things
and minus 1 times unless we modify our
pseudocode, as I did verbally earlier,
I proposed this.
Inside of that outer loop, if you make
a pass across all of the volunteers,
and your mental counter
has made no swaps,
you have to keep track
with some kind of variable,
well then, you might as well stop.
Because if you do a whole
pass and make no swaps,
why would you waste time doing it
again expecting different behavior?
So to help visualize these, whereby
now bubble sort can be advantageous
if the data is already
sorted or mostly sorted.
Why?
Because it does have this
short circuit detail.
At least if we implement
it like that, how
can we go about visualizing these
things a little more clearly?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me pull up, here, a visualization
of exactly these algorithms,
thanks to a third party tool here
that's going to help us visualize
these sorting algorithms as follows.
Small bars represent small numbers.
Big bars represent big numbers.
And so the idea, now, is
when I hit a button here
to get all of the small bars this
way, all of the big bars this way.
So just like our volunteers.
But instead of holding lighted numbers,
it's bars representing their magnitude.
So let's go ahead and start with,
for instance, selection sort.
And you'll see in pink,
is being highlighted
the current number
that is being selected
and then pulled all the way to the left.
So this is selection sort.
And again, it's selecting
the next smallest element.
But you can see here, all the more
visibly, that just like my human feet,
we're taking a lot of steps.
So is this algorithm touching these
elements, again and again and again.
And this is why the n
squared is really a thing.
There's got to be some
inherent redundancy here.
Like, why do we keep looking at the
same darn elements again and again?
We do, in terms of our
pseudocode need to do so.
But it's this redundant
comparisons that kind of explains
why n squared is indeed the case.
So now it's done.
Small bars here, big bars there.
And I had to just keep
talking there to kill time,
because it's relatively slow.
Well, let me re-randomize
the array, just
so we start with a different order.
And now let me click on bubble sort.
And you'll see similar idea,
but different algorithm.
So now, the two bars in
pink are the two that
are being compared and fixed,
potentially, if they're out of order.
And you can see already
that the biggest bars
are bubbling their way up to the top.
But now, you can also
see this redundancy,
like we keep swooping through
the list again and again, just
like I kept walking back and forth.
And this is n squared.
This is not that many bars.
What?
10, 20, there's like 40 or
something bars, I'm guessing.
That's pretty slow already
just to sort 40 numbers.
And I think it's going to get
tedious if I keep talking over this.
So let's just assume that
this too is relatively slow.
Had I gotten lucky and the list
were almost sorted already,
bubble sort would have been pretty fast.
But this was a truly random
array, so we did not get lucky.
So indeed, the worst case might
be what's kicking in here.
So I feel like it'll be anticlimactic,
like holding in a sneeze, if I
don't let you see the end of this.
So here we go.
Nothing interesting is about to happen.
Almost done.
OK, done.
All right, so thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
So still somewhat slow though.
How though can we, perhaps, do
a little better fundamentally?
So we can do so if we introduce
yet another technique.
And this one isn't so much a
function of code as it is concept.
And it's something that you might
have seen in the real world,
but perhaps not so obviously so.
So it turns out, in
programming, recursion
refers to the ability of
a function to call itself.
In the world of mathematics,
if you have a function f,
if f appears on both the left side
and the right side of a formula,
that would be a recursive
function in the math world too.
Whenever f is defined in terms
of itself, or in our case,
in compute-- in programming, any
time a function calls itself,
that function is said to be recursive.
And this is actually something
we've seen already in class,
even though we didn't call it as much.
So for instance,
consider this pseudocode
from earlier, whereby
this was the pseudocode
for searching via binary
search, a whole bunch of doors.
If no doors are left
returned false, that
was the additional conditional we added.
But then if number behind
middle door returned true,
and here's the interesting part,
if number is less than middle door,
search the left half.
Else if number is greater than
middle door, search the right half.
This pseudocode earlier
was, itself, recursive.
Why?
Because here is an
algorithm for searching.
But what's the algorithm telling us?
Well, on this line and this line, it's
telling us to search something else.
So even though it's not explicitly
defined in code as having a name,
if this is a search algorithm, and yet
the search algorithm is using a search
algorithm, this pseudocode is recursive.
Now, that could quickly get you
into trouble if a function just
calls itself again and again and again.
But why, intuitively,
is it not problematic
that this code, this
pseudocode, calls itself?
Why will the algorithm still stop?
Yeah.
STUDENT: It has an exit condition, as in
if there is no doors left, [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
It has some exit condition,
like if no doors left.
And more importantly, any
time you search the left half,
you're searching a smaller
version of the problem.
Any time you search
the right half, you're
searching a smaller version of the
problem, literally half the size.
So this is why, in the
phone book, obviously
I couldn't tear the phone book
in half infinitely many times,
because it was literally
getting smaller each time.
So recursion is this ability
to call yourself, if you will.
But what's important is that you do
it on a smaller, smaller problem,
so that eventually, you have
no more problems to solve
or no more data, no more doors at all.
So these two lines here would
be the recursive elements here.
But if we go back to week 0, we could
have used recursion in some other way.
So this was our pseudocode for
the phone book back in week 0.
And recall that we
described these yellow lines
as really representing a loop,
some kind of cycle again and again.
But there was a missed opportunity here.
What if I had re-implemented
this code to do this?
Instead of saying open to
middle of left half of book
and then go back to line 3,
like literally inducing a loop,
or open to middle of right
half a book and go back
to line 3 inducing
another loop, why don't I
just recognize that
what I'm staring at now
is a algorithm for
searching a phone book?
And if you want to search a smaller
phone book, like A through M or N
through Z, we'll just
use this same algorithm.
So I can replace these yellow lines
with just this, casually speaking.
Search left half of book,
search right half of book.
This would be implicitly,
and now I can shorten
the whole thing, a recursive
implementation of the phone book
pseudocode from week 0.
And it's recursive, because
if this is a search algorithm,
and you're saying go search
something else, that's fine.
That's recursive.
But because you're searching
half of the phone book,
it's indeed going to
get smaller and smaller.
Even in the real world or
the real real virtual world,
you can see recursive data
structures in the wild,
or at least in Super
Mario Brothers like this.
Let me get rid of all
the distractions here
and focus on this pyramid,
where you have one block,
then two, then three, then four.
Well, this itself, is technically
recursively-defined in the sense that,
well, what is a pyramid of height for?
Well, it's really, what?
How would you describe
a pyramid of height 4
is actually the same
thing as a pyramid of--
STUDENT: Height 3.
DAVID MALAN: --of height
3, plus 1 additional layer.
Well, what's a pyramid of height 3?
Well, it's technically a pyramid of
height 2 plus 1 additional layer.
And so even physical
structures can be recursive
if you can define them
in terms of itself.
Now, at some point, you have to say
that if the pyramid is of height 1,
there's just one block.
You can't forever say it's defined
in terms of a height negative 1,
negative 2, you would never stop.
So you have to kind of
have a special case there.
But let's go ahead and translate
something like this, in fact, to code.
Let me go back to VS code here, and let
me implement a program called iteration
that refers to a loop iterating.
And let me implement a very
simple pyramid like that.
So let me go ahead and
include the CS50 library.
I'll include our standard io.h int main
void, no command line arguments today.
And let's go ahead and do this.
Let's declare a variable
called height, ask the human
for the height of this pyramid.
And then let's go ahead and
draw a pyramid of that height.
Now, of course, draw does not yet exist.
So I'm going to need to
invent the draw function.
Let me go ahead and define a function
that doesn't have a return value.
It's just going to have side effects.
It's just going to print bricks
on the screen, called draw.
And it takes in an
integer, n, as its input.
And how am I going to implement this?
Well again, I want to print one block,
then two, then three, then four.
That's pretty straightforward, at least
once you're comfortable with loops.
Let me go back to the code here.
Let me go ahead and say 4, int i, get 0.
i is less than n.
i plus plus.
And that's going to iterate,
essentially row by row.
And on each row, I want to print
out one, then two, then three, then
four bricks.
But I'm iterating from 0 to 1 to 2 to 3.
So I think that's OK.
I can just say something
like 4 int j get 0.
j, let's be clever about
this, is less than i.
j++.
And now, let me go ahead
and, inside of this loop,
I think I can get away with just
printing out a single hash sign.
But then outside of that
loop, similar to last week,
I'm going to print my
new line separately.
So a little non-obvious at first.
But this outer loop iterates row
by row, line by line, if you will.
And then the inner loop just makes sure
that when i equals zero, let's see.
Oh nope, there's a bug.
I need to make sure that
it's j is less than i plus 1.
So when i is 0 on my
first line of output,
I'm going to print out one brick.
When i is 1, I'm going to print
out two bricks and so forth.
So let me go ahead and
run make iteration.
All right, and now, seems to compile.
Uh oh, huh.
Implicit declaration of function draw.
So I'm making week one mistakes again.
What?
Say again.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
The prototype is missing.
I didn't declare it at the top.
That's an easy fix, and
the only time, really, it's
OK and necessary to copy paste.
Let me copy the functions declaration
there and it with a semicolon.
So that clang now knows
that draw will exist.
Make iteration.
Now it works.
Thank you. dot slash iteration.
We'll type in something like 4.
And there we have it, our pyramid
of height one, two, three, four,
that looks pretty similar to
this, albeit using hashes.
So that's how we would have implemented
this, like, two weeks ago in week one,
maybe last week, but just using arrays.
But let me propose that we could
do something recursively instead.
Let me close this version of the code.
And let me go back to VS
Code and open up recursion.c,
just to demonstrate
something recursively.
And I'll do it incorrectly
deliberately the first time.
So let me include cs50.h.
Let me include standard io.h.
Let me do int main void.
And let me just blindly draw a
pyramid initially of height 1.
But now in my draw function, let me
re-implement it a little differently.
So my draw function this time is
still going to take a number n.
But that's how many hashes
it's going to print.
So let's do 4, int i get 0.
i is less than n.
i++.
Then let's go ahead and print
out a single hash mark here.
And then after that, let's print out
the end of the line, just as before.
But now this, of course, is
only going to draw a single row.
It's going to print out one hash or
two hashes or three hashes, but only
on one line.
Let me now, incorrectly, but just
kind of curiously say, all right.
Well, if this draws a
pyramid of height 1,
let's just use ourselves to draw
a pyramid of height n plus 1.
So the first time I call draw,
it will print out one hash.
Then the second time I call draw, it
will print out two hashes, then three,
then four.
So we're kind of laying these
bricks down from top to bottom.
Make recursion.
Whoops, I screwed up again.
So let's copy the prototype here.
Let's put this down
over here, semicolon.
Let's do this again.
Make recursion.
All right, all good,
dot slash recursion.
And now let me increase the
size of my terminal window,
just so you can see more of the output.
And here we have.
OK, bad, but thank you.
So we have an infinitely tall pyramid.
And it's just flying
across the screen, which
is why it looks kind of like a mess.
But I printed out a pyramid of height
1, and then 2, and then 3, and then 4.
And unfortunately, what am I
lacking any sort of quick condition,
any kind of condition that says,
wait a minute, when it's too tall,
stop altogether.
So this is an infinite loop.
But it's not a loop.
It's a recursive call.
And actually, doing this
in general, is very bad.
We'll see next week that if you
call a function too many times,
you can actually trigger yet another
of those segmentation faults,
because you're using too
much memory, essentially.
But for now, I haven't
triggered that yet.
Control C is your friend to cancel.
And as an aside, if you're playing
along at home or playing with this code
later, I actually cheated here.
We have a special clang
configuration feature
that prevents you from
calling a function like that
and creating a problem.
I overrode it just for
demonstration sake.
But odds are at home, you wouldn't be
able to compile this code yourself.
But let me do a proper version
recursively of this code as follows.
Let me go back into the code here.
Let me go ahead and, not just
blindly start drawing one, then two,
then three layers of bricks.
Let me prompt the human as before
for the height of the pyramid
they want using our get int function.
And now let me call
draw of height again.
So now I'm going back to
the loop-like version.
But instead of using a loop now, this
is where recursion gets rather elegant,
if you will.
Let me go ahead and execute and
code the draw function as follows.
Per your definition, if
a pyramid of height 4
is really just a pyramid of
height 3 plus another row, well,
let's take that literally.
Let me go back to my code.
And if you want to draw a pyramid
of height 4, well go right ahead
and draw a pyramid of height 3
first, or more generally, n minus 1.
But what's the second step?
Well, once you've drawn a pyramid
of height 3, draw an extra row.
So I at least have to bite off
that part of the problem myself.
So let me just do for int i get 0.
i is less than n i++.
And let me, the programmer of this
function, print out my hashes.
And then at the very
bottom, print out a new line
so the cursor moves to the next line.
But this is kind of elegant now, I
dare say, in that draw is recursive,
because I'm literally translating
from English to C code,
this idea that a pyramid of height 4
is really just a pyramid of height 3.
So I do that first.
And I'm sort of trusting
that this will work.
Then I just have to lay one more
layer of bricks, four of them.
So if n is 4, this is just a
simple for loop, a la week 1,
that will print out an additional layer.
But this, of course, is going
to be problematic eventually.
Why?
It's not done yet, this program.
How many times will draw
call itself in this model?
STUDENT: It's infinite.
DAVID MALAN: Infinitely many times.
Why?
STUDENT: Because there's
no quit function.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, there's
no equivalent of quit.
Like, if you've printed enough
already, then quit, well,
how do we capture that?
Well, I don't think we
want this to go negative.
It would make no sense to draw
a negative height pyramid.
So I think we can just pluck off,
as the programmer, an easy case,
an easy answer, a so-called base case.
And I'm just going to do this.
At the top of my draw function,
let me just say, if n is less than
or, heck, less than or
equal to 0, that's it.
Go ahead and just return.
There's nothing more to do.
And that simple condition,
technically known as a base case,
will ensure that the
code doesn't run forever.
Why?
Well, suppose that draw is
called with an argument of 4.
4 is, of course, not less
than 0, so we don't return.
But we do draw a pyramid of height 3.
And here's where things get
a little mentally tricky.
You don't move on to line 20
until draw has been called.
So when draw is called
with an argument of 3,
it's as though you're executing
from the top of this function again.
3 is not less than 0.
So what do you do?
You draw 2.
How do you draw 2?
Well, 2 is not less than
0, so you don't return.
So you draw 1.
Got to be careful here.
Draw 1.
And now, we go ahead
back to the beginning.
How do you draw 1?
Well, 1 is not less than
0, so you don't return.
You draw height 0.
How do you draw height 0?
Wait a minute.
0 is less than or equal to 0.
And you return.
And so it's kind of like this
mental stack, this to do list.
You keep postponing, executing
these lower lines of code,
because you keep restarting,
restarting, restarting the draw function
until, finally, one of those function
calls says there's nothing to do,
return.
And now the whole thing starts
to unravel, if you will.
And you pick back up where you left off.
And this is, perhaps, the best scenario.
We won't do it in class.
But if you'd like to wrestle
through this on your own
using debug50 to keep stepping
into, step into, step into, each
of those lines, logically, you'll see
exactly what's actually happening.
So let me go to my terminal
and do make recursion,
which is now this correct version
of the code, dot slash recursion.
Let's type in a height of 4.
And voila, now we have that same
pyramid, not using iteration per se,
though admittedly, we're using
iteration to print the additional layer.
We're now using draw recursively to
print all of the smaller pyramids
that need come before it.
STUDENT: Can you only use
recursion for void function?
[INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: No.
Question is, can you only use
recursion with a void function?
No, not at all.
In fact, it's very common to have
a return value like an integer
or something else so that you can
actually do something constructively
with that actual value.
Other questions on this.
STUDENT: When is line
21 getting executed?
DAVID MALAN: Say it a little louder.
STUDENT: When is line
21 getting executed?
DAVID MALAN: When is
line 21 getting executed?
So if you continue to--
let me scroll down a bit more so
you can see the top of the code.
So line 21 will be executed once
line 19 is done executing itself.
Now, in the story I told, we kept
calling draw again, again, again.
But as soon as one of
those function calls
where n equals 0 returns
immediately, then we
don't keep drawing again and again.
So now if you kind of think
of the process as reversing,
then you continue to line 21, then
line 21 again, then line 21 again,
and as the sort of logic unravels.
And next week, we'll actually
paint a picture of what's actually
happening in the computer's memory.
But for now, it's just, it's very
similar to the pseudocode for the phone
book.
You're just searching again and again.
But you're waiting until the very
end to get back the final result.
Google now, who I keep
mentioning by coincidence today,
is full of programmers of course.
Here's a fun exercise.
Let me go back to a browser.
I'm going to go ahead and search for
recursion, because I want to learn
a little something about recursion.
Here is kind of an
internet meme or joke.
If I zoom in here, the engineers
at Google are kind of funny.
See why?
STUDENT: Ah.
DAVID MALAN: Ah, there you go.
Yes.
Yes, this is recursion.
And there's going to be so many
memes you'll come across now, where
recursion, like if you've ever
pointed a camera at the TV that's
showing the camera, and you sort of see
yourself or the image again and again,
that's really recursion.
And in that case, it only stops once
you hit the base case of a single pixel.
But this is a very funny
joke in some circles
when it comes to recursion and Google.
So how can we actually
use Google, or rather,
how can we actually use
recursion constructively?
Well, let me propose that
we actually introduced
a third and final algorithm for
sorting that hopefully does better
than the two sorts thus far.
We've done selection
sort and bubble sort.
Bubble sort, we liked a little better,
at least insofar as in the best case
where the list is already sorted.
Bubble sort's at least
smarter, and it will actually
terminate early, giving
us a better lower bound,
in terms of our omega notation.
But it turns out that
recursion, and this is not
necessarily a feature of recursion,
but something we can now leverage.
It turns out, using recursion, we can
take a fundamentally different approach
to sorting a whole bunch
of numbers in such a way
that we can do far fewer
comparisons and, ideally, speed up
our final results.
So here is the pseudocode
for what we're about to see
for something called merge sort.
And it really is this terse.
Sort the left half of numbers.
Sort the right half of numbers.
Merge the sorted halves.
This is almost sort of
nonsensical, because if you're
asked for an algorithm to sort, and you
respond with, well, sort the left half,
sort the right half.
That's being difficult, because well,
I'm asking for a sorting algorithm.
You're just telling me to sort
the left half and the right half.
But implicit in that last line,
merging is a pretty powerful feature
of this sort.
Now, we do need another
base case at the top.
So let me add this.
If we find ourselves with a
list, an array, of size 1,
well, that array is obviously sorted.
If there's only one element in
it, there's no work to be done.
So that's going to be our base case.
But allowing us now, in just these,
what, four, six lines of pseudocode,
to actually sort some elements.
But let's focus first on
just a subset of this.
Let's consider for a moment what
it means to merge sorted halves.
So Carter has wonderfully
come up to volunteer here just
to help us reset these numbers.
Suppose that in the middle of
the story we're about to tell,
we have two sorted halves.
I've already sorted the
left half of these numbers,
and indeed, 2, 4, 5, 7 is
sorted from smallest to largest.
And the right half appears to be already
sorted, 0, 1, 3, 6, already sorted.
So in my pseudocode, we're
already done sorting the left half
and the right half somehow.
But we'll see how in a moment.
Well, how do I go about
merging these two halves?
Well, because they're sorted already,
and you want to merge them in order,
I think we can flip down.
We can hide all but the first
numbers in each of these sublists.
So here, we have a half
that starts with 2.
And I don't really care
what the other numbers are,
because they're clearly larger than 2.
I can focus only on
2, and 0 too, 0 also.
We know that 0 is the smallest there,
so let's just ignore the numbers
that Carter kindly flipped down.
So how do I merge these two lists
into a new sorted larger list?
Well, I compare the two
on my left with the 0
on my right, obviously,
which comes first, the 0.
So let me put this down here.
And Carter, if you want to
give us the next element.
Now I have two sorted halves.
But I've already plucked one off.
So now I compare the two against the 1.
1 obviously comes next.
So I'm going to take out the
1 and put it in place here.
Now I'm going to compare
the two halves again.
2 and 3, which do I merge first?
Obviously the 2 comes next.
And now, notice, each time I do
this, my hands are theoretically
making forward progress.
I'm not doubling back like I kept
doing with selection sort or bubble
sort, back and forth, back and forth.
My fingers are constantly
advancing forward,
and that's going to be a key detail.
So I compare 4 and 3, 3 obviously.
I compare 4 and 6, 4 obviously.
I compare 5 and 6, 5 obviously.
And then I compare 7 and 6, 6 of course.
And then lastly, we have
just one element left.
And even though I'm kind of
moving awkwardly as a human,
my hands technically were
only moving to the right.
I was never looping back doing
something again and again.
And that's, perhaps, the intuition,
and just enough room for the 7.
So that, then, is how you
would merge two sorted halves.
We started with left half
sorted, right half sorted.
And merging is just like
what you would do as a human.
And Carter just flipped
the numbers down,
so our focus was only on the
smallest elements in each.
Any questions before we forge
ahead with what it means, then,
to be merged in this way?
So now, here is an original list.
We deliberately put it at
the top, because there's
one detail of merge sort that's key.
Merge sort is technically going
to use a little more space.
And so whereas, previously, we
just kept moving our humans around
and swapping people and making
sure they stayed ultimately
in the original positions.
With merge sort, pretends that
here's our original array of memory.
I'm going to need at least
one other array of memory.
And I'm going to cheat, and I'm
going to use even more memory.
But technically, I could
actually go back and forth
between 1 array and a secondary array.
But it is going to take me more space.
So how do I go about implementing
merge sort on this code?
Well, let's consider this.
Here is a array of size 8.
If only one number quit,
obviously not applicable.
So let's focus on the juicy part there.
Sort the left half of the numbers.
All right, how do I sort the
left half of the numbers?
I'm going to just nudge them over just
to be clear, which is the left half.
Here is now a sublist of size 4.
How do I sort the left half?
Well, do I have an
algorithm for sorting?
Yeah, what do I do?
Here's a list of size 4.
How do I sort it?
What's step one?
Sort the left half.
So I now sort of, conceptually in my
mind, take this sublist of size 4.
And I sort it by first sorting the
left half, focusing now on the 7 and 2.
All right, here's a list of size 2.
How do I sort a list of size 2?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: Sorry?
I think we just keep
following our instructions.
Sort the left half.
All right, here is a list of size 1.
How do I sort a list of size 1?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID MALAN: I'm done.
It's done.
So I leave this alone.
What was the next step in the story?
I've just sorted the left half of
the left half of the left half.
What comes next?
I sort the right half of the
left half of the left half,
and I'm done, because it's
just a list of size 1.
What comes after this?
Merge.
So this is where it
gets a little trippy,
because you have to remember where
we're pausing the story to do things
recursively again and again.
But if I've just sorted the left half
and I've just sorted the right half,
now I merge them together.
This is a super short list, so we don't
need Carter's help here as before.
But I think the first
number I take here is the 2.
And then the second number I take,
because it's the only option, is the 7.
But what's nice now is that, notice,
the left half of the left half
is indeed sorted, because I
trivially sorted the left half of it
and the right half of it.
But then merging is really
where the magic happens.
All right, again, if you
rewind now in your mind,
if I've just sorted the left half
of the left half, what happens next?
Sort the right half of the left half.
So again, you kind of rewind in time.
So how do I do this?
I've got a list of size 2.
I sort the left half, just the 5, done.
Sort the right half, 4, done.
Now the interesting part, I merge
the left half and the right half
of the right half of the left half.
So what do I do?
4 comes down here.
5 comes down here.
And now, notice what I have.
Left half is sorted.
Right half is sorted.
If you rewind in time,
where is my next step, 3?
Merge the two halves.
And so this is what Carter
helped me do before.
Let's focus only on
the smallest elements,
just so there's less distraction.
I compare the 2 and the 4.
2 comes first, so let's
obviously put that here.
Now, I compare the new
beginning of this list
and the old beginning of this list.
4 obviously comes next.
And now, I compare the 7 against the 5.
5 obviously comes next.
And now, lastly, I'm
left with one number.
So now I'm down to the 7.
So even if you've kind of lost
track of some of the nuances
here, if you just kind
of take a step back,
we have the original right
half here still untouched.
But the left half of the original
input is now, indeed, sorted,
all by way of doing sorting left half,
right half, left half, right half,
but with those merges in between.
All right, so if we've
just sorted the left half,
we rewind all the way to the beginning.
What do I now do?
All right, so sort the right half.
So sort the right half.
How do I sort a list of size 4?
Well, I first sort the
left half, the 1 and the 6.
How do I sort a list of size 2?
You sort the left half,
just the number 1.
Obviously, there's no work to be done.
Done, sorting the left half.
6, done, sorting the right half.
Now, what do I do?
I merge the left half here
with the right half here.
And that one's pretty straightforward.
Now, what do I do?
I've just merged.
So now I sort it.
I've just sorted the left
half of the right half.
So now I sort the right
So I consider the 0, done.
I consider the 3, done.
I now merge these two together.
0, of course, comes first.
Then comes the 3.
And now I'm at the
point of the story where
I've sorted the left
half of the right half
and the right half of the right half.
So step 3 is merge.
And I'll do it again
like we did with Carter.
All right, 1 and 0,
obviously the 0 comes first.
Now, compare the 1 and the 3.
Obviously, the 1 comes first.
Compare the 6 and the
3, obviously the 3.
And then lastly, the 6.
So now, where are we?
We've taken the left half of
the whole thing and sorted it.
We then took the right half of
So now we're at, lastly,
step 3 for the last time.
What do we do?
Merge.
And so just to be consistent, let me
push these down, and let's compare.
Left hand or right hand, noticing
that they only make forward progress,
none of this back and forth comparisons.
2 and 0, of course, the 0.
So we'll put that in place.
2 and 1, of course, the 1.
So we put that in place.
2 and 3, we merge in, of
course, the 2 in this case.
4 and 3, we now merge
in the 3 in this case.
4 and 6, we now merge, of
course, the 4 in place.
And now, we compare 5 and 6.
We keep the 5.
Bug.
OK, well pretend that the 5 is on.
Oh, this is why.
All right, so now we
compare the 7 and the 6.
6th is gone.
And lastly, 7 is the last one in place.
And even though I grant
that of all the algorithms,
this is probably the hardest
one to stay on top of,
especially when I'm
doing it as a voice over.
Realize that what we've just done is
only those three steps, recursively.
We started with a list of size 8.
We sorted the left half.
We sorted the right half.
And then we merge the two together.
But if you go down each of
those rabbit holes, so to speak,
sorting the left half involves
sorting the left half of the left half
and the right half of the
left half, and so forth.
But this germ of an idea of really
dividing and conquering the problem,
not such that you're having the
problem and only dealing with one half.
Clearly, we're sorting one
half and the other half
and merging them together, ultimately.
It does still lead us
to the same solution.
And if we visualize the remnants of
this now, if I depict this as follows,
where on the screen here, you see
where the numbers originally started
in the top row from left to right.
Essentially, even though
this is in a different order,
I divided that list of size 8,
ultimately, into eight lists of size 1.
And that's where the base
case kicked in and just said,
OK, we're done sorting that.
And after that, logically, I
then merged two lists of size 1
into many lists of size 2 and those
lists of size 2 into lists of size 4.
And then finally, the list of size 4
into one big list sorted of size 8.
And so I put forth this picture
with the little line indicators
here, because how many times did
I divide, divide, divide in half?
Or really double, double, double.
So exponent is the opposite--
spoiler.
How many times did I divide?
So three, concretely.
But if there's eight elements
total, and there's n more generally,
it really is a matter of dividing
and conquering log n times.
You start this, and you can divide
one, two, three times, log n times.
Or conversely, you can start here
and exponentially double, double,
double three times, which is log n.
But on every row, every
shelf, literally, I
made a fuss about pointing my hands
only from the left to the right,
constantly advancing them, such
that every time I did those merges,
I touched every element
once and only once.
There was none of this back and
forth, back and forth on stage.
So if I'm doing something
log n times, or if I'm doing,
rather, n things log n times, what
would be our big O formula, perhaps?
n things log n times?
STUDENT: Oh, it's n log n.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so n log n.
The order of n log n is,
indeed, how we would describe
the running time of merge sort.
And so of all of the sorts thus far,
we've seen that merge sort here,
actually, is n log n, which is
strictly better than n squared,
which is where both selection
sort and bubble sort landed.
But it's also slower than
linear search, for instance.
But you would rather expect that.
If you have to do a lot
of work up front sorting
some elements versus
just searching them,
you're going to have
to put in more effort.
And so the question of whether or
not you should just search something
blindly with linear search
and not bother sorting it,
really boils down to, can you
afford to spend this amount of time?
And if you're the Googles
of the world, odds
are you don't want to be searching
their database linearly every time.
Why?
Because you can sort it once and then
benefit millions, billions of people,
subsequently using something like
binary search or, frankly in practice,
something even fancier and
faster than binary search.
But there's always going
to be this trade off.
You can achieve binary search
only if the elements are sorted.
How much does it cost you to sort them?
Well, maybe n squared, if you used
some of the earlier algorithms.
But it turns out, n log
in is pretty fast as well.
So at the end of the day, these
running times involve trade offs.
And indeed, in merge sort 2, I should
note that the lower bound on merge
sort is also going to
be omega of n log n.
As such, we can describe it in
terms of our theta notation,
saying that merge sort is,
indeed, in theta of n log n.
So generally speaking, probably better
to use something like merge sort
or some other algorithm that's n log n.
In practice, most programmers are not
implementing these sorting algorithms
themselves.
Odds are, they're using
a library off the shelf
that themselves have made the decision
as to which of these algorithms to do.
But generally speaking, and we're
seeing now this for the first time,
if you want to improve time, like
use less time, write faster code,
you've got to pay a price.
And that might be your
human time, just takes you
more time to code up
something more sophisticated,
more difficult to implement.
Or you need to spend
something like space.
And as these shelves
suggest, that too is
one of the key details of merge sort.
You can't just have the
elements swapping in place.
You need at least an auxiliary array,
so that when you do the merging,
you have a place to put them.
And this is excessive,
this amount of memory.
I could have just gone back and forth
between top shelf and bottom shelf.
But it's a little more
interesting to go top down.
But you do need more space.
Back in the day, decades ago,
space was really expensive.
And so you know what?
It might have been better to not
use merge sort, use bubble sort
or selection sort even, or some
other algorithm altogether.
Nowadays, space is relatively cheap.
And so these are more
acceptable trade offs.
But it totally depends
on the application.
The very last thing we thought we'd
do is show you an actual comparison
of some of these sorting algorithms.
It's about 60 seconds long.
And it will compare for you,
selection sort, bubble sort,
and merge sort in parallel
simultaneously with some fun sorting
music, showing you
ultimately what it really
means to be an O of n squared,
or better yet, big O of n log n.
Selection on the top.
Bubble on the bottom.
Merge in the middle.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right, that's it for CS50.
We'll see you next time.